<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="ceilometer-conf-changes-kilo">
  <!-- Warning: Do not edit this file. It is automatically generated and your changes will be overwritten. The tool to do so lives in the openstack-doc-tools repository. -->
  <title>New, updated and deprecated options in Kilo for Telemetry</title>
  <table>
    <caption>New options</caption>
    <col width="50%"/>
    <col width="50%"/>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <td>Option = default value</td>
        <td>(Type) Help string</td>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tr>
      <td>[DEFAULT] event_pipeline_cfg_file = event_pipeline.yaml</td>
      <td>(StrOpt) Configuration file for event pipeline definition.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>[DEFAULT] magnetodb_control_exchange = magnetodb</td>
      <td>(StrOpt) Exchange name for Magnetodb notifications.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>[DEFAULT] policy_dirs = ['policy.d']</td>
      <td>(MultiStrOpt) Directories where policy configuration files are stored. They can be relative to any directory in the search path defined by the config_dir option, or absolute paths. The file defined by policy_file must exist for these directories to be searched.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>[DEFAULT] polling_namespaces = ['compute', 'central']</td>
      <td>(MultiChoicesOpt) Polling namespace(s) to be used while resource polling</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>[DEFAULT] pollster_list = []</td>
      <td>(MultiChoicesOpt) List of pollsters (or wildcard templates) to be used while polling</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>[DEFAULT] reserved_metadata_keys = </td>
      <td>(ListOpt) List of metadata keys reserved for metering use. And these keys are additional to the ones included in the namespace.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>[DEFAULT] zaqar_control_exchange = zaqar</td>
      <td>(StrOpt) Exchange name for Messaging service notifications.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>[alarm] evaluation_service = default</td>
      <td>(StrOpt) Driver to use for alarm evaluation service. DEPRECATED: "singleton" and "partitioned" alarm evaluator services will be removed in Kilo in favour of the default alarm evaluation service using tooz for partitioning.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>[coordination] check_watchers = 10.0</td>
      <td>(FloatOpt) Number of seconds between checks to see if group membership has changed</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>[database] db2nosql_resource_id_maxlen = 512</td>
      <td>(IntOpt) The max length of resources id in DB2 nosql, the value should be larger than len(hostname) * 2 as compute node's resource id is &lt;hostname&gt;_&lt;nodename&gt;.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>[database] event_connection = None</td>
      <td>(StrOpt) The connection string used to connect to the event database. (if unset, connection is used)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>[database] mongodb_replica_set = </td>
      <td>(StrOpt) The name of the replica set which is used to connect to MongoDB database. If it is set, MongoReplicaSetClient will be used instead of MongoClient.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>[dispatcher_http] cadf_only = False</td>
      <td>(BoolOpt) The flag which indicates if only cadf message should be posted. If false, all meters will be posted.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>[dispatcher_http] target = </td>
      <td>(StrOpt) The target where the http request will be sent to. If this is not set, no data will be posted. For example: target = http://hostname:1234/path</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>[dispatcher_http] timeout = 5</td>
      <td>(IntOpt) The max time in second to wait for a request to timeout.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>[notification] workload_partitioning = False</td>
      <td>(BoolOpt) Enable workload partitioning, allowing multiple notification agents to be run simultaneously.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>[oslo_concurrency] disable_process_locking = False</td>
      <td>(BoolOpt) Enables or disables inter-process locks.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>[oslo_concurrency] lock_path = None</td>
      <td>(StrOpt) Directory to use for lock files.  For security, the specified directory should only be writable by the user running the processes that need locking. Defaults to environment variable OSLO_LOCK_PATH. If external locks are used, a lock path must be set.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>[polling] partitioning_group_prefix = None</td>
      <td>(StrOpt) Work-load partitioning group prefix. Use only if you want to run multiple polling agents with different config files. For each sub-group of the agent pool with the same partitioning_group_prefix a disjoint subset of pollsters should be loaded.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>[vmware] host_port = 443</td>
      <td>(IntOpt) Port of the VMware Vsphere host.</td>
    </tr>
  </table>
  <table>
    <caption>New default values</caption>
    <col width="33%"/>
    <col width="33%"/>
    <col width="33%"/>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <td>Option</td>
        <td>Previous default value</td>
        <td>New default value</td>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tr>
      <td>[DEFAULT] rpc_zmq_matchmaker</td>
      <td>oslo.messaging._drivers.matchmaker.MatchMakerLocalhost</td>
      <td>oslo_messaging._drivers.matchmaker.MatchMakerLocalhost</td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</section>
