<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <!-- Warning: Do not edit this file. It is automatically
     generated and your changes will be overwritten.
     The tool to do so lives in openstack-doc-tools repository. -->
  <table rules="all" xml:id="config_table_cinder_netapp_7mode_nfs">
    <caption>Description of NetApp 7-Mode NFS driver configuration options</caption>
    <col width="50%"/>
    <col width="50%"/>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th>Configuration option = Default value</th>
        <th>Description</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <th colspan="2">[DEFAULT]</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>expiry_thres_minutes</option> = <replaceable>720</replaceable></td>
        <td>(IntOpt) This option specifies the threshold for last access time for images in the NFS image cache. When a cache cleaning cycle begins, images in the cache that have not been accessed in the last M minutes, where M is the value of this parameter, will be deleted from the cache to create free space on the NFS share.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>netapp_login</option> = <replaceable>None</replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) Administrative user account name used to access the storage system or proxy server.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>netapp_partner_backend_name</option> = <replaceable>None</replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) The name of the config.conf stanza for a Data ONTAP (7-mode) HA partner.  This option is only used by the driver when connecting to an instance with a storage family of Data ONTAP operating in 7-Mode, and it is required if the storage protocol selected is FC.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>netapp_password</option> = <replaceable>None</replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) Password for the administrative user account specified in the netapp_login option.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>netapp_server_hostname</option> = <replaceable>None</replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) The hostname (or IP address) for the storage system or proxy server.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>netapp_server_port</option> = <replaceable>None</replaceable></td>
        <td>(IntOpt) The TCP port to use for communication with the storage system or proxy server. If not specified, Data ONTAP drivers will use 80 for HTTP and 443 for HTTPS; E-Series will use 8080 for HTTP and 8443 for HTTPS.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>netapp_storage_family</option> = <replaceable>ontap_cluster</replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) The storage family type used on the storage system; valid values are ontap_7mode for using Data ONTAP operating in 7-Mode, ontap_cluster for using clustered Data ONTAP, or eseries for using E-Series.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>netapp_storage_protocol</option> = <replaceable>None</replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) The storage protocol to be used on the data path with the storage system; valid values are iscsi, fc, or nfs.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>netapp_transport_type</option> = <replaceable>http</replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) The transport protocol used when communicating with the storage system or proxy server. Valid values are http or https.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>netapp_vfiler</option> = <replaceable>None</replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) The vFiler unit on which provisioning of block storage volumes will be done. This option is only used by the driver when connecting to an instance with a storage family of Data ONTAP operating in 7-Mode and the storage protocol selected is NFS. Only use this option when utilizing the MultiStore feature on the NetApp storage system.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>thres_avl_size_perc_start</option> = <replaceable>20</replaceable></td>
        <td>(IntOpt) If the percentage of available space for an NFS share has dropped below the value specified by this option, the NFS image cache will be cleaned.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>thres_avl_size_perc_stop</option> = <replaceable>60</replaceable></td>
        <td>(IntOpt) When the percentage of available space on an NFS share has reached the percentage specified by this option, the driver will stop clearing files from the NFS image cache that have not been accessed in the last M minutes, where M is the value of the expiry_thres_minutes configuration option.</td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</para>
