<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!-- Warning: Do not edit this file. It is automatically
             generated and your changes will be overwritten.
             The tool to do so lives in the tools directory of this
             repository -->
        <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
        <table rules="all">
          <caption>Description of configuration options for netapp</caption>
           <col width="50%"/>
           <col width="50%"/>
           <thead>
              <tr>
                  <td>Configuration option=Default value</td>
                  <td>Description</td>
              </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
              <tr>
                       <td>expiry_thres_minutes=720</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Threshold minutes after which cache file can be cleaned.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>netapp_login=None</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) Login user name for the storage 7-Mode controller/clustered Data ONTAP management.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>netapp_password=None</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) Login password for the 7-Mode controller/clustered Data ONTAP management.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>netapp_server_hostname=None</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) The management IP address for the 7-Mode controller or clustered Data ONTAP.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>netapp_server_port=80</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) The 7-Mode controller/Clustered ONTAP data port to use for communication.
                           As a custom, 80 is used for HTTP and 443 is used for HTTPS communication.
                           The defaults should be changed if other ports are used for ONTAPI.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>netapp_size_multiplier=1.2</td>
                       <td>(FloatOpt) When creating volumes, the quantity to be
                        multiplied to the requested OpenStack volume size to ensure enough space is available on
                        the 7-Mode Controller/Clustered Data ONTAP Vserver.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>netapp_storage_family=ontap_cluster</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) Storage family type. Valid values are ontap_7mode for using a 7-Mode controller
                       or ontap_cluster for a Clustered Data ONTAP.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>netapp_storage_protocol=None</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) The storage protocol to be used. Valid options are nfs or iscsi,
                       but we recommended that you consult the detailed explanation.
                       If None is selected, nfs will be used.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>netapp_transport_type=http</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) Transport protocol for communicating with the 7-Mode controller or Clustered Data ONTAP.
                       Supported protocols include http and https.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>netapp_vfiler=None</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) The vFiler unit to be use for provisioning OpenStack Volumes. Use this only if using
                       MultiStore®.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>netapp_volume_list=None</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) Comma separated list of NetApp volumes to
                        be used for provisioning on 7-Mode controller. This
                        option is used to restrict provisioning to the
                        specified NetApp controller volumes. In case this
                        option is not specified all NetApp controller volumes
                        except the controller root volume are used for
                        provisioning OpenStack volumes.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>netapp_vserver=None</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) The Vserver on the cluster on which
                provisioning of OpenStack volumes occurs. If using netapp_storage_protocol=nfs,
                it is a mandatory parameter for storage service catalog support.
                If specified the exports belonging to the
                vserver will only be used for provisioning in future.
                OpenStack volumes on exports not belonging to the vserver
                will continue to function in a normal manner and recieve
                Block Storage operations like snapshot creation etc.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>thres_avl_size_perc_start=20</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Threshold available percent to start cache cleaning.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>thres_avl_size_perc_stop=60</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Threshold available percent to stop cache cleaning.</td>
              </tr>
       </tbody>
        </table>
        </para>
