<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <!-- Warning: Do not edit this file. It is automatically
     generated and your changes will be overwritten.
     The tool to do so lives in openstack-doc-tools repository. -->
  <table rules="all" xml:id="config_table_cinder_api">
    <caption>Description of API configuration options</caption>
    <col width="50%"/>
    <col width="50%"/>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th>Configuration option = Default value</th>
        <th>Description</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <th colspan="2">[DEFAULT]</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>api_paste_config = api-paste.ini</td>
        <td>(StrOpt) File name for the paste.deploy config for cinder-api</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>api_rate_limit = True</td>
        <td>(BoolOpt) Enables or disables rate limit of the API.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>az_cache_duration = 3600</td>
        <td>(IntOpt) Cache volume availability zones in memory for the provided duration in seconds</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>backdoor_port = None</td>
        <td>(StrOpt) Enable eventlet backdoor.  Acceptable values are 0, &lt;port&gt;, and &lt;start&gt;:&lt;end&gt;, where 0 results in listening on a random tcp port number; &lt;port&gt; results in listening on the specified port number (and not enabling backdoor if that port is in use); and &lt;start&gt;:&lt;end&gt; results in listening on the smallest unused port number within the specified range of port numbers.  The chosen port is displayed in the service's log file.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>enable_v1_api = True</td>
        <td>(BoolOpt) Deploy v1 of the Cinder API.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>enable_v2_api = True</td>
        <td>(BoolOpt) Deploy v2 of the Cinder API.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>extra_capabilities = {}</td>
        <td>(StrOpt) User defined capabilities, a JSON formatted string specifying key/value pairs.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>max_header_line = 16384</td>
        <td>(IntOpt) Maximum line size of message headers to be accepted. max_header_line may need to be increased when using large tokens (typically those generated by the Keystone v3 API with big service catalogs).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>osapi_max_limit = 1000</td>
        <td>(IntOpt) The maximum number of items that a collection resource returns in a single response</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>osapi_max_request_body_size = 114688</td>
        <td>(IntOpt) Max size for body of a request</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>osapi_volume_base_URL = None</td>
        <td>(StrOpt) Base URL that will be presented to users in links to the OpenStack Volume API</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>osapi_volume_ext_list = </td>
        <td>(ListOpt) Specify list of extensions to load when using osapi_volume_extension option with cinder.api.contrib.select_extensions</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>osapi_volume_extension = ['cinder.api.contrib.standard_extensions']</td>
        <td>(MultiStrOpt) osapi volume extension to load</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>osapi_volume_listen = 0.0.0.0</td>
        <td>(StrOpt) IP address on which OpenStack Volume API listens</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>osapi_volume_listen_port = 8776</td>
        <td>(IntOpt) Port on which OpenStack Volume API listens</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>osapi_volume_workers = None</td>
        <td>(IntOpt) Number of workers for OpenStack Volume API service. The default is equal to the number of CPUs available.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>transfer_api_class = cinder.transfer.api.API</td>
        <td>(StrOpt) The full class name of the volume transfer API class</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>volume_api_class = cinder.volume.api.API</td>
        <td>(StrOpt) The full class name of the volume API class to use</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>volume_name_template = volume-%s</td>
        <td>(StrOpt) Template string to be used to generate volume names</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>volume_number_multiplier = -1.0</td>
        <td>(FloatOpt) Multiplier used for weighing volume number. Negative numbers mean to spread vs stack.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>volume_transfer_key_length = 16</td>
        <td>(IntOpt) The number of characters in the autogenerated auth key.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>volume_transfer_salt_length = 8</td>
        <td>(IntOpt) The number of characters in the salt.</td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</para>
