<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <!-- Warning: Do not edit this file. It is automatically
     generated and your changes will be overwritten.
     The tool to do so lives in openstack-doc-tools repository. -->
  <table rules="all" xml:id="config_table_glance_api">
    <caption>Description of API configuration options</caption>
    <col width="50%"/>
    <col width="50%"/>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th>Configuration option = Default value</th>
        <th>Description</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <th colspan="2">[DEFAULT]</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>admin_role</option> = <replaceable>admin</replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) Role used to identify an authenticated user as administrator.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>allow_anonymous_access</option> = <replaceable>False</replaceable></td>
        <td>(BoolOpt) Allow unauthenticated users to access the API with read-only privileges. This only applies when using ContextMiddleware.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>enable_v1_api</option> = <replaceable>True</replaceable></td>
        <td>(BoolOpt) Deploy the v1 OpenStack Images API.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>enable_v1_registry</option> = <replaceable>True</replaceable></td>
        <td>(BoolOpt) Deploy the v1 OpenStack Registry API.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>enable_v2_api</option> = <replaceable>True</replaceable></td>
        <td>(BoolOpt) Deploy the v2 OpenStack Images API.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>enable_v2_registry</option> = <replaceable>True</replaceable></td>
        <td>(BoolOpt) Deploy the v2 OpenStack Registry API.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>image_size_cap</option> = <replaceable>1099511627776</replaceable></td>
        <td>(IntOpt) Maximum size of image a user can upload in bytes. Defaults to 1099511627776 bytes (1 TB).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>location_strategy</option> = <replaceable>location_order</replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) This value sets what strategy will be used to determine the image location order. Currently two strategies are packaged with Glance 'location_order' and 'store_type'.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>max_header_line</option> = <replaceable>16384</replaceable></td>
        <td>(IntOpt) Maximum line size of message headers to be accepted. max_header_line may need to be increased when using large tokens (typically those generated by the Keystone v3 API with big service catalogs</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>owner_is_tenant</option> = <replaceable>True</replaceable></td>
        <td>(BoolOpt) When true, this option sets the owner of an image to be the tenant. Otherwise, the owner of the  image will be the authenticated user issuing the request.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>public_endpoint</option> = <replaceable>None</replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) Public url to use for versions endpoint. The default is None, which will use the request's host_url attribute to populate the URL base. If Glance is operating behind a proxy, you will want to change this to represent the proxy's URL.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>send_identity_headers</option> = <replaceable>False</replaceable></td>
        <td>(BoolOpt) Whether to pass through headers containing user and tenant information when making requests to the registry. This allows the registry to use the context middleware without keystonemiddleware's auth_token middleware, removing calls to the keystone auth service. It is recommended that when using this option, secure communication between glance api and glance registry is ensured by means other than auth_token middleware.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>show_multiple_locations</option> = <replaceable>False</replaceable></td>
        <td>(BoolOpt) Whether to include the backend image locations in image properties. Revealing storage location can be a security risk, so use this setting with caution!  The overrides show_image_direct_url.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>tcp_keepidle</option> = <replaceable>600</replaceable></td>
        <td>(IntOpt) The value for the socket option TCP_KEEPIDLE.  This is the time in seconds that the connection must be idle before TCP starts sending keepalive probes.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>use_user_token</option> = <replaceable>True</replaceable></td>
        <td>(BoolOpt) Whether to pass through the user token when making requests to the registry.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th colspan="2">[glance_store]</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>default_store</option> = <replaceable>file</replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) Default scheme to use to store image data. The scheme must be registered by one of the stores defined by the 'stores' config option.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>stores</option> = <replaceable>file, http</replaceable></td>
        <td>(ListOpt) List of stores enabled</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th colspan="2">[paste_deploy]</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>config_file</option> = <replaceable>None</replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) Name of the paste configuration file.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>flavor</option> = <replaceable>None</replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) Partial name of a pipeline in your paste configuration file with the service name removed. For example, if your paste section name is [pipeline:glance-api-keystone] use the value "keystone"</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th colspan="2">[store_type_location_strategy]</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>store_type_preference</option> = <replaceable></replaceable></td>
        <td>(ListOpt) The store names to use to get store preference order. The name must be registered by one of the stores defined by the 'stores' config option. This option will be applied when you using 'store_type' option as image location strategy defined by the 'location_strategy' config option.</td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</para>
