<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <!-- Warning: Do not edit this file. It is automatically
     generated and your changes will be overwritten.
     The tool to do so lives in openstack-doc-tools repository. -->
  <table rules="all" xml:id="config_table_glance_common">
    <caption>Description of common configuration options</caption>
    <col width="50%"/>
    <col width="50%"/>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th>Configuration option = Default value</th>
        <th>Description</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <th colspan="2">[DEFAULT]</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>allow_additional_image_properties</option> = <replaceable>True</replaceable></td>
        <td>(BoolOpt) Whether to allow users to specify image properties beyond what the image schema provides</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>api_limit_max</option> = <replaceable>1000</replaceable></td>
        <td>(IntOpt) Maximum permissible number of items that could be returned by a request</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>backlog</option> = <replaceable>4096</replaceable></td>
        <td>(IntOpt) The backlog value that will be used when creating the TCP listener socket.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>bind_host</option> = <replaceable>0.0.0.0</replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) Address to bind the server.  Useful when selecting a particular network interface.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>bind_port</option> = <replaceable>None</replaceable></td>
        <td>(IntOpt) The port on which the server will listen.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>data_api</option> = <replaceable>glance.db.sqlalchemy.api</replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) Python module path of data access API</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>image_location_quota</option> = <replaceable>10</replaceable></td>
        <td>(IntOpt) Maximum number of locations allowed on an image. Negative values evaluate to unlimited.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>image_member_quota</option> = <replaceable>128</replaceable></td>
        <td>(IntOpt) Maximum number of image members per image. Negative values evaluate to unlimited.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>image_property_quota</option> = <replaceable>128</replaceable></td>
        <td>(IntOpt) Maximum number of properties allowed on an image. Negative values evaluate to unlimited.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>image_tag_quota</option> = <replaceable>128</replaceable></td>
        <td>(IntOpt) Maximum number of tags allowed on an image. Negative values evaluate to unlimited.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>limit_param_default</option> = <replaceable>25</replaceable></td>
        <td>(IntOpt) Default value for the number of items returned by a request if not specified explicitly in the request</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>memcached_servers</option> = <replaceable>None</replaceable></td>
        <td>(ListOpt) Memcached servers or None for in process cache.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>metadata_encryption_key</option> = <replaceable>None</replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) Key used for encrypting sensitive metadata while talking to the registry or database.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>metadata_source_path</option> = <replaceable>/etc/glance/metadefs/</replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) Path to the directory where json metadata files are stored</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>property_protection_file</option> = <replaceable>None</replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) The location of the property protection file.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>property_protection_rule_format</option> = <replaceable>roles</replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) This config value indicates whether "roles" or "policies" are used in the property protection file.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>show_image_direct_url</option> = <replaceable>False</replaceable></td>
        <td>(BoolOpt) Whether to include the backend image storage location in image properties. Revealing storage location can be a security risk, so use this setting with caution!</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>user_storage_quota</option> = <replaceable>0</replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) Set a system wide quota for every user. This value is the total capacity that a user can use across all storage systems. A value of 0 means unlimited.Optional unit can be specified for the value. Accepted units are B, KB, MB, GB and TB representing Bytes, KiloBytes, MegaBytes, GigaBytes and TeraBytes respectively. If no unit is specified then Bytes is assumed. Note that there should not be any space between value and unit and units are case sensitive.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>workers</option> = <replaceable>4</replaceable></td>
        <td>(IntOpt) The number of child process workers that will be created to service requests. The default will be equal to the number of CPUs available.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th colspan="2">[glance_store]</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>os_region_name</option> = <replaceable>None</replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) Region name of this node</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th colspan="2">[image_format]</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>container_formats</option> = <replaceable>ami, ari, aki, bare, ovf, ova</replaceable></td>
        <td>(ListOpt) Supported values for the 'container_format' image attribute</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>disk_formats</option> = <replaceable>ami, ari, aki, vhd, vmdk, raw, qcow2, vdi, iso</replaceable></td>
        <td>(ListOpt) Supported values for the 'disk_format' image attribute</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th colspan="2">[keystone_authtoken]</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>memcached_servers</option> = <replaceable>None</replaceable></td>
        <td>(ListOpt) Optionally specify a list of memcached server(s) to use for caching. If left undefined, tokens will instead be cached in-process.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th colspan="2">[task]</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>eventlet_executor_pool_size</option> = <replaceable>1000</replaceable></td>
        <td>(IntOpt) Specifies the maximum number of eventlet threads which can be spun up by the eventlet based task executor to perform execution of Glance tasks.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>task_executor</option> = <replaceable>eventlet</replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) Specifies which task executor to be used to run the task scripts.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>task_time_to_live</option> = <replaceable>48</replaceable></td>
        <td>(IntOpt) Time in hours for which a task lives after, either succeeding or failing</td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</para>
