<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <!-- Warning: Do not edit this file. It is automatically
     generated and your changes will be overwritten.
     The tool to do so lives in openstack-doc-tools repository. -->
  <table rules="all" xml:id="config_table_keystone_identity">
    <caption>Description of identity configuration options</caption>
    <col width="50%"/>
    <col width="50%"/>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th>Configuration option = Default value</th>
        <th>Description</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <th colspan="2">[identity]</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>default_domain_id = default</td>
        <td>(StrOpt) This references the domain to use for all Identity API v2 requests (which are not aware of domains). A domain with this ID will be created for you by keystone-manage db_sync in migration 008. The domain referenced by this ID cannot be deleted on the v3 API, to prevent accidentally breaking the v2 API. There is nothing special about this domain, other than the fact that it must exist to order to maintain support for your v2 clients.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>domain_config_dir = /etc/keystone/domains</td>
        <td>(StrOpt) Path for Keystone to locate the domain specific identity configuration files if domain_specific_drivers_enabled is set to true.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>domain_specific_drivers_enabled = False</td>
        <td>(BoolOpt) A subset (or all) of domains can have their own identity driver, each with their own partial configuration file in a domain configuration directory. Only values specific to the domain need to be placed in the domain specific configuration file. This feature is disabled by default; set to true to enable.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>driver = keystone.identity.backends.sql.Identity</td>
        <td>(StrOpt) Identity backend driver.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>list_limit = None</td>
        <td>(IntOpt) Maximum number of entities that will be returned in an identity collection.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>max_password_length = 4096</td>
        <td>(IntOpt) Maximum supported length for user passwords; decrease to improve performance.</td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</para>
