<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!-- Warning: Do not edit this file. It is automatically
             generated and your changes will be overwritten.
             The tool to do so lives in the tools directory of this
             repository -->
        <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
        <table rules="all">
          <caption>Description of configuration options for nicira</caption>
           <col width="50%"/>
           <col width="50%"/>
           <thead>
              <tr>
                  <th>Configuration option = Default value</th>
                  <th>Description</th>
              </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
              <tr>
                       <td>agent_mode = agent</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) The mode used to implement DHCP/metadata services.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>always_read_status = False</td>
                       <td>(BoolOpt) Always read operational status from backend on show operations. Enabling this option might slow down the system.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>concurrent_connections = 10</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Maximum concurrent connections to each NVP controller.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>datacenter_moid = None</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) Optional parameter identifying the ID of datacenter to deploy NSX Edges</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>datastore_id = None</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) Optional parameter identifying the ID of datastore to deploy NSX Edges</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>default_interface_name = breth0</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) Name of the interface on a L2 Gateway transport nodewhich should be used by default when setting up a network connection</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>default_l2_gw_service_uuid = None</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) Unique identifier of the NVP L2 Gateway service which will be used by default for network gateways</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>default_l3_gw_service_uuid = None</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) Unique identifier of the NVP L3 Gateway service which will be used for implementing routers and floating IPs</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>default_transport_type = stt</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) The default network tranport type to use (stt, gre, bridge, ipsec_gre, or ipsec_stt)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>default_tz_uuid = None</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) This is uuid of the default NVP Transport zone that will be used for creating tunneled isolated "Neutron" networks. It needs to be created in NVP before starting Neutron with the nvp plugin.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>deployment_container_id = None</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) Optional parameter identifying the ID of datastore to deploy NSX Edges</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>external_network = None</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) Network ID for physical network connectivity</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>http_timeout = 10</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Time before aborting a request</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>manager_uri = None</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) uri for vsm</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>max_lp_per_bridged_ls = 5000</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Maximum number of ports of a logical switch on a bridged transport zone (default 5000)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>max_lp_per_overlay_ls = 256</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Maximum number of ports of a logical switch on an overlay transport zone (default 256)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>max_random_sync_delay = 0</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Maximum value for the additional random delay in seconds between runs of the state synchronization task</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>metadata_mode = access_network</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) If set to access_network this enables a dedicated connection to the metadata proxy for metadata server access via Neutron router. If set to dhcp_host_route this enables host route injection via the dhcp agent. This option is only useful if running on a host that does not support namespaces otherwise access_network should be used.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>min_chunk_size = 500</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Minimum number of resources to be retrieved from NVP during state synchronization</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>min_sync_req_delay = 10</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Minimum delay, in seconds, between two state synchronization queries to NVP. It must not exceed state_sync_interval</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>nvp_cluster_uuid = None</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) Optional paramter identifying the UUID of the cluster in NVP.  This can be retrieved from NVP management console "admin" section.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>nvp_controllers = None</td>
                       <td>(ListOpt) Lists the NVP controllers in this cluster</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>nvp_gen_timeout = -1</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Number of seconds a generation id should be valid for (default -1 meaning do not time out)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>nvp_password = admin</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) Password for NVP controllers in this cluster</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>nvp_user = admin</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) User name for NVP controllers in this cluster</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>redirects = 2</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Number of times a redirect should be followed</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>req_timeout = 30</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Total time limit for a cluster request</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>resource_pool_id = default</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) Shared resource pool id</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>retries = 2</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Number of time a request should be retried</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>state_sync_interval = 120</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Interval in seconds between runs of the state synchronization task. Set it to 0 to disable it</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>task_status_check_interval = 2000</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Task status check interval</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>user = admin</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) User name for vsm</td>
              </tr>
       </tbody>
        </table>
        </para>
