<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <!-- Warning: Do not edit this file. It is automatically
     generated and your changes will be overwritten.
     The tool to do so lives in openstack-doc-tools repository. -->
  <table rules="all" xml:id="config_table_neutron_ml2_arista">
    <caption>Description of ML2 Arista mechanism driver configuration options</caption>
    <col width="50%"/>
    <col width="50%"/>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th>Configuration option = Default value</th>
        <th>Description</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <th colspan="2">[ml2_arista]</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>eapi_host</option> = <replaceable></replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) Arista EOS IP address. This is required field. If not set, all communications to Arista EOSwill fail.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>eapi_password</option> = <replaceable></replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) Password for Arista EOS. This is required field. If not set, all communications to Arista EOS will fail.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>eapi_username</option> = <replaceable></replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) Username for Arista EOS. This is required field. If not set, all communications to Arista EOSwill fail.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>region_name</option> = <replaceable>RegionOne</replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) Defines Region Name that is assigned to this OpenStack Controller. This is useful when multiple OpenStack/Neutron controllers are managing the same Arista HW clusters. Note that this name must match with the region name registered (or known) to keystone service. Authentication with Keysotne is performed by EOS. This is optional. If not set, a value of "RegionOne" is assumed.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>sync_interval</option> = <replaceable>180</replaceable></td>
        <td>(IntOpt) Sync interval in seconds between Neutron plugin and EOS. This interval defines how often the synchronization is performed. This is an optional field. If not set, a value of 180 seconds is assumed.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>use_fqdn</option> = <replaceable>True</replaceable></td>
        <td>(BoolOpt) Defines if hostnames are sent to Arista EOS as FQDNs ("node1.domain.com") or as short names ("node1"). This is optional. If not set, a value of "True" is assumed.</td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</para>
