<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <!-- Warning: Do not edit this file. It is automatically
     generated and your changes will be overwritten.
     The tool to do so lives in openstack-doc-tools repository. -->
  <table rules="all" xml:id="config_table_neutron_l3_arista">
    <caption>Description of Arista layer-3 service plug-in configuration options</caption>
    <col width="50%"/>
    <col width="50%"/>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th>Configuration option = Default value</th>
        <th>Description</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <th colspan="2">[l3_arista]</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>l3_sync_interval</option> = <replaceable>180</replaceable></td>
        <td>(IntOpt) Sync interval in seconds between L3 Service plugin and EOS. This interval defines how often the synchronization is performed. This is an optional field. If not set, a value of 180 seconds is assumed</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>mlag_config</option> = <replaceable>False</replaceable></td>
        <td>(BoolOpt) This flag is used indicate if Arista Switches are configured in MLAG mode. If yes, all L3 config is pushed to both the switches automatically. If this flag is set to True, ensure to specify IP addresses of both switches. This is optional. If not set, a value of "False" is assumed.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>primary_l3_host</option> = <replaceable></replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) Arista EOS IP address. This is required field. If not set, all communications to Arista EOS will fail</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>primary_l3_host_password</option> = <replaceable></replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) Password for Arista EOS. This is required field. If not set, all communications to Arista EOS will fail</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>primary_l3_host_username</option> = <replaceable></replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) Username for Arista EOS. This is required field. If not set, all communications to Arista EOS will fail</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>secondary_l3_host</option> = <replaceable></replaceable></td>
        <td>(StrOpt) Arista EOS IP address for second Switch MLAGed with the first one. This an optional field, however, if mlag_config flag is set, then this is required. If not set, all communications to Arista EOS will fail</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>use_vrf</option> = <replaceable>False</replaceable></td>
        <td>(BoolOpt) A "True" value for this flag indicates to create a router in VRF. If not set, all routers are created in default VRF.This is optional. If not set, a value of "False" is assumed.</td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</para>
