<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!-- Warning: Do not edit this file. It is automatically
             generated and your changes will be overwritten.
             The tool to do so lives in the tools directory of this
             repository -->
        <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
        <table rules="all">
          <caption>Description of configuration options for quotas</caption>
           <col width="50%"/>
           <col width="50%"/>
           <thead>
              <tr>
                  <th>Configuration option = Default value</th>
                  <th>Description</th>
              </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
              <tr>
                  <th colspan="2">[DEFAULT]</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>max_routes = 30</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Maximum number of routes</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                  <th colspan="2">[QUOTAS]</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>default_quota = -1</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Default number of resource allowed per tenant. A negative value means unlimited.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>quota_driver = neutron.db.quota_db.DbQuotaDriver</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) Default driver to use for quota checks</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>quota_firewall = 1</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Number of firewalls allowed per tenant. A negative value means unlimited.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>quota_firewall_policy = 1</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Number of firewall policies allowed per tenant. A negative value means unlimited.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>quota_firewall_rule = -1</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Number of firewall rules allowed per tenant. A negative value means unlimited.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>quota_floatingip = 50</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Number of floating IPs allowed per tenant. A negative value means unlimited.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>quota_health_monitor = -1</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Number of health monitors allowed per tenant. A negative value means unlimited.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>quota_items = network, subnet, port</td>
                       <td>(ListOpt) Resource name(s) that are supported in quota features</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>quota_member = -1</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Number of pool members allowed per tenant. A negative value means unlimited.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>quota_network = 10</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Number of networks allowed per tenant.A negative value means unlimited.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>quota_network_gateway = 5</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Number of network gateways allowed per tenant, -1 for unlimited</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>quota_packet_filter = 100</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Number of packet_filters allowed per tenant, -1 for unlimited</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>quota_pool = 10</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Number of pools allowed per tenant. A negative value means unlimited.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>quota_port = 50</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Number of ports allowed per tenant. A negative value means unlimited.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>quota_router = 10</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Number of routers allowed per tenant. A negative value means unlimited.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>quota_security_group = 10</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Number of security groups allowed per tenant. A negative value means unlimited.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>quota_security_group_rule = 100</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Number of security rules allowed per tenant. A negative value means unlimited.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>quota_subnet = 10</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Number of subnets allowed per tenant, A negative value means unlimited.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>quota_vip = 10</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Number of vips allowed per tenant. A negative value means unlimited.</td>
              </tr>
       </tbody>
        </table>
        </para>
