<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!-- Warning: Do not edit this file. It is automatically
             generated and your changes will be overwritten.
             The tool to do so lives in the tools directory of this
             repository -->
        <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
        <table rules="all">
          <caption>Description of configuration options for api</caption>
           <col width="50%"/>
           <col width="50%"/>
           <thead>
              <tr>
                  <th>Configuration option = Default value</th>
                  <th>Description</th>
              </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
              <tr>
                  <th colspan="2">[DEFAULT]</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>enable_new_services = True</td>
                       <td>(BoolOpt) Services to be added to the available pool on create</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>enabled_apis = ec2, osapi_compute, metadata</td>
                       <td>(ListOpt) A list of APIs to enable by default</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>enabled_ssl_apis = </td>
                       <td>(ListOpt) A list of APIs with enabled SSL</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>instance_name_template = instance-%08x</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) Template string to be used to generate instance names</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>max_header_line = 16384</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Maximum line size of message headers to be accepted. max_header_line may need to be increased when using large tokens (typically those generated by the Keystone v3 API with big service catalogs).</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>multi_instance_display_name_template = %(name)s-%(uuid)s</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) When creating multiple instances with a single request using the os-multiple-create API extension, this template will be used to build the display name for each instance. The benefit is that the instances end up with different hostnames. To restore legacy behavior of every instance having the same name, set this option to "%(name)s".  Valid keys for the template are: name, uuid, count.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>non_inheritable_image_properties = cache_in_nova, bittorrent</td>
                       <td>(ListOpt) These are image properties which a snapshot should not inherit from an instance</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>null_kernel = nokernel</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) Kernel image that indicates not to use a kernel, but to use a raw disk image instead</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>osapi_compute_ext_list = </td>
                       <td>(ListOpt) Specify list of extensions to load when using osapi_compute_extension option with nova.api.openstack.compute.contrib.select_extensions</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>osapi_compute_extension = ['nova.api.openstack.compute.contrib.standard_extensions']</td>
                       <td>(MultiStrOpt) osapi compute extension to load</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>osapi_compute_link_prefix = None</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) Base URL that will be presented to users in links to the OpenStack Compute API</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>osapi_compute_listen = 0.0.0.0</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) The IP address on which the OpenStack API will listen.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>osapi_compute_listen_port = 8774</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) The port on which the OpenStack API will listen.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>osapi_compute_workers = None</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Number of workers for OpenStack API service. The default will be the number of CPUs available.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>osapi_hide_server_address_states = building</td>
                       <td>(ListOpt) List of instance states that should hide network info</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>servicegroup_driver = db</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) The driver for servicegroup service (valid options are: db, zk, mc)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>snapshot_name_template = snapshot-%s</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) Template string to be used to generate snapshot names</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>use_forwarded_for = False</td>
                       <td>(BoolOpt) Treat X-Forwarded-For as the canonical remote address. Only enable this if you have a sanitizing proxy.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                  <th colspan="2">[database]</th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>use_tpool = False</td>
                       <td>(BoolOpt) Enable the experimental use of thread pooling for all DB API calls</td>
              </tr>
       </tbody>
        </table>
        </para>
