<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!-- Warning: Do not edit this file. It is automatically
             generated and your changes will be overwritten.
             The tool to do so lives in the tools directory of this
             repository -->
        <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
        <table rules="all">
          <caption>Description of configuration options for policy</caption>
           <col width="50%"/>
           <col width="50%"/>
           <thead>
              <tr>
                  <th>Configuration option = Default value</th>
                  <th>Description</th>
              </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
              <tr>
                       <td>allow_instance_snapshots = True</td>
                       <td>(BoolOpt) Permit instance snapshot operations.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>allow_migrate_to_same_host = False</td>
                       <td>(BoolOpt) Allow migrate machine to the same host. Useful when testing in single-host environments.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>allow_resize_to_same_host = False</td>
                       <td>(BoolOpt) Allow destination machine to match source for resize. Useful when testing in single-host environments.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>max_age = 0</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) number of seconds between subsequent usage refreshes</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>max_local_block_devices = 3</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Maximum number of devices that will result in a local image being created on the hypervisor node. Setting this to 0 means nova will allow only boot from volume. A negative number means unlimited.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>osapi_compute_unique_server_name_scope = </td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) When set, compute API will consider duplicate hostnames invalid within the specified scope, regardless of case. Should be empty, "project" or "global".</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>osapi_max_limit = 1000</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) the maximum number of items returned in a single response from a collection resource</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>osapi_max_request_body_size = 114688</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) the maximum body size per each osapi request(bytes)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>password_length = 12</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Length of generated instance admin passwords</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>policy_default_rule = default</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) Rule checked when requested rule is not found</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>policy_file = policy.json</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) JSON file representing policy</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>reservation_expire = 86400</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) number of seconds until a reservation expires</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>resize_fs_using_block_device = False</td>
                       <td>(BoolOpt) Attempt to resize the filesystem by accessing the image over a block device. This is done by the host and may not be necessary if the image contains a recent version of cloud-init. Possible mechanisms require the nbd driver (for qcow and raw), or loop (for raw).</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>until_refresh = 0</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) count of reservations until usage is refreshed</td>
              </tr>
       </tbody>
        </table>
        </para>