<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <!-- The tool that generated this table lives in the
     openstack-doc-tools repository. The editions made in
     this file will *not* be lost if you run the script again. -->
  <table rules="all">
    <caption>Description of configuration options for
        <literal>[filter-keystoneauth]</literal> in <filename>proxy-server.conf</filename>
    </caption>
    <col width="50%"/>
    <col width="50%"/>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th>Configuration option = Default value</th>
        <th>Description</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td><option>allow_names_in_acls</option> = <replaceable>true</replaceable></td>
        <td>The backwards compatible behavior can be disabled by setting this
option to False.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>allow_overrides</option> = <replaceable>true</replaceable></td>
        <td>This option allows middleware higher in the WSGI pipeline to override auth
processing, useful for middleware such as tempurl and formpost. If you know
you are not going to use such middleware and you want a bit of extra security,
you can set this to False.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>default_domain_id</option> = <replaceable>default</replaceable></td>
        <td>Name of the default domain. It is identified by its UUID, which by default has the value "default".</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>is_admin</option> = <replaceable>false</replaceable></td>
        <td>If this option is set to True, it allows to give a user whose username is the same as the project name and who has any role in the project access rights elevated to be the same as if the user had one of the operator_roles. Note that the condition compares names rather than
UUIDs. This option is deprecated. It is False by default.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>operator_roles</option> = <replaceable>admin, swiftoperator</replaceable></td>
        <td>Operator role defines the user which is allowed to manage a tenant and create containers or give ACL to others. This parameter may be prefixed with an appropriate
prefix.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>reseller_admin_role</option> = <replaceable>ResellerAdmin</replaceable></td>
        <td>The reseller admin role gives the ability to create and delete accounts.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>reseller_prefix</option> = <replaceable>AUTH</replaceable></td>
        <td>The naming scope for the auth service. Swift</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>service_roles</option> = <replaceable></replaceable></td>
        <td>When present, this option requires that the X-Service-Token header supplies a token from a user who has a role listed in service_roles. This parameter may be prefixed with an appropriate
prefix.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><option>use</option> = <replaceable>egg:swift#keystoneauth</replaceable></td>
        <td>Entry point of paste.deploy in the server</td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</para>
