<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <!-- The tool that generated this table lives in the
     openstack-doc-tools repository. The editions made in
     this file will *not* be lost if you run the script again. -->
  <table rules="all">
    <caption>Description of configuration options for
        <literal>[DEFAULT]</literal> in <literal>proxy-server.conf</literal>
    </caption>
    <col width="50%"/>
    <col width="50%"/>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th>Configuration option = Default value</th>
        <th>Description</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td>admin_key = secret_admin_key</td>
        <td>to use for admin calls that are HMAC signed.  Default is empty, which will disable admin calls to /info. the proxy server.  For most cases, this should be `egg:swift#proxy`. request whenever it has to failover to a handoff node</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>backlog = 4096</td>
        <td>Maximum number of allowed pending TCP connections</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>bind_ip = 0.0.0.0</td>
        <td>IP Address for server to bind to</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>bind_port = 80</td>
        <td>Port for server to bind to</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>bind_timeout = 30</td>
        <td>Seconds to attempt bind before giving up</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>cert_file = /etc/swift/proxy.crt</td>
        <td>to the ssl .crt. This should be enabled for testing purposes only.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>client_timeout = 60</td>
        <td>Timeout to read one chunk from a client external services</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>cors_allow_origin = </td>
        <td>is a list of hosts that are included with any CORS request by default and returned with the Access-Control-Allow-Origin header in addition to what the container has set. to call to setup custom log handlers. for eventlet the proxy server.  For most cases, this should be `egg:swift#proxy`. request whenever it has to failover to a handoff node</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>disallowed_sections = container_quotas, tempurl, bulk_delete.max_failed_deletes</td>
        <td>No help text available for this option.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>eventlet_debug = false</td>
        <td>If true, turn on debug logging for eventlet</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>expiring_objects_account_name = expiring_objects</td>
        <td>No help text available for this option.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>expiring_objects_container_divisor = 86400</td>
        <td>No help text available for this option.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>expose_info = true</td>
        <td>Enables exposing configuration settings via HTTP GET /info.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>key_file = /etc/swift/proxy.key</td>
        <td>to the ssl .key. This should be enabled for testing purposes only.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>log_address = /dev/log</td>
        <td>Location where syslog sends the logs to</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>log_custom_handlers = </td>
        <td>Comma-separated list of functions to call to setup custom log handlers.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>log_facility = LOG_LOCAL0</td>
        <td>Syslog log facility</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>log_headers = false</td>
        <td>No help text available for this option.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>log_level = INFO</td>
        <td>Logging level</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>log_max_line_length = 0</td>
        <td>Caps the length of log lines to the value given; no limit if set to 0, the default.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>log_name = swift</td>
        <td>Label used when logging</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>log_statsd_default_sample_rate = 1.0</td>
        <td>Defines the probability of sending a sample for any given event or
                    timing measurement.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>log_statsd_host = localhost</td>
        <td>If not set, the StatsD feature is disabled.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>log_statsd_metric_prefix = </td>
        <td>Value will be prepended to every metric sent to the StatsD server.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>log_statsd_port = 8125</td>
        <td>Port value for the StatsD server.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>log_statsd_sample_rate_factor = 1.0</td>
        <td>Not recommended to set this to a value less than 1.0, if frequency
                    of logging is too high, tune the
                    log_statsd_default_sample_rate instead.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>log_udp_host = </td>
        <td>If not set, the UDP receiver for syslog is disabled.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>log_udp_port = 514</td>
        <td>Port value for UDP receiver, if enabled.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>max_clients = 1024</td>
        <td>Maximum number of clients one worker can process simultaneously
Lowering the number of clients handled per worker, and raising the
number of workers can lessen the impact that a CPU intensive, or
blocking, request can have on other requests served by the same
worker. If the maximum number of clients is set to one, then a given worker
will not perform another call while processing, allowing
other workers a chance to process it.
</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>swift_dir = /etc/swift</td>
        <td>Swift configuration directory</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>trans_id_suffix = </td>
        <td>No help text available for this option.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>user = swift</td>
        <td>User to run as</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>workers = auto</td>
        <td>a much higher value, one can reduce the impact of slow file system operations in one request from negatively impacting other requests.</td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</para>
