<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<preface xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
    xml:id="openstack_user_guide">
    <title>How can I use an OpenStack cloud?</title>
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <para>As an OpenStack cloud end user, you can provision your own
        resources within the limits set by administrators. You can set
        up access and security for your instances through security
        group rules and keypairs. You can launch and manage instances,
        create and manage volumes, images, and snapshots, and track
        usage. This guide shows you how to interact with a cloud by
        using the <xref linkend="ch_dashboard"/> and <xref
            linkend="ch_cli"/>.</para>
    <para>The dashboard, also known as <link
            xlink:href="https://github.com/openstack/horizon/"
            >horizon</link>, is a Web-based graphical interface that
        enables cloud administrators and end users to manage various
        OpenStack resources and services. .</para>
    <para>The command-line clients let you run simple commands to
        create and manage resources in a cloud and automate tasks by
        using scripts. Each of the core OpenStack projects has its own
        command-line client. </para>
    <para>However, these are not the only ways to interact with
        OpenStack resources and services. After you learn how to use
        the dashboard and the command-line clients, this guide shows
        you how to access the OpenStack APIs indirectly through <link
            xlink:href="http://curl.haxx.se/">cURL</link> commands or
        open SDKs, or directly through the APIs. You can automate
        access or build tools to manage resources and services by
        using the native OpenStack APIs or the EC2 compatibility
        API.</para>
    <para>To use the OpenStack APIs, it helps to be familiar with
        HTTP/1.1, RESTful web services, the OpenStack services, and
        JSON or XML data serialization formats.</para>
<section xml:id="concepts"><title>OpenStack concepts</title>
        <para>Instances are virtual machines that run inside the
            cloud.</para>
        <para>You can launch an instance directly from one of the
            available OpenStack images or from an image that you have
            copied to a persistent volume. The OpenStack Image Service
            provides a pool of images that are accessible to members
            of different projects.</para>
        </section>
</preface>
