<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
    xml:id="how_to_interact_with_openstack">
    <title>How do I use an OpenStack cloud?</title>
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <para>OpenStack cloud users and administrators can launch and
        manage instances, create and manage volumes, create and manage
        images and snapshots, set up cloud access and security, and
        track usage. Cloud administrators can also create and manage
        users and projects. </para>
    <para>You can achieve most of these tasks with the OpenStack
        dashboard or the OpenStack command-line clients. The dashboard
        and the command-line clients are not the only ways to interact
        with OpenStack resources and services. You can automate access
        or build tools to manage resources and services by using the
        native OpenStack APIs or the EC2 compatibility API.</para>
    <para>For each exercise in this guide, you choose one of the
        following methods to complete tasks in the cloud: <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">The OpenStack
                        dashboard</emphasis>. The OpenStack dashboard
                    provides administrators and users a graphical
                    interface to access, provision, and automate
                    cloud-based resources. You can customize the
                    dashboard with your own brand. The dashboard is an
                    extensible web app that allows cloud
                    administrators and users to control their compute,
                    storage, and networking resources. </para>
                <para>As a cloud administrator, the dashboard provides
                    an overall view of the size and state of your
                    cloud. You can create users and projects, assign
                    users to projects and set limits on the resources
                    for those projects. The dashboard provides users a
                    self-service portal to provision their own
                    resources within the limits set by administrators.
                    To see a demo of the dashboard, go to <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.openstack.org/software/openstack-dashboard/"
                        >OpenStack Dashboard</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">The OpenStack command-line
                        clients</emphasis>. We recommend that you use
                    the OpenStack command-line clients to run simple
                    commands that make API calls. These open-source
                    Python clients run on Linux or Mac OS X systems
                    and are easy to learn and use. You can specify a
                        <parameter>debug</parameter> parameter on any
                    client command to show the underlying API request
                    for the command. This is a good way to become
                    familiar with the OpenStack API requests. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Other methods</emphasis>. <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold"><link
                                   xlink:href="http://curl.haxx.se/"
                                   >cURL</link> commands</emphasis>.
                                If you are familiar with or want to
                                learn cURL commands, choose this
                                method. With cURL, you send HTTP
                                requests with embedded API calls from
                                the command line. The cURL examples in
                                this guide include request bodies that
                                are in JSON format. </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Rackspace SDKs. <link
                                   xlink:href="http://developer.rackspace.com"
                                   >Rackspace Developer
                                Center</link>.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>
</chapter>
