<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
    xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
    xml:id="how_to_interact_with_openstack">
    <title>How do I use an OpenStack cloud?</title>
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <para>OpenStack cloud users and administrators can launch and
        manage instances, create and manage volumes, create and manage
        images and snapshots, set up cloud access and security, and
        track usage. Cloud administrators can also create and manage
        users and projects. </para>
    <db:para>As a cloud administrator, the dashboard provides you with
        an overall view of the size and state of your cloud. You can
        create users and projects, assign users to projects and set
        limits on the resources for those projects. As a cloud user,
        the dashboard enables you to provision your own resources
        within the limits set by administrators. </db:para>
    <para>You can achieve most of these tasks with the OpenStack
        dashboard or the OpenStack command-line clients. The dashboard
        and the command-line clients are not the only ways to interact
        with OpenStack resources and services. You can automate access
        or build tools to manage resources and services by using the
        native OpenStack APIs or the EC2 compatibility API.</para>
    <para>This guide helps OpenStack cloud administrators and users
        launch and manage instances and manage volumes. </para>
    <para>For each exercise in this guide, you choose one of the
        following methods to complete tasks in the cloud:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>OpenStack dashboard, also known as <link
                    xlink:href="https://github.com/openstack/horizon/"
                    >horizon</link>, is a Web-based graphical
                interface that enables cloud administrators and users
                to access, provision, and automate cloud-based
                resources.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>OpenStack command-line clients let cloud
                administrators and users run simple commands to manage
                resources and services within a cloud and automate
                tasks by using scripts. Each of the core OpenStack
                projects has its own command-line client. </para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>You can also interact with an OpenStack cloud in the
        following ways:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para><link
                        xlink:href="http://curl.haxx.se/">cURL</link>
                    commands. If you are familiar with or
                want to learn cURL commands, choose this method. With
                cURL, you send HTTP requests with embedded API calls
                from the command line. The cURL examples in this guide
                include request bodies that are in JSON format.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Rackspace SDKs. See <link
                    xlink:href="http://developer.rackspace.com"
                    >Rackspace Developer Center</link>.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</chapter>
