<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
        <!-- Some useful entities borrowed from HTML -->
        <!ENTITY ndash  "&#x2013;">
        <!ENTITY mdash  "&#x2014;">
        <!ENTITY hellip "&#x2026;">
        
        <!-- Useful for describing APIs -->
        <!ENTITY GET    '<command xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">GET</command>'>
        <!ENTITY PUT    '<command xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">PUT</command>'>
        <!ENTITY POST   '<command xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">POST</command>'>
        <!ENTITY DELETE '<command xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">DELETE</command>'>
        
        <!-- Product references -->
        
        <!ENTITY CS 'Cloud Servers'>
<!ENTITY HOST 'dfw.servers.api.rackspacecloud.com'>
<!ENTITY URL 'https://&HOST;/v2/'>
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="novaclient">
    <title>How the nova and supernova Clients Work</title>
    <para>The nova client is an open-source Python client that lets
        you run simple commands to make API v2 calls. This client is
        easy to learn and use. Each nova client command runs cURL
        commands that embed API v2 requests. You can run the nova
        client from a desktop machine or remote system, such as a
        Cloud Server. </para>
    <para>You install the nova client on a Linux distribution or on
        Mac OS X. </para>
    <para>To configure the nova client, you update your bash profile
        to set and export nova environment variables. </para>
    <para>The optional supernova client lets you to use the nova
        client with multiple OpenStack nova environments. For example,
        if you maintain multiple Cloud Servers accounts or call
        different cloud services, you can export a different set of
        environment variables for each environment. Then, when you run
        supernova, you pass a parameter that indicates which
        environment you want to use. </para>
    <para>Though this guide does not explicitly show supernova client
        commands, you can easily modify the examples in this guide for
        supernova. The supernova client commands are identical to the
        nova client commands except that you include the parameter in
        each supernova command that indicates which environment you
        are sourcing. For example, you might run the following
        supernova command to source the
            <parameter>production</parameter> environment and list
        images:</para>
    <programlisting language="bash" role="gutter: false"><prompt>$</prompt> supernova <parameter>production</parameter> image-list</programlisting>
    <para>You install the supernova client through the
            <command>supernova</command> package.</para>
    <para>After you install the client, you must create a supernova
        profile that defines nova environment variables for one or
        more environments.</para>
    <note>
        <para>You can specify a debug parameter on any nova or
            supernova command to show the underlying API request for
            the command. This is a good way to become familiar with
            the API requests. </para>
    </note>
    <para>Rackspace does not maintain the nova and supernova clients,
        which are considered to be software in development. </para>
</section>
