<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section 
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0"
    xml:id="managing-openstack-object-storage-with-swift-cli">
    <title>Managing OpenStack Object Storage with CLI
        Swift</title>
    <para>In the Object Store (swift) project there is a tool that
        can perform a variety of tasks on your storage cluster
        named swift. This client utility can be used for adhoc
        processing, to gather statistics, list items, update
        metadata, upload, download and delete files. It is based
        on the native swift client library client.py.
        Incorporating client.py into swift provides many benefits
        such as seamlessly re-authorizing if the current token
        expires in the middle of processing, retrying operations
        up to five times and a processing concurrency of 10. All
        of these things help make the swift tool robust and great
        for operational use.</para>
    <section xml:id="swift-acls">
        <title>Swift ACLs</title>
        <para>Swift ACLs work with users and accounts. Users have
            roles on accounts - such as '.admin', which allows
            full access to all containers and objects under the
            account. ACLs are set at the container level and
            support lists for read and write access, which are set
            with the X-Container-Read and X-Container-Write header
            respectively.</para>
        <para>The swift client can be used to set the acls, using
            the post subcommand with the option '-r' for the read
            ACL, and '-w' for the write ACL. This example allows
            the user 'testuser' to read objects in the container:
            <programlisting>
        $ swift post -r 'testuser'
        </programlisting>
            This could instead be a list of users.</para>
        <para>If you are using the StaticWeb middleware to allow
            OpenStack Object Storage to serve public web content,
            you should also be aware of the ACL syntax for
            managing allowed referrers. The syntax is '.r:'
            followed by a list of allowed referrers. For example,
            this command allows all referring domains access to
            the object:
            <programlisting>
        $ swift post -r '.r:*'
        </programlisting>
        </para>
    </section>

</section>
