<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="user-requirements-hybrid">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>User requirements</title>
    <para>Hybrid cloud architectures are complex, especially those
       that use heterogeneous cloud platforms. Ensure that design choices
       match requirements so that the benefits outweigh the inherent additional
       complexity and risks.</para>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Business considerations when designing a hybrid
        cloud deployment</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Cost</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>A hybrid cloud architecture involves multiple
                vendors and technical architectures. These
                architectures may be more expensive to deploy and
                maintain. Operational costs can be higher because of
                the need for more sophisticated orchestration and
                brokerage tools than in other architectures. In
                contrast, overall operational costs might be lower by
                virtue of using a cloud brokerage tool to deploy the
                workloads to the most cost effective platform.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Revenue opportunity</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>Revenue opportunities vary based on the intent and use case
                of the cloud. As a commercial, customer-facing product, you
                must consider whether building over multiple platforms makes
                the design more attractive to customers.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Time-to-market</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>One common reason to use cloud platforms is to improve the
                time-to-market of a new product or application. For example,
                using multiple cloud platforms is viable because there is an
                existing investment in several applications. It is faster to
                tie the investments together rather than migrate the
                components and refactoring them to a single platform.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Business or technical diversity</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>Organizations leveraging cloud-based services can
                embrace business diversity and utilize a hybrid cloud
                design to spread their workloads across multiple cloud
                providers. This ensures that no single cloud provider is
                the sole host for an application.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Application momentum</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>Businesses with existing applications may find that it is
                more cost effective to integrate applications on multiple
                cloud platforms than migrating them to a single platform.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <section xml:id="workload-considerations">
      <title>Workload considerations</title>
    <para>A workload can be a single application or a suite of applications
      that work together. It can also be a duplicate set of applications that
      need to run on multiple cloud environments. In a hybrid cloud
      deployment, the same workload often needs to function
      equally well on radically different public and private cloud
      environments. The architecture needs to address these
      potential conflicts, complexity, and platform
      incompatibilities.</para>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Use cases for a hybrid cloud architecture</title>
      <varlistentry>
      <term>Dynamic resource expansion or bursting</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>An application that requires additional resources may suit
                a multiple cloud architecture.
                For example, a retailer needs additional resources
                during the holiday season, but does not want to add private
                cloud resources to meet the peak demand. The user can
                accommodate the increased load by bursting to
                a public cloud for these peak load
                periods. These bursts could be for long or short
                cycles ranging from hourly to yearly.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
      <term>Disaster recovery and business continuity</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>Cheaper storage makes the public
                cloud suitable for maintaining backup applications.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
      <term>Federated hypervisor and instance management</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>Adding self-service, charge back, and transparent delivery of
                the resources from a federated pool can be cost
                effective. In a hybrid cloud environment, this is a
                particularly important consideration. Look for a cloud
                that provides cross-platform hypervisor support and
                robust instance management tools.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
      <term>Application portfolio integration</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>An enterprise cloud delivers efficient application portfolio
                management and deployments by leveraging
                self-service features and rules according to use. Integrating
                existing cloud environments is a common driver when building
                hybrid cloud architectures.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
      <term>Migration scenarios</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>Hybrid cloud architecture enables the migration of
                applications between different clouds.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
      <term>High availability</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>A combination of locations and platforms enables a
                level of availability that is not
                possible with a single platform. This approach increases
                design complexity.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>As running a workload on multiple cloud platforms increases design
        complexity, we recommend first exploring options such as transferring
        workloads across clouds at the application, instance, cloud platform,
        hypervisor, and network levels.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="tools-considerations-hybrid">
      <title>Tools considerations</title>
    <para>Hybrid cloud designs must incorporate tools to facilitate working
        across multiple clouds.</para>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Tool functions</title>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Broker between clouds</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>Brokering software evaluates relative costs between different
                cloud platforms. Cloud Management Platforms (CMP)
                allow the designer to determine the right location for the
                workload based on predetermined criteria.</para>
        </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Facilitate orchestration across the clouds</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>CMPs simplify the migration of application workloads between
                public, private, and hybrid cloud platforms. We recommend
                using cloud orchestration tools for managing a diverse
                portfolio of systems and applications across multiple cloud
                platforms.</para>
        </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="network-considerations-hybrid">
      <title>Network considerations</title>
    <para>It is important to consider the functionality, security, scalability,
        availability, and testability of network when choosing a CMP and cloud
        provider.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Decide on a network framework and
                design minimum functionality tests. This ensures
                testing and functionality persists during and after
                upgrades.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Scalability across multiple cloud providers may
                dictate which underlying network framework you
                choose in different cloud providers. It is important
                to present the network API functions and to
                verify that functionality persists across all cloud
                endpoints chosen.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>High availability implementations vary in
                functionality and design. Examples of some common
                methods are active-hot-standby, active-passive, and
                active-active. Development of high availability and test
                frameworks is necessary to insure understanding of
                functionality and limitations.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Consider the security of data between the client and the
                endpoint, and of traffic that traverses the multiple
                clouds.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="risk-mitigation-management-hybrid">
      <title>Risk mitigation and management considerations</title>
    <para>Hybrid cloud architectures introduce additional risk because
        they are more complex than a single cloud design and may involve
        incompatible components or tools. However, they also reduce
        risk by spreading workloads over multiple providers.</para>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Hybrid cloud risks</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Provider availability or implementation details</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                Business changes can affect provider availability. Likewise,
                changes in a provider's service can disrupt a hybrid cloud
                environment or increase costs.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Differing SLAs</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>Hybrid cloud designs must accommodate differences in SLAs
                between providers, and consider their enforceability.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Security levels</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>Securing multiple cloud
                environments is more complex than securing single
                cloud environments. We recommend addressing concerns at
                the application, network, and cloud platform levels.
                Be aware that each cloud platform approaches security
                differently, and a hybrid cloud design must address and
                compensate for these differences.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Provider API changes</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>Consumers of external clouds rarely have control over
                provider changes to APIs, and changes can break compatibility.
                Using only the most common and basic APIs can minimize
                potential conflicts.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
</section>
