<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="arch-guide-hybrid-operational-considerations">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Operational considerations</title>
    <para>Hybrid cloud deployments present complex operational
        challenges. There are several factors to consider that affect
        the way each cloud is deployed and how users and operators
        will interact with each cloud. Not every cloud provider
        implements infrastructure components the same way which may
        lead to incompatible interactions with workloads or a specific
        Cloud Management Platform (CMP). Different cloud providers may
        also offer different levels of integration with competing
        cloud offerings.</para>
    <para>When selecting a CMP, one of the most important aspects to
        consider is monitoring. Gaining valuable insight into each
        cloud is critical to gaining a holistic view of all involved
        clouds. In choosing an existing CMP, determining whether it
        supports monitoring of all the clouds involved or if
        compatible APIs are available which can be queried for the
        necessary information, is vital. Once all the information
        about each cloud can be gathered and stored in a searchable
        database, proper actions can be taken on that data offline so
        workloads will not be impacted.</para>
    <section xml:id="agility"><title>Agility</title>
    <para>Implementing a hybrid cloud solution can provide application
        availability across disparate cloud environments and
        technologies. This availability enables the deployment to
        survive a complete disaster in any single cloud environment.
        Each cloud should provide the means to quickly spin up new
        instances in the case of capacity issues or complete
        unavailability of a single cloud installation.</para></section>
    <section xml:id="application-readiness-hybrid">
      <title>Application readiness</title>
    <para>It is important to understand the type of application
        workloads that will be deployed across the hybrid cloud
        environment. Enterprise workloads that depend on the
        underlying infrastructure for availability are not designed to
        run on OpenStack. Although these types of applications can run
        on an OpenStack cloud, if the application is not able to
        tolerate infrastructure failures, it is likely to require
        significant operator intervention to recover. Cloud workloads,
        however, are designed with fault tolerance in mind and the SLA
        of the application is not tied to the underlying
        infrastructure. Ideally, cloud applications will be designed
        to recover when entire racks and even data centers full of
        infrastructure experience an outage.</para></section>
    <section xml:id="upgrades">
      <title>Upgrades</title>
    <para>OpenStack is a complex and constantly evolving collection of
        software. Upgrades may be performed to one or more of the
        cloud environments involved. If a public cloud is involved in
        the deployment, predicting upgrades may not be possible. Be
        sure to examine the advertised SLA for any public cloud
        provider being used. Note that at massive scale, even when
        dealing with a cloud that offers an SLA with a high percentage
        of uptime, workloads must be able to recover at short
        notice.</para>
    <para>Similarly, when upgrading private cloud deployments, care
        must be taken to minimize disruption by making incremental
        changes and providing a facility to either rollback or
        continue to roll forward when using a continuous delivery
        model.</para>
    <para>Another consideration is upgrades to the CMP which may need
        to be completed in coordination with any of the hybrid cloud
        upgrades. This may be necessary whenever API changes are made
        in one of the cloud solutions in use to support the new
        functionality.</para></section>
    <section xml:id="network-operation-center-noc">
      <title>Network Operation Center (NOC)</title>
    <para>When planning the Network Operation Center for a hybrid
        cloud environment, it is important to recognize where control
        over each piece of infrastructure resides. If a significant
        portion of the cloud is on externally managed systems, be
        prepared for situations in which it may not be possible to
        make changes at all or at the most convenient time.
        Additionally, situations of conflict may arise in which
        multiple providers have differing points of view on the way
        infrastructure must be managed and exposed. This can lead to
        delays in root cause and analysis where each insists the blame
        lies with the other provider.</para>
    <para>It is important to ensure that the structure put in place
        enables connection of the networking of both clouds to form an
        integrated system, keeping in mind the state of handoffs.
        These handoffs must both be as reliable as possible and
        include as little latency as possible to ensure the best
        performance of the overall system.</para></section>
    <section xml:id="maintainability">
      <title>Maintainability</title>
    <para>Operating hybrid clouds is a situation in which there is a
        greater reliance on third party systems and processes. As a
        result of a lack of control of various pieces of a hybrid
        cloud environment, it is not necessarily possible to guarantee
        proper maintenance of the overall system. Instead, the user
        must be prepared to abandon workloads and spin them up again
        in an improved state. Having a hybrid cloud deployment does,
        however, provide agility for these situations by allowing the
        migration of workloads to alternative clouds in response to
        cloud-specific issues.</para></section>
</section>
