<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="arch-guide-hybrid-operational-considerations">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Operational considerations</title>
    <para>Hybrid cloud deployments present complex operational
        challenges. There are several factors to consider that affect
        the way each cloud is deployed and how users and operators
        will interact with each cloud. Each cloud provider implements
        infrastructure components differently. This can lead to incompatible
        interactions with workloads, or a specific Cloud Management
        Platform (CMP). Different cloud providers may
        also offer different levels of integration with competing
        cloud offerings.</para>
    <para>Monitoring is an important aspect to consider when selecting
        a CMP. Gaining valuable insight into each
        cloud is critical to gaining a holistic view of all involved
        clouds. It is vital to determine whether an existing CMP supports
        monitoring of all the clouds involved, or if compatible APIs
        are available to be queried for necessary information.
        Gather all the information about each cloud, you can now take
        appropriate actions on the offline data to avoid impacting workloads.</para>

    <section xml:id="agility">
      <title>Agility</title>
    <para>The implemention of a hybrid cloud solution provides application
        availability across different cloud environments and
        technologies. This availability enables the deployment to
        survive disaster in any single cloud environment.
        Each cloud should provide the means to quickly spin up new
        instances in the case of capacity issues or complete
        unavailability of a single cloud installation.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="application-readiness-hybrid">
      <title>Application readiness</title>
    <para>It is important to understand the type of application
        workload that is to be deployed across a hybrid cloud environment.
        Enterprise workloads that depend on the
        underlying infrastructure for availability are not designed to
        run on OpenStack. Although these types of applications can run
        on an OpenStack cloud, if the application is not able to
        tolerate infrastructure failures, it is likely to require
        significant operator intervention to recover. However, cloud
        workloads are designed to handle fault tolerance. The SLA
        of the application is not tied to the underlying
        infrastructure. Ideally, cloud applications are designed
        to recover when entire racks and even data centers full of
        infrastructure experience an outage.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="upgrades">
      <title>Upgrades</title>
    <para>If the deployment includes a public cloud, predicting
        upgrades may not be possible. Examine the advertised SLA for
        any public cloud provider being used.</para>
      <note>
        <para>At massive scale, even when
        dealing with a cloud that offers an SLA with a high percentage
        of uptime, workloads must be able to recover at short
        notice.</para>
      </note>
    <para>When upgrading private cloud deployments, care
        must be taken to minimize disruption by making incremental
        changes and providing a facility to either rollback or
        continue to roll forward when using a continuous delivery
        model.</para>
    <para>Upgrades to the CMP may need to be completed in coordination
        with any of the hybrid cloud upgrades. This is necessary
        whenever API changes are made.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="network-operation-center-noc">
      <title>Network Operation Center</title>
    <para>It is important to recognize control over infrastructure particulates
        when planning the Network Operation Center (NOC)
        for a hybrid cloud environment. If a significant
        portion of the cloud is on externally managed systems,
        prepare for situations where it may not be possible to
        make changes.
        Additionally, situations of conflict may arise in which
        multiple providers have differing points of view on the way
        infrastructure must be managed and exposed. This can lead to
        delays in root cause and analysis where each insists the blame
        lies with the other provider.</para>
    <para>It is important to ensure that the structure put in place
        enables connection of the networking of both clouds to form an
        integrated system, keeping in mind the state of handoffs.
        These handoffs must both be as reliable as possible and
        include as little latency as possible to ensure the best
        performance of the overall system.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="maintainability">
      <title>Maintainability</title>
    <para>Operating hybrid clouds is a situation in which there is a
        greater reliance on third party systems and processes. As a
        result of a lack of control of various pieces of a hybrid
        cloud environment, it is not possible to guarantee
        proper maintenance of the overall system. Instead, the user
        must be prepared to abandon workloads and spin them up again
        in an improved state. Having a hybrid cloud deployment does,
        however, provide agility for these situations by allowing the
        migration of workloads to alternative clouds in response to
        cloud-specific issues.</para>
     </section>
</section>
