<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0"
    xml:id="arch-guide-intro-storage-focus">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>Cloud storage is a model of data storage where digital data
        is stored in logical pools and physical storage that spans
        across multiple servers and locations. Cloud storage commonly
        refers to a hosted object storage service, however the term
        has extended to include other types of data storage that are
        available as a service, for example block storage.</para>
    <para>Cloud storage is based on virtualized infrastructure and
        resembles broader cloud computing in terms of accessible
        interfaces, elasticity, scalability, multi-tenancy, and
        metered resources. Cloud storage services can be utilized from
        an off-premises service or deployed on-premises.</para>
    <para>Cloud storage is made up of many distributed, yet still
        synonymous resources, and is often referred to as integrated
        storage clouds. Cloud storage is highly fault tolerant through
        redundancy and the distribution of data. It is highly durable
        through the creation of versioned copies, and can be
        consistent with regard to data replicas.</para>
    <para>At a certain scale, management of data operations can become
        a resource intensive process to an organization. Hierarchical
        storage management (HSM) systems and data grids can help
        annotate and report a baseline data valuation to make
        intelligent decisions and automate data decisions. HSM allows
        for automating tiering and movement, as well as orchestration
        of data operations. A data grid is an architecture, or set of
        services evolving technology, that brings together sets of
        services allowing users to manage large data sets.</para>
    <para>Examples of applications that can be deployed with cloud
        storage characteristics are:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Active archive, backups and hierarchical storage
                management.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>General content storage and synchronization. An
                example of this is private dropbox.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Data analytics with parallel file systems.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Unstructured data store for services. For example,
                social media back-end storage.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Persistent block storage.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Operating system and application image store.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Media streaming.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Databases.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Content distribution.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Cloud storage peering.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</section>