<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="user-requirements-storage-focus">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>User Requirements</title>
    <para>Storage-focused clouds are defined by their requirements for
        data including, but not limited to, performance, access
        patterns, and data structures. A balance between cost and user
        requirements dictate what methods and technologies will be
        used in a cloud architecture.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Cost: The user pays only for the storage they
                actually use. This limit typically reflects average
                user consumption during a month. This does not mean
                that cloud storage is less expensive, only that it
                incurs operating expenses rather the capital expenses.
                From a business perspective, it should be beneficial
                for the solution to scale properly to prevent the
                up-front purchase of a large amount of storage that
                goes underutilized.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Legal requirements: Multiple jurisdictions have
                legislative and regulatory requirements governing the
                storage and management of data in cloud environments.
                Common areas of regulation include data retention
                policies and data ownership policies.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <section xml:id="legal-requirements-storage-focus"><title>Legal Requirements</title>
    <para>Many jurisdictions have legislative and regulatory
        requirements governing the storage and management of data in
        cloud environments. Common areas of regulation include:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Data retention: Policies ensuring storage of
                persistent data and records management to meet data
                archival requirements.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Data ownership: Policies governing the possession
                and responsibility for data.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Data sovereignty: Policies governing the storage of
                data in foreign countries or otherwise separate
                jurisdictions.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Data compliance: Policies governing types of
                information that are required to reside in certain
                locations due to regular issues and cannot reside in
                other locations for the same reason.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Examples of such legal frameworks include the data
        protection framework of the European Union
        (http://ec.europa.eu/justice/data-protection/ ) and the
        requirements of the Financial Industry Regulatory Authority
        (http://www.finra.org/Industry/Regulation/FINRARules/ ) in the
        United States. Consult a local regulatory body for more
        information.</para></section>
    <section xml:id="technical-requirements-storage-focus"><title>Technical Requirements</title>
    <para>The following are some technical requirements that could be
        incorporated into the architecture design.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Storage Proximity: In order to provide high
                performance or large amounts of storage space the
                design may have to accommodate storage that is each of
                the hypervisors or served from a central storage
                device.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Performance: To boost performance the organization
                may want to make use of different technologies to
                cache disk activity.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Availability: Specific requirements regarding
                availability will influence the technology used to
                store and protect data. These requirements will be
                influence the cost and solution that will be
                implemented.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Security: Data will need to be protected both in
                transit and at rest.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></section>
</section>