<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0"
    xml:id="technical-considerations-storage-focus">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Technical Considerations</title>
    <para>Some of the key technical considerations that are critical
        to a storage focused OpenStack design architecture
        include:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>I-O requirements: I-O performance requirements need
                to be researched and modeled before deciding on a
                final storage framework. Running benchmarks for I-O
                performance will help provide a baseline for expected
                performance levels. If these tests include details,
                for example, object size in an object storage system
                or varying capacity levels for both object storage and
                block storage, then the resulting data can help model
                behavior and results during different workloads.
                Running scripted smaller benchmarks during the
                life cycle of the architecture helps record the system
                health at different points in time. The data from
                these scripted benchmarks will assist in future
                scoping and gaining a deeper understanding of an
                organization's needs.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Scale: The scale of the storage solution in a
                storage focused OpenStack architecture design is
                driven both by initial requirements, including IOPS,
                capacity, and bandwidth, as well as future needs.
                Planning capacity based on projected needs over the
                course of a budget cycle is important for a design.
                Ideally, the chosen architecture should balance cost
                and capacity while also allowing enough flexibility
                for new technologies and methods to be implemented as
                they become available.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Security: Security design around data has multiple
                points of focus that vary depending on SLAs, legal
                requirements, industry regulations, and certifications
                needed for systems or people. HIPPA, ISO9000, and SOX
                compliance should be considered based on the type of
                data. Levels of access control can be important for
                certain organizations.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>OpenStack compatibility: Interoperability and
                integration with OpenStack can be paramount in
                deciding on a storage hardware and storage management
                platform. Interoperability and integration includes
                factors such as OpenStack Cinder interoperability,
                OpenStack Swift compatibility, and hypervisor
                compatibility (which affects the ability to use
                storage for ephemeral instance storage).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Storage management: A range of storage
                management-related considerations must be addressed in
                the design of a storage focused OpenStack cloud. These
                considerations include, but are not limited to, backup
                strategy (and restore strategy, since a backup that
                can not be restored is useless), data
                valuation-hierarchical storage management, retention
                strategy, data placement, and workflow
                automation.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Data Grids: Data grids can be helpful in
                deterministically answering questions around data
                valuation. A fundamental challenge of today’s
                information sciences is determining which data is
                worth keeping, on what tier of access and performance
                should it reside, and how long should it remain in a
                storage system. Data grids improve decision making
                through correlation of access patterns, ownership, and
                business-unit revenue with other metadata values to
                deliver actionable information about data.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Strive to build a flexible design that is based on a
        industry standard core. One way of accomplishing this might be
        through the use of different back ends serving different use
        cases.</para>
</section>