<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="ch_creating_images_automatically">
    <title>Tool support for image creation</title>
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <para>There are several tools that are designed to automate image
        creation.</para>
    <section xml:id="oz">
        <title>Oz</title>
        <para><link xlink:href="https://github.com/clalancette/oz/wiki"
                >Oz</link> is a command-line tool that automates the process of
            creating a virtual machine image file. Oz is a Python app that
            interacts with KVM to step through the process of installing a
            virtual machine. It uses a predefined set of kickstart (Red
            Hat-based systems) and preseed files (Debian-based systems) for
            operating systems that it supports, and it can also be used to
            create Microsoft Windows images. On Fedora, install Oz with yum:<screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>yum install oz</userinput></screen><note>
                <para>As of this writing, there are no Oz packages for Ubuntu,
                    so you will need to either install from source or build your
                    own .deb file.</para>
            </note></para>
        <para>A full treatment of Oz is beyond the scope of this document, but
            we will provide an example. You can find additional examples of Oz
            template files on GitHub at <link
                xlink:href="https://github.com/rackerjoe/oz-image-build/tree/master/templates"
                >rackerjoe/oz-image-build/templates</link>. Here's how you would
            create a CentOS 6.4 image with Oz.</para>
        <para>Create a template file (we'll call it
                <filename>centos64.tdl</filename>) with the following contents.
            The only entry you will need to change is the
                <literal>&lt;rootpw></literal>
            contents.<programlisting language="xml">&lt;template>
  &lt;name>centos64&lt;/name>
  &lt;os>
    &lt;name>CentOS-6&lt;/name>
    &lt;version>4&lt;/version>
    &lt;arch>x86_64&lt;/arch>
    &lt;install type='iso'>
      &lt;iso>http://mirror.rackspace.com/CentOS/6/isos/x86_64/CentOS-6.4-x86_64-bin-DVD1.iso&lt;/iso>
    &lt;/install>
    &lt;rootpw>CHANGE THIS TO YOUR ROOT PASSWORD&lt;/rootpw>
  &lt;/os>
  &lt;description>CentOS 6.4 x86_64&lt;/description>
  &lt;repositories>
    &lt;repository name='epel-6'>
      &lt;url>http://download.fedoraproject.org/pub/epel/6/$basearch&lt;/url>
      &lt;signed>no&lt;/signed>
    &lt;/repository>
  &lt;/repositories>
  &lt;packages>
    &lt;package name='epel-release'/>
    &lt;package name='cloud-utils'/>
    &lt;package name='cloud-init'/>
  &lt;/packages>
  &lt;commands>
    &lt;command name='update'>
yum -y update
yum clean all
sed -i '/^HWADDR/d' /etc/sysconfig/network-scripts/ifcfg-eth0
echo -n > /etc/udev/rules.d/70-persistent-net.rules
echo -n > /lib/udev/rules.d/75-persistent-net-generator.rules
    &lt;/command>
  &lt;/commands>
&lt;/template></programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>This Oz template specifies where to download the Centos 6.4
            install ISO. Oz will use the version information to identify which
            kickstart file to use. In this case, it will be <link
                xlink:href="https://github.com/clalancette/oz/blob/master/oz/auto/RHEL6.auto"
                >RHEL6.auto</link>. It adds EPEL as a repository and install the
                <literal>epel-release</literal>, <literal>cloud-utils</literal>,
            and <literal>cloud-init</literal> packages, as specified in the
                <literal>packages</literal> section of the file.</para>
        <para>After Oz does the initial OS install using the kickstart file, it
            updates the image's install packages with <command>yum
                update</command>. It also removes any reference to the eth0
            device that libvirt creates while Oz does the customizing, as
            specified in the <literal>command</literal> section of the XML
            file.</para>
        <para>To run this, do, as root:</para>
        <para><screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>oz-install -d3 -u centos64.tdl -x centos64-libvirt.xml</userinput></screen><itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The <literal>-d3</literal> flag tells Oz to show
                        status information as it runs.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The <literal>-u</literal> tells Oz to do the
                        customization (install extra packages, run the commands)
                        once it does the initial install.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The <literal>-x &lt;filename></literal> flag tells Oz
                        what filename to use to write out a libvirt XML file
                        (otherwise it will default to something like
                            <filename>centos64Apr_03_2013-12:39:42</filename>).</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>If you leave out the <literal>-u</literal> flag, or
            you want to edit the file to do additional customizations, you can
            use the <command>oz-customize</command> command, using the libvirt
            XML file that <command>oz-install</command> creates. For example:
            <screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>oz-customize -d3 centos64.tdl centos64-libvirt.xml</userinput></screen>
            Oz will invoke libvirt to boot the image inside of KVM, then Oz will
            ssh into the instance and perform the customizations.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="vmbuilder">
        <title>VMBuilder</title>
        <para><link xlink:href="https://launchpad.net/vmbuilder"
                >VMBuilder</link> (Virtual Machine Builder) is a
            command-line tool that creates virtual machine images for
            different hypervisors. The version of VMBuilder that ships
            with Ubuntu can only create Ubuntu virtual machine guests.
            The version of VMBuilder that ships with Debian can create
            Ubuntu and Debian virtual machine guests.</para>
        <para>The <link
                xlink:href="https://help.ubuntu.com/12.04/serverguide/jeos-and-vmbuilder.html"
                    ><citetitle>Ubuntu Server Guide</citetitle></link>
            has documentation on how to use VMBuilder to create an
            Ubuntu image.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="boxgrinder">
        <title>BoxGrinder</title>
        <para>
            <link xlink:href="http://boxgrinder.org/"
                >BoxGrinder</link> is another tool for creating
            virtual machine images, which it calls appliances.
            BoxGrinder can create Fedora, Red Hat Enterprise Linux, or
            CentOS images. BoxGrinder is currently only supported on
            Fedora.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="veewee">
        <title>VeeWee</title>
        <para><link xlink:href="https://github.com/jedi4ever/veewee">
                VeeWee</link> is often used to build <link
                xlink:href="http://vagrantup.com">Vagrant</link>
            boxes, but it can also be used to build KVM images.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="packer">
        <title>Packer</title>
        <para><link xlink:href="http://www.packer.io/">
                Packer</link> is a tool for creating machine images for multiple platforms
                from a single source configuration.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="imagefactory">
        <title>imagefactory</title>
        <para><link xlink:href="http://imgfac.org/"
                >imagefactory</link> is a newer tool designed to
            automate the building, converting, and uploading images to
            different cloud providers. It uses Oz as its back-end and
            includes support for OpenStack-based clouds.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="susestudio">
        <title>SUSE Studio</title>
        <para><link xlink:href="http://susestudio.com">SUSE
                Studio</link> is a web application for building and
            testing software applications in a web browser. It
            supports the creation of physical, virtual or cloud-based
            applications and includes support for building images for
            OpenStack based clouds using SUSE Linux Enterprise and
            openSUSE as distributions.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
