<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!-- Some useful entities borrowed from HTML -->
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="ch_openstack_images">
    <title>OpenStack Linux image requirements</title>
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <para>For a Linux-based image to have full functionality in an
        OpenStack Compute cloud, there are a few requirements. For
        some of these, the requirement can be fulfilled by installing
        the <link
            xlink:href="https://cloudinit.readthedocs.org/en/latest/"
                ><package>cloud-init</package></link> package. Read
        this section before you create your own image to be sure that
        the image supports the OpenStack features that you plan on
        using.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Disk partitions and resize root partition on boot
                    (<package>cloud-init</package>)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>No hard-coded MAC address information</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>SSH server running</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Disable firewall</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Access instance using ssh public key
                    (<package>cloud-init</package>)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Process user data and other metadata
                    (<package>cloud-init</package>)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Paravirtualized Xen support in Linux kernel (Xen
                hypervisor only with Linux kernel version &lt;
                3.0)</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <section xml:id="support-resizing">
        <title>Disk partitions and resize root partition on boot
            (cloud-init)</title>
        <para>When you create a Linux image, you must decide how to
            partition the disks. The choice of partition method can
            affect the resizing functionality, as described in the
            following sections.</para>
        <para>The size of the disk in a virtual machine image is
            determined when you initially create the image. However,
            OpenStack lets you launch instances with different size
            drives by specifying different flavors. For example, if
            your image was created with a 5&nbsp;GB disk, and you
            launch an instance with a flavor of
                <literal>m1.small</literal>. The resulting virtual
            machine instance has, by default, a primary disk size of
            10&nbsp;GB. When the disk for an instance is resized up,
            zeros are just added to the end.</para>
        <para>Your image must be able to resize its partitions on boot
            to match the size requested by the user. Otherwise, after
            the instance boots, you must manually resize the
            partitions to access the additional storage to which you
            have access when the disk size associated with the flavor
            exceeds the disk size with which your image was
            created.</para>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Xen: 1 ext3/ext4 partition (no LVM, no /boot, no
                swap)</title>
            <para>If you use the OpenStack XenAPI driver, the Compute
                service automatically adjusts the partition and file
                system for your instance on boot. Automatic resize
                occurs if the following conditions are all
                true:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>auto_disk_config=True</literal> is
                        set as a property on the image in the image
                        registry.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The disk on the image has only one
                        partition.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The file system on the one partition is ext3
                        or ext4.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Therefore, if you use Xen, we recommend that when
                you create your images, you create a single ext3 or
                ext4 partition (not managed by LVM). Otherwise, read
                on.</para>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Non-Xen with cloud-init/cloud-tools: One ext3/ext4
                partition (no LVM, no /boot, no swap)</title>
            <para>You must configure these items for your
                image:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The partition table for the image describes
                        the original size of the image</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The file system for the image fills the
                        original size of the image</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Then, during the boot process, you must:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Modify the partition table to make it aware
                        of the additional space:</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>If you do not use LVM, you must
                                modify the table to extend the
                                existing root partition to encompass
                                this additional space.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>If you use LVM, you can add a new
                                LVM entry to the partition table,
                                create a new LVM physical volume, add
                                it to the volume group, and extend the
                                logical partition with the root
                                volume.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Resize the root volume file system.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>The simplest way to support this in your image is to
                install the <link
                    xlink:href="https://launchpad.net/cloud-utils"
                    >cloud-utils</link> package (contains the
                    <command>growpart</command> tool for extending
                partitions), the <link
                    xlink:href="https://launchpad.net/cloud-initramfs-tools"
                    >cloud-initramfs-tools</link> package (which
                supports resizing root partition on the first boot),
                and the <link
                    xlink:href="https://launchpad.net/cloud-init"
                        ><package>cloud-init</package></link> package
                into your image. With these installed, the image
                performs the root partition resize on boot. For
                example, in the <filename>/etc/rc.local</filename>
                file. These packages are in the Ubuntu and Debian
                package repository, as well as the EPEL repository
                (for Fedora/RHEL/CentOS/Scientific Linux
                guests).</para>
            <para>If you cannot install
                    <literal>cloud-initramfs-tools</literal>, Robert
                Plestenjak has a github project called <link
                    xlink:href="https://github.com/flegmatik/linux-rootfs-resize"
                    >linux-rootfs-resize</link> that contains scripts
                that update a ramdisk by using
                    <command>growpart</command> so that the image
                resizes properly on boot.</para>
            <para>If you can install the cloud-utils and
                    <package>cloud-init</package> packages, we
                recommend that when you create your images, you create
                a single ext3 or ext4 partition (not managed by
                LVM).</para>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Non-Xen without
                    <package>cloud-init</package>/<package>cloud-tools</package>:
                LVM</title>
            <para>If you cannot install <package>cloud-init</package>
                and <package>cloud-tools</package> inside of your
                guest, and you want to support resize, you must write
                a script that your image runs on boot to modify the
                partition table. In this case, we recommend using LVM
                to manage your partitions. Due to a limitation in the
                Linux kernel (as of this writing), you cannot modify a
                partition table of a raw disk that has partitions
                currently mounted, but you can do this for LVM.</para>
            <para>Your script must do something like the following:<orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Detect if any additional space is
                            available on the disk. For example, parse
                            the output of <command>parted /dev/sda
                                --script "print
                            free"</command>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Create a new LVM partition with the
                            additional space. For example,
                                <command>parted /dev/sda --script
                                "mkpart lvm ..."</command>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Create a new physical volume. For
                            example, <command>pvcreate
                                   /dev/<replaceable>sda6</replaceable></command>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Extend the volume group with this
                            physical partition. For example,
                                <command>vgextend
                                   <replaceable>vg00</replaceable>
                                   /dev/<replaceable>sda6</replaceable></command>.)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Extend the logical volume contained the
                            root partition by the amount of space. For
                            example, <command>lvextend
                                   /dev/mapper/<replaceable>node-root</replaceable>
                                   /dev/<replaceable>sda6</replaceable></command>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Resize the root file system. For
                            example, <command>resize2fs
                                   /dev/mapper/<replaceable>node-root</replaceable></command>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist></para>
            <para>You do not need a <filename>/boot</filename>
                partition unless your image is an older Linux
                distribution that requires that
                    <filename>/boot</filename> is not managed by LVM.</para>
        </simplesect>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="mac-adddress">
        <title>No hard-coded MAC address information</title>
        <para>You must remove the network persistence rules in the
            image because they cause the network interface in the
            instance to come up as an interface other than eth0. This
            is because your image has a record of the MAC address of
            the network interface card when it was first installed,
            and this MAC address is different each time that the
            instance boots. You should alter the following
            files:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Replace
                        <filename>/etc/udev/rules.d/70-persistent-net.rules</filename>
                    with an empty file (contains network persistence
                    rules, including MAC address)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Replace
                        <filename>/lib/udev/rules.d/75-persistent-net-generator.rules</filename>
                    with an empty file (this generates the file
                    above)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Remove the HWADDR line from
                        <filename>/etc/sysconfig/network-scripts/ifcfg-eth0</filename>
                    on Fedora-based images</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <note>
            <para>If you delete the network persistent rules files,
                you may get a udev kernel warning at boot time, which
                is why we recommend replacing them with empty files
                instead.</para>
        </note>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ensure-ssh-server">
        <title>Ensure ssh server runs</title>
        <para>You must install an ssh server into the image and ensure
            that it starts up on boot, or you cannot connect to your
            instance by using ssh when it boots inside of OpenStack.
            This package is typically called
                <literal>openssh-server</literal>.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="disable-firewall">
        <title>Disable firewall</title>
        <para>In general, we recommend that you disable any firewalls
            inside of your image and use OpenStack security groups to
            restrict access to instances. The reason is that having a
            firewall installed on your instance can make it more
            difficult to troubleshoot networking issues if you cannot
            connect to your instance.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ssh-public-key">
        <title>Access instance by using ssh public key
            (cloud-init)</title>
        <para>The typical way that users access virtual machines
            running on OpenStack is to ssh using public key
            authentication. For this to work, your virtual machine
            image must be configured to download the ssh public key
            from the OpenStack metadata service or config drive, at
            boot time.</para>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Use <package>cloud-init</package> to fetch the
                public key</title>
            <para>The <package>cloud-init</package> package
                automatically fetches the public key from the metadata
                server and places the key in an account. The account
                varies by distribution. On Ubuntu-based virtual
                machines, the account is called
                    <literal>ubuntu</literal>. On Fedora-based virtual
                machines, the account is called
                    <literal>ec2-user</literal>.</para>
            <para>You can change the name of the account used by
                    <package>cloud-init</package> by editing the
                    <filename>/etc/cloud/cloud.cfg</filename> file and
                adding a line with a different user. For example, to
                configure <package>cloud-init</package> to put the key
                in an account named <literal>admin</literal>, edit the
                configuration file so it has the line:</para>
            <programlisting>user: admin</programlisting>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Write a custom script to fetch the public
                key</title>
            <para>If you are unable or unwilling to install
                    <package>cloud-init</package> inside the guest,
                you can write a custom script to fetch the public key
                and add it to a user account.</para>
            <para>To fetch the ssh public key and add it to the root
                account, edit the <filename>/etc/rc.local</filename>
                file and add the following lines before the line
                “touch /var/lock/subsys/local”. This code fragment is
                taken from the <link
                    xlink:href="https://github.com/rackerjoe/oz-image-build/blob/master/templates/centos60_x86_64.tdl"
                    >rackerjoe oz-image-build CentOS 6
                template</link>.</para>
            <programlisting language="bash">if [ ! -d /root/.ssh ]; then
  mkdir -p /root/.ssh
  chmod 700 /root/.ssh
fi

# Fetch public key using HTTP
ATTEMPTS=30
FAILED=0
while [ ! -f /root/.ssh/authorized_keys ]; do
  curl -f http://169.254.169.254/latest/meta-data/public-keys/0/openssh-key > /tmp/metadata-key 2>/dev/null
  if [ $? -eq 0 ]; then
    cat /tmp/metadata-key >> /root/.ssh/authorized_keys
    chmod 0600 /root/.ssh/authorized_keys
    restorecon /root/.ssh/authorized_keys
    rm -f /tmp/metadata-key
    echo "Successfully retrieved public key from instance metadata"
    echo "*****************"
    echo "AUTHORIZED KEYS"
    echo "*****************"
    cat /root/.ssh/authorized_keys
    echo "*****************"
  else
    FAILED=`expr $FAILED + 1`
    if [ $FAILED -ge $ATTEMPTS ]; then
      echo "Failed to retrieve public key from instance metadata after $FAILED attempts, quitting"
      break
    fi
      echo "Could not retrieve public key from instance metadata (attempt #$FAILED/$ATTEMPTS), retrying in 5 seconds..."
      sleep 5
  fi
done</programlisting>
            <note>
                <para>Some VNC clients replace : (colon) with ;
                    (semicolon) and _ (underscore) with - (hyphen). If
                    editing a file over a VNC session, make sure it's
                    http: not http; and authorized_keys not
                    authorized-keys.</para>
            </note>


        </simplesect>

    </section>
    <section xml:id="metadata">
        <title>Process user data and other metadata
            (cloud-init)</title>
        <para>In addition to the ssh public key, an image might need
            additional information from OpenStack, such as <link
                xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/user-guide/content/user-data.html"
                >user data</link> that the user submitted when
            requesting the image. For example, you might want to set
            the host name of the instance when it is booted. Or, you
            might wish to configure your image so that it executes
            user data content as a script on boot.</para>
        <para>This information is accessible through the metadata
            service or the <link
                xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/user-guide/content/config-drive.html"
                >config drive</link>. As the OpenStack metadata
            service is compatible with version 2009-04-04 of the
            Amazon EC2 metadata service, consult the Amazon EC2
            documentation on <link
                xlink:href="http://docs.amazonwebservices.com/AWSEC2/2009-04-04/UserGuide/AESDG-chapter-instancedata.html"
                >Using Instance Metadata</link> for details on how to
            retrieve user data.</para>

        <para>The easiest way to support this type of functionality is
            to install the <package>cloud-init</package> package into
            your image, which is configured by default to treat user
            data as an executable script, and sets the host
            name.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="write-to-console">
        <title>Ensure image writes boot log to console</title>
        <para>You must configure the image so that the kernel writes
            the boot log to the <literal>ttyS0</literal> device. In
            particular, the <literal>console=ttyS0</literal> argument
            must be passed to the kernel on boot.</para>
        <para>If your image uses grub2 as the boot loader, there
            should be a line in the grub configuration file. For
            example, <filename>/boot/grub/grub.cfg</filename>, which
            looks something like this:</para>
        <programlisting>linux /boot/vmlinuz-3.2.0-49-virtual root=UUID=6d2231e4-0975-4f35-a94f-56738c1a8150 ro console=ttyS0</programlisting>
        <para>If <literal>console=ttyS0</literal> does not appear, you
            must modify your grub configuration. In general, you
            should not update the <filename>grub.cfg</filename>
            directly, since it is automatically generated. Instead,
            you should edit <filename>/etc/default/grub</filename> and
            modify the value of the
                <literal>GRUB_CMDLINE_LINUX_DEFAULT</literal>
            variable:
            <programlisting language="bash">GRUB_CMDLINE_LINUX_DEFAULT="console=ttyS0"</programlisting></para>
        <para>Next, update the grub configuration. On Debian-based
            operating-systems such as Ubuntu,
            do:<screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>sudo update-grub</userinput></screen></para>
        <para>On Fedora-based systems such as RHEL and CentOS,
            do:<screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>sudo grub2-mkconfig -o /boot/grub2/grub.cfg</userinput></screen></para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="image-xen-pv">
        <title>Paravirtualized Xen support in the kernel (Xen
            hypervisor only)</title>
        <para>Prior to Linux kernel version 3.0, the mainline branch
            of the Linux kernel did not have support paravirtualized
            Xen virtual machine instances (what Xen calls DomU
            guests). If you are running the Xen hypervisor with
            paravirtualization, and you want to create an image for an
            older Linux distribution that has a pre 3.0 kernel, you
            must ensure that the image boots a kernel that has been
            compiled with Xen support.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="image-cache-management">
        <title>Manage the image cache</title>
        <para>Use options in <filename>nova.conf</filename> to control
            whether, and for how long, unused base images are stored
            in <filename>/var/lib/nova/instances/_base/</filename>. If
            you have configured live migration of instances, all your
            compute nodes share one common
                <filename>/var/lib/nova/instances/</filename>
            directory.</para>
        <para>For information about libvirt images in OpenStack, see
                <link
                xlink:href="http://www.pixelbeat.org/docs/openstack_libvirt_images/"
                >The life of an OpenStack libvirt image from Pádraig
                Brady</link>.</para>
        <table rules="all">
            <caption>Image cache management configuration
                options</caption>
            <col width="50%"/>
            <col width="50%"/>
            <thead>
                <tr>
                    <td>Configuration option=Default value</td>
                    <td>(Type) Description</td>
                </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
                <tr>
                    <td>preallocate_images=none</td>
                    <td><para>(StrOpt) VM image preallocation
                            mode:</para><itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para><literal>none</literal>. No
                                   storage provisioning occurs up
                                   front.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para><literal>space</literal>.
                                   Storage is fully allocated at
                                   instance start. The
                                   <literal>$instance_dir/</literal>
                                   images are <link
                                   xlink:href="http://www.kernel.org/doc/man-pages/online/pages/man2/fallocate.2.html"
                                   >fallocate</link>d to immediately
                                   determine if enough space is
                                   available, and to possibly improve
                                   VM I/O performance due to ongoing
                                   allocation avoidance, and better
                                   locality of block
                                   allocations.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>remove_unused_base_images=True</td>
                    <td>(BoolOpt) Should unused base images be
                        removed? When set to True, the interval at
                        which base images are removed are set with the
                        following two settings. If set to False base
                        images are never removed by Compute.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>remove_unused_original_minimum_age_seconds=86400</td>
                    <td>(IntOpt) Unused unresized base images younger
                        than this are not removed. Default is 86400
                        seconds, or 24 hours.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>remove_unused_resized_minimum_age_seconds=3600</td>
                    <td>(IntOpt) Unused resized base images younger
                        than this are not removed. Default is 3600
                        seconds, or one hour.</td>
                </tr>
            </tbody>
        </table>
        <para>To see how the settings affect the deletion of a running
            instance, check the directory where the images are
            stored:</para>
        <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>sudo ls -lash /var/lib/nova/instances/_base/</userinput></screen>
        <para>Then look for the identifier in
                <filename>/var/log/compute/compute.log</filename>:</para>
        <screen><computeroutput>2012-02-18 04:24:17 41389 WARNING nova.virt.libvirt.imagecache [-] Unknown base file: /var/lib/nova/instances/_base/06a057b9c7b0b27e3b496f53d1e88810
a0d1d5d3_20
2012-02-18 04:24:17 41389 INFO nova.virt.libvirt.imagecache [-] Removable base files: /var/lib/nova/instances/_base/06a057b9c7b0b27e3b496f53d1e88810
a0d1d5d3 /var/lib/nova/instances/_base/06a057b9c7b0b27e3b496f53d1e88810a0d1d5d3_20
2012-02-18 04:24:17 41389 INFO nova.virt.libvirt.imagecache [-] Removing base file: /var/lib/nova/instances/_base/06a057b9c7b0b27e3b496f53d1e88810a0d1d5d3</computeroutput></screen>
        <para>Because 86400 seconds (24 hours) is the default time for
                <literal>remove_unused_original_minimum_age_seconds</literal>,
            you can either wait for that time interval to see the base
            image removed, or set the value to a shorter time period
            in <filename>nova.conf</filename>. Restart all nova
            services after changing a setting in
                <filename>nova.conf</filename>.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
