<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
    <section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="windows-image">
<title>Example: Microsoft Windows image</title>
    <para>We do not yet have a fully documented example of how to create a Microsoft Windows image.
        You can use libvirt to install Windows from an installation DVD using the same approach as
        with the CentOS and Ubuntu examples. Once the initial install is done, you will need to
        perform some Windows-specific customizations.</para>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Install VirtIO drivers</title>
            <para>Installing the <link
                xlink:href="http://www.linux-kvm.org/page/WindowsGuestDrivers/Download_Drivers"
                >VirtIO paravirtualizaion drivers for Windows</link> will improve virtual machine
            performance when using KVM as the hypervisor to run Windows.</para>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect><title>Sysprep</title>
            <para>Microsoft has a special tool called <link
                xlink:href="http://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc766049(v=ws.10).aspx"
                >Sysprep</link> that must be run inside of a Windows guest to prepare it for use as
            a virtual machine image. On Windows, invoke sysprep, as follows:
            <screen><userinput>c:\windows\system32\sysprep\sysprep.exe</userinput></screen></para>
        </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>cloudbase-init</title>
        <para><link xlink:href="http://www.cloudbase.it/cloud-init-for-windows-instances/"
                >cloudbase-init</link> is a Windows port of cloud-init that should be installed
            inside of the guest. The <link xlink:href="https://github.com/cloudbase/cloudbase-init"
                >source code</link> is available on GitHub.</para>
    </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Jordan Rinke's OpenStack Windows resources</title>
            <para>Jordan Rinke maintains <link xlink:href="https://github.com/jordanrinke/openstack"
                >a collection of resources</link> for managing OpenStack Windows virtual machine
            guests.</para>
        </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
    <title>Windows instances require the timezone to be "localtime"</title>
    <para>When uploading Windows images, you must set the <literal>os_type</literal>
    parameter to <literal>windows</literal>, which causes instances to use the
    local time zone.
    Failing to set this will cause the clock timezone to be UTC, which has unexpected
    side effects in Windows.</para>
    </simplesect>
    </section>
