<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" 
    xml:id="ch_openstack-object-storage-tutorials">
    
    <title>OpenStack Object Storage Tutorials</title> 
    <para>We want people to use OpenStack for practical problem solving, and the increasing size and
        density of web content makes for a great use-case for object storage. These tutorials show
        you how to use your OpenStack Object Storage installation for practical purposes, and it
        assumes Object Storage is already installed.</para>
    <section xml:id="storing-large-photos-or-videos-on-the-cloud">
        
        <title>Storing Large Photos or Videos on the Cloud</title>
        
        <para>In this OpenStack tutorial, we’ll walk through using an Object Storage installation to
            back up all your photos or videos. As the sensors on consumer-grade and pro-sumer grade
            cameras generate more and more megapixels, we all need a place to back our files to and
            know they are safe. </para>
        
        <para>We'll go through this tutorial in parts:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            
            <listitem>
                <para>Setting up secure access to Object Storage.</para></listitem>
            
            <listitem><para>Configuring Cyberduck for connecting to OpenStack Object Storage.</para></listitem>
            
            <listitem><para>Copying files to the cloud.</para></listitem>
            
        </itemizedlist>
        <section xml:id="part-i-setting-up-secure-access">
            
            <title>Part I: Setting Up Secure Access</title>
            <para>In this part, we'll get the proxy server running with SSL on the Object Storage
                installation. It's a requirement for using Cyberduck as a client interface to Object
                Storage.</para>
            <para>You will need a key and certificate to do this, which we can create as a
                self-signed for the tutorial since we can do the extra steps to have Cyberduck
                accept it. Creating a self-signed cert can usually be done with these commands on
                the proxy server: </para>
                <literallayout class="monospaced">cd /etc/swift
openssl req -new -x509 -nodes -out cert.crt -keyout cert.key</literallayout> 
                
            <para>Ensure these generated files are in /etc/swift/cert.crt and /etc/swift/cert.key. </para>
            <para>You also should configure your iptables to enable https traffic. Here's an example
                setup that works.</para>
            <literallayout class="monospaced">Chain INPUT (policy ACCEPT 0 packets, 0 bytes)
 pkts bytes target     prot opt in     out     source               destination         
76774 1543M ACCEPT     all  --  lo     any     localhost            anywhere            
 416K  537M ACCEPT     all  --  any    any     anywhere             anywhere            state RELATED,ESTABLISHED 
  106  6682 ACCEPT     tcp  --  any    any     anywhere             anywhere            tcp dpt:https 
   13   760 ACCEPT     tcp  --  any    any     anywhere             anywhere            tcp dpt:ssh 
    3   124 ACCEPT     icmp --  any    any     anywhere             anywhere            icmp echo-request 
  782 38880 DROP       all  --  any    any     anywhere             anywhere            

Chain FORWARD (policy ACCEPT 0 packets, 0 bytes)
 pkts bytes target     prot opt in     out     source               destination         
    0     0 DROP       all  --  any    any     anywhere             anywhere            

Chain OUTPUT (policy ACCEPT 397K packets, 1561M bytes)
 pkts bytes target     prot opt in     out     source               destination   </literallayout>
            <para>If you don't have access to the Object Storage installation to configure these
                settings, ask your service provider to set up secure access for you. </para><para>Then, edit your proxy-server.conf file to include the following in the [DEFAULT] sections. </para>
            <literallayout class="monospaced">[DEFAULT]                           
bind_port = 443
cert_file = /etc/swift/cert.crt
key_file = /etc/swift/cert.key </literallayout>
            <para>Also, make sure you use https: for all references to the URL for the server in the
                .conf files as needed.</para>
            <para>Verify that you can connect using the Public URL to Object Storage by using the
                "swift" tool:</para>
            <para>
                <literallayout class="monospaced">swift -A https://yourswiftinstall.com:11000/v1.0 -U test:tester -K testing stat</literallayout>
            </para>
          
                <para>Okay, you've created the access that Cyberduck expects for your Object Storage
                    installation. Let's start configuring the Cyberduck side of things.</para>
            
        </section>
        <section xml:id="part-ii-configuring-cyberduck">
            
            <title>Part II: Configuring Cyberduck</title>
            <para>Next, you want to change the context of the URL from the default /v1.0 by opening
                a Terminal window and using <code>defaults write ch.sudo.cyberduck
                    cf.authentication.context &lt;string></code> to change the URL. Substitute
                /auth/v1.0 for the &lt;string> (Mac OSX). </para>
            <para>Cyberduck 3.8.1 includes a drop-down for selecting Swift (OpenStack Object
                Storage) when opening a connection. Launch Cyberduck, and then click the New
                Connection toolbar button or choose File > Open Connection. </para>
            <para>Select Swift (OpenStack Object Storage). Enter the following values:</para>
            <para>Server: Enter the URL of the installed Swift server.</para>
            <para>Port: Enter 443 since you are connecting via https.</para>
            <para>Username: Enter the account name followed by a colon and then the user name, for
                example test:tester.</para>
            <para>Password: Enter the password for the account and user name entered above.<figure>
                    <title>Example Cyberduck Swift Connection</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="figures/cyberduck_swift_connection.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure></para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="part-iii-copying-files">
            <title>Part III: Creating Containers (Folders) and Uploading Files</title>
            <para>Now you want to create containers to hold your files. Without containers, Object
                Storage doesn't know where to put the files. In the Action menu, choose New Folder
                and name the folder.</para>
            <para>Next you can drag and drop files into the created folder or select File > Upload
                to select files to upload to the OpenStack Object Storage service. <figure>
                    <title>Example Cyberduck Swift Showing Uploads</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="figures/cyberduck_swift_uploads.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure></para><para>Et voila! You can back up terabytes of data if you just have the space and the data. That's a lot of pictures or video, so get snapping and rolling!</para>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
