<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
  xml:id="orchestration-service">
  <title>Orchestration service overview</title>
  <para>The Orchestration service provides a template-based
    orchestration for describing a cloud application by running
    OpenStack API calls to generate running cloud applications. The
    software integrates other core components of OpenStack into a
    one-file template system. The templates enable you to create most
    OpenStack resource types, such as instances, floating IPs,
    volumes, security groups, users, and so on. Also, provides some
    more advanced functionality, such as instance high availability,
    instance auto-scaling, and nested stacks. By providing very tight
    integration with other OpenStack core projects, all OpenStack core
    projects could receive a larger user base.</para>
  <para>The service enables deployers to integrate with the
    Orchestration service directly or through custom plug-ins.</para>
  <para>The Orchestration service consists of the following
    components:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><code>heat</code> command-line client. A CLI that communicates with the
        heat-api to run AWS CloudFormation APIs. End developers could
        also use the Orchestration REST API directly.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><code>heat-api</code> component. Provides an
        OpenStack-native REST API that processes API requests by
        sending them to the heat-engine over RPC.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><code>heat-api-cfn</code> component. Provides an AWS Query
        API that is compatible with AWS CloudFormation and processes
        API requests by sending them to the heat-engine over
        RPC.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><code>heat-engine</code>. Orchestrates the launching of
        templates and provides events back to the API consumer.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</section>
