<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
  xml:id="compute-service">
  <title>Compute service</title>
  <para>The Compute service is a cloud computing fabric controller,
    which is the main part of an IaaS system. Use it to host and
    manage cloud computing systems. The main modules are implemented
    in Python.</para>
  <para>Compute interacts with the Identity Service for
    authentication, Image Service for images, and the Dashboard for
    the user and administrative interface. Access to images is limited
    by project and by user; quotas are limited per project (for
    example, the number of instances). The Compute service scales
    horizontally on standard hardware, and downloads images to launch
    instances as required.</para>
  <para>The Compute service is made up of the following functional
    areas and their underlying components:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <title>API</title>
    <listitem>
      <para><systemitem class="service">nova-api</systemitem> service.
        Accepts and responds to end user compute API calls. Supports
        the OpenStack Compute API, the Amazon EC2 API, and a special
        Admin API for privileged users to perform administrative
        actions. Also, initiates most orchestration activities, such
        as running an instance, and enforces some policies.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><systemitem class="service">nova-api-metadata</systemitem>
        service. Accepts metadata requests from instances. The
          <systemitem class="service">nova-api-metadata</systemitem>
        service is generally only used when you run in multi-host mode
        with <systemitem class="service">nova-network</systemitem>
        installations. For details, see <link
          xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/admin-guide-cloud/content/section_metadata-service.html"
          >Metadata service</link> in the <citetitle>Cloud
          Administrator Guide</citetitle>.</para>
      <para>On Debian systems, it is included in the <systemitem
          class="service">nova-api</systemitem> package, and can be
        selected through <package>debconf</package>.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <itemizedlist>
    <title>Compute core</title>
    <listitem>
      <para><systemitem class="service">nova-compute</systemitem>
        process. A worker daemon that creates and terminates virtual
        machine instances through hypervisor APIs. For example, XenAPI
        for XenServer/XCP, libvirt for KVM or QEMU, VMwareAPI for
        VMware, and so on. The process by which it does so is fairly
        complex but the basics are simple: Accept actions from the
        queue and perform a series of system commands, like launching
        a KVM instance, to carry them out while updating state in the
        database.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><systemitem class="service">nova-scheduler</systemitem>
        process. Conceptually the simplest piece of code in Compute.
        Takes a virtual machine instance request from the queue and
        determines on which compute server host it should run.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><systemitem class="service">nova-conductor</systemitem>
        module. Mediates interactions between <systemitem
          class="service">nova-compute</systemitem> and the database.
        Aims to eliminate direct accesses to the cloud database made
        by <systemitem class="service">nova-compute</systemitem>. The
          <systemitem class="service">nova-conductor</systemitem>
        module scales horizontally. However, do not deploy it on any
        nodes where <systemitem class="service"
          >nova-compute</systemitem> runs. For more information, see
          <link
          xlink:href="http://russellbryantnet.wordpress.com/2012/11/19/a-new-nova-service-nova-conductor/"
          >A new Nova service: nova-conductor</link>.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <itemizedlist>
    <title>Networking for VMs</title>
    <listitem>
      <para><systemitem class="service">nova-network</systemitem>
        worker daemon. Similar to <systemitem class="service"
          >nova-compute</systemitem>, it accepts networking tasks from
        the queue and performs tasks to manipulate the network, such
        as setting up bridging interfaces or changing iptables rules.
        This functionality is being migrated to OpenStack Networking,
        which is a separate OpenStack service.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><systemitem class="service">nova-dhcpbridge</systemitem>
        script. Tracks IP address leases and records them in the
        database by using the dnsmasq <literal>dhcp-script</literal>
        facility. This functionality is being migrated to OpenStack
        Networking. OpenStack Networking provides a different
        script.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <?hard-pagebreak?>
  <itemizedlist>
    <title>Console interface</title>
    <listitem>
      <para><systemitem class="service">nova-consoleauth</systemitem>
        daemon. Authorizes tokens for users that console proxies
        provide. See <systemitem class="service"
          >nova-novncproxy</systemitem> and <systemitem
          class="service">nova-xvpnvcproxy</systemitem>. This service
        must be running for console proxies to work. Many proxies of
        either type can be run against a single <systemitem
          class="service">nova-consoleauth</systemitem> service in a
        cluster configuration. For information, see <link
          xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/trunk/config-reference/content/about-nova-consoleauth.html"
          >About nova-consoleauth</link>.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><systemitem class="service">nova-novncproxy</systemitem>
        daemon. Provides a proxy for accessing running instances
        through a VNC connection. Supports browser-based novnc
        clients.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><systemitem class="service">nova-xvpnvncproxy</systemitem>
        daemon. A proxy for accessing running instances through a VNC
        connection. Supports a Java client specifically designed for
        OpenStack.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><systemitem class="service">nova-cert</systemitem> daemon.
        Manages x509 certificates.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para os="debian">In Debian, a unique
      <package>nova-consoleproxy</package> package provides the
      <package>nova-novncproxy</package>,
      <package>nova-spicehtml5proxy</package>, and
      <package>nova-xvpvncproxy</package> packages. To select
    packages, edit the
      <filename>/etc/default/nova-consoleproxy</filename> file or use
    the <package>debconf</package> interface. You can also manually
    edit the <filename>/etc/default/nova-consoleproxy</filename> file
    and stop and start the console daemons.</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <title>Image management (EC2 scenario)</title>
    <listitem>
      <para><systemitem class="service">nova-objectstore</systemitem>
        daemon. Provides an S3 interface for registering images with
        the Image Service. Mainly used for installations that must
        support euca2ools. The euca2ools tools talk to <systemitem
          class="service">nova-objectstore</systemitem> in <emphasis
          role="italic">S3 language</emphasis>, and <systemitem
          class="service">nova-objectstore</systemitem> translates S3
        requests into Image Service requests.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>euca2ools client. A set of command-line interpreter
        commands for managing cloud resources. Though not an OpenStack
        module, you can configure <systemitem class="service"
          >nova-api</systemitem> to support this EC2 interface. For
        more information, see the <link
          xlink:href="http://www.eucalyptus.com/eucalyptus-cloud/documentation/2.0"
          >Eucalyptus 2.0 Documentation</link>.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <itemizedlist>
    <title>Command-line clients and other interfaces</title>
    <listitem>
      <para>nova client. Enables users to submit commands as a tenant
        administrator or end user.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>nova-manage client. Enables cloud administrators to submit
        commands.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <itemizedlist>
    <title>Other components</title>
    <listitem>
      <para>The queue. A central hub for passing messages between
        daemons. Usually implemented with <link
          xlink:href="http://www.rabbitmq.com/">RabbitMQ</link>, but
        could be any AMPQ message queue, such as <link
          xlink:href="http://qpid.apache.org/">Apache Qpid</link> or
          <link xlink:href="http://www.zeromq.org/">Zero
        MQ</link>.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>SQL database. Stores most build-time and runtime states
        for a cloud infrastructure. Includes instance types that are
        available for use, instances in use, available networks, and
        projects. Theoretically, OpenStack Compute can support any
        database that SQL-Alchemy supports, but the only databases
        widely used are SQLite3 databases (only appropriate for test
        and development work), MySQL, and PostgreSQL.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>The Compute service interacts with other OpenStack services:
    Identity Service for authentication, Image Service for images, and
    the OpenStack dashboard for a web interface.</para>
</section>
