<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="keystone-concepts">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Identity Service concepts</title>
    <para>The Identity Service performs the following
        functions:</para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
            <para>User management. Tracks users and their
                permissions.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Service catalog. Provides a catalog of available
                services with their API endpoints.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>To understand the Identity Service, you must understand the
        following concepts:</para>
    <variablelist wordsize="10">
        <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">User</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
                <para>Digital representation of a person, system, or
                    service who uses OpenStack cloud services. The
                    Identity Service validates that incoming requests
                    are made by the user who claims to be making the
                    call. Users have a login and may be assigned
                    tokens to access resources. Users can be directly
                    assigned to a particular tenant and behave as if
                    they are contained in that tenant.</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">Credentials</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
                <para>Data that is known only by a user that proves
                    who they are. In the Identity Service, examples
                    are: User name and password, user name and API
                    key, or an authentication token provided by the
                    Identity Service.</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold"
                >Authentication</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
                <para>The act of confirming the identity of a user.
                    The Identity Service confirms an incoming request
                    by validating a set of credentials supplied by the
                    user.</para>
                <para>These credentials are initially a user name and
                    password or a user name and API key. In response
                    to these credentials, the Identity Service issues
                    an authentication token to the user, which the
                    user provides in subsequent requests.</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">Token</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
                <para>An arbitrary bit of text that is used to access
                    resources. Each token has a scope which describes
                    which resources are accessible with it. A token
                    may be revoked at any time and is valid for a
                    finite duration.</para>
                <para>While the Identity Service supports token-based
                    authentication in this release, the intention is
                    for it to support additional protocols in the
                    future. The intent is for it to be an integration
                    service foremost, and not aspire to be a
                    full-fledged identity store and management
                    solution.</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">Tenant</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
                <para>A container used to group or isolate resources
                    and/or identity objects. Depending on the service
                    operator, a tenant may map to a customer, account,
                    organization, or project.</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">Service</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
                <para>An OpenStack service, such as Compute (Nova),
                    Object Storage (Swift), or Image Service (Glance).
                    Provides one or more endpoints through which users
                    can access resources and perform
                    operations.</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">Endpoint</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
                <para>A network-accessible address, usually described
                    by a URL, from where you access a service. If using
                    an extension for templates, you can create an
                    endpoint template, which represents the templates
                    of all the consumable services that are available
                    across the regions.</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">Role</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
                <para>A personality that a user assumes that enables
                    them to perform a specific set of operations. A
                    role includes a set of rights and privileges. A
                    user assuming that role inherits those rights and
                    privileges.</para>
                <para>In the Identity Service, a token that is issued
                    to a user includes the list of roles that user
                    has. Services that are being called by that user
                    determine how they interpret the set of roles a
                    user has and to which operations or resources each
                    role grants access.</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>The following diagram shows the Identity Service process
        flow:</para>
    <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata
                fileref="figures/SCH_5002_V00_NUAC-Keystone.png"
                format="PNG" scale="40"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata
                fileref="figures/SCH_5002_V00_NUAC-Keystone.png"
                format="PNG" scale="10"/>
        </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
</section>
