<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="section_objectstorage-ringbuilder">
    <title>Ring-builder</title>
    <para>Use the swift-ring-builder utility to build and manage rings. This
        utility assigns partitions to devices and writes an optimized
        Python structure to a gzipped, serialized file on disk for
        transmission to the servers. The server processes occasionally
        check the modification time of the file and reload in-memory
        copies of the ring structure as needed. If you use a slightly
        older version of the ring, one of the three replicas for a
        partition subset will be incorrect because of the way the
        ring-builder manages changes to the ring. You can work around
        this issue.</para>
    <para>The ring-builder also keeps its own builder file with the
        ring information and additional data required to build future
        rings. It is very important to keep multiple backup copies of
        these builder files. One option is to copy the builder files
        out to every server while copying the ring files themselves.
        Another is to upload the builder files into the cluster
        itself. If you lose the builder file, you have to create a new
        ring from scratch. Nearly all partitions would be assigned to
        different devices and, therefore, nearly all of the stored
        data would have to be replicated to new locations. So,
        recovery from a builder file loss is possible, but data would
        be unreachable for an extended time.</para>
    <section xml:id="section_ring-data-structure">
        <title>Ring data structure</title>
        <para>The ring data structure consists of three top level
            fields: a list of devices in the cluster, a list of lists
            of device ids indicating partition to device assignments,
            and an integer indicating the number of bits to shift an
            MD5 hash to calculate the partition for the hash.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section_partition-assignment">
        <title>Partition assignment list</title>
        <para>This is a list of <literal>array('H')</literal> of
            devices ids. The outermost list contains an
                <literal>array('H')</literal> for each replica. Each
                <literal>array('H')</literal> has a length equal to
            the partition count for the ring. Each integer in the
                <literal>array('H')</literal> is an index into the
            above list of devices. The partition list is known
            internally to the Ring class as
                <literal>_replica2part2dev_id</literal>.</para>
        <para>So, to create a list of device dictionaries assigned to
            a partition, the Python code would look like:
            <programlisting>devices = [self.devs[part2dev_id[partition]] for
part2dev_id in self._replica2part2dev_id]</programlisting></para>
        <para>That code is a little simplistic because it does not
            account for the removal of duplicate devices. If a ring
            has more replicas than devices, a partition will have more
            than one replica on a device.</para>
        <para><literal>array('H')</literal> is used for memory
            conservation as there may be millions of
            partitions.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section_fractional-replicas">
        <title>Replica counts</title>
        <para>To support the gradual change in replica counts, a ring
            can have a real number of replicas and is not restricted
            to an integer number of replicas.</para>
        <para>A fractional replica count is for the whole ring and not
            for individual partitions. It indicates the average number
            of replicas for each partition. For example, a replica
            count of 3.2 means that 20 percent of partitions have four
            replicas and 80 percent have three replicas.</para>
        <para>The replica count is adjustable.</para>
        <para>Example:</para>
        <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>swift-ring-builder account.builder set_replicas 4</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>swift-ring-builder account.builder rebalance</userinput></screen>
        <para>You must rebalance the replica ring in globally
            distributed clusters. Operators of these clusters
            generally want an equal number of replicas and regions.
            Therefore, when an operator adds or removes a region, the
            operator adds or removes a replica. Removing unneeded
            replicas saves on the cost of disks.</para>
        <para>You can gradually increase the replica count at a rate
            that does not adversely affect cluster performance.</para>
        <para>For example:</para>
        <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>swift-ring-builder object.builder set_replicas 3.01</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>swift-ring-builder object.builder rebalance</userinput>
<computeroutput>&lt;distribute rings and wait&gt;...</computeroutput>

<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>swift-ring-builder object.builder set_replicas 3.02</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>swift-ring-builder object.builder rebalance</userinput>
<computeroutput>&lt;creatdistribute rings and wait&gt;...</computeroutput></screen>
        <para>Changes take effect after the ring is rebalanced.
            Therefore, if you intend to change from 3 replicas to 3.01
            but you accidentally type <literal>2.01</literal>, no data
            is lost.</para>
        <para>Additionally, <command>swift-ring-builder
                    <replaceable>X.builder</replaceable>
                create</command> can now take a decimal argument for
            the number of replicas.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section_partition-shift-value">
        <title>Partition shift value</title>
        <para>The partition shift value is known internally to the
            Ring class as <literal>_part_shift</literal>. This value
            is used to shift an MD5 hash to calculate the partition
            where the data for that hash should reside. Only the top
            four bytes of the hash is used in this process. For
            example, to compute the partition for the
                <literal>/account/container/object</literal> path, the
            Python code might look like the following code:
            <programlisting>partition = unpack_from('&gt;I',
md5('/account/container/object').digest())[0] &gt;&gt;
self._part_shift</programlisting></para>
        <para>For a ring generated with part_power P, the partition
            shift value is <literal>32 - P</literal>.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section_build-ring">
        <title>Build the ring</title>
        <para>The ring builder process includes these high-level
            steps:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>The utility calculates the number of partitions to
                    assign to each device based on the weight of the
                    device. For example, for a partition at the power
                    of 20, the ring has 1,048,576 partitions. One
                    thousand devices of equal weight each want
                    1,048.576 partitions. The devices are sorted by
                    the number of partitions they desire and kept in
                    order throughout the initialization
                    process.</para>
                <note>
                    <para>Each device is also assigned a random
                        tiebreaker value that is used when two devices
                        desire the same number of partitions. This
                        tiebreaker is not stored on disk anywhere, and
                        so two different rings created with the same
                        parameters will have different partition
                        assignments. For repeatable partition
                        assignments,
                            <literal>RingBuilder.rebalance()</literal>
                        takes an optional seed value that seeds the
                        Python pseudo-random number generator.</para>
                </note>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The ring builder assigns each partition replica
                    to the device that requires most partitions at
                    that point while keeping it as far away as
                    possible from other replicas. The ring builder
                    prefers to assign a replica to a device in a
                    region that does not already have a replica. If no
                    such region is available, the ring builder
                    searches for a device in a different zone, or on a
                    different server. If it does not find one, it
                    looks for a device with no replicas. Finally, if
                    all options are exhausted, the ring builder
                    assigns the replica to the device that has the
                    fewest replicas already assigned.</para>
                <note>
                    <para>The ring builder assigns multiple replicas
                        to one device only if the ring has fewer
                        devices than it has replicas.</para>
                </note>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>When building a new ring from an old ring, the
                    ring builder recalculates the desired number of
                    partitions that each device wants.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The ring builder unassigns partitions and
                    gathers these partitions for reassignment, as
                    follows: <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The ring builder unassigns any
                                assigned partitions from any removed
                                devices and adds these partitions to
                                the gathered list.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The ring builder unassigns any
                                partition replicas that can be spread
                                out for better durability and adds
                                these partitions to the gathered list.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The ring builder unassigns random
                                partitions from any devices that have
                                more partitions than they need and
                                adds these partitions to the gathered
                                list.</para>
                        </listitem>

                    </itemizedlist></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The ring builder reassigns the gathered
                    partitions to devices by using a similar method to
                    the one described previously.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>When the ring builder reassigns a replica to a
                    partition, the ring builder records the time of
                    the reassignment. The ring builder uses this value
                    when it gathers partitions for reassignment so
                    that no partition is moved twice in a configurable
                    amount of time. The RingBuilder class knows this
                    configurable amount of time as
                        <literal>min_part_hours</literal>. The ring
                    builder ignores this restriction for replicas of
                    partitions on removed devices because removal of a
                    device happens on device failure only, and
                    reassignment is the only choice.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>Theses steps do not always perfectly rebalance a ring
            due to the random nature of gathering partitions for
            reassignment. To help reach a more balanced ring, the
            rebalance process is repeated until near perfect (less
            than 1 percent off) or when the balance does not improve
            by at least 1 percent (indicating we probably cannot get
            perfect balance due to wildly imbalanced zones or too many
            partitions recently moved).</para>
    </section>
</section>
