<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
  xml:id="orchestration-service">
  <title>Orchestration module</title>
  <para>The Orchestration module provides a template-based
    orchestration for describing a cloud application, by running
    OpenStack API calls to generate running cloud applications. The
    software integrates other core components of OpenStack into a
    one-file template system. The templates allow you to create most
    OpenStack resource types, such as instances, floating IPs,
    volumes, security groups and users. It also provides advanced
    functionality, such as instance high availability, instance auto-scaling,
    and nested stacks. This enables OpenStack core projects to receive a larger
    user base.</para>
  <para>The service enables deployers to integrate with the
    Orchestration module directly or through custom plug-ins.</para>
  <para>The Orchestration module consists of the following
    components:</para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><code>heat</code> command-line client</term>
      <listitem><para>A CLI that communicates with the heat-api to run AWS
      CloudFormation APIs. End developers can directly use the Orchestration
      REST API.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><code>heat-api</code> component</term><listitem><para>An
        OpenStack-native REST API that processes API requests by sending them to
        the heat-engine over Remote Procedure Call (RPC).</para>
    </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><code>heat-api-cfn</code> component</term> <listitem><para>An AWS
        Query API that is compatible with AWS CloudFormation. It processes
        API requests by sending them to the heat-engine over
        RPC.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><code>heat-engine</code></term>
      <listitem><para>Orchestrates the launching of templates and provides
        events back to the API consumer.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>
