<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
  xml:id="swift_commands">
  <title>swift commands</title>
  <para>The swift client is the command-line interface for the
    OpenStack Object Storage API.</para>
  <para>For help on a specific swift command, enter:</para>
  <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>swift <option>help</option> <replaceable>COMMAND</replaceable></userinput></screen>
  <example>
    <title>Usage</title>
    <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput><command>swift</command> <replaceable>COMMAND</replaceable> <option>[options]</option> <option>[args]</option></userinput></screen>
  </example>
  <example>
    <title>Commands</title>
    <screen><computeroutput>  stat [container] [object]
    Displays information for the account, container, or object depending on the
    args given (if any).

  list [options] [container]
    Lists the containers for the account or the objects for a container. -p or
    --prefix is an option that will only list items beginning with that prefix.
    -l produces output formatted like 'ls -l' and --lh like 'ls -lh'.
    -d or --delimiter is option (for container listings only) that will roll up
    items with the given delimiter (see http://docs.openstack.org/
        api/openstack-object-storage/1.0/content/list-objects.html)

  upload [options] container file_or_directory [file_or_directory] [...]
    Uploads to the given container the files and directories specified by the
    remaining args. -c or --changed is an option that will only upload files
    that have changed since the last upload. -S &lt;size> or --segment-size &lt;size>
    will upload the files in segments no larger than size. -C &lt;container> or
    --segment-container &lt;container> will specify the location of the segments
    to &lt;container>. --leave-segments are options as well (see --help for more).

  post [options] [container] [object]
    Updates meta information for the account, container, or object depending on
    the args given. If the container is not found, it will be created
    automatically; but this is not true for accounts and objects. Containers
    also allow the -r (or --read-acl) and -w (or --write-acl) options. The -m
    or --meta option is allowed on all and used to define the user meta data
    items to set in the form Name:Value. This option can be repeated. Example:
    post -m Color:Blue -m Size:Large

  download --all OR download container [options] [object] [object] ...
    Downloads everything in the account (with --all), or everything in a
    container, or a list of objects depending on the args given. For a single
    object download, you may use the -o [--output] &lt;filename> option to
    redirect the output to a specific file or if "-" then just redirect to
    stdout.

  delete [options] --all OR delete container [options] [object] [object] ...
    Deletes everything in the account (with --all), or everything in a
    container, or a list of objects depending on the args given. Segments of
    manifest objects will be deleted as well, unless you specify the
    --leave-segments option.</computeroutput></screen>
  </example>
  <example>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>swift -A https://auth.api.rackspacecloud.com/v1.0 -U user -K key stat</userinput></screen>
    <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>swift --os-auth-url https://api.example.com/v2.0 --os-tenant-name tenant \
      --os-usernameuser --os-password password list</userinput></screen>
<screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>swift --os-auth-token 6ee5eb33efad4e45ab46806eac010566 \
      --os-storage-url https://10.1.5.2:8080/v1/AUTH_ced809b6a4baea7aeab61a \
      list</userinput></screen>
<screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>swift list --lh</userinput></screen>
  </example>
</section>
