<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
    <section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="metering-service">
      <title>Telemetry module</title>
      <para>The Telemetry module performs the following functions:</para>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Efficiently collects the metering data about the CPU
          and network costs.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Collects data by monitoring notifications sent from
          services or by polling the infrastructure.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Configures the type of collected data to meet
          various operating requirements. It accesses and inserts the
          metering data through the REST API.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Expands the framework to collect custom usage data
          by additional plug-ins.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Produces signed metering messages that cannot be
          repudiated.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
     </para>
      <para>The Telemetry module consists of the following
        components:</para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry><term>A compute agent (<systemitem class="service"
          >ceilometer-agent-compute</systemitem>)</term>
          <listitem><para>Runs on each compute node and polls for resource
          utilization statistics. There may be other types of agents in the
          future, but for now our focus is creating the compute agent.</para>
        </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>A central agent (<systemitem class="service"
           >ceilometer-agent-central</systemitem>)</term>
          <listitem><para>Runs on a central management server to poll for
           resource utilization statistics for resources not tied to instances
           or compute nodes.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>A collector (<systemitem class="service"
           >ceilometer-collector</systemitem></term>
          <listitem><para>Runs on central management server(s) to monitor the
           message queues (for notifications and for metering data coming from
           the agent). Notification messages are processed and turned into
           metering messages, which are sent to the message bus using the
           appropriate topic. Telemetry messages are written to the data store
           without modification.</para>
        </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>An alarm notifier (<systemitem class="service"
            >ceilometer-alarm-notifier</systemitem>)</term>
          <listitem><para>Runs on one or more central management servers to
            allow alarms to be set based on the threshold evaluation for a
            collection of samples.</para></listitem>
     </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>A data store</term>
          <listitem><para>A database capable of handling
            concurrent writes (from one or more collector instances)
            and reads (from the API server).</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
          <term>An API server (<systemitem
           class="service">ceilometer-api</systemitem>)</term>
          <listitem><para>Runs on one or more central management servers to
           provide data access from the data store.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <para>These services communicate by using the OpenStack messaging bus.
        Only the collector and API server have access
        to the data store.</para>
    </section>
