<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="keystone-token-binding">
    <title>Configure the Identity Service for token binding</title>
    <para>Token binding refers to the practice of embedding
    information from external authentication providers (like a
    company's Kerberos server) inside the token such that a client may
    enforce that the token only be used in conjunction with that
    specified authentication. This is an additional security mechanism
    as it means that if a token is stolen it will not be usable
    without also providing the external authentication. </para>
  <para> To activate token binding you must specify the types of
    authentication that token binding should be used for in
      <filename>keystone.conf</filename>:
    <programlisting language="ini">[token]
    bind = kerberos</programlisting>
    Currently only <literal>kerberos</literal> is supported.</para>
   <para>
To enforce checking of token binding the <literal>enforce_token_bind</literal> parameter
should be set to one of the following modes:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><literal>disabled</literal> disable token bind checking</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><literal>permissive</literal> enable bind checking, if a token is bound to a mechanism that
  is unknown to the server then ignore it. This is the default.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><literal>strict</literal> enable bind checking, if a token is bound to a mechanism that is
  unknown to the server then this token should be rejected.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><literal>required</literal> enable bind checking and require that at least 1 bind mechanism
  is used for tokens.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><literal>named</literal> enable bind checking and require that the specified authentication
  mechanism is used:
<programlisting language="ini">[token]
    enforce_token_bind = kerberos</programlisting></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
  <note><para>Do not set <literal>enforce_token_bind = named</literal> as there is not an authentication
  mechanism called <literal>named</literal>.</para></note>
</para>
</section>
