<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="managing-volumes">
    <title>Managing Volumes</title>
    <para>The OpenStack Block Storage service enables you to add extra
        block-level storage to your OpenStack Compute instances. This
        service is similar to the Amazon EC2 Elastic Block Storage
        (EBS) offering.</para>
    <para>The default OpenStack Block Storage service implementation
        is an iSCSI solution that uses Logical Volume Manager (LVM)
        for Linux.</para>
    <note>
        <para>The OpenStack Block Storage service is not a shared
            storage solution like SAN of NFS, where you can attach a
            volume to multiple servers. With the OpenStack Block
            Storage service, you can attach a volume to only one
            instance at a time. </para>
        <para>The OpenStack Block Storage service also provides
            drivers that enable you to use several vendors' back-end
            storage devices, in addition to or instead of the base LVM
            implementation.</para>
    </note>
    <para>The following high-level procedure shows you how to create
        and attach a volume to a server instance. </para>
    <procedure>
        <title>To create and attach a volume to a server
            instance:</title>
        <step><para>You must configure both OpenStack Compute and the
            OpenStack Block Storage service through the
                <filename>cinder.conf</filename> file.</para></step>
        <step>

            <para>Create a volume through the <command>cinder create</command> command. This command
                creates an LV into the volume group (VG) "cinder-volumes." </para>
        </step>

        <step>
            <para>Attach the volume to an instance through the
                    <command>nova volume-attach</command> command.
                This command creates a unique iSCSI IQN that is
                exposed to the compute node.</para>
            <substeps>
                <step>
                    <para>The compute node, which runs the instance, now has an active ISCSI session
                        and new local storage (usually a /dev/sdX disk).</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>libvirt uses that local storage as storage for the instance. The instance
                        get a new disk, usually a /dev/vdX disk.</para>
                </step>
            </substeps>
        </step>
    </procedure>
    <para>For this particular walk through, there is one cloud
        controller running <literal>nova-api</literal>,
        <literal>nova-scheduler</literal>,
        <literal>nova-objectstore</literal>,
        <literal>nova-network</literal> and
        <literal>cinder-*</literal> services. There are two
        additional compute nodes running
        <literal>nova-compute</literal>. The walk through uses
        a custom partitioning scheme that carves out 60GB of space
        and labels it as LVM. The network uses
        <literal>FlatManger</literal> is the
        <literal>NetworkManager</literal> setting for
        OpenStack Compute (Nova). </para>
    <para>Please note that the network mode doesn't interfere at
        all with the way cinder works, but networking must be set
        up for cinder to work. Please refer to <link
            xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/grizzly/openstack-network/admin/content/">Networking Administration</link> for more
        details.</para>
    <para>To set up Compute to use volumes, ensure that Block
        Storage is installed along with lvm2. The guide will be
        split in four parts : </para>
    <para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Installing the Block Storage service on the
                    cloud controller.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Configuring the
                    <literal>cinder-volumes</literal> volume
                    group on the compute nodes.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Troubleshooting your installation.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Backup your nova volumes.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <xi:include href="../openstack-install/cinder-install.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="backup-block-storage-disks.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="troubleshoot-cinder.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="multi_backend.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="add-volume-node.xml"/>
    <section xml:id="boot-from-volume">
        <title>Boot From Volume</title>
        <para>In some cases, instances can be stored and run from inside volumes. This is explained in further detail in the <link xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/grizzly/openstack-compute/admin/content/instance-creation.html#boot_from_volume">Boot From Volume</link> 
            section of the Compute Admin manual.</para>
    </section>
    
</chapter>
