<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
<!ENTITY % openstack SYSTEM "../../common/entities/openstack.ent">
%openstack;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="prescriptive-example-multisite">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Prescriptive examples</title>
    <para>Based on the needs of the intended workloads, there are
        multiple ways to build a multi-site OpenStack installation.
        Below are example architectures based on different
        requirements. These examples are meant as a reference, and not
        a hard and fast rule for deployments. Use the previous
        sections of this chapter to assist in selecting specific
        components and implementations based on specific needs.</para>
    <para>A large content provider needs to deliver content to
        customers that are geographically dispersed. The workload is
        very sensitive to latency and needs a rapid response to
        end-users. After reviewing the user, technical and operational
        considerations, it is determined beneficial to build a number
        of regions local to the customer’s edge. In this case rather
        than build a few large, centralized data centers, the intent
        of the architecture is to provide a pair of small data centers
        in locations that are closer to the customer. In this use
        case, spreading applications out allows for different
        horizontal scaling than a traditional compute workload scale.
        The intent is to scale by creating more copies of the
        application in closer proximity to the users that need it
        most, in order to ensure faster response time to user
        requests. This provider will deploy two datacenters at each of
        the four chosen regions. The implications of this design are
        based around the method of placing copies of resources in each
        of the remote regions. Swift objects, Glance images, and block
        storage will need to be manually replicated into each region.
        This may be beneficial for some systems, such as the case of
        content service, where only some of the content needs to exist
        in some but not all regions. A centralized Keystone is
        recommended to ensure authentication and that access to the
        API endpoints is easily manageable.</para>
    <para>Installation of an automated DNS system such as Designate is
        highly recommended. Unless an external Dynamic DNS system is
        available, application administrators will need a way to
        manage the mapping of which application copy exists in each
        region and how to reach it. Designate will assist by making
        the process automatic and by populating the records in the
        each region's zone.</para>
    <para>Telemetry for each region is also deployed, as each region
        may grow differently or be used at a different rate.
        Ceilometer will run to collect each region's metrics from each
        of the controllers and report them back to a central location.
        This is useful both to the end user and the administrator of
        the OpenStack environment. The end user will find this method
        useful, in that it is possible to determine if certain
        locations are experiencing higher load than others, and take
        appropriate action. Administrators will also benefit by
        possibly being able to forecast growth per region, rather than
        expanding the capacity of all regions simultaneously,
        therefore maximizing the cost-effectiveness of the multi-site
        design.</para>
    <para>One of the key decisions of running this sort of
        infrastructure is whether or not to provide a redundancy
        model. Two types of redundancy and high availability models in
        this configuration will be implemented. The first type
        revolves around the availability of the central OpenStack
        components. Keystone will be made highly available in three
        central data centers that will host the centralized OpenStack
        components. This prevents a loss of any one of the regions
        causing an outage in service. It also has the added benefit of
        being able to run a central storage repository as a primary
        cache for distributing content to each of the regions.</para>
    <para>The second redundancy topic is that of the edge data center
        itself. A second data center in each of the edge regional
        locations will house a second region near the first. This
        ensures that the application will not suffer degraded
        performance in terms of latency and availability.</para>
    <para>This figure depicts the solution designed to have both a
        centralized set of core data centers for OpenStack services
        and paired edge data centers:</para>
    <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentwidth="4in"
                fileref="../images/Multi-Site_Customer_Edge.png"/>
        </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <section xml:id="geo-redundant-load-balancing">
      <title>Geo-redundant load balancing</title>
    <para>A large-scale web application has been designed with cloud
        principles in mind. The application is designed provide
        service to application store, on a 24/7 basis. The company has
        typical 2-tier architecture with a web front-end servicing the
        customer requests and a NoSQL database back end storing the
        information.</para>
    <para>As of late there has been several outages in number of major
        public cloud providers&mdash;usually due to the fact these
        applications were running out of a single geographical
        location. The design therefore should mitigate the chance of a
        single site causing an outage for their business.</para>
    <para>The solution would consist of the following OpenStack
        components:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>A firewall, switches and load balancers on the
                public facing network connections.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>OpenStack Controller services running, Networking,
                dashboard, Block Storage and Compute running locally in
                each of the three regions. The other services,
                Identity, Orchestration, Telemetry, Image Service and
                Object Storage will be
                installed centrally&mdash;with nodes in each of the region
                providing a redundant OpenStack Controller plane
                throughout the globe.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>OpenStack Compute nodes running the KVM
                hypervisor.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>OpenStack Object Storage for serving static objects
                such as images will be used to ensure that all images
                are standardized across all the regions, and
                replicated on a regular basis.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>A Distributed DNS service available to all
                regions&mdash;that allows for dynamic update of DNS records of
                deployed instances.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>A geo-redundant load balancing service will be used
                to service the requests from the customers based on
                their origin.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>An autoscaling heat template will used to deploy the
        application in the three regions. This template will
        include:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Web Servers, running Apache.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Appropriate <literal>user_data</literal> to populate the central DNS
                servers upon instance launch.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Appropriate Telemetry alarms that maintain state of
                the application and allow for handling of region or
                instance failure.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Another autoscaling Heat template will be used to deploy a
        distributed MongoDB shard over the three locations&mdash;with the
        option of storing required data on a globally available swift
        container. according to the usage and load on the database
        server&mdash;additional shards will be provisioned according to
        the thresholds defined in Telemetry.</para>
    <para>The reason that three regions were selected here was because of
        the fear of having abnormal load on a single region in the
        event of a failure. Two data center would have been sufficient
        had the requirements been met.</para>
    <para>Orchestration is used because of the built-in functionality of
        autoscaling and auto healing in the event of increased load.
        Additional configuration management tools, such as Puppet or
        Chef could also have been used in this scenario, but were not
        chosen due to the fact that Orchestration had the appropriate built-in
        hooks into the OpenStack cloud&mdash;whereas the other tools were
        external and not native to OpenStack. In addition&mdash;since this
        deployment scenario was relatively straight forward&mdash;the
        external tools were not needed.</para>
    <para>
        OpenStack Object Storage is used here to serve as a back end for
        the Image Service since was the most suitable solution for a
        globally distributed storage solution&mdash;with its own
        replication mechanism. Home grown solutions could also have
        been used including the handling of replication&mdash;but were not
        chosen, because Object Storage is already an intricate part of the
        infrastructure&mdash;and proven solution.</para>
    <para>An external load balancing service was used and not the
        LBaaS in OpenStack because the solution in OpenStack is not
        redundant and does not have any awareness of geo location.</para>
    <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentwidth="4in"
                fileref="../images/Multi-site_Geo_Redundant_LB.png"/>
        </imageobject>
    </mediaobject></section>
    <section xml:id="location-local-services"><title>Location-local service</title>
    <para>A common use for a multi-site deployment of OpenStack, is
        for creating a Content Delivery Network. An application that
        uses a location-local architecture will require low network
        latency and proximity to the user, in order to provide an
        optimal user experience, in addition to reducing the cost of
        bandwidth and transit, since the content resides on sites
        closer to the customer, instead of a centralized content store
        that would require utilizing higher cost cross country
        links.</para>
    <para>This architecture usually includes a geo-location component
        that places user requests at the closest possible node. In
        this scenario, 100% redundancy of content across every site is
        a goal rather than a requirement, with the intent being to
        maximize the amount of content available that is within a
        minimum number of network hops for any given end user. Despite
        these differences, the storage replication configuration has
        significant overlap with that of a geo-redundant load
        balancing use case.</para>
    <para>In this example, the application utilizing this multi-site
        OpenStack install that is location aware would launch web
        server or content serving instances on the compute cluster in
        each site. Requests from clients will first be sent to a
        global services load balancer that determines the location of
        the client, then routes the request to the closest OpenStack
        site where the application completes the request.</para>
    <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentwidth="4in"
                fileref="../images/Multi-Site_shared_keystone1.png"/>
        </imageobject>
    </mediaobject></section>
</section>
