<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0"
    xml:id="operational-considerations-multi-site">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Operational Considerations</title>
    <para>Deployment of a multi-site OpenStack cloud using regions
        requires that the service catalog contains per-region entries
        for each service deployed other than the Identity service
        itself. There is limited support amongst currently available
        off-the-shelf OpenStack deployment tools for defining multiple
        regions in this fashion.</para>
    <para>Deployers must be aware of this and provide the appropriate
        customization of the service catalog for their site either
        manually or via customization of the deployment tools in
        use.</para>
    <para>Note that, as of the Icehouse release, documentation for
        implementing this feature is in progress. See this bug for
        more information:
        https://bugs.launchpad.net/openstack-manuals/+bug/1340509</para>
    <section xml:id="licensing"><title>Licensing</title>
    <para>Multi-site OpenStack deployments present additional
        licensing considerations over and above regular OpenStack
        clouds, particularly where site licenses are in use to provide
        cost efficient access to software licenses. The licensing for
        host operating systems, guest operating systems, OpenStack
        distributions (if applicable), software-defined infrastructure
        including network controllers and storage systems, and even
        individual applications need to be evaluated in light of the
        multi-site nature of the cloud.</para>
    <para>Topics to consider include:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>The specific definition of what constitutes a site
                in the relevant licenses, as the term does not
                necessarily denote a geographic or otherwise
                physically isolated location in the traditional
                sense.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Differentiations between "hot" (active) and "cold"
                (inactive) sites where significant savings may be made
                in situations where one site is a cold standby for
                disaster recovery purposes only.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Certain locations might require local vendors to
                provide support and services for each site provides
                challenges, but will vary on the licensing agreement
                in place.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></section>
    <section xml:id="logging-and-monitoring-multi-site"><title>Logging and Monitoring</title>
    <para>Logging and monitoring does not significantly differ for a
        multi-site OpenStack cloud. The same well known tools
        described in the Operations Guide
        (http://docs.openstack.org/openstack-ops/content/logging_monitoring.html)
        remain applicable. Logging and monitoring can be provided both
        on a per-site basis and in a common centralized
        location.</para>
    <para>When attempting to deploy logging and monitoring facilities
        to a centralized location, care must be taken with regards to
        the load placed on the inter-site networking links.</para></section>
    <section xml:id="upgrades-multi-site"><title>Upgrades</title>
    <para>In multi-site OpenStack clouds deployed using regions each
        site is, effectively, an independent OpenStack installation
        which is linked to the others by using centralized services
        such as Identity which are shared between sites. At a high
        level the recommended order of operations to upgrade an
        individual OpenStack environment is
        (http://docs.openstack.org/openstack-ops/content/ops_upgrades-general-steps.html):</para>
    <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Upgrade the OpenStack Identity Service
                (Keystone).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Upgrade the OpenStack Image Service (Glance).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Upgrade OpenStack Compute (Nova), including
                networking components.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Upgrade OpenStack Block Storage (Cinder).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Upgrade the OpenStack dashboard.(Horizon)</para>
        </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>The process for upgrading a multi-site environment is not
        significantly different:</para>
    <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Upgrade the shared OpenStack Identity Service
                (Keystone) deployment.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Upgrade the OpenStack Image Service (glance) at each
                site.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Upgrade OpenStack Compute (Nova), including
                networking components, at each site.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Upgrade OpenStack Block Storage (Cinder) at each
                site.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Upgrade the OpenStack dashboard (Horizon), at each
                site - or in the single central location if it is
                shared.</para>
        </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>Note that, as of the OpenStack Icehouse release, compute
        upgrades within each site can also be performed in a rolling
        fashion. Compute controller services (API, Scheduler, and
        Conductor) can be upgraded prior to upgrading of individual
        compute nodes. This maximizes the ability of operations staff
        to keep a site operational for users of compute services while
        performing an upgrade.</para></section>
    <section xml:id="quota-management-multi-site"><title>Quota Management</title>
    <para>To prevent system capacities from being exhausted without
        notification, OpenStack provides operators with the ability to
        define quotas. Quotas are used to set operational limits and
        are currently enforced at the tenant (or project) level rather
        than at the user level.</para>
    <para>Quotas are defined on a per-region basis. Operators may wish
        to define identical quotas for tenants in each region of the
        cloud to provide a consistent experience, or even create a
        process for synchronizing allocated quotas across regions. It
        is important to note that only the operational limits imposed
        by the quotas will be aligned consumption of quotas by users
        will not be reflected between regions.</para>
    <para>For example, given a cloud with two regions, if the operator
        grants a user a quota of 25 instances in each region then that
        user may launch a total of 50 instances spread across both
        regions. They may not, however, launch more than 25 instances
        in any single region.</para>
    <para>For more information on managing quotas refer to Chapter 9.
        Managing Projects and Users
        (http://docs.openstack.org/openstack-ops/content/projects_users.html)
        of the OpenStack Operators Guide.</para></section>
    <section xml:id="policy-management-multi-site"><title>Policy Management</title>
    <para>OpenStack provides a default set of Role Based Access
        Control (RBAC) policies, defined in a <filename>policy.json</filename> file, for
        each service. Operators edit these files to customize the
        policies for their OpenStack installation. If the application
        of consistent RBAC policies across sites is considered a
        requirement, then it is necessary to ensure proper
        synchronization of the <filename>policy.json</filename> files to all
        installations.</para>
    <para>This must be done using normal system administration tools
        such as rsync as no functionality for synchronizing policies
        across regions is currently provided within OpenStack.</para></section>
    <section xml:id="documentation-multi-site"><title>Documentation</title>
    <para>Users must be able to leverage cloud infrastructure and
        provision new resources in the environment. It is important
        that user documentation is accessible by users of the cloud
        infrastructure to ensure they are given sufficient information
        to help them leverage the cloud. As an example, by default
        OpenStack will schedule instances on a compute node
        automatically. However, when multiple regions are available,
        it is left to the end user to decide in which region to
        schedule the new instance. Horizon will present the user with
        the first region in your configuration. The API and CLI tools
        will not execute commands unless a valid region is specified.
        It is therefore important to provide documentation to your
        users describing the region layout as well as calling out that
        quotas are region-specific. If a user reaches his or her quota
        in one region, OpenStack will not automatically build new
        instances in another. Documenting specific examples will help
        users understand how to operate the cloud, thereby reducing
        calls and tickets filed with the help desk.</para></section>
</section>
