<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="arch-guide-why-and-who-we-wrote-this-book">
    <title>Why and How We Wrote this Book</title>
    <para>The velocity at which OpenStack environments are moving from
        proof-of-concepts to production deployments is leading to
        increasing questions and issues related to architecture design
        considerations. By and large these considerations are not
        addressed in the existing documentation, which typically
        focuses on the specifics of deployment and configuration
        options or operational considerations, rather than the bigger
        picture.</para>
    <para>We wrote this book to guide readers in designing an
        OpenStack architecture that meets the needs of their
        organization. This guide concentrates on identifying important
        design considerations for common cloud use cases and provides
        examples based on these design guidelines. This guide does not
        aim to provide explicit instructions for installing and
        configuring the cloud, but rather focuses on design principles
        as they relate to user requirements as well as technical and
        operational considerations. For specific guidance with
        installation and configuration there are a number of resources
        already available in the OpenStack documentation that help in
        that area.</para>
    <para>This book was written in a book sprint format, which is a
        facilitated, rapid development production method for books.
        For more information, see the Book Sprints website
        (www.booksprints.net).</para>
    <para>This book was written in five days during July 2014 while
        exhausting the M&amp;M, Mountain Dew and healthy options
        supply, complete with juggling entertainment during lunches at
        VMware's headquarters in Palo Alto. The event was also
        documented on Twitter using the #OpenStackDesign hashtag. The
        Book Sprint was facilitated by Faith Bosworth and Adam
        Hyde.</para>
    <para>We would like to thank VMware for their generous
        hospitality, as well as our employers, Cisco, Cloudscaling,
        Comcast, EMC, Mirantis, Rackspace, Red Hat, Verizon, and
        VMware, for enabling us to contribute our time. We would
        especially like to think Anne Gentle and Kenneth Hui for all
        of their shepherding and organization in making this
        happen.</para>
    <para>The author team includes:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Kenneth Hui (EMC)
                  <link xlink:href="http://twitter.com/hui_kenneth"
                  >@hui_kenneth</link></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Alexandra Settle (Rackspace)
                  <link xlink:href="http://twitter.com/dewsday"
                  >@dewsday</link></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Anthony Veiga (Comcast)
                  <link xlink:href="http://twitter.com/daaelar"
                  >@daaelar</link></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Beth Cohen (Verizon)
                  <link xlink:href="http://twitter.com/bfcohen"
                  >@bfcohen</link></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Kevin Jackson (Rackspace)
                  <link xlink:href="http://twitter.com/itarchitectkev"
                  >@itarchitectkev</link></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Maish Saidel-Keesing (Cisco)
                  <link xlink:href="http://twitter.com/maishsk"
                  >@maishsk</link></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Nick Chase (Mirantis)
                  <link xlink:href="http://twitter.com/NickChase"
                  >@NickChase</link></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Scott Lowe (VMware)
                  <link xlink:href="http://twitter.com/scott_lowe"
                  >@scott_lowe</link></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Sean Collins (Comcast)
                  <link xlink:href="http://twitter.com/sc68cal"
                  >@sc68cal</link></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Sean Winn (Cloudscaling)
                  <link xlink:href="http://twitter.com/seanmwinn"
                  >@seanmwinn</link></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Sebastian Gutierrez (Red Hat)
                  <link xlink:href="http://twitter.com/gutseb"
                  >@gutseb</link></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Stephen Gordon (Red Hat)
                  <link xlink:href="http://twitter.com/xsgordon"
                  >@xsgordon</link></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Vinny Valdez (Red Hat)
                  <link xlink:href="http://twitter.com/VinnyValdez"
                  >@VinnyValdez</link></para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</section>
