<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="arch-guide-how-this-book-is-organized">
    <title>How this book is organized</title>
    <para>This book has been organized into various chapters that help
        define the use cases associated with making architectural
        choices related to an <glossterm>OpenStack</glossterm> cloud
        installation. Each
        chapter is intended to stand alone to encourage individual
        chapter readability, however each chapter is designed to
        contain useful information that may be applicable in
        situations covered by other chapters. Cloud architects may use
        this book as a comprehensive guide by reading all of the use
        cases, but it is also possible to review only the chapters
        which pertain to a specific use case. When choosing to read
        specific use cases, note that it may be necessary to read more
        than one section of the guide to formulate a complete design
        for the cloud. The use cases covered in this guide
        include:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>
              <link linkend="generalpurpose">General purpose</link>: A
              cloud built with common components that should address
              80% of common use cases.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
              <link linkend="compute_focus">Compute focused</link>: A
              cloud designed to address compute intensive workloads
              such as high performance computing (HPC).
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
              <link linkend="storage_focus">Storage focused</link>: A
              cloud focused on storage intensive workloads such as
              data analytics with parallel file systems.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
              <link linkend="network_focus">Network focused</link>: A
              cloud depending on high performance and reliable
              networking, such as a <glossterm
              >content delivery network (CDN)</glossterm>.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
              <link linkend="multi_site">Multi-site</link>: A cloud
              built with multiple sites available for application
              deployments for geographical, reliability or data
              locality reasons.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
              <link linkend="hybrid">Hybrid cloud</link>: An
              architecture where multiple disparate clouds are
              connected either for failover, hybrid cloud bursting, or
              availability.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
              <link linkend="massively_scalable">Massively
              scalable</link>: An architecture that is intended for
              cloud service providers or other extremely large
              installations.
            </para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      A chapter titled <link linkend="specialized">Specialized
      cases</link> provides information on architectures that have not
      previously been covered in the defined use cases.
    </para>
    <para>Each chapter in the guide is then further broken down into
        the following sections:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Introduction: Provides an overview of the
                architectural use case.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>User requirements: Defines the set of user
                considerations that typically come into play for that
                use case.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Technical considerations: Covers the technical
                issues that must be accounted when dealing with this
                use case.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Operational considerations: Covers the ongoing
                operational tasks associated with this use case and
                architecture.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Architecture: Covers the overall architecture
                associated with the use case.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Prescriptive examples: Presents one or more
                scenarios where this architecture could be
                deployed.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      A glossary covers the terms used in the book.
    </para>

</section>
