<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- Converted by db4-upgrade version 1.0 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0-extension RaxBook-1.0" xml:id="quick-guide-to-getting-started-with-glance"><info><title>Quick Guide to Getting Started with Glance</title></info>
  
  <para>
    Glance is a server that provides the following services:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Ability to store and retrieve virtual machine images
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Ability to store and retrieve metadata about these virtual
        machine images
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        FUTURE: Convert a virtual machine image from one format to
        another
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        FUTURE: Help caching proxies such as Varnish or Squid cache
        machine images
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
    Communication with Glance occurs via a REST-like HTTP interface.
  </para>
  <para>
    However, Glance includes a Client class that
    makes working with Glance easy and straightforward.
  </para>
  <para>
    As of the Cactus release, there are also command-line tools for
    interacting with Glance.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="overview-of-glance-architecture"><info><title>Overview of Glance Architecture</title></info>
    
    <para>
      There are two main parts to Glance's architecture:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Glance API server
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Glance Registry server(s)
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <section xml:id="glance-api-server"><info><title>Glance API Server</title></info>
      
      <para>
        The API server is the main interface for Glance. It routes
        requests from clients to registries of image metadata and to its
        <emphasis role="strong">backend stores</emphasis>, which are the
        mechanisms by which Glance actually saves incoming virtual
        machine images.
      </para>
      <para>
        The backend stores that Glance can work with are as follows:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Swift</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            Swift is the highly-available object storage project in
            OpenStack. More information can be found about Swift
            <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://swift.openstack.org">here</link>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Filesystem</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            The default backend that Glance uses to store virtual
            machine images is the filesystem backend. This simple
            backend writes image files to the local filesystem.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">S3</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            This backend allows Glance to store virtual machine images
            in Amazon's S3 service.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">HTTP</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>
            Glance can read virtual machine images that are available
            via HTTP somewhere on the Internet. This store is
            <emphasis role="strong">readonly</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="glance-registry-servers"><info><title>Glance Registry Servers</title></info>
      
      <para>
        Glance registry servers are servers that conform to the Glance
        Registry API. Glance ships with a reference implementation of a
        registry server that complies with this API
        (<literal>glance-registry</literal>).
      </para>
      <para>
        For more details on Glance's architecture see the Architecture section. For more information on what a Glance
        registry server is, see the Registries section.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
