<section xml:id="ceph-backup-driver"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0">
    <title>Ceph Backup Driver</title>
        <para>The Ceph backup driver supports backing up volumes of any type
              to a Ceph backend store. It is also capable of detecting whether
              the volume to be backed up is a Ceph RBD volume and if so,
              attempts to perform incremental/differential backups.
        </para>
        <para>Support is also included for the following in the case of source
                volume being a Ceph RBD volume:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>backing up within the same Ceph pool
            (not recommended)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem><para>backing up between different Ceph pools</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem><para>backing up between different Ceph clusters</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>At the time of writing, differential backup support in
                Ceph/librbd was quite new so this driver accounts for this
                by first attempting differential backup and falling back to
                full backup/copy if the former fails.
        </para>
        <para>If incremental backups are used, multiple backups of the same
                volume are stored as snapshots so that minimal space is
                consumed in the backup store and restoring the volume takes
                a far reduced amount of time compared to a full copy.
        </para>
        <para>Note that Cinder supports restoring to a new volume or the
                original volume the backup was taken from. For the latter
                case, a full copy is enforced since this was deemed the safest
                action to take. It is therefore recommended to always
                restore to a new volume (default).
        </para>
        <para>To enable the Ceph backup driver, include the following option
                in cinder.conf:</para>
        <programlisting>
        backup_driver=cinder.backup.driver.ceph
        </programlisting>
        <para>The following configuration options are available for the
                Ceph backup driver.
        </para>
        <xi:include href="../../../common/tables/cinder-backups_ceph.xml" />
        <para>Here is an example of the default options for the Ceph backup
                driver.
        </para>
        <programlisting>
        backup_ceph_conf=/etc/ceph/ceph.conf
        backup_ceph_user=cinder
        backup_ceph_chunk_size=134217728
        backup_ceph_pool=backups
        backup_ceph_stripe_unit=0
        backup_ceph_stripe_count=0
        </programlisting>
</section>
