<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
<!ENTITY % openstack SYSTEM "../../common/entities/openstack.ent">
%openstack;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="glance-nova-image-download">
  <title>Image download: how it works</title>
  <para>
    Prior to starting a virtual machine, the virtual machine image
    used must be transferred to the compute node from the Image
    Service. How this works can change depending on the settings
    chosen for the compute node and the Image Service.
  </para>
  <para>
    Typically, the Compute service will use the image identifier
  passed to it by the scheduler service and request the image from the
  Image API. Though images are not stored in glance&mdash;rather in a
  back end, which could be Object Storage, a filesystem or any other
  supported method&mdash;the connection is made from the compute node
  to the Image Service and the image is transferred over this
  connection. The Image Service streams the image from the back end to the
  compute node.
  </para>
  <para>
    Certain back ends support a more direct method, where on request
    the Image Service will return a URL that can be used to
    download the image directly from the back-end store. Currently the
    only store to support the direct download approach is the
    filesystem store. It can be configured using the
    <option>filesystems</option> option in the
    <literal>image_file_url</literal> section of the
    <filename>nova.conf</filename> file on compute nodes.
  </para>
  <para>
    Compute nodes also implement caching of images, meaning that if an
    image has been used before it won't necessarily be downloaded
    every time. Information on the configuration options for caching
    on compute nodes can be found in the <link
    xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/trunk/config-reference/content/"><citetitle>Configuration
    Reference</citetitle></link>.
  </para>
</section>
