<section xml:id="section_compute-cells"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    version="5.0">
    <title>Cells</title>
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <para><emphasis role="italic">Cells</emphasis> functionality allows you to scale an OpenStack
        Compute cloud in a more distributed fashion without having to use complicated technologies
        like database and message queue clustering. It is intended to support very large
        deployments.</para>
    <para>When this functionality is enabled, the hosts in an OpenStack Compute cloud are
        partitioned into groups called cells. Cells are configured as a tree. The top-level cell
        should have a host that runs a <systemitem class="service">nova-api</systemitem> service,
        but no <systemitem class="service">nova-compute</systemitem> services. Each child cell
        should run all of the typical <systemitem class="service">nova-*</systemitem> services in a
        regular Compute cloud except for <systemitem class="service">nova-api</systemitem>. You can
        think of cells as a normal Compute deployment in that each cell has its own database server
        and message queue broker.</para>
    <para>The <systemitem class="service">nova-cells</systemitem> service handles communication
        between cells and selects cells for new instances. This service is required for every cell.
        Communication between cells is pluggable, and currently the only option is communication through
        RPC.</para>
    <para>Cells scheduling is separate from host scheduling. <systemitem
        class="service">nova-cells</systemitem>
        first picks a cell. Once a cell is selected and the new build
        request reaches its <systemitem
        class="service">nova-cells</systemitem> service, it is sent
        over to the host scheduler in that cell and the build proceeds
        as it would have without cells.</para>
        <warning>
            <para>Cell functionality is currently considered experimental.</para>
        </warning>
    <section xml:id="cell-config-options">
        <title>Cell configuration options</title>
        <para>Cells are disabled by default. All cell-related configuration options go under a
                <literal>[cells]</literal> section in <filename>nova.conf</filename>. The following
            cell-related options are currently supported:<variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><literal>enable</literal></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Set this is <literal>True</literal> to turn on cell functionality,
                            which is off by default.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><literal>name</literal></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Name of the current cell. This must be unique for each cell.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><literal>capabilities</literal></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>List of arbitrary
                                    <literal><replaceable>key</replaceable>=<replaceable>value</replaceable></literal>
                            pairs defining capabilities of the current cell.
                            Values include
                                <literal>hypervisor=xenserver;kvm,os=linux;windows</literal>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><literal>call_timeout</literal></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>How long in seconds to wait for replies from calls
                            between cells.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>scheduler_filter_classes</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Filter classes that the cells scheduler should use. By default, uses
                                "<literal>nova.cells.filters.all_filters</literal>" to map to all
                            cells filters included with Compute.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>scheduler_weight_classes</term>
                    <listitem><para>Weight classes the cells scheduler should use. By default, uses
                                "<literal>nova.cells.weights.all_weighers</literal>"
                            to map to all cells weight algorithms (weighers)
                            included with Compute.</para></listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>ram_weight_multiplier</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Multiplier used for weighing ram. Negative numbers
                            mean you want Compute to stack VMs on one host
                            instead of spreading out new VMs to more hosts in
                            the cell. Default value is 10.0.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="config-API-cell">
        <title>Configure the API (top-level) cell</title>
        <para>The compute API class must be changed in the API cell so that requests can be proxied
            through nova-cells down to the correct cell properly. Add the following to
                <filename>nova.conf</filename> in the API
            cell:<programlisting language="ini">[DEFAULT]
compute_api_class=nova.compute.cells_api.ComputeCellsAPI
...

[cells]
enable=True
name=api</programlisting></para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="config-child-cell">
        <title>Configure the child cells</title>
        <para>Add the following to <filename>nova.conf</filename> in the child cells, replacing
                <replaceable>cell1</replaceable> with the name of each
            cell:<programlisting language="ini">[DEFAULT]
# Disable quota checking in child cells.  Let API cell do it exclusively.
quota_driver=nova.quota.NoopQuotaDriver

[cells]
enable=True
name=<replaceable>cell1</replaceable></programlisting></para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="config-cell-db">
        <title>Configure the database in each cell</title>
        <para>Before bringing the services online, the database in each cell needs to be configured
            with information about related cells. In particular, the API cell needs to know about
            its immediate children, and the child cells must know about their immediate agents.
            The information needed is the <application>RabbitMQ</application> server credentials
            for the particular cell.</para>
        <para>Use the <command>nova-manage cell create</command> command to add this information to
            the database in each
            cell:<screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>nova-manage cell create -h</userinput>
<computeroutput>Options:
  -h, --help            show this help message and exit
  --name=&lt;name>         Name for the new cell
  --cell_type=&lt;parent|child>
                        Whether the cell is a parent or child
  --username=&lt;username>
                        Username for the message broker in this cell
  --password=&lt;password>
                        Password for the message broker in this cell
  --hostname=&lt;hostname>
                        Address of the message broker in this cell
  --port=&lt;number>       Port number of the message broker in this cell
  --virtual_host=&lt;virtual_host>
                        The virtual host of the message broker in this cell
  --woffset=&lt;float>
                        (weight offset) It might be used by some cell scheduling code in the future
  --wscale=&lt;float>
                        (weight scale) It might be used by some cell scheduling code in the future
</computeroutput></screen></para>
        <para>As an example, assume we have an API cell named <literal>api</literal> and a child
            cell named <literal>cell1</literal>. Within the api cell, we have the following RabbitMQ
            server
            info:<programlisting language="ini">rabbit_host=10.0.0.10
rabbit_port=5672
rabbit_username=api_user
rabbit_password=api_passwd
rabbit_virtual_host=api_vhost</programlisting></para>
        <para>And in the child cell named <literal>cell1</literal> we have the following RabbitMQ
            server
            info:<programlisting language="ini">rabbit_host=10.0.1.10
rabbit_port=5673
rabbit_username=cell1_user
rabbit_password=cell1_passwd
rabbit_virtual_host=cell1_vhost</programlisting></para>
        <para>We would run this in the API cell, as
            root.<screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>nova-manage cell create --name=cell1 --cell_type=child \
  --username=cell1_user --password=cell1_passwd --hostname=10.0.1.10 \
  --port=5673 --virtual_host=cell1_vhost --woffset=1.0 --wscale=1.0</userinput></screen>
        </para>
        <para>Repeat the above for all child cells.</para>
        <para>In the child cell, we would run the following, as
            root:<screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>nova-manage cell create --name=api --cell_type=parent \
  --username=api_user --password=api_passwd --hostname=10.0.0.10 \
  --port=5672 --virtual_host=api_vhost --woffset=1.0 --wscale=1.0</userinput></screen>
        </para>
        <para>To customize the Compute cells, use the configuration option
            settings documented in <xref
                linkend="config_table_nova_cells"/>.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="cell-weights-filters">
        <title>Cell scheduling configuration</title>
        <para>To determine the best cell for launching a new instance, Compute  uses a set of
            filters and weights configured in <filename>/etc/nova/nova.conf</filename>. The
            following options are available to prioritize cells for scheduling:</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><code>scheduler_filter_classes</code> - Specifies the list of filter
                        classes. By default <code>nova.cells.weights.all_filters</code> is
                        specified, which maps to all cells filters included with Compute (see
                        <xref linkend="scheduler-filters"/>).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><code>scheduler_weight_classes</code> - Specifies the list of weight
                        classes. By default <code>nova.cells.weights.all_weighers</code> is
                        specified, which maps to all cell weight algorithms (weighers) included with
                        Compute. The following modules are available:</para>
                    <itemizedlist><listitem>
                            <para><code>mute_child</code>: Downgrades the likelihood of child cells
                                being chosen for scheduling requests, which haven't sent capacity or
                                capability updates in a while. Options include
                                    <code>mute_weight_multiplier</code> (multiplier for mute
                                children; value should be negative) and
                                    <code>mute_weight_value</code> (assigned to mute children;
                                should be a positive value).</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><code>ram_by_instance_type</code>: Select cells with the most RAM
                                capacity for the instance type being requested. Because higher
                                weights win, Compute returns the number of available units for the
                                instance type requested. The <code>ram_weight_multiplier</code>
                                option defaults to 10.0 that adds to the weight by a factor of 10.
                                Use a negative number to stack VMs on one host instead of spreading
                                out new VMs to more hosts in the cell.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem><para><code>weight_offset</code>: Allows modifying the database to weight a particular cell. You can
                                use this when you want to disable a cell (for example, '0'), or to
                                set a default cell by making its weight_offset very high (for
                                example, '999999999999999'). The highest weight will be the first
                                cell to be scheduled for launching an instance.</para></listitem></itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
       </para>
        <para>Additionally, the following options are available for the cell scheduler:</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><code>scheduler_retries</code> - Specifies how many times the scheduler
                        tries to launch a new instance when no cells are available (default=10).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><code>scheduler_retry_delay</code> - Specifies the delay (in seconds)
                        between retries (default=2).</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
       </para>
        <para>As an admin user, you can also add a filter that directs builds to
            a particular cell. The <filename>policy.json</filename> file must
            have a line with <literal>"cells_scheduler_filter:TargetCellFilter"
                : "is_admin:True"</literal> to let an admin user specify a
            scheduler hint to direct a build to a particular cell.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="cell-config-optional-json">
        <title>Optional cell configuration</title>
        <para>Cells currently keeps all inter-cell communication data, including
            user names and passwords, in the database. This is undesirable and
            unnecessary since cells data isn't updated very frequently. Instead,
            create a JSON file to input cells data specified via a
                <code>[cells]cells_config</code> option. When specified, the
            database is no longer consulted when reloading cells data. The file
            will need the columns present in the Cell model (excluding common
            database fields and the <code>id</code> column). The queue
            connection information must be specified through a
                <code>transport_url</code> field, instead of
                <code>username</code>, <code>password</code>, and so on. The
                <code>transport_url</code> has the following form:</para>
            <programlisting>rabbit://<replaceable>USERNAME</replaceable>:<replaceable>PASSWORD</replaceable>@<replaceable>HOSTNAME</replaceable>:<replaceable>PORT</replaceable>/<replaceable>VIRTUAL_HOST</replaceable></programlisting>
        <para>The scheme can be either <literal>qpid</literal> or <literal>rabbit</literal>, as shown previously. The following sample shows this optional configuration:</para>
        <programlisting language="json"><xi:include href="samples/cells-resp.json" parse="text"/></programlisting>
    </section>
</section>
