<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="baremetal">
    <title>Baremetal driver</title>
    <para>The baremetal driver is a hypervisor driver for OpenStack Nova
        Compute. Within the OpenStack framework, it has the same role as the
        drivers for other hypervisors (libvirt, xen, etc), and yet it is
        presently unique in that the hardware is not virtualized - there is no
        hypervisor between the tenants and the physical hardware. It exposes
        hardware through the OpenStack APIs, using pluggable sub-drivers to deliver
        machine imaging (PXE) and power control (IPMI). With this, provisioning
        and management of physical hardware is accomplished by using common cloud
        APIs and tools, such as the Orchestration module (heat) or salt-cloud.
        However, due to this unique
        situation, using the baremetal driver requires some additional
        preparation of its environment, the details of which are beyond the
        scope of this guide.</para>
    <note><para>Some OpenStack Compute features are not implemented by
            the baremetal hypervisor driver.  See the <link
                xlink:href="http://wiki.openstack.org/HypervisorSupportMatrix">
                hypervisor support matrix</link> for details.</para></note>
    <para>For the Baremetal driver to be loaded and function properly,
        ensure that the following options are set in
        <filename>/etc/nova/nova.conf</filename> on your <systemitem
            class="service">nova-compute</systemitem> hosts.</para>
        <programlisting language="ini">[default]
compute_driver=nova.virt.baremetal.driver.BareMetalDriver
firewall_driver = nova.virt.firewall.NoopFirewallDriver
scheduler_host_manager=nova.scheduler.baremetal_host_manager.BaremetalHostManager
ram_allocation_ratio=1.0
reserved_host_memory_mb=0</programlisting>
    <para>Many configuration options are specific to the
        Baremetal driver.  Also, some additional steps are
        required, such as building the baremetal deploy ramdisk.  See
        the <link
            xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Baremetal">main wiki page</link> for details and implementation suggestions.
   </para>
   <para>To customize the Baremetal driver, use the configuration option
       settings documented in <xref
           linkend="config_table_nova_baremetal"/>.</para>
</section>
