<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="section_compute-configure-xen">
    <title>Xen configuration reference</title>
    <para>
        The following section discusses some commonly changed options in
        XenServer.  The table below provides a complete reference of all
        configuration options available for configuring Xen with OpenStack.
    </para>
    <para>
        The recommended way to use Xen with OpenStack is through the XenAPI
        driver. To enable the XenAPI driver, add the following configuration
        options <filename>/etc/nova/nova.conf</filename> and restart the
        <systemitem class="service">nova-compute</systemitem> service:
    </para>
    <programlisting language="ini">compute_driver = xenapi.XenAPIDriver
xenapi_connection_url = http://your_xenapi_management_ip_address
xenapi_connection_username = root
xenapi_connection_password = your_password</programlisting>
    <para>
        These connection details are used by the OpenStack Compute service to
        contact your hypervisor and are the same details you use to connect
        XenCenter, the XenServer management console, to your XenServer or XCP
        box.
    </para>
    <note>
        <para>
            The <literal>xenapi_connection_url</literal> is generally the
            management network IP address of the XenServer. Though it is
            possible to use the internal network IP Address (169.250.0.1) to
            contact XenAPI, this does not allow live migration between hosts.
            Other functionalities such as host aggregates, do not work.
        </para>
    </note>
    <para>
        It is possible to manage Xen using libvirt, though this is not
        well-tested or supported. To experiment using Xen through libvirt add
        the following configuration options
        <filename>/etc/nova/nova.conf</filename>:
        <programlisting language="ini">compute_driver = libvirt.LibvirtDriver

[libvirt]
virt_type = xen</programlisting>
    </para>
    <section xml:id="xen-agent">
        <title>Agent</title>
        <para>
            If you don't have the guest agent on your VMs, it takes a long time
            for nova to decide the VM has successfully started.  Generally a
            large timeout is required for Windows instances, but you may want
            to tweak <literal>agent_version_timeout</literal>.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="xen-firewall">
        <title>Firewall</title>
        <para>
            If using nova-network, iptables is supported:
            <programlisting language="ini">firewall_driver = nova.virt.firewall.IptablesFirewallDriver</programlisting>
            Alternately, doing the isolation in Dom0:
            <programlisting language="ini">firewall_driver = nova.virt.xenapi.firewall.Dom0IptablesFirewallDriver</programlisting>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="xen-vnc">
        <title>VNC proxy address</title>
        <para>
            Assuming you are talking to XenAPI through the host local
            management network, and XenServer is on the address: 169.254.0.1,
            you can use the following:
            <literal>vncserver_proxyclient_address=169.254.0.1</literal>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="xen-storage">
        <title>Storage</title>
        <para>
            You can specify which Storage Repository to use with nova by
            looking at the following flag.  The default is to use the
            local-storage setup by the default installer:
            <programlisting language="ini">sr_matching_filter = "other-config:i18n-key=local-storage"</programlisting>
            Another good alternative is to use the "default" storage (for
            example if you have attached NFS or any other shared storage):
            <programlisting language="ini">sr_matching_filter = "default-sr:true"</programlisting>
            <note>
                <para>
                    To use a XenServer pool, you must create the pool by using
                    the Host Aggregates feature.
                </para>
            </note>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="xen-config-reference-table">
        <title>Xen configuration reference</title>
        <para>
            To customize the Xen driver, use the configuration option settings
            documented in <xref linkend="config_table_nova_xen"/>.
        </para>
    </section>
</section>
