<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="section_conductor">
    <title>Conductor</title>
<para>The <systemitem class="service">nova-conductor</systemitem>
        service enables OpenStack to function without compute nodes
        accessing the database. Conceptually, it implements a new
        layer on top of <systemitem class="service"
            >nova-compute</systemitem>. It should not be deployed on
        compute nodes, or else the security benefits of removing
        database access from <systemitem class="service"
            >nova-compute</systemitem> are negated. Just like
        other nova services such as <systemitem class="service"
            >nova-api</systemitem> or nova-scheduler, it can be scaled
        horizontally. You can run multiple instances of <systemitem
            class="service">nova-conductor</systemitem> on different
        machines as needed for scaling purposes.</para>
<para>The methods exposed by <systemitem
            class="service">nova-conductor</systemitem> are relatively
        simple methods used by <systemitem class="service"
            >nova-compute</systemitem> to offload its database
        operations. Places where <systemitem class="service"
            >nova-compute</systemitem> previously performed database
        access are now talking to <systemitem class="service"
            >nova-conductor</systemitem>. However, we have plans in
        the medium to long term to move more and more of what is
        currently in <systemitem class="service"
            >nova-compute</systemitem> up to the <systemitem
            class="service">nova-conductor</systemitem> layer. The
        Compute service will start to look like a less intelligent
        slave service to <systemitem class="service"
            >nova-conductor</systemitem>. The conductor service will
        implement long running complex operations, ensuring forward
        progress and graceful error handling. This will be especially
        beneficial for operations that cross multiple compute nodes,
        such as migrations or resizes.</para>
<para>To customize the Conductor, use the configuration option settings
    documented in <xref linkend="config_table_nova_conductor"/>.</para>
</section>

