<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
xml:id="docker">
    <title>Docker driver</title>
    <para>The Docker driver is a hypervisor driver for OpenStack Compute,
    introduced with the Havana release. Docker is an open-source engine which
    automates the deployment of applications as highly portable, self-sufficient
    containers which are independent of hardware, language, framework, packaging
    system and hosting provider. Docker extends LXC with a high level API
    providing a lightweight virtualization solution that runs processes in
    isolation. It provides a way to automate software deployment in a secure and
    repeatable environment. A standard container in Docker contains a software
    component along with all of its dependencies - binaries, libraries,
    configuration files, scripts, virtualenvs, jars, gems and tarballs. Docker
    can be run on any x86_64 Linux kernel that supports cgroups and aufs. Docker
    is a way of managing LXC containers on a single machine. However used behind
    OpenStack Compute makes Docker much more powerful since it is then possible
    to manage several hosts which will then manage hundreds of containers. The
    current Docker project aims for full OpenStack compatibility. Containers
    don't aim to be a replacement for VMs, they are just complementary in the
    sense that they are better for specific use cases. Compute's support for VMs
    is currently advanced thanks to the variety of hypervisors running VMs.
    However it's not the case for containers even though libvirt/LXC is a good
    starting point. Docker aims to go the second level of integration.</para>
    <note><para>
            Some OpenStack Compute features are not implemented by
            the docker driver.  See the <link
                xlink:href="http://wiki.openstack.org/HypervisorSupportMatrix">
                hypervisor support matrix</link> for details.
   </para></note>
   <important>
       <para>
           The Docker driver only supports Linux Bridge networking
           at this time.
       </para>
   </important>
    <para>To enable Docker, ensure the following options are set in
      <filename>/etc/nova/nova-compute.conf</filename> on all hosts running the
      <systemitem class="service">nova-compute</systemitem> service.
      <programlisting language="ini">compute_driver=docker.DockerDriver</programlisting></para>
    <para>Glance also needs to be configured to support the Docker container format, in
    <filename>/etc/glance-api.conf</filename>:
     <programlisting language="ini">container_formats = ami,ari,aki,bare,ovf,docker</programlisting></para>
<xi:include href="../../common/tables/nova-docker.xml"/>
</section>
