<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="introduction-to-xen">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title xml:id="introduction-to-xen.title">Xen, XAPI, XenServer</title>
    <para>
        This section describes XAPI managed hypervisors, and how to
        use them with OpenStack.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="basic-terminology">
        <title>Terminology</title>
        <section xml:id="terminology-xen">
            <title>Xen</title>
            <para>
                A hypervisor that provides the fundamental isolation between
                virtual machines. Xen is open source (GPLv2) and is managed by
                Xen.org, a cross-industry organization and a Linux
                Foundation Collaborative project.
            </para>
            <para>
                Xen is a component of many different products and projects. The
                hypervisor itself is very similar across all these projects,
                but the way that it is managed can be different, which can
                cause confusion if you're not clear which toolstack you are
                using. Make sure you know what toolstack you want before you
                get started.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="terminology-xapi">
            <title>XAPI</title>
            <para>
                XAPI is one of the toolstacks that could control a Xen based
                hypervisor. XAPI's role is similar to libvirt's in the KVM
                world. The API provided by XAPI is called XenAPI. To learn more
                about the provided interface, look at
                <link
                    xlink:href="http://docs.vmd.citrix.com/XenServer/6.2.0/1.0/en_gb/sdk.html#object_model_overview" >
                    XenAPI Object Model Overview
                </link>
                for definitions of XAPI specific terms such as SR, VDI, VIF
                and PIF.
            </para>
            <para>
                OpenStack has a compute driver which talks to XAPI, therefore
                all XAPI managed servers could be used with OpenStack.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="terminology-xenapi">
            <title>XenAPI</title>
            <para>
                XenAPI is the API provided by XAPI. This name is also used by
                the python library that is a client for XAPI.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="terminology-xenserver">
            <title>XenServer</title>
            <para>
                An Open Source virtualization software which includes the Xen
                hypervisor and XAPI for the management. For more information
                and product downloads, visit
                <link
                    xlink:href="http://xenserver.org/">
                    xenserver.org
                </link>.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="privileged-and-unprivileged-domains">
            <title>Privileged and unprivileged domains</title>
            <para>
                A Xen host runs a number of virtual machines, VMs, or domains
                (the terms are synonymous on Xen). One of these is in charge of
                running the rest of the system, and is known as domain 0, or
                dom0. It is the first domain to boot after Xen, and owns the
                storage and networking hardware, the device drivers, and the
                primary control software. Any other VM is unprivileged, and is
                known as a domU or guest.  All customer VMs are unprivileged,
                but you should note that on Xen, the OpenStack Compute service
                (<systemitem class="service">nova-compute</systemitem>)
                also runs in a domU.  This gives a level of security isolation
                between the privileged system software and the OpenStack
                software (much of which is customer-facing). This architecture
                is described in more detail later.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="paravirtualized-vs-hvm-domains">
            <title>Paravirtualized versus hardware virtualized domains</title>
            <para>
                A Xen virtual machine can be paravirtualized (PV) or hardware
                virtualized (HVM). This refers to the interaction between Xen,
                domain 0, and the guest VM's kernel.  PV guests are aware of
                the fact that they are virtualized and will co-operate with Xen
                and domain 0; this gives them better performance
                characteristics. HVM guests are not aware of their environment,
                and the hardware has to pretend that they are running on an
                unvirtualized machine. HVM guests do not need to modify the
                guest operating system, which is essential when running
                Windows.
            </para>
            <para>
                In OpenStack, customer VMs may run in either PV or HVM mode.
                However, the OpenStack domU (that's the one running
                <systemitem class="service">nova-compute</systemitem>) must be
                running in PV mode.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="xenapi-deployment-architecture">
        <title xml:id="xenapi-deployment-architecture.title">
            XenAPI deployment architecture
        </title>
        <para>
            A basic OpenStack deployment on a XAPI-managed server, assuming
            that the network provider is nova-network, looks like this:
            <informalfigure>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata
                            fileref="../../common/figures/xenserver_architecture.png"
                            contentwidth="140mm"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
        </para>
        <para>
            Key things to note:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The hypervisor: Xen
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Domain 0: runs XAPI and some small pieces from
                        OpenStack, the XAPI plug-ins.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        OpenStack VM: The
                        <systemitem class="service">Compute</systemitem>
                        service runs in a paravirtualized virtual machine, on
                        the host under management. Each host runs a local
                        instance of
                        <systemitem class="service">Compute</systemitem>.
                        It is also running an instance of nova-network.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        OpenStack Compute uses the XenAPI Python library to
                        talk to XAPI, and it uses the Management Network to
                        reach from the OpenStack VM to Domain 0.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
            Some notes on the networking:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The above diagram assumes FlatDHCP networking.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        There are three main OpenStack networks:
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Management network: RabbitMQ, MySQL,
                                    inter-host communication, and compute-XAPI
                                    communication.  Please note that the VM
                                    images are downloaded by the XenAPI
                                    plug-ins, so make sure that the OpenStack
                                    Image Service is accessible through this
                                    network. It usually means binding those
                                    services to the management interface.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Tenant network: controlled by
                                    nova-network, this is used for tenant
                                    traffic.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Public network: floating IPs, public API
                                    endpoints.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The networks shown here must be connected to the
                        corresponding physical networks within the data center.
                        In the simplest case, three individual physical network
                        cards could be used. It is also possible to use VLANs
                        to separate these networks. Please note, that the
                        selected configuration must be in line with the
                        networking model selected for the cloud.  (In case of
                        VLAN networking, the physical channels have to be able
                        to forward the tagged traffic.)
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="further-reading">
        <title>Further reading</title>
        <para>
            Here are some of the resources available to learn more
            about Xen:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Citrix XenServer official documentation:
                        <link
                            xlink:href="http://docs.vmd.citrix.com/XenServer/6.2.0/1.0/en_gb/">
                            http://docs.vmd.citrix.com/XenServer
                        </link>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        What is Xen? by Xen.org:
                        <link
                            xlink:href="http://xen.org/files/Marketing/WhatisXen.pdf">
                            http://xen.org/files/Marketing/WhatisXen.pdf
                        </link>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Xen Hypervisor project:
                        <link
                            xlink:href="http://www.xenproject.org/developers/teams/hypervisor.html">
                            http://www.xenproject.org/developers/teams/hypervisor.html
                        </link>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Xapi project:
                        <link
                            xlink:href="http://www.xenproject.org/developers/teams/xapi.html">
                            http://www.xenproject.org/developers/teams/xapi.html
                        </link>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Further XenServer and OpenStack information:
                        <link
                            xlink:href="http://wiki.openstack.org/XenServer">
                            http://wiki.openstack.org/XenServer
                        </link>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
    <xi:include href="section_xen-install.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="section_compute-configure-xen.xml"/>
</section>
