<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="section_compute-configure-xen">
    <title>Xen configuration reference</title>
    <para>
        The following section discusses some commonly changed options when
        using the XenAPI driver. The table below provides a complete reference
        of all configuration options available for configuring XAPI with
        OpenStack.
    </para>
    <para>
        The recommended way to use XAPI with OpenStack is through the XenAPI
        driver. To enable the XenAPI driver, add the following configuration
        options to <filename>/etc/nova/nova.conf</filename> and restart
        <systemitem class="service">OpenStack Compute</systemitem>:
    </para>
    <programlisting language="ini">compute_driver = xenapi.XenAPIDriver
[xenserver]
connection_url = http://<replaceable>your_xenapi_management_ip_address</replaceable>
connection_username = root
connection_password = <replaceable>your_password</replaceable></programlisting>
    <para>
        These connection details are used by OpenStack Compute service to
        contact your hypervisor and are the same details you use to connect
        XenCenter, the XenServer management console, to your XenServer node.
    </para>
    <note>
        <para>
            The <literal>connection_url</literal> is generally the
            management network IP address of the XenServer.
        </para>
    </note>
    <section xml:id="xen-agent">
        <title>Agent</title>
        <para>
            The agent is a piece of software that runs on the instances, and
            communicates with OpenStack. In case of the XenAPI driver, the
            agent communicates with OpenStack through XenStore (see
            <link xlink:href="http://wiki.xen.org/wiki/XenStore">the Xen Wiki</link>
            for more information on XenStore).
        </para>
        <para>
            If you don't have the guest agent on your VMs, it takes a long time
            for OpenStack Compute to detect that the VM has successfully
            started.  Generally a large timeout is required for Windows
            instances, but you may want to adjust:
            <literal>agent_version_timeout</literal> within the
            <literal>[xenserver]</literal> section.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="xen-vnc">
        <title>VNC proxy address</title>
        <para>
            Assuming you are talking to XAPI through a management network, and
            XenServer is on the address: 10.10.1.34 specify the same address
            for the vnc proxy address:
            <literal>vncserver_proxyclient_address=<replaceable>10.10.1.34</replaceable></literal>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="xen-storage">
        <title>Storage</title>
        <para>
            You can specify which Storage Repository to use with nova by
            editing the following flag. To use the local-storage setup by the
            default installer:
            <programlisting language="ini">sr_matching_filter = "other-config:i18n-key=local-storage"</programlisting>
            Another alternative is to use the "default" storage (for example if
            you have attached NFS or any other shared storage):
            <programlisting language="ini">sr_matching_filter = "default-sr:true"</programlisting>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="xen-config-reference-table">
        <title>XenAPI configuration reference</title>
        <para>
            To customize the XenAPI driver, use the configuration option
            settings documented in <xref linkend="config_table_nova_xen"/>.
        </para>
    </section>
</section>
