<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="introduction-to-xen">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title xml:id="introduction-to-xen.title">Xen, XenAPI, XenServer,
        and XCP</title>
    <warning><title>This section needs help</title>
    <para>This section is low quality, and contains out of date information.
    The Documentation Team is currently looking for individuals with
    experience with the hypervisor to
    <link xlink:href="https://blueprints.launchpad.net/openstack-manuals/+spec/redocument-xen">Re-document
     Xen integration with OpenStack</link>.</para>
    </warning>
    <para>This section describes Xen, XenAPI, XenServer, and XCP,
        their differences, and how to use them with OpenStack. After
        you understand how the Xen and KVM architectures differ, you
        can determine when to use each architecture in your OpenStack
        cloud.</para>
    <section xml:id="basic-terminology">
        <title>Xen terminology</title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Xen</emphasis>. A hypervisor that
            provides the fundamental isolation between virtual
            machines. Xen is open source (GPLv2) and is managed by
            Xen.org, an cross-industry organization.</para>
        <para>Xen is a component of many different products and
            projects. The hypervisor itself is very similar across all
            these projects, but the way that it is managed can be
            different, which can cause confusion if you're not clear
            which tool stack you are using. Make sure you know what
            tool stack you want before you get started.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Xen Cloud Platform
                (XCP)</emphasis>. An open source (GPLv2) tool stack
            for Xen. It is designed specifically as a platform for
            enterprise and cloud computing, and is well integrated
            with OpenStack. XCP is available both as a binary
            distribution, installed from an iso, and from Linux
            distributions, such as <link
                xlink:href="http://packages.ubuntu.com/precise/xcp-xapi"
                >xcp-xapi</link> in Ubuntu. The current versions of
            XCP available in Linux distributions do not yet include
            all the features available in the binary distribution of
            XCP.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Citrix XenServer</emphasis>. A
            commercial product. It is based on XCP, and exposes the
            same tool stack and management API. As an analogy, think
            of XenServer being based on XCP in the way that Red Hat
            Enterprise Linux is based on Fedora. XenServer has a free
            version (which is very similar to XCP) and paid-for
            versions with additional features enabled. Citrix provides
            support for XenServer, but as of July 2012, they do not
            provide any support for XCP. For a comparison between
            these products see the <link
                xlink:href="http://wiki.xen.org/wiki/XCP/XenServer_Feature_Matrix"
                > XCP Feature Matrix</link>.</para>
        <para>Both XenServer and XCP include Xen, Linux, and the
            primary control daemon known as <emphasis role="bold"
                >xapi</emphasis>.</para>
        <para>The API shared between XCP and XenServer is called
                <emphasis role="bold">XenAPI</emphasis>. OpenStack
            usually refers to XenAPI, to indicate that the integration
            works equally well on XCP and XenServer. Sometimes, a
            careless person will refer to XenServer specifically, but
            you can be reasonably confident that anything that works
            on XenServer will also work on the latest version of XCP.
            Read the <link
                xlink:href="http://docs.vmd.citrix.com/XenServer/6.0.0/1.0/en_gb/sdk.html#object_model_overview"
                > XenAPI Object Model Overview</link> for definitions
            of XenAPI specific terms such as SR, VDI, VIF and
            PIF.</para>
        <section xml:id="privileged-and-unprivileged-domains">
            <title>Privileged and unprivileged domains</title>
            <para>A Xen host runs a number of virtual machines, VMs,
                or domains (the terms are synonymous on Xen). One of
                these is in charge of running the rest of the system,
                and is known as "domain 0," or "dom0." It is the first
                domain to boot after Xen, and owns the storage and
                networking hardware, the device drivers, and the
                primary control software. Any other VM is
                unprivileged, and are known as a "domU" or "guest".
                All customer VMs are unprivileged of course, but you
                should note that on Xen the OpenStack control software
                    (<systemitem class="service"
                    >nova-compute</systemitem>) also runs in a domU.
                This gives a level of security isolation between the
                privileged system software and the OpenStack software
                (much of which is customer-facing). This architecture
                is described in more detail later.</para>
            <para>There is an ongoing project to split domain 0 into
                multiple privileged domains known as <emphasis
                    role="bold">driver domains</emphasis> and
                    <emphasis role="bold">stub domains</emphasis>.
                This would give even better separation between
                critical components. This technology is what powers
                Citrix XenClient RT, and is likely to be added into
                XCP in the next few years. However, the current
                architecture just has three levels of separation:
                dom0, the OpenStack domU, and the completely
                unprivileged customer VMs.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="paravirtualized-vs-hvm-domains">
            <title>Paravirtualized versus hardware virtualized
                domains</title>
            <para>A Xen virtual machine can be <emphasis role="bold"
                    >paravirtualized (PV)</emphasis> or <emphasis
                    role="bold">hardware virtualized (HVM)</emphasis>.
                This refers to the interaction between Xen, domain 0,
                and the guest VM's kernel. PV guests are aware of the
                fact that they are virtualized and will co-operate
                with Xen and domain 0; this gives them better
                performance characteristics. HVM guests are not aware
                of their environment, and the hardware has to pretend
                that they are running on an unvirtualized machine. HVM
                guests do not need to
                modify the guest operating system, which is essential
                when running Windows.</para>
            <para>In OpenStack, customer VMs may run in either PV or
                HVM mode. However, the OpenStack domU (that's the one
                running <systemitem class="service"
                    >nova-compute</systemitem>) <emphasis role="bold"
                    >must</emphasis> be running in PV mode.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="xenapi-deployment-architecture">
        <title xml:id="xenapi-deployment-architecture.title">XenAPI
            Deployment Architecture</title>
        <para>When you deploy OpenStack on XCP or XenServer, you get
            something similar to this: <informalfigure>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata
                            fileref="../../common/figures/xenserver_architecture.png"
                            contentwidth="140mm"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure></para>
        <para>Key things to note: <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The hypervisor: Xen</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Domain 0: runs xapi and some small pieces
                        from OpenStack (some xapi plug-ins and network
                        isolation rules). The majority of this is
                        provided by XenServer or XCP (or yourself
                        using Kronos).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>OpenStack VM: The <systemitem
                            class="service">nova-compute</systemitem>
                        code runs in a paravirtualized virtual
                        machine, running on the host under management.
                        Each host runs a local instance of <systemitem
                            class="service">nova-compute</systemitem>.
                        It will often also be running nova-network
                        (depending on your network mode). In this
                        case, nova-network is managing the addresses
                        given to the tenant VMs through DHCP.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Nova uses the XenAPI Python library to talk
                        to xapi, and it uses the Management Network to
                        reach from the domU to dom0 without leaving
                        the host.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        <para>Some notes on the networking: <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The above diagram assumes FlatDHCP
                        networking (the DevStack default).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>There are three main OpenStack Networks:<itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Management network - RabbitMQ,
                                   MySQL, and other services. Please note that
                                   the VM images are downloaded by the XenAPI
                                   plug-ins, so make sure that the
                                   images can be downloaded through
                                   the management network. It usually
                                   means binding those services to the
                                   management interface.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Tenant network - controlled by
                                   nova-network. The parameters of
                                   this network depend on the
                                   networking model selected (Flat,
                                   Flat DHCP, VLAN).</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Public network - floating IPs,
                                   public API endpoints.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The networks shown here must be connected
                        to the corresponding physical networks within
                        the data center. In the simplest case, three
                        individual physical network cards could be
                        used. It is also possible to use VLANs to
                        separate these networks. Please note, that the
                        selected configuration must be in line with
                        the networking model selected for the cloud.
                        (In case of VLAN networking, the physical
                        channels have to be able to forward the tagged
                        traffic.)</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="pools">
        <title>XenAPI pools</title>
        <para>The host-aggregates feature enables you to create pools
            of XenServer hosts to enable live migration when using
            shared storage. However, you cannot configure shared
            storage.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="further-reading">
        <title>Further reading</title>
        <para>Here are some of the resources available to learn more
            about Xen: <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Citrix XenServer official
                            documentation:<link
                            xlink:href="http://docs.vmd.citrix.com/XenServer/6.0.0/1.0/en_gb/"
                            >
                            http://docs.vmd.citrix.com/XenServer</link>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What is Xen? by Xen.org: <link
                            xlink:href="http://xen.org/files/Marketing/WhatisXen.pdf"
                            >
                            http://xen.org/files/Marketing/WhatisXen.pdf</link>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Xen Hypervisor project: <link
                            xlink:href="http://xen.org/products/xenhyp.html"
                            >
                            http://xen.org/products/xenhyp.html</link>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>XCP project: <link
                            xlink:href="http://xen.org/products/cloudxen.html"
                            >
                            http://xen.org/products/cloudxen.html</link>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Further XenServer and OpenStack information:
                            <link
                            xlink:href="http://wiki.openstack.org/XenServer"
                            >
                            http://wiki.openstack.org/XenServer</link>.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>
    <xi:include href="../../common/section_xen-install.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="section_compute-configure-xen.xml"/>
</section>
