<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
  xml:id="vmware">
  <title>VMware vSphere</title>
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
  <section xml:id="vmware-intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>OpenStack Compute supports the VMware vSphere product family
      and enables access to advanced features such as vMotion, High
      Availability, and Dynamic Resource Scheduling (DRS). This
      section describes how to configure VMware-based virtual machine
      images for launch. vSphere versions 4.1 and newer are
      supported.</para>
    <para>The VMware vCenter driver enables the <systemitem
      class="service">nova-compute</systemitem> service to communicate with
      a VMware vCenter server that manages one or more ESX host
      clusters. The driver aggregates the ESX hosts in each cluster to
      present one large hypervisor entity for each cluster to the
      Compute scheduler. Because individual ESX hosts are not exposed
      to the scheduler, Compute schedules to the granularity of
      clusters and vCenter uses DRS to select the actual ESX host
      within the cluster. When a virtual machine makes its way into a
      vCenter cluster, it can use all vSphere features.</para>
    <para>The following sections describe how to configure the VMware
      vCenter driver.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="vmware_architecture">
    <title>High-level architecture</title>
    <para>The following diagram shows a high-level view of the VMware
      driver architecture:</para>
    <figure>
      <title>VMware driver architecture</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata
            fileref="../../common/figures/vmware-nova-driver-architecture.jpg"
            format="JPG" contentwidth="6in"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>As the figure shows, the OpenStack Compute Scheduler sees
      three hypervisors that each correspond to a cluster in vCenter.
        <systemitem class="service">Nova-compute</systemitem> contains
      the VMware driver. You can run with multiple <systemitem
        class="service">nova-compute</systemitem> services. While
      Compute schedules at the granularity of a cluster, the VMware
      driver inside <systemitem class="service"
        >nova-compute</systemitem> interacts with the vCenter APIs to
      select an appropriate ESX host within the cluster. Internally,
      vCenter uses DRS for placement.</para>
    <para>The VMware vCenter driver also interacts with the OpenStack
      Image Service to copy VMDK images from the Image Service back
      end store. The dotted line in the figure represents VMDK images
      being copied from the OpenStack Image Service to the vSphere
      data store. VMDK images are cached in the data store so the copy
      operation is only required the first time that the VMDK image is
      used.</para>
    <para>After OpenStack boots a VM into a vSphere cluster, the VM
      becomes visible in vCenter and can access vSphere advanced
      features. At the same time, the VM is visible in the OpenStack
      dashboard and you can manage it as you would any other OpenStack
      VM. You can perform advanced vSphere operations in vCenter while
      you configure OpenStack resources such as VMs through the
      OpenStack dashboard.</para>
    <para>The figure does not show how networking fits into the
      architecture. Both <systemitem class="service"
        >nova-network</systemitem> and the OpenStack Networking
      Service are supported. For details, see <xref
        linkend="VMWare_networking"/>.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="vmware_configuration_overview">
    <title>Configuration overview</title>
    <para>To get started with the VMware vCenter driver, complete the
      following high-level steps:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Configure vCenter correctly. See <xref
            linkend="vmware-prereqs"/>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Configure <filename>nova.conf</filename> for the VMware
          vCenter driver. See <xref linkend="VMWareVCDriver_details"
          />.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Load desired VMDK images into the OpenStack Image
          Service. See <xref linkend="VMWare_images"/>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Configure networking with either <systemitem
            class="service">nova-network</systemitem> or the OpenStack
          Networking Service. See <xref linkend="VMWare_networking"
          />.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="vmware-prereqs">
    <title>Prerequisites and limitations</title>
    <para>Use the following list to prepare a vSphere environment that
      runs with the VMware vCenter driver:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Copying VMDK files (vSphere 5.1
          only).</emphasis> In vSphere 5.1, copying large image files
          (for example, 12 GB and greater) from Glance can take a long
          time. To improve performance, VMware recommends that you
          upgrade to VMware vCenter Server 5.1 Update 1 or later. For
          more information, see the <link xlink:href="https://www.vmware.com/support/vsphere5/doc/vsphere-vcenter-server-51u1-release-notes.html#resolvedissuescimapi">Release Notes</link>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">vCenter inventory</emphasis>. Make
          sure that any vCenter used by OpenStack contains a single
          data center. A future Havana stable release will address
          this temporary limitation.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">DRS</emphasis>. For any cluster
          that contains multiple ESX hosts, enable DRS and enable
          fully automated placement.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Shared storage</emphasis>. Only
          shared storage is supported and data stores must be shared
          among all hosts in a cluster. It is recommended to remove
          data stores not intended for OpenStack from clusters being
          configured for OpenStack.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Clusters and data
            stores</emphasis>. Do not use OpenStack clusters and data
          stores for other purposes. If you do, OpenStack displays
          incorrect usage information.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Networking</emphasis>. The
          networking configuration depends on the desired networking
          model. See <xref linkend="VMWare_networking"/>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Security groups</emphasis>. If you
          use the VMware driver with OpenStack Networking and the NSX
          plug-in, security groups are supported. If you use
            <systemitem class="service">nova-network</systemitem>,
          security groups are not supported.</para>
        <note><para>The NSX plug-in is the only plug-in that is
          validated for vSphere.</para></note>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">VNC</emphasis>. The port range
          5900 - 6105 (inclusive) is automatically enabled for VNC
          connections on every ESX host in all clusters under
          OpenStack control. For more information about using a VNC
          client to connect to virtual machine, see <link
            xlink:href="http://kb.vmware.com/selfservice/microsites/search.do?language=en_US&amp;cmd=displayKC&amp;externalId=1246"
            >http://kb.vmware.com/selfservice/microsites/search.do?language=en_US&amp;cmd=displayKC&amp;externalId=1246</link>.
        </para>
        <note><para>In addition to the default VNC port
          numbers (5900 to 6000) specified in the above document, the
          following ports are also used: 6101, 6102, and 6105.</para></note>
        <para>You must modify the ESXi firewall configuration to allow
          the VNC ports. Additionally, for the firewall modifications
          to persist after a reboot, you must create a custom vSphere
          Installation Bundle (VIB) which is then installed onto the
          running ESXi host or added to a custom image profile used to
          install ESXi hosts. For details about how to create a VIB
          for persisting the firewall configuration modifications, see
            <link
            xlink:href="http://kb.vmware.com/selfservice/microsites/search.do?language=en_US&amp;cmd=displayKC&amp;externalId=2007381"
            >
            http://kb.vmware.com/selfservice/microsites/search.do?language=en_US&amp;cmd=displayKC&amp;externalId=2007381</link>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Ephemeral Disks</emphasis>.
          Ephemeral disks are not supported. A future stable release
          will address this temporary limitation.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="VMWareVCDriver_details">
    <title>VMware vCenter driver</title>
    <para>Use the VMware vCenter driver (VMwareVCDriver) to connect
      OpenStack Compute with vCenter. This recommended configuration
      enables access through vCenter to advanced vSphere features like
      vMotion, High Availability, and Dynamic Resource Scheduling
      (DRS).</para>
    <section xml:id="VMWareVCDriver_configuration_options">
      <title>VMwareVCDriver configuration options</title>
      <para>When you use the VMwareVCDriver (vCenter versions 5.1 and
        later) with OpenStack Compute, add the following
        VMware-specific configuration options to the
        <filename>nova.conf</filename> file:</para>
      <programlisting language="ini">[DEFAULT]
compute_driver=vmwareapi.VMwareVCDriver

[vmware]
host_ip=&lt;vCenter host IP&gt;
host_username=&lt;vCenter username&gt;
host_password=&lt;vCenter password&gt;
cluster_name=&lt;vCenter cluster name&gt;
datastore_regex=&lt;optional datastore regex&gt;</programlisting>
      <note>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>vSphere vCenter versions 5.0 and earlier: You must
              specify the location of the WSDL files by adding the
            <code>wsdl_location=http://127.0.0.1:8080/vmware/SDK/wsdl/vim25/vimService.wsdl</code>
              setting to the above configuration. For more
              information, see
              <link linkend="VMWare_additional_config">vSphere 5.0 and
              earlier additional set up</link>.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Clusters: The vCenter driver can support multiple
              clusters. To use more than one cluster, simply add
              multiple <option>cluster_name</option> lines in
                <filename>nova.conf</filename> with the appropriate
              cluster name. Clusters and data stores used by the
              vCenter driver should not contain any VMs other than
              those created by the driver.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Data stores: The <option>datastore_regex</option>
              setting specifies the data stores to use with Compute.
              For example, <option>datastore_regex="nas.*"</option>
              selects all the data stores that have a name starting
              with "nas". If this line is omitted, Compute uses the
              first data store returned by the vSphere API. It is
              recommended not to use this field and instead remove
              data stores that are not intended for OpenStack.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Reserved host memory:
              The <option>reserved_host_memory_mb</option> setting is set
              to 512 MB by default. However, VMware recommends setting
              this value to 0 MB because the vCenter driver reports
              the effective memory available to the virtual machines.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </note>
      <para>A <systemitem class="service">nova-compute</systemitem>
        service can control one or more clusters containing multiple
        ESX hosts, making <systemitem class="service"
          >nova-compute</systemitem> a critical service from a high
        availability perspective. Because the host that runs
          <systemitem class="service">nova-compute</systemitem> can
        fail while the vCenter and ESX still run, you must protect the
          <systemitem class="service">nova-compute</systemitem>
        service against host failures.</para>
      <note>
        <para>Many <filename>nova.conf</filename> options are relevant
          to libvirt but do not apply to this driver.</para>
      </note>
      <para>You must complete additional configuration for
        environments that use vSphere 5.0 and earlier. See <xref
          linkend="VMWare_additional_config"/>.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="VMWare_images">
    <title>Images with VMware vSphere</title>
    <para>The vCenter driver supports images in the VMDK format. Disks
      in this format can be obtained from VMware Fusion or from an ESX
      environment. It is also possible to convert other formats, such
      as qcow2, to the VMDK format using the <option>qemu-img</option>
      utility. After a VMDK disk is available, load it into the
      OpenStack Image Service. Then, you can use it with the VMware
      vCenter driver. The following sections provide additional
      details on the supported disks and the commands used for
      conversion and upload.</para>
    <section xml:id="VMware_supported_images">
      <title>Supported image types</title>
      <para>Upload images to the OpenStack Image Service in VMDK
        format. The following VMDK disk types are supported:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">VMFS Flat Disks</emphasis>
            (includes thin, thick, zeroedthick, and eagerzeroedthick).
            Note that once a VMFS thin disk is exported from VMFS to a
            non-VMFS location, like the OpenStack Image Service, it
            becomes a preallocated flat disk. This impacts the
            transfer time from the OpenStack Image Service to the data
            store when the full preallocated flat disk, rather than
            the thin disk, must be transferred.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="italic">Monolithic Sparse
              disks</emphasis>. Sparse disks get imported from the
            OpenStack Image Service into ESX as thin provisioned
            disks. Monolithic Sparse disks can be obtained from VMware
            Fusion or can be created by converting from other virtual
            disk formats using the <code>qemu-img</code>
            utility.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>The following table shows the <option>vmware_disktype</option>
        property that applies to each of the supported VMDK disk
        types:</para>
      <table rules="all">
        <caption>OpenStack Image Service disk type settings</caption>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>vmware_disktype property</th>
            <th>VMDK disk type</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>sparse</td>
            <td>
              <para>Monolithic Sparse</para>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>thin</td>
            <td>
              <para>VMFS flat, thin provisioned</para>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>preallocated (default)</td>
            <td>
              <para>VMFS flat,
                thick/zeroedthick/eagerzeroedthick</para>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>

      <para>The <option>vmware_disktype</option> property is set when an
        image is loaded into the OpenStack Image Service. For example,
        the following command creates a Monolithic Sparse image by
        setting <option>vmware_disktype</option> to
          <literal>sparse</literal>:</para>
      <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>glance image-create name="ubuntu-sparse" disk_format=vmdk \
container_format=bare is_public=true \
--property vmware_disktype="sparse" \
--property vmware_ostype="ubuntu64Guest" &lt; ubuntuLTS-sparse.vmdk</userinput></screen>
      <para>Note that specifying <literal>thin</literal> does not
        provide any advantage over <literal>preallocated</literal>
        with the current version of the driver. Future versions might
        restore the thin properties of the disk after it is downloaded
        to a vSphere data store.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="VMware_converting_images">
      <title>Convert and load images</title>
      <para>Using the <code>qemu-img</code> utility, disk images in
        several formats (such as, qcow2) can be converted to the VMDK
        format.</para>
      <para>For example, the following command can be used to convert
        a <link
          xlink:href="http://cloud-images.ubuntu.com/precise/current/precise-server-cloudimg-amd64-disk1.img"
          >qcow2 Ubuntu Precise cloud image</link>:</para>
      <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>qemu-img convert -f qcow2 ~/Downloads/precise-server-cloudimg-amd64-disk1.img \
-O vmdk precise-server-cloudimg-amd64-disk1.vmdk</userinput></screen>
      <para>VMDK disks converted through <code>qemu-img</code> are
          <emphasis role="italic">always</emphasis> monolithic sparse
        VMDK disks with an IDE adapter type. Using the previous
        example of the Precise Ubuntu image after the
          <code>qemu-img</code> conversion, the command to upload the
        VMDK disk should be something like:</para>
      <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>glance image-create --name precise-cloud --is-public=True \
--container-format=bare --disk-format=vmdk \
--property vmware_disktype="sparse" \
--property vmware_adaptertype="ide" &lt; \
precise-server-cloudimg-amd64-disk1.vmdk</userinput></screen>
      <para>Note that the <option>vmware_disktype</option> is set to
          <emphasis role="italic">sparse</emphasis> and the
          <code>vmware_adaptertype</code> is set to <emphasis
          role="italic">ide</emphasis> in the previous command.</para>
      <para>If the image did not come from the <code>qemu-img</code>
        utility, the <code>vmware_disktype</code> and
          <code>vmware_adaptertype</code> might be different. To
        determine the image adapter type from an image file, use the
        following command and look for the
          <option>ddb.adapterType=</option> line:</para>
      <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>head -20 &lt;vmdk file name></userinput></screen>
      <para>Assuming a preallocated disk type and an iSCSI lsiLogic
        adapter type, the following command uploads the VMDK
        disk:</para>
      <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>glance image-create name="ubuntu-thick-scsi" disk_format=vmdk \
container_format=bare is_public=true \
--property vmware_adaptertype="lsiLogic" \
--property vmware_disktype="preallocated" \
--property vmware_ostype="ubuntu64Guest" &lt; ubuntuLTS-flat.vmdk</userinput></screen>
      <para>Currently, OS boot VMDK disks with an IDE adapter type
        cannot be attached to a virtual SCSI controller and likewise
        disks with one of the SCSI adapter types (such as, busLogic,
        lsiLogic) cannot be attached to the IDE controller. Therefore,
        as the previous examples show, it is important to set the
          <option>vmware_adaptertype</option> property correctly. The
        default adapter type is lsiLogic, which is SCSI, so you can
        omit the <parameter>vmware_adaptertype</parameter> property if
        you are certain that the image adapter type is
        lsiLogic.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="VMware_tagging_images">
      <title>Tag VMware images</title>
      <para>In a mixed hypervisor environment, OpenStack Compute uses
        the <option>hypervisor_type</option> tag to match images to the
        correct hypervisor type. For VMware images, set the hypervisor
        type to <literal>vmware</literal>. Other valid hypervisor
        types include: xen, qemu, kvm, lxc, uml, and hyperv.</para>
      <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>glance image-create name="ubuntu-thick-scsi" disk_format=vmdk \
container_format=bare is_public=true \
--property vmware_adaptertype="lsiLogic" \
--property vmware_disktype="preallocated" \
--property hypervisor_type="vmware" \
--property vmware_ostype="ubuntu64Guest" &lt; ubuntuLTS-flat.vmdk</userinput></screen>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="VMware_optimizing_images">
      <title>Optimize images</title>
      <para>Monolithic Sparse disks are considerably faster to
        download but have the overhead of an additional conversion
        step. When imported into ESX, sparse disks get converted to
        VMFS flat thin provisioned disks. The download and conversion
        steps only affect the first launched instance that uses the
        sparse disk image. The converted disk image is cached, so
        subsequent instances that use this disk image can simply use
        the cached version.</para>
      <para>To avoid the conversion step (at the cost of longer
        download times) consider converting sparse disks to thin
        provisioned or preallocated disks before loading them into the
        OpenStack Image Service. Below are some tools that can be used
        to pre-convert sparse disks.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Using vSphere CLI (or sometimes
              called the remote CLI or rCLI) tools</emphasis></para>
          <para>Assuming that the sparse disk is made available on a
            data store accessible by an ESX host, the following
            command converts it to preallocated format:</para>
          <programlisting>vmkfstools --server=ip_of_some_ESX_host -i /vmfs/volumes/datastore1/sparse.vmdk /vmfs/volumes/datastore1/converted.vmdk</programlisting>
          <para>(Note that the vifs tool from the same CLI package can
            be used to upload the disk to be converted. The vifs tool
            can also be used to download the converted disk if
            necessary.)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Using vmkfstools directly on the
              ESX host</emphasis></para>
          <para>If the SSH service is enabled on an ESX host, the
            sparse disk can be uploaded to the ESX data store via scp
            and the vmkfstools local to the ESX host can use used to
            perform the conversion: (After logging in to the host via
            ssh)</para>
          <programlisting>vmkfstools -i /vmfs/volumes/datastore1/sparse.vmdk /vmfs/volumes/datastore1/converted.vmdk</programlisting>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold"
            >vmware-vdiskmanager</emphasis></para>
          <para><code>vmware-vdiskmanager</code> is a utility that
            comes bundled with VMware Fusion and VMware Workstation.
            Below is an example of converting a sparse disk to
            preallocated format:</para>
          <programlisting>'/Applications/VMware Fusion.app/Contents/Library/vmware-vdiskmanager' -r sparse.vmdk -t 4 converted.vmdk</programlisting>
          <para>In all of the above cases, the converted vmdk is
            actually a pair of files: the descriptor file <emphasis
              role="italic">converted.vmdk</emphasis> and the actual
            virtual disk data file <emphasis role="italic"
              >converted-flat.vmdk</emphasis>. The file to be uploaded
            to the OpenStack Image Service is <emphasis role="italic"
              >converted-flat.vmdk</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="VMware_copying_images">
      <title>Image handling</title>
      <para>The ESX hypervisor requires a copy of the VMDK file in
        order to boot up a virtual machine. As a result, the vCenter
        OpenStack Compute driver must download the VMDK via HTTP from
        the OpenStack Image Service to a data store that is visible to
        the hypervisor. To optimize this process, the first time a
        VMDK file is used, it gets cached in the data store.
        Subsequent virtual machines that need the VMDK use the cached
        version and don't have to copy the file again from the
        OpenStack Image Service.</para>
      <para>Even with a cached VMDK, there is still a copy operation
        from the cache location to the hypervisor file directory in
        the shared data store. To avoid this copy, boot the image in
        linked_clone mode. To learn how to enable this mode, see <xref
          linkend="VMWare_config"/>. Note also that it is possible to
        override the linked_clone mode on a per-image basis by using
        the <code>vmware_linked_clone</code> property in the OpenStack
        Image Service.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="VMWare_networking">
    <title>Networking with VMware vSphere</title>
    <para>The VMware driver supports networking with the <systemitem
        class="service">nova-network</systemitem> service or the
      OpenStack Networking Service. Depending on your installation,
      complete these configuration steps before you provision
      VMs:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">
          The <systemitem class="service">nova-network</systemitem>
          service with the FlatManager or FlatDHCPManager</emphasis>.
          Create a port group with the same name as the
          <literal>flat_network_bridge</literal> value in the
          <filename>nova.conf</filename> file. The default value is
          <literal>br100</literal>. If you specify another value,
          the new value must be a valid linux bridge identifier that
          adheres to linux bridge naming conventions.</para>
         <para>All VM NICs are attached to this port group.</para>
         <para>Ensure that the flat interface of the node that runs
          the <systemitem class="service">nova-network</systemitem>
          service has a path to this network.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">The <systemitem class="service"
              >nova-network</systemitem> service with the
            VlanManager</emphasis>. Set the
            <literal>vlan_interface</literal> configuration option to
          match the ESX host interface that handles VLAN-tagged VM
          traffic.</para>
        <para>OpenStack Compute automatically creates the
          corresponding port groups.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If you are using the OpenStack Networking Service:
          Before provisioning VMs, create a port group with the same
          name as the <literal>vmware.integration_bridge</literal> 
          value in <filename>nova.conf</filename> (default is
          <literal>br-int</literal>). All VM NICs are attached to
          this port group for management by the OpenStack Networking
          plug-in.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="VMWare_volumes">
    <title>Volumes with VMware vSphere</title>
    <para>The VMware driver supports attaching volumes from the
      OpenStack Block Storage service. The VMware VMDK driver for
      OpenStack Block Storage is recommended and should be used for
      managing volumes based on vSphere data stores. More information
      about the VMware VMDK driver can be found at: <link
        xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/trunk/config-reference/content/vmware-vmdk-driver.html"
        >VMware VMDK Driver</link>. Also an iscsi volume driver
      provides limited support and can be used only for
      attachments.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="VMWare_additional_config">
    <title>vSphere 5.0 and earlier additional set up</title>
    <para>Users of vSphere 5.0 or earlier must host their WSDL files
      locally. These steps are applicable for vCenter 5.0 or ESXi 5.0
      and you can either mirror the WSDL from the vCenter or ESXi
      server that you intend to use or you can download the SDK
      directly from VMware. These workaround steps fix a <link
        xlink:href="http://kb.vmware.com/selfservice/microsites/search.do?cmd=displayKC&amp;externalId=2010507"
        >known issue</link> with the WSDL that was resolved in later
      versions.</para>
    <para>When setting the VMwareVCDriver configuration options, you
      must include the <code>wsdl_location</code> option. For more
      information, see
      <link linkend="VMWareVCDriver_configuration_options">VMwareVCDriver
      configuration options</link> above.</para>
    <procedure>
      <title>Mirror WSDL from vCenter (or ESXi)</title>
      <step>
        <para>Set the <code>VMWAREAPI_IP</code> shell variable to the
          IP address for your vCenter or ESXi host from where you plan
          to mirror files. For example:</para>
        <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>export VMWAREAPI_IP=&lt;your_vsphere_host_ip&gt;</userinput></screen>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>Create a local file system directory to hold the WSDL
          files:</para>
        <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>mkdir -p /opt/stack/vmware/wsdl/5.0</userinput></screen>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>Change into the new directory.
          <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>cd /opt/stack/vmware/wsdl/5.0</userinput> </screen></para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>Use your OS-specific tools to install a command-line
          tool that can download files like
          <command>wget</command>.</para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>Download the files to the local file cache:</para>
        <programlisting language="bash">wget  --no-check-certificate https://$VMWAREAPI_IP/sdk/vimService.wsdl
wget  --no-check-certificate https://$VMWAREAPI_IP/sdk/vim.wsdl
wget  --no-check-certificate https://$VMWAREAPI_IP/sdk/core-types.xsd
wget  --no-check-certificate https://$VMWAREAPI_IP/sdk/query-messagetypes.xsd
wget  --no-check-certificate https://$VMWAREAPI_IP/sdk/query-types.xsd
wget  --no-check-certificate https://$VMWAREAPI_IP/sdk/vim-messagetypes.xsd
wget  --no-check-certificate https://$VMWAREAPI_IP/sdk/vim-types.xsd
wget  --no-check-certificate https://$VMWAREAPI_IP/sdk/reflect-messagetypes.xsd
wget  --no-check-certificate https://$VMWAREAPI_IP/sdk/reflect-types.xsd</programlisting>
        <para>Because the <filename>reflect-types.xsd</filename> and
            <filename>reflect-messagetypes.xsd</filename> files do not
          fetch properly, you must stub out these files. Use the
          following XML listing to replace the missing file content.
          The XML parser underneath Python can be very particular and
          if you put a space in the wrong place, it can break the
          parser. Copy the following contents and formatting
          carefully.</para>
        <programlisting language="xml">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
  &lt;schema
     targetNamespace="urn:reflect"
     xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
     xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
     elementFormDefault="qualified"&gt;
  &lt;/schema&gt;       </programlisting>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>Now that the files are locally present, tell the driver
          to look for the SOAP service WSDLs in the local file system
          and not on the remote vSphere server. Add the following
          setting to the <filename>nova.conf</filename> file for your
            <systemitem class="service">nova-compute</systemitem>
          node:</para>
        <programlisting language="ini">[vmware]
wsdl_location=file:///opt/stack/vmware/wsdl/5.0/vimService.wsdl</programlisting>
      </step>
    </procedure>
    <para>Alternatively, download the version appropriate SDK from
        <link
        xlink:href="http://www.vmware.com/support/developer/vc-sdk/"
        >http://www.vmware.com/support/developer/vc-sdk/</link> and
      copy it to the <filename>/opt/stack/vmware</filename> file. Make
      sure that the WSDL is available, in for example
        <filename>/opt/stack/vmware/SDK/wsdl/vim25/vimService.wsdl</filename>.
      You must point <filename>nova.conf</filename> to fetch this WSDL
      file from the local file system by using a URL.</para>
    <para>When using the VMwareVCDriver (vCenter) with OpenStack
      Compute with vSphere version 5.0 or earlier,
        <filename>nova.conf</filename> must include the following
      extra config option:</para>
    <programlisting language="ini">[vmware]
wsdl_location=file:///opt/stack/vmware/SDK/wsdl/vim25/vimService.wsdl</programlisting>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="VMWareESXDriver_details">
    <title>VMware ESX driver</title>
    <para>This section covers details of using the VMwareESXDriver.
      The ESX Driver has not been extensively tested and is not
      recommended. To configure the VMware vCenter driver instead, see
        <xref linkend="VMWareVCDriver_details"/>.</para>
    <section xml:id="VMWareESXDriver_configuration_options">
      <title>VMwareESXDriver configuration options</title>
      <para>When you use the VMwareESXDriver (no vCenter) with
        OpenStack Compute, add the following VMware-specific
        configuration options to the <filename>nova.conf</filename>
        file:</para>
      <programlisting language="ini">[DEFAULT]
compute_driver=vmwareapi.VMwareESXDriver

[vmware]
host_ip=&lt;ESXi host IP&gt;
host_username=&lt;ESXi host username&gt;
host_password=&lt;ESXi host password&gt;
wsdl_location=http://127.0.0.1:8080/vmware/SDK/wsdl/vim25/vimService.wsdl</programlisting>
      <para>Remember that you will have one <systemitem
          class="service">nova-compute</systemitem> service for each
        ESXi host. It is recommended that this host run as a VM on the
        same ESXi host that it manages.</para>
      <note>
        <para>Many <filename>nova.conf</filename> options are relevant
          to libvirt but do not apply to this driver.</para>
      </note>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="VMwareESXDriver_limitations">
      <title>Requirements and limitations</title>
      <para>The ESXDriver cannot use many of the vSphere platform
        advanced capabilities, namely vMotion, high availability, and
        DRS.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="VMWare_config">
    <title>Configuration reference</title>
    <xi:include href="../../common/tables/nova-vmware.xml"/>
  </section>
</section>
