     <section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="s-neutron-server">

          <title>Highly available OpenStack Networking server</title>

        <para>OpenStack Networking is the network connectivity service in OpenStack.
Making the OpenStack Networking Server service highly available in active / passive mode involves the following tasks:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Configure OpenStack Networking to listen on the virtual IP address,
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Manage the OpenStack Networking API Server daemon with the Pacemaker cluster manager,
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Configure OpenStack services to use the virtual IP address.
</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <note>
          <para>Here is the <link xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/trunk/install-guide/install/apt/content/ch_networking.html">documentation</link> for installing OpenStack Networking service.</para>
        </note>
        <section xml:id="_add_openstack_networking_server_resource_to_pacemaker">

            <title>Add OpenStack Networking Server resource to Pacemaker</title>

          <para>First of all, you need to download the resource agent to your system:</para>
          <screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>cd /usr/lib/ocf/resource.d/openstack</userinput>
<prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>wget https://raw.github.com/madkiss/openstack-resource-agents/master/ocf/neutron-server</userinput>
<prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>chmod a+rx *</userinput></screen>
          <para>You can now add the Pacemaker configuration for
OpenStack Networking Server resource. Connect to the Pacemaker cluster with <literal>crm
configure</literal>, and add the following cluster resources:</para>
          <programlisting>primitive p_neutron-server ocf:openstack:neutron-server \
    params os_password="secret" os_username="admin" os_tenant_name="admin" \
    keystone_get_token_url="http://192.168.42.103:5000/v2.0/tokens" \
    op monitor interval="30s" timeout="30s"</programlisting>
          <para>This configuration creates <literal>p_neutron-server</literal>, a resource for manage OpenStack Networking Server service</para>
          <para><literal>crm configure</literal> supports batch input, so you may copy and paste the
above into your live pacemaker configuration, and then make changes as
required. For example, you may enter <literal>edit p_neutron-server</literal> from the
<literal>crm configure</literal> menu and edit the resource to match your preferred
virtual IP address.</para>
          <para>Once completed, commit your configuration changes by entering <literal>commit</literal>
from the <literal>crm configure</literal> menu. Pacemaker will then start the OpenStack Networking API
service, and its dependent resources, on one of your nodes.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="_configure_openstack_networking_server">

            <title>Configure OpenStack Networking server</title>

          <para>Edit <filename>/etc/neutron/neutron.conf</filename>:</para>
          <programlisting language="ini"># We bind the service to the VIP:
bind_host = 192.168.42.103

# We bind OpenStack Networking Server to the VIP:
bind_host = 192.168.42.103

# We send notifications to Highly available RabbitMQ:
notifier_strategy = rabbit
rabbit_host = 192.168.42.102

[database]
# We have to use MySQL connection to store data:
connection = mysql://neutron:password@192.168.42.101/neutron</programlisting>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="_configure_openstack_services_to_use_highly_available_openstack_networking_server">

            <title>Configure OpenStack services to use highly available OpenStack Networking server</title>

          <para>Your OpenStack services must now point their OpenStack Networking Server configuration to
the highly available, virtual cluster IP address — rather than an
OpenStack Networking server’s physical IP address as you normally would.</para>
          <para>For example, you should configure OpenStack Compute for using highly available OpenStack Networking server in editing <literal>nova.conf</literal> file:</para>
          <programlisting language="ini">neutron_url = http://192.168.42.103:9696</programlisting>
          <para>You need to create the OpenStack Networking server endpoint with this IP.</para>
          <note>
            <para>If you are using both private and public IP addresses, you should create two Virtual IP addresses and define your endpoint like this:</para>
          </note>
          <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>keystone endpoint-create --region $KEYSTONE_REGION --service-id $service-id \
  --publicurl 'http://PUBLIC_VIP:9696/' \
  --adminurl 'http://192.168.42.103:9696/' \
  --internalurl 'http://192.168.42.103:9696/'</userinput></screen>
        </section>
      </section>
