<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xml:id="object-storage-network-planning"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"><title>Object Storage Network Planning</title>
    <para>For both conserving network resources and ensuring that
        network administrators understand the needs for networks and
        public IP addresses for providing access to the APIs and
        storage network as necessary, this section offers
        recommendations and required minimum sizes. Throughput of at
        least 1000 Mbps is suggested.</para>
  <para>This document refers to three networks. One is a public network for
        connecting to the Proxy server. The second is a storage network that is not
        accessible from outside the cluster, to which all of the nodes are
        connected. The third is a replication network that is also isolated from
        outside networks and dedicated to replication traffic between Storage nodes.</para>
  <para>The public and storage networks are mandatory. The replication network
        is optional and must be configured in the Ring.</para>
  <para>By default, all of the OpenStack Object Storage services, as well as the
        rsync daemon on the Storage nodes, are configured to listen on their
        <literal>STORAGE_LOCAL_NET</literal> IP addresses.</para>
    <para>If a replication network is configured in the Ring, then Account, Container
          and Object servers listen on both the <literal>STORAGE_LOCAL_NET</literal>
          and <literal>STORAGE_REPLICATION_NET</literal>
          IP addresses. The rsync daemon will only listen on the
          <literal>STORAGE_REPLICATION_NET</literal> IP
          address in this case.</para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Public Network (Publicly routable IP range)</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>This network provides public IP accessibility to the API endpoints
        within the cloud infrastructure.</para>
      <para>Minimum size: one IP address per proxy server.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Storage Network (RFC1918 IP Range, not publicly routable)</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>This network is utilized for all inter-server communications
        within the Object Storage infrastructure.</para>
      <para>Minimum size: one IP address per storage node, and proxy server.</para>
      <para>Recommended size: as above, with room for expansion to the largest your
        cluster will be (For example, 255 or CIDR /24)</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Replication Network (RFC1918 IP Range, not publicly routable)</term>
      <listitem>
      <para>This network is utilized for replication-related communications
        between storage servers within the Object Storage infrastructure.</para>
      <para>Recommended size: as for <literal>STORAGE_LOCAL_NET</literal></para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</section>
