<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xml:id="object-storage-network-planning"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
  <title>Plan networking for Object Storage</title>
  <para>For both conserving network resources and ensuring that
    network administrators understand the needs for networks and
    public IP addresses for providing access to the APIs and storage
    network as necessary, this section offers recommendations and
    required minimum sizes. Throughput of at least 1000 Mbps is
    suggested.</para>
  <para>This guide describes the following networks:<itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>A mandatory public network. Connects to the proxy
          server.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>A mandatory storage network. Not accessible from outside
the cluster. All nodes connect to this network.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>An optional replication network. Not accessible from
          outside the cluster. Dedicated to replication traffic among
          storage nodes. Must be configured in the Ring.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>
  <para>This figure shows the basic architecture for the public
    network, the storage network, and the optional replication
    network.</para>
  <para><inlinemediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata
        fileref="../figures/networking-interactions-swift.png"
      />
    </imageobject>
  </inlinemediaobject></para>
  <para>By default, all of the OpenStack Object Storage services, as
    well as the rsync daemon on the storage nodes, are configured to
    listen on their <literal>STORAGE_LOCAL_NET</literal> IP
    addresses.</para>
  <para>If you configure a replication network in the Ring, the
    Account, Container and Object servers listen on both the
      <literal>STORAGE_LOCAL_NET</literal> and
      <literal>STORAGE_REPLICATION_NET</literal> IP addresses. The
    rsync daemon only listens on the
      <literal>STORAGE_REPLICATION_NET</literal> IP address.</para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Public Network (Publicly routable IP range)</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Provides public IP accessibility to the API endpoints
          within the cloud infrastructure.</para>
        <para>Minimum size: one IP address for each proxy
          server.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Storage Network (RFC1918 IP Range, not publicly
        routable)</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Manages all inter-server communications within the
          Object Storage infrastructure.</para>
        <para>Minimum size: one IP address for each storage node and
          proxy server.</para>
        <para>Recommended size: as above, with room for expansion to
          the largest your cluster size. For example, 255 or CIDR
          /24.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Replication Network (RFC1918 IP Range, not publicly
        routable)</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Manages replication-related communications among storage
          servers within the Object Storage infrastructure.</para>
        <para>Recommended size: as for
            <literal>STORAGE_LOCAL_NET</literal>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</section>
