<section xml:id="nexenta-driver"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         version="5.0">
    <title>Nexenta Drivers</title>
    <para>
        NexentaStor Appliance is NAS/SAN software platform designed for
        building reliable and fast network storage arrays. The Nexenta Storage
        Appliance uses ZFS as a disk management system. NexentaStor can serve
        as a storage node for the OpenStack and for the virtual servers through
        iSCSI and NFS protocols.
    </para>
    <para>
        With the NFS option, every Compute volume is represented by a directory
        designated to be its own file system in the ZFS file system. These file
        systems are exported using NFS.
    </para>
    <para>
        With either option some minimal setup is required to tell OpenStack
        which NexentaStor servers are being used, whether they are supporting
        iSCSI and/or NFS and how to access each of the servers.
    </para>
    <para>
        Typically the only operation required on the NexentaStor servers is to
        create the containing directory for the iSCSI or NFS exports. For NFS
        this containing directory must be explicitly exported via NFS. There is
        no software that must be installed on the NexentaStor servers; they are
        controlled using existing management plane interfaces.
    </para>
    <!-- iSCSI driver section -->
    <section xml:id="nexenta-iscsi-driver">
        <title>Nexenta iSCSI driver</title>
        <para>
            The Nexenta iSCSI driver allows you to use NexentaStor appliance to
            store Compute volumes. Every Compute volume is represented by a
            single zvol in a predefined Nexenta namespace. For every new volume
            the driver creates a iSCSI target and iSCSI target group that are
            used to access it from compute hosts.
        </para>
        <para>
            The Nexenta iSCSI volume driver should work with all versions of
            NexentaStor. The NexentaStor appliance must be installed and
            configured according to the relevant Nexenta documentation. A pool
            and an enclosing namespace must be created for all iSCSI volumes to
            be accessed through the volume driver. This should be done as
            specified in the release specific NexentaStor documentation.
        </para>
        <para>
            The NexentaStor Appliance iSCSI driver is selected using the normal
            procedures for one or multiple backend volume drivers. The
            following items will need to be configured for each NexentaStor
            appliance that the iSCSI volume driver will control:
        </para>
        <section xml:id="nexenta-iscsi-driver-options">
            <title>
                Enabling the Nexenta iSCSI driver and related options
            </title>
            <para>
                The following table contains the options supported by the
                Nexenta iSCSI driver.
            </para>
            <table rules="all">
                <caption>
                    List of configuration flags for Nexenta iSCSI driver
                </caption>
                <col width="35%"/>
                <col width="15%"/>
                <col width="15%"/>
                <col width="35%"/>
                <thead>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Flag Name</td>
                        <td>Type</td>
                        <td>Default</td>
                        <td>Description</td>
                    </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                            <para><code>nexenta_rest_protocol</code></para>
                        </td>
                        <td><para>Optional</para></td>
                        <td><para>auto</para></td>
                        <td>
                            <para>
                                (StrOpt) NMS protocol can be set to
                                <code>http</code> or <code>https</code>, but
                                the default is <code>auto</code> which makes
                                the driver try to use HTTP and switch to HTTPS
                                in case of failure.
                            </para>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><para><code>nexenta_host</code></para></td>
                        <td><para>Mandatory</para></td>
                        <td><para/></td>
                        <td>
                            <para>
                                (StrOpt) Hostname or IP of your NexentaStor
                                appliance.
                            </para>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><para><code>nexenta_rest_port</code></para></td>
                        <td><para>Optional</para></td>
                        <td><para><code>2000</code></para></td>
                        <td>
                            <para>
                                (IntOpt) The port where Nexenta listens for
                                REST requests (the same port where the NMV
                                works).
                            </para>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><para><code>nexenta_user</code></para></td>
                        <td><para>Optional</para></td>
                        <td><para>admin</para></td>
                        <td>
                            <para>
                                (StrOpt) Username of the NMS user with all
                                necessary privileges on the appliance,
                                including the access to REST API.
                            </para>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><para><code>nexenta_password</code></para></td>
                        <td><para>Optional</para></td>
                        <td><para>nexenta</para></td>
                        <td>
                            <para>
                                (StrOpt) Password of the NMS user with all
                                necessary privileges on the appliance,
                                including the access to REST API.
                            </para>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><para><code>nexenta_volume</code></para></td>
                        <td><para>Optional</para></td>
                        <td><para>cinder</para></td>
                        <td>
                            <para>
                                (StrOpt) Name of the volume on the NexentaStor
                                appliance that you would like to use in
                                Compute, this volume must exist on appliance.
                            </para>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                            <para><code>nexenta_target_prefix</code></para>
                        </td>
                        <td><para>Optional</para></td>
                        <td><para>iqn.1986-03.com.sun:02:cinder-</para></td>
                        <td>
                            <para>
                                (StrOpt) The prefix that is prepended to volume
                                id to form the iSCSI target name. The target
                                prefix does not change the name of the ZVol on
                                the selected NexentaStor appliance, just the
                                name that is exported.
                            </para>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                            <para>
                                <code>nexenta_target_group_prefix</code>
                            </para>
                        </td>
                        <td><para>Optional</para></td>
                        <td><para>cinder/</para></td>
                        <td>
                            <para>
                                (StrOpt) The prefix for iSCSI target groups.
                            </para>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                            <para>
                                <code>nexenta_iscsi_target_portal_port</code>
                            </para>
                        </td>
                        <td><para>Optional</para></td>
                        <td><para>3260</para></td>
                        <td>
                            <para>
                                (IntOpt) The port to connect to NexentaStor
                                appliance over iSCSI.
                            </para>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><para><code>nexenta_blocksize</code></para></td>
                        <td><para>Optional</para></td>
                        <td><para>8KB</para></td>
                        <td>
                            <para>
                                (StrOpt) The size of the blocks in newly
                                created zvols on appliance, with the suffix;
                                for example, the default 8K means 8 kilobytes.
                            </para>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><para><code>nexenta_sparse</code></para></td>
                        <td><para>Optional</para></td>
                        <td><para>True</para></td>
                        <td>
                            <para>
                                (BoolOpt) Use sparse zvols. Sparse zvols do not
                                pre-allocate disk space before content is
                                actually written.
                            </para>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                </tbody>
            </table>
            <para>
                To use Compute with the Nexenta iSCSI driver, first set the
                <code>volume_driver</code>:
            </para>
            <para>
                <code>
                    volume_driver=
                    cinder.volume.drivers.nexenta.volume.NexentaDriver
                </code>
            </para>
            <para>
                Then set value for <code>nexenta_host</code> and other
                parameters from table if needed.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <!-- / iSCSI driver section -->
    <!-- NFS driver section -->
    <section xml:id="nexenta-nfs-driver">
        <title>Nexenta NFS driver</title>
        <para>
            The Nexenta NFS driver allows you to use NexentaStor appliance to
            store Compute volumes via NFS. Every Compute volume is represented
            by a single NFS file within a shared directory.
        </para>
        <para>
            While the NFS protocols standardize file access for users, they do
            not standardize administrative actions such as taking snapshots or
            replicating file systems. The Openstack Volume Drivers bring a
            common interface to these operations. The Nexenta NFS driver
            implements these standard actions using the ZFS management plane
            that already is deployed on NexentaStor appliances.
        </para>
        <para>
            The Nexenta NFS volume driver should work with all versions of
            NexentaStor. The NexentaStor appliance must be installed and
            configured according to the relevant Nexenta documentation. A
            single parent file system must be created for all virtual disk
            directories supported for OpenStack. This directory must be created
            and exported on each NexentaStor appliance. This should be done as
            specified in the release specific NexentaStor documentation.
        </para>
        <section xml:id="nexenta-nfs-driver-options">
            <title>Enabling the Nexenta NFS driver and related options</title>
            <para>
                To use Compute with the Nexenta NFS driver, first set the
                <code>volume_driver</code>:
            </para>
            <para>
                <code>
                    volume_driver=
                    cinder.volume.drivers.nexenta.nfs.NexentaNfsDriver
                </code>
            </para>
            <para>
                The following table contains the options supported by the
                Nexenta NFS driver.
            </para>
            <table rules="all">
                <caption>
                    List of configuration flags for Nexenta NFS driver
                </caption>
                <col width="35%"/>
                <col width="15%"/>
                <col width="15%"/>
                <col width="35%"/>
                <thead>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Flag Name</td>
                        <td>Type</td>
                        <td>Default</td>
                        <td>Description</td>
                    </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                            <para>
                                <code>nexenta_shares_config</code>
                            </para>
                        </td>
                        <td><para>Mandatory</para></td>
                        <td>
                            <para>
                                <filename>/etc/cinder/nfs_shares</filename>
                            </para>
                        </td>
                        <td>
                            <para>
                                (StrOpt) File with the list of available NFS
                                shares.
                            </para>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                            <para><code>nexenta_mount_point_base</code></para>
                        </td>
                        <td><para>Optional</para></td>
                        <td><para><code>$state_path/mnt</code></para></td>
                        <td>
                            <para>
                                (StrOpt) Base dir where NFS shares are expected
                                to be mounted.
                            </para>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                            <para><code>nexenta_sparsed_volumes</code></para>
                        </td>
                        <td><para>Optional</para></td>
                        <td><para>True</para></td>
                        <td>
                            <para>
                                (BoolOpt) Create volumes as sparsed files which
                                take no space. If set to False, volume is
                                created as regular file. In such case volume
                                creation takes a lot of time.
                            </para>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                            <para>
                                <code>nexenta_volume_compression</code>
                            </para>
                        </td>
                        <td><para>Optional</para></td>
                        <td><para>on</para></td>
                        <td>
                            <para>
                                (StrOpt) ZFS compression value for new volumes.
                            </para>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                            <para><code>nexenta_mount_options</code></para>
                        </td>
                        <td><para>Optional</para></td>
                        <td><para><code>None</code></para></td>
                        <td>
                            <para>
                                (StrOpt) Mount options passed to the NFS client.
                                See section of the nfs man page for details.
                            </para>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><para><code>nexenta_used_ratio</code></para></td>
                        <td><para>Optional</para></td>
                        <td><para><code>0.95</code></para></td>
                        <td>
                            <para>
                                (FloatOpt) Percent of ACTUAL usage of the
                                underlying volume before no new volumes can be
                                allocated to the volume destination.
                            </para>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                            <para><code>nexenta_oversub_ratio</code></para>
                        </td>
                        <td><para>Optional</para></td>
                        <td><para><code>1.0</code></para></td>
                        <td>
                            <para>
                                (FloatOpt) This compares the allocated to
                                available space on the volume destination. If
                                the ratio exceeds this number, the destination
                                is no longer valid.
                            </para>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                </tbody>
            </table>
            <para>
                Add your list of Nexenta NFS servers to the file you specified
                with the <code>nexenta_shares_config</code> option. For
                example, if the value of this option was set to
                <filename>/etc/cinder/nfs_shares</filename>, then:
            </para>
            <screen>
<prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>cat /etc/cinder/nfs_shares</userinput>
<computeroutput>192.168.1.200:/storage http://admin:nexenta@192.168.1.200:2000</computeroutput>
<computeroutput>192.168.1.201:/storage http://admin:nexenta@192.168.1.201:2000</computeroutput>
<computeroutput>192.168.1.202:/storage http://admin:nexenta@192.168.1.202:2000</computeroutput>
            </screen>
            <para>
                Comments are allowed in this file. They begin with a
                <code>#</code>.
            </para>
            <para>
                Each line in this file represents a NFS share. The first part
                of the line is the NFS share URL, the second is the connection
                URL to the NexentaStor Appliance.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <!-- / NFS driver section -->
</section>
