<section xml:id="nexenta-driver"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0">
            <title>Nexenta</title>
            <para>NexentaStor Appliance is NAS/SAN software platform designed for building reliable and fast network storage arrays. The
                the OpenSolaris and uses ZFS as a disk management system. NexentaStor can serve as a storage node for the OpenStack and
                for the virtual servers through iSCSI protocol.</para>
            <para>The Nexenta driver allows you to use Nexenta SA to
        store Compute volumes. Every Compute volume is represented by
        a single zvol in a predefined Nexenta volume. For every new
        volume the driver creates a iSCSI target and iSCSI target
        group that are used to access it from compute hosts.</para>
            <para>To use Compute with Nexenta Storage Appliance, you
        should set these options in
        <filename>cinder.conf</filename>:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem><para>set
                            <literal>volume_driver=nova.volume.nexenta.volume.NexentaDriver</literal>.</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>set <literal>--nexenta_host</literal> flag to the hostname or IP
                of your NexentaStor.</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>set <literal>--nexenta_user</literal> and
                    <literal>--nexenta_password</literal> to the
                username and password of the user with all necessary
                privileges on the appliance, including the access to
                REST API.</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>set <literal>--nexenta_volume</literal> to the name of the
                        volume on the appliance that you would like to
                        use in Nova, or create a volume named
                            <literal>nova</literal> (which is the default).</para></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            <para>Nexenta driver has a lot of tunable flags. Some of them you might want to change:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem><para><literal>nexenta_target_prefix</literal> defines the prefix that
                        is prepended to the volume ID to form target
                        name on Nexenta</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para><literal>nexenta_target_group_prefix</literal> defines the
                prefix for target groups.</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para><literal>nexenta_blocksize</literal> can be set to the size of
                the blocks in newly created zvols on the appliance,
                with the suffix; for example, the default 8K means 8
                kilobytes.</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para><literal>nexenta_sparse</literal> is boolean and can be set to
                use sparse zvols to save space on the
                appliance.</para></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            <para>Some flags that you might want to keep with the
                default values:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem><para><literal>nexenta_rest_port</literal> is the port where Nexenta
                listens for REST requests (the same port where the NMV
                works).</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para><literal>nexenta_rest_protocol</literal> can be set to
                    <literal>http</literal> or
                    <literal>https</literal>, but the default is
                    <literal>auto</literal> which makes the driver try
                to use HTTP and switch to HTTPS in case of
                failure.</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para><literal>nexenta_iscsi_target_portal_port</literal> is the port
                to connect to Nexenta over iSCSI.</para></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
</section>
