<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="prescriptive-example-online-classifieds">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Prescriptive Example</title>
    <para>An online classified advertising company wants to run web applications
        consisting of Tomcat, Nginx and MariaDB in a private cloud. In order to
        meet policy requirements, the cloud infrastructure will run in their own
        data center. They have predictable load requirements but require an
        element of scaling to cope with nightly increases in demand. Their
        current environment is not flexible enough to align with their goal of
        running an open source API driven environment. Their current environment
        consists of the following:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Between 120 and 140 installations of Nginx and
                Tomcat, each with 2 vCPUs and 4 GB of RAM</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>A three-node MariaDB and Galera cluster, each with 4
                vCPUs and 8 GB RAM</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>The company runs hardware load balancers and multiple web
        applications serving the sites. The company orchestrates their
        environment using a combination of scripts and Puppet. The
        websites generate a large amount of log data each day that
        needs to be archived.</para>
    <para>The solution would consist of the following OpenStack
        components:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>A firewall, switches and load balancers on the
                public facing network connections.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>OpenStack Controller services running Image,
                Identity, Networking and supporting services such as
                MariaDB and RabbitMQ. The controllers will run in a
                highly available configuration on at least three
                controller nodes.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>OpenStack Compute nodes running the KVM
                hypervisor.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>OpenStack Block Storage for use by compute instances
                that require persistent storage such as databases for
                dynamic sites.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>OpenStack Object Storage for serving static objects
                such as images.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata contentwidth="6in"
                    fileref="../images/General_Architecture3.png"
                /></imageobject></mediaobject>
    <para>Running up to 140
        web instances and the small number of MariaDB instances
        requires 292 vCPUs available, as well as 584 GB RAM. On a
        typical 1U server using dual-socket hex-core Intel CPUs with
        Hyperthreading, and assuming 2:1 CPU overcommit ratio, this
        would require 8 OpenStack Compute nodes.</para>
    <para>The web application instances run from local storage on each
        of the OpenStack Compute nodes. The web application instances
        are stateless, meaning that any of the instances can fail and
        the application will continue to function.</para>
    <para>MariaDB server instances store their data on shared
        enterprise storage, such as NetApp or Solidfire devices. If a
        MariaDB instance fails, storage would be expected to be
        re-attached to another instance and rejoined to the Galera
        cluster.</para>
    <para>Logs from the web application servers are shipped to
        OpenStack Object Storage for later processing and
        archiving.</para>
    <para>In this scenario, additional capabilities can be realized by
        moving static web content to be served from OpenStack Object
        Storage containers, and backing the OpenStack Image Service
        with OpenStack Object Storage. Note that an increase in
        OpenStack Object Storage means that network bandwidth needs to
        be taken in to consideration. It is best to run OpenStack
        Object Storage with network connections offering 10 GbE or
        better connectivity.</para>
    <para>There is also a potential to leverage the Orchestration and
        Telemetry OpenStack modules to provide an auto-scaling,
        orchestrated web application environment. Defining the web
        applications in Heat Orchestration Templates (HOT) would
        negate the reliance on the scripted Puppet solution currently
        employed.</para>
    <para>OpenStack Networking can be used to control hardware load
        balancers through the use of plug-ins and the Networking API.
        This would allow a user to control hardware load balance pools
        and instances as members in these pools, but their use in
        production environments must be carefully weighed against
        current stability.</para>
</section>
