<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="prescriptive-example-online-classifieds">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Prescriptive example</title>
    <para>An online classified advertising company wants to run web applications
        consisting of Tomcat, Nginx and MariaDB in a private cloud. To be able
        to meet policy requirements, the cloud infrastructure will run in their
        own data center. The company has predictable load requirements, but requires
        scaling to cope with nightly increases in demand. Their current environment
        does not have the flexibility to align with their goal of running an open
        source API environment. The current environment consists of the following:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Between 120 and 140 installations of Nginx and
                Tomcat, each with 2 vCPUs and 4 GB of RAM</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>A three-node MariaDB and Galera cluster, each with 4
                vCPUs and 8 GB RAM</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>The company runs hardware load balancers and multiple web
        applications serving their websites, and orchestrates environments
        using combinations of scripts and Puppet. The website generates large amounts of
        log data daily that requires archiving.</para>
    <para>The solution would consist of the following OpenStack
        components:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>A firewall, switches and load balancers on the
                public facing network connections.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>OpenStack Controller service running Image,
                Identity, Networking, combined with support services such as
                MariaDB and RabbitMQ, configured for high availability on at
                least three controller nodes.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>OpenStack Compute nodes running the KVM
                hypervisor.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>OpenStack Block Storage for use by compute instances,
            requiring persistent storage (such as databases for
                dynamic sites).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>OpenStack Object Storage for serving static objects
                (such as images).</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata contentwidth="4in"
                    fileref="../figures/General_Architecture3.png"
                /></imageobject></mediaobject>
    <para>Running up to 140
        web instances and the small number of MariaDB instances
        requires 292 vCPUs available, as well as 584 GB RAM. On a
        typical 1U server using dual-socket hex-core Intel CPUs with
        Hyperthreading, and assuming 2:1 CPU overcommit ratio, this
        would require 8 OpenStack Compute nodes.</para>
    <para>The web application instances run from local storage on each
        of the OpenStack Compute nodes. The web application instances
        are stateless, meaning that any of the instances can fail and
        the application will continue to function.</para>
    <para>MariaDB server instances store their data on shared
        enterprise storage, such as NetApp or Solidfire devices. If a
        MariaDB instance fails, storage would be expected to be
        re-attached to another instance and rejoined to the Galera
        cluster.</para>
    <para>Logs from the web application servers are shipped to
        OpenStack Object Storage for processing and
        archiving.</para>
    <para>Additional capabilities can be realized by
        moving static web content to be served from OpenStack Object
        Storage containers, and backing the OpenStack Image Service
        with OpenStack Object Storage.</para>
      <note>
        <para>
          Increasing OpenStack Object Storage means network bandwidth
          needs to be taken into consideration. Running OpenStack Object
          Storage with network connections offering 10 GbE or better connectivity
          is advised.
        </para>
      </note>
    <para>Leveraging Orchestration and Telemetry modules is also a potential issue when
        providing auto-scaling, orchestrated web application environments.
        Defining the web applications in <glossterm
        baseform="Heat Orchestration Template (HOT)">Heat Orchestration Templates (HOT)</glossterm>
        negates the reliance on the current scripted Puppet solution.</para>
    <para>OpenStack Networking can be used to control hardware load
        balancers through the use of plug-ins and the Networking API.
        This allows users to control hardware load balance pools
        and instances as members in these pools, but their use in
        production environments must be carefully weighed against
        current stability.</para>
</section>
