<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="arch-guide-intro-general-purpose">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>An OpenStack general purpose cloud is often considered a
        starting point for building a cloud deployment. General
        purpose clouds, by their nature, balance the components and do
        not emphasize (or heavily emphasize) any particular aspect of
        the overall computing environment. The expectation is that the
        compute, network, and storage components will be given equal
        weight in the design. General purpose clouds can be found in
        private, public, and hybrid environments. They lend themselves
        to many different use cases but, since they are homogeneous
        deployments, they are not suited to specialized environments
        or edge case situations. Common uses to consider for a general
        purpose cloud could be, but are not limited to, providing a
        simple database, a web application runtime environment, a
        shared application development platform, or lab test bed. In
        other words, any use case that would benefit from a scale-out
        rather than a scale-up approach is a good candidate for a
        general purpose cloud architecture.</para>
    <para>A general purpose cloud, by definition, is something that is
        designed to have a range of potential uses or functions; not
        specialized for a specific use. General purpose architecture
        is largely considered a scenario that would address 80% of the
        potential use cases. The infrastructure, in itself, is a
        specific use case. It is also a good place to start the design
        process. As the most basic cloud service model, general
        purpose clouds are designed to be platforms suited for general
        purpose applications.</para>
    <para>General purpose clouds are limited to the most basic
        components, but they can include additional resources such
        as:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Virtual-machine disk image library</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Raw block storage</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>File or object storage</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Firewalls</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Load balancers</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>IP addresses</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Network overlays or virtual local area networks
                (VLANs)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Software bundles</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</section>
