<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="ch_deployment">
    <title>Deployment</title>
      <para>
        OpenStack Networking provides an extreme amount of flexibility when
        deploying networking in support of a compute environment. As a
        result, the exact layout of a deployment will depend on a
        combination of expected workloads, expected scale, and available
        hardware.
      </para>
       <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../common/figures/Neutron-PhysNet-Diagram.png" align="center" width="6in"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <para>
        For demonstration purposes, this chapter concentrates on a
        networking deployment that consists of these types of nodes:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Service node:</emphasis>
            The service node exposes the networking API to clients and
            handles incoming requests before forwarding them to a message
            queue. Requests are then actioned by the other nodes. The
            service node hosts both the networking service itself and
            the active networking plug-in. In environments that use
            controller nodes to host the client-facing APIs, and
            schedulers for all services, the controller node would also
            fulfill the role of service node as it is applied in this
            chapter.
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Network node:</emphasis>
            The network node handles the majority of the networking
            workload. It hosts the DHCP agent, the Layer-3 (L3) agent, the
            Layer-2 (L2) agent, and the metadata proxy.
            In addition to plug-ins that require an agent, it runs an instance
            of the plug-in agent (as do all other systems that handle data
            packets in an environment where such plug-ins are in use). Both
            the Open vSwitch and Linux Bridge mechanism drivers include an
            agent.
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Compute node:</emphasis>
            The compute node hosts the compute instances themselves. To
            connect compute instances to the networking services, compute
            nodes must also run the L2 agent. Like all other systems that
            handle data packets it must also run an instance of the plug-in
            agent.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

    <xi:include href="section_deployment-architecture.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="section_deployment-scenarios.xml"/>

</chapter>
