<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
<!ENTITY % openstack SYSTEM "../common/entities/openstack.ent">
%openstack;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="intro-layers">
    <title>Networking layers</title>

    <para>Network communications is commonly described in terms of the OSI model,
    a seven-layer model that describes how various protocols and mechanisms fit
    together. Each layer depends on the protocols in the layer beneath it.</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>7 Application</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The Application layer of the OSI model is the user interface
            layer.  Everything here is application specific. Some examples at
            this layer which could be Telnet, FTP, email.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>6 Presentation</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Here is where data gets translated from the application into
            network format and back again. The presentation layer transforms
            data into a form that the application layer can accept. The
            presentation layer formats and encrypts data which prevents
            compatibility problems.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>5 Session</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The Session layer manages connections between applications. It
            is responsible for session and connection coordination.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>4 Transport</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This layer deals with transporting data usually over TCP or
            Transmission Control Protocol.
            TCP enables two hosts to establish, connect, and exchange streams
            of data together. TCP also guarantees delivery of data and the
            order in which packets are sent.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>3 Network</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This layer handles transmission for data from node to node.
            The network layer handles routing, forwarding, addressing,
            internetworking, and error handling.  Usually this is the
            IP portion of TCP/IP.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>2 Data link</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The data link layer where most LAN technologies like Ethernet
            live.  The layer is divided into two sublayers:
          <emphasis role="bold">MAC (Media Access Control):</emphasis> Handles
          access to data and permissions to translate it.
          <emphasis role="bold">LLC (Logical Link Control):</emphasis> Manages
          traffic across the physical layer.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>1 Physical</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The physical layer is the description of the physical media or
            signals used in networking. Examples include the size of the Ethernet,
            hubs, or other physical devices used to establish a network.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>OpenStack Networking is primarily concerned with Layer 2 and Layer 3.</para>

    <para>Layer-3 protocols include the Internet Protocol Suite, which includes
    IPv4, IPv6, and the Internet Control Message Protocol (ICMP).</para>
</section>
