<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="section_image-mgmt">
    <title>Image management</title>
    <para>The OpenStack Image Service discovers, registers, and
        retrieves virtual machine images. The service also includes a
        RESTful API that allows you to query VM image metadata and
        retrieve the actual image with HTTP requests. For more
        information about the API, see the <link
            xlink:href="http://developer.openstack.org/api-ref.html"
            >OpenStack API Complete Reference</link> and the <link
            xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/developer/python-glanceclient/"
            >Python API</link>.</para>
    <para>The OpenStack Image Service can be controlled using a
        command-line tool. For more information about the using
        OpenStack Image command-line tool, see the <link
            xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/user-guide/content/cli_manage_images.html"
            >Manage Images</link> section in the <citetitle>OpenStack
            End User Guide</citetitle>.</para>
    <para>Virtual images that have been made available through the
        Image Service can be stored in a variety of ways. In order to
        use these services, you must have a working installation of
        the Image Service, with a working endpoint, and users that
        have been created in OpenStack Identity. Additionally, you
        must meet the environment variables required by the Compute
        and Image Service clients.</para>
    <para>The Image Service supports these back-end stores:</para>
    <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>File system</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>The OpenStack Image Service stores virtual
                    machine images in the file system back end by
                    default. This simple back end writes image files
                    to the local file system.</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>Object Storage service</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>The OpenStack highly available service for
                    storing objects.</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>S3</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>The Amazon S3 service.</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>HTTP</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>OpenStack Image Service can read virtual machine
                    images that are available on the internet using
                    HTTP. This store is read only.</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>Rados block device (RBD)</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>Stores images inside of a Ceph storage cluster
                    using Ceph's RBD interface.</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>GridFS</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>Stores images using MongoDB.</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
</section>
