<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="section_networking-nova">
    <title>Networking with nova-network</title>
    <para>Understanding the networking configuration options helps you design the best configuration
        for your Compute instances.</para>
    <para>You can choose to either install and configure <systemitem class="service"
            >nova-network</systemitem> for networking between VMs or use the OpenStack Networking
        service (neutron) for networking. To configure Compute networking options with OpenStack
        Networking, see <xref linkend="ch_networking"/>.</para>
    <section xml:id="section_networking-options">
        <title>Networking concepts</title>
        <para>This section offers a brief overview of networking concepts for Compute.</para>
        <para>Compute assigns a private IP address to each VM instance. (Currently, Compute with
                <systemitem class="service">nova-network</systemitem> only supports Linux bridge
            networking that enables the virtual interfaces to connect to the outside network through
            the physical interface.) Compute makes a distinction between <emphasis role="italic"
                >fixed IPs</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">floating IPs</emphasis>. Fixed IPs
            are IP addresses that are assigned to an instance on creation and stay the same until
            the instance is explicitly terminated. By contrast, floating IPs are addresses that can
            be dynamically associated with an instance. A floating IP address can be disassociated
            and associated with another instance at any time. A user can reserve a floating IP for
            their project.</para>
        <para>The network controller with <systemitem class="service">nova-network</systemitem>
            provides virtual networks to enable compute servers to interact with each other and with
            the public network. Compute with <systemitem class="service">nova-network</systemitem>
            supports the following network modes, which are implemented as “Network Manager”
            types.</para>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Flat Network Manager</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>In <emphasis role="bold">Flat</emphasis> mode, a network administrator
                        specifies a subnet. IP addresses for VM instances are assigned from the
                        subnet, and then injected into the image on launch. Each instance receives a
                        fixed IP address from the pool of available addresses. A system
                        administrator must create the Linux networking bridge (typically named
                            <literal>br100</literal>, although this is configurable) on the systems
                        running the <systemitem class="service">nova-network</systemitem> service.
                        All instances of the system are attached to the same bridge, and this is
                        configured manually by the network administrator.</para>
                    <note>
                        <para>Configuration injection currently only works on Linux-style systems
                            that keep networking configuration in
                                <filename>/etc/network/interfaces</filename>.</para>
                    </note>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Flat DHCP Network Manager</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>In <emphasis role="bold">FlatDHCP</emphasis> mode, OpenStack starts a DHCP
                        server (<systemitem>dnsmasq</systemitem>) to allocate IP addresses to VM
                        instances from the specified subnet, in addition to manually configuring the
                        networking bridge. IP addresses for VM instances are assigned from a subnet
                        specified by the network administrator.</para>
                    <para>Like Flat Mode, all instances are attached to a single bridge on the
                        compute node. Additionally, a DHCP server is running to configure instances
                        (depending on single-/multi-host mode, alongside each <systemitem
                            class="service">nova-network</systemitem>). In this mode, Compute does a
                        bit more configuration in that it attempts to bridge into an Ethernet device
                            (<literal>flat_interface</literal>, eth0 by default). For every
                        instance, Compute allocates a fixed IP address and configures dnsmasq with
                        the MAC/IP pair for the VM. Dnsmasq does not take part in the IP address
                        allocation process, it only hands out IPs according to the mapping done by
                        Compute. Instances receive their fixed IPs by doing a
                            <command>dhcpdiscover</command>. These IPs are <emphasis role="italic"
                            >not</emphasis> assigned to any of the host's network interfaces, only
                        to the guest-side interface for the VM.</para>
                    <para>In any setup with flat networking, the hosts providing the <systemitem
                            class="service">nova-network</systemitem> service are responsible for
                        forwarding traffic from the private network. They also run and configure
                            <systemitem>dnsmasq</systemitem> as a DHCP server listening on this
                        bridge, usually on IP address 10.0.0.1 (see <link linkend="section_dnsmasq"
                            >DHCP server: dnsmasq </link>). Compute can determine the NAT entries
                        for each network, although sometimes NAT is not used, such as when
                        configured with all public IPs or a hardware router is used (one of the HA
                        options). Such hosts need to have <literal>br100</literal> configured and
                        physically connected to any other nodes that are hosting VMs. You must set
                        the <literal>flat_network_bridge</literal> option or create networks with
                        the bridge parameter in order to avoid raising an error. Compute nodes have
                        iptables/ebtables entries created for each project and instance to protect
                        against IP/MAC address spoofing and ARP poisoning.</para>
                    <note>
                        <para>In single-host Flat DHCP mode you <emphasis role="italic"
                                >will</emphasis> be able to ping VMs through their fixed IP from the
                                <systemitem>nova-network</systemitem> node, but you <emphasis
                                role="italic">cannot</emphasis> ping them from the compute nodes.
                            This is expected behavior.</para>
                    </note>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>VLAN Network Manager</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">VLANManager</emphasis> mode is the default mode for
                        OpenStack Compute. In this mode, Compute creates a VLAN and bridge for each
                        tenant. For multiple-machine installation, the VLAN Network Mode requires a
                        switch that supports VLAN tagging (IEEE 802.1Q). The tenant gets a range of
                        private IPs that are only accessible from inside the VLAN. In order for a
                        user to access the instances in their tenant, a special VPN instance (code
                        named cloudpipe) needs to be created. Compute generates a certificate and
                        key for the user to access the VPN and starts the VPN automatically. It
                        provides a private network segment for each tenant's instances that can be
                        accessed through a dedicated VPN connection from the Internet. In this mode,
                        each tenant gets its own VLAN, Linux networking bridge, and subnet.</para>
                    <para>The subnets are specified by the network administrator, and are assigned
                        dynamically to a tenant when required. A DHCP Server is started for each
                        VLAN to pass out IP addresses to VM instances from the subnet assigned to
                        the tenant. All instances belonging to one tenant are bridged into the same
                        VLAN for that tenant. OpenStack Compute creates the Linux networking bridges
                        and VLANs when required.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <para>These network managers can co-exist in a cloud system. However, because you cannot
            select the type of network for a given tenant, you cannot configure multiple network
            types in a single Compute installation.</para>
        <para>All network managers configure the network using <emphasis role="italic">network
                drivers</emphasis>. For example, the Linux L3 driver (<literal>l3.py</literal> and
                <literal>linux_net.py</literal>), which makes use of <literal>iptables</literal>,
                <literal>route</literal> and other network management facilities, and the libvirt
                <link xlink:href="http://libvirt.org/formatnwfilter.html">network filtering
                facilities</link>. The driver is not tied to any particular network manager; all
            network managers use the same driver. The driver usually initializes (creates bridges
            and so on) only when the first VM lands on this host node.</para>
        <para>All network managers operate in either <emphasis role="italic">single-host</emphasis>
            or <emphasis role="italic">multi-host</emphasis> mode. This choice greatly influences
            the network configuration. In single-host mode, a single <systemitem class="service"
                >nova-network</systemitem> service provides a default gateway for VMs and hosts a
            single DHCP server (<systemitem>dnsmasq</systemitem>). In multi-host mode, each compute
            node runs its own <systemitem class="service">nova-network</systemitem> service. In both
            cases, all traffic between VMs and the outer world flows through <systemitem
                class="service">nova-network</systemitem>. Each mode has its pros and cons (see the
                <citetitle>Network Topology</citetitle> section in the <link
                xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/openstack-ops/content/"><citetitle>OpenStack
                    Operations Guide</citetitle></link>.</para>
        <note>
            <para>All networking options require network connectivity to be already set up between
                OpenStack physical nodes. OpenStack does not configure any physical network
                interfaces. All network managers automatically create VM virtual interfaces. Some,
                but not all, managers create network bridges such as
                <literal>br100</literal>.</para>
            <para>All machines must have a <emphasis role="italic">public</emphasis> and <emphasis
                    role="italic">internal</emphasis> network interface (controlled by the options:
                    <literal>public_interface</literal> for the public interface, and
                    <literal>flat_interface</literal> and <literal>vlan_interface</literal> for the
                internal interface with flat / VLAN managers). This guide refers to the public
                network as the external network and the private network as the internal or tenant
                network.</para>
            <para>The internal network interface is used for communication with VMs; the interface
                should not have an IP address attached to it before OpenStack installation (it
                serves merely as a fabric where the actual endpoints are VMs and dnsmasq). Also, you
                must put the internal network interface in <emphasis role="italic">promiscuous
                    mode</emphasis>, because it must receive packets whose target MAC address is of
                the guest VM, not of the host.</para>
            <para>Throughout this documentation, the public network is sometimes referred to as the
                external network, while the internal network is also sometimes referred to as the
                private network or tenant network.</para>
        </note>
        <para>For flat and flat DHCP modes, use the following command to create a network:</para>
        <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>nova network-create vmnet \
  --fixed-range-v4=10.0.0.0/24 --fixed-cidr=10.20.0.0/16 --bridge=br100</userinput></screen>
        <para>Where:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><option>--fixed-range-v4-</option> specifies the network subnet.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><option>--fixed-cidr</option> specifies a range of fixed IP addresses to
                    allocate, and can be a subset of the <option>--fixed-range-v4</option>
                    argument.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><option>--bridge</option> specifies the bridge device to which this network is
                    connected on every compute node.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section_dnsmasq">
        <title>DHCP server: dnsmasq</title>
        <para>The Compute service uses <link
                xlink:href="http://www.thekelleys.org.uk/dnsmasq/doc.html">dnsmasq</link> as the
            DHCP server when running with either that Flat DHCP Network Manager or the VLAN Network
            Manager. The <systemitem class="service">nova-network</systemitem> service is
            responsible for starting up <systemitem>dnsmasq</systemitem> processes.</para>
        <para>The behavior of <systemitem>dnsmasq</systemitem> can be customized by creating a
                <systemitem>dnsmasq</systemitem> configuration file. Specify the configuration file
            using the <literal>dnsmasq_config_file</literal> configuration option. For
            example:</para>
        <programlisting language="ini">dnsmasq_config_file=/etc/dnsmasq-nova.conf</programlisting>
        <para>For an example of how to change the behavior of <systemitem>dnsmasq</systemitem> using
            a <systemitem>dnsmasq</systemitem> configuration file, see the <link
                xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/trunk/config-reference/content/"
                    ><citetitle>OpenStack Configuration Reference</citetitle></link>. The
                <systemitem>dnsmasq</systemitem> documentation also has a more comprehensive <link
                xlink:href="http://www.thekelleys.org.uk/dnsmasq/docs/dnsmasq.conf.example">dnsmasq
                configuration file example</link>.</para>
        <para><systemitem>dnsmasq</systemitem> also acts as a caching DNS server for instances. You
            can explicitly specify the DNS server that <systemitem>dnsmasq</systemitem> should use
            by setting the <literal>dns_server</literal> configuration option in
                <filename>/etc/nova/nova.conf</filename>. The following example would configure
                <systemitem>dnsmasq</systemitem> to use Google's public DNS server:</para>
        <programlisting language="ini">dns_server=8.8.8.8</programlisting>
        <para>Logging output for <systemitem>dnsmasq</systemitem> goes to the
                <systemitem>syslog</systemitem> (typically <filename>/var/log/syslog</filename> or
                <filename>/var/log/messages</filename>, depending on Linux distribution).
                <systemitem>dnsmasq</systemitem> logging output can be useful for troubleshooting if
            VM instances boot successfully but are not reachable over the network.</para>
        <para>A network administrator can run <code>nova-manage fixed reserve
                    --address=<replaceable>IP_ADDRESS</replaceable></code> to specify the starting
            point IP address
                (<replaceable>n</replaceable>.<replaceable>n</replaceable>.<replaceable>n</replaceable>.<replaceable>n</replaceable>)
            to reserve with the DHCP server. This reservation only affects which IP address the VMs
            start at, not the fixed IP addresses that the <systemitem class="service"
                >nova-network</systemitem> service places on the bridges.</para>
    </section>
    <xi:include href="section_compute-configure-ipv6.xml"/>
    <section xml:id="section_metadata-service">
        <title>Metadata service</title>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <para>The Compute service uses a special metadata service to enable virtual machine
                instances to retrieve instance-specific data. Instances access the metadata service
                at <literal>http://169.254.169.254</literal>. The metadata service supports two sets
                of APIs: an OpenStack metadata API and an EC2-compatible API. Each of the APIs is
                versioned by date.</para>
            <para>To retrieve a list of supported versions for the OpenStack metadata API, make a
                GET request to <literal>http://169.254.169.254/openstack</literal> For
                example:</para>
            <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>curl http://169.254.169.254/openstack</userinput>
<computeroutput>2012-08-10
latest</computeroutput></screen>
            <para>To list supported versions for the EC2-compatible metadata API, make a GET request
                to <literal>http://169.254.169.254</literal>.</para>
            <para>For example:</para>
            <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>curl http://169.254.169.254</userinput>
<computeroutput>1.0
2007-01-19
2007-03-01
2007-08-29
2007-10-10
2007-12-15
2008-02-01
2008-09-01
2009-04-04
latest</computeroutput></screen>
            <para>If you write a consumer for one of these APIs, always attempt to access the most
                recent API version supported by your consumer first, then fall back to an earlier
                version if the most recent one is not available.</para>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>OpenStack metadata API</title>
            <para>Metadata from the OpenStack API is distributed in JSON format. To retrieve the
                metadata, make a GET request to
                    <literal>http://169.254.169.254/openstack/2012-08-10/meta_data.json</literal>.</para>
            <para>For example:</para>
            <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>curl http://169.254.169.254/openstack/2012-08-10/meta_data.json</userinput></screen>
            <programlisting language="json"><xi:include href="../../common/samples/list_metadata.json" parse="text"/></programlisting>
            <para>Instances also retrieve user data (passed as the <literal>user_data</literal>
                parameter in the API call or by the <literal>--user_data</literal> flag in the
                    <command>nova boot</command> command) through the metadata service, by making a
                GET request to
                    <literal>http://169.254.169.254/openstack/2012-08-10/user_data</literal>.</para>
            <para>For example:</para>
            <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>curl http://169.254.169.254/openstack/2012-08-10/user_data</userinput>
                        <computeroutput>#!/bin/bash
echo 'Extra user data here'</computeroutput></screen>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>EC2 metadata API</title>
            <para>The metadata service has an API that is compatible with version 2009-04-04 of the
                    <link
                    xlink:href="http://docs.amazonwebservices.com/AWSEC2/2009-04-04/UserGuide/AESDG-chapter-instancedata.html"
                    >Amazon EC2 metadata service</link>; virtual machine images that are designed
                for EC2 work properly with OpenStack.</para>
            <para>The EC2 API exposes a separate URL for each metadata. You can retrieve a listing
                of these elements by making a GET query to
                    <literal>http://169.254.169.254/2009-04-04/meta-data/</literal></para>
            <para>For example:</para>
            <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>curl http://169.254.169.254/2009-04-04/meta-data/</userinput>
<computeroutput>ami-id
ami-launch-index
ami-manifest-path
block-device-mapping/
hostname
instance-action
instance-id
instance-type
kernel-id
local-hostname
local-ipv4
placement/
public-hostname
public-ipv4
public-keys/
ramdisk-id
reservation-id
security-groups</computeroutput></screen>
            <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>curl http://169.254.169.254/2009-04-04/meta-data/block-device-mapping/</userinput>
<computeroutput>ami</computeroutput></screen>
            <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>curl http://169.254.169.254/2009-04-04/meta-data/placement/</userinput>
<computeroutput>availability-zone</computeroutput></screen>
            <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>curl http://169.254.169.254/2009-04-04/meta-data/public-keys/</userinput>
<computeroutput>0=mykey</computeroutput></screen>
            <para>Instances can retrieve the public SSH key (identified by keypair name when a user
                requests a new instance) by making a GET request to
                    <literal>http://169.254.169.254/2009-04-04/meta-data/public-keys/0/openssh-key</literal>.</para>
            <para>For example:</para>
            <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>curl http://169.254.169.254/2009-04-04/meta-data/public-keys/0/openssh-key</userinput>
<computeroutput>ssh-rsa AAAAB3NzaC1yc2EAAAADAQABAAAAgQDYVEprvtYJXVOBN0XNKVVRNCRX6BlnNbI+USLGais1sUWPwtSg7z9K9vhbYAPUZcq8c/s5S9dg5vTHbsiyPCIDOKyeHba4MUJq8Oh5b2i71/3BISpyxTBH/uZDHdslW2a+SrPDCeuMMoss9NFhBdKtDkdG9zyi0ibmCP6yMdEX8Q== Generated by Nova</computeroutput></screen>
            <para>Instances can retrieve user data by making a GET request to
                    <literal>http://169.254.169.254/2009-04-04/user-data</literal>.</para>
            <para>For example:</para>
            <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>curl http://169.254.169.254/2009-04-04/user-data</userinput>
<computeroutput>#!/bin/bash
echo 'Extra user data here'</computeroutput></screen>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Run the metadata service</title>
            <para>The metadata service is implemented by either the <systemitem class="service"
                    >nova-api</systemitem> service or the <systemitem class="service"
                    >nova-api-metadata</systemitem> service. (The <systemitem class="service"
                    >nova-api-metadata</systemitem> service is generally only used when running in
                multi-host mode, it retrieves instance-specific metadata). If you are running the
                    <systemitem class="service">nova-api</systemitem> service, you must have
                    <literal>metadata</literal> as one of the elements of the list of the
                    <literal>enabled_apis</literal> configuration option in
                    <filename>/etc/nova/nova.conf</filename>. The default
                    <literal>enabled_apis</literal> configuration setting includes the metadata
                service, so you should not need to modify it.</para>
            <para>Hosts access the service at <literal>169.254.169.254:80</literal>, and this is
                translated to <literal>metadata_host:metadata_port</literal> by an iptables rule
                established by the <systemitem class="service">nova-network</systemitem> service. In
                multi-host mode, you can set <option>metadata_host</option> to
                    <literal>127.0.0.1</literal>.</para>
            <para>To enable instances to reach the metadata service, the <systemitem class="service"
                    >nova-network</systemitem> service configures iptables to NAT port
                    <literal>80</literal> of the <literal>169.254.169.254</literal> address to the
                IP address specified in <option>metadata_host</option> (default
                    <literal>$my_ip</literal>, which is the IP address of the <systemitem
                    class="service">nova-network</systemitem> service) and port specified in
                    <option>metadata_port</option> (default <literal>8775</literal>) in
                    <filename>/etc/nova/nova.conf</filename>.</para>
            <warning>
                <para>The <literal>metadata_host</literal> configuration option must be an IP
                    address, not a host name.</para>
            </warning>
            <note>
                <para>The default Compute service settings assume that the <systemitem
                        class="service">nova-network</systemitem> service and the <systemitem
                        class="service">nova-api</systemitem> service are running on the same host.
                    If this is not the case, you must make this change in the
                        <filename>/etc/nova/nova.conf</filename> file on the host running the
                        <systemitem class="service">nova-network</systemitem> service:</para>
                <para>Set the <literal>metadata_host</literal> configuration option to the IP
                    address of the host where the <systemitem class="service">nova-api</systemitem>
                    service runs.</para>
            </note>
            <xi:include href="../../common/tables/nova-metadata.xml"/>
        </simplesect>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section_enable-ping-and-ssh-on-vms">
        <title>Enable ping and SSH on VMs</title>
        <para>Be sure you enable access to your VMs by using the <command>euca-authorize</command>
            or <command>nova secgroup-add-rule</command> command. These commands enable you to
                <command>ping</command> and <command>ssh</command> to your VMs:</para>
        <note>
            <para>You must run these commands as root only if the credentials used to interact with
                    <systemitem class="service">nova-api</systemitem> are in
                    <filename>/root/.bashrc</filename>. If the EC2 credentials are the
                    <filename>.bashrc</filename> file for another user, you must run these commands
                as the user.</para>
        </note>
        <para>Run <command>nova</command> commands:</para>
        <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>nova secgroup-add-rule default icmp -1 -1 0.0.0.0/0</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>nova secgroup-add-rule default tcp 22 22 0.0.0.0/0</userinput>           </screen>
        <para>Using euca2ools:</para>
        <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>euca-authorize -P icmp -t -1:-1 -s 0.0.0.0/0 default</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>euca-authorize -P tcp -p 22 -s 0.0.0.0/0 default</userinput>         </screen>
        <para>If you still cannot ping or SSH your instances after issuing the <command>nova
                secgroup-add-rule</command> commands, look at the number of
                <literal>dnsmasq</literal> processes that are running. If you have a running
            instance, check to see that TWO <literal>dnsmasq</literal> processes are running. If
            not, perform the following commands as root:</para>
        <screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>killall dnsmasq</userinput>
<prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>service nova-network restart</userinput>         </screen>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="nova-associate-public-ip">
        <title>Configure public (floating) IP addresses</title>
        <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
        <para>If you are using Compute's <systemitem class="service">nova-network</systemitem>
            instead of OpenStack Networking (neutron) for networking in OpenStack, use procedures in
            this section to configure floating IP addresses. For instructions on how to configure
            OpenStack Networking (neutron) to provide access to instances through floating IP
            addresses, see <xref linkend="section_l3_router_and_nat"/>.</para>
        <section xml:id="private-and-public-IP-addresses">
            <title>Private and public IP addresses</title>
            <para>Every virtual instance is automatically assigned a private IP address. You can
                optionally assign public IP addresses to instances. The term <glossterm
                    baseform="floating IP address">floating IP</glossterm> refers to an IP address,
                typically public, that you can dynamically add to a running virtual instance.
                OpenStack Compute uses Network Address Translation (NAT) to assign floating IPs to
                virtual instances.</para>
            <para>If you plan to use this feature, you must add edit the
                    <filename>/etc/nova/nova.conf</filename> file to specify to which interface the
                    <systemitem class="service">nova-network</systemitem> service binds public IP
                addresses, as follows:</para>
            <programlisting language="ini">public_interface=<replaceable>VLAN100</replaceable></programlisting>
            <para>If you make changes to the <filename>/etc/nova/nova.conf</filename> file while the
                    <systemitem class="service">nova-network</systemitem> service is running, you
                must restart the service.</para>
            <note>
                <title>Traffic between VMs using floating IPs</title>
                <para>Because floating IPs are implemented by using a source NAT (SNAT rule in
                    iptables), security groups can display inconsistent behavior if VMs use their
                    floating IP to communicate with other VMs, particularly on the same physical
                    host. Traffic from VM to VM across the fixed network does not have this issue,
                    and so this is the recommended path. To ensure that traffic does not get SNATed
                    to the floating range, explicitly set:</para>
                <programlisting language="ini">dmz_cidr=x.x.x.x/y</programlisting>
                <para>The <literal>x.x.x.x/y</literal> value specifies the range of floating IPs for
                    each pool of floating IPs that you define. If the VMs in the source group have
                    floating IPs, this configuration is also required.</para>
            </note>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="Enabling_ip_forwarding">
            <title>Enable IP forwarding</title>
            <para>By default, IP forwarding is disabled on most Linux distributions. To use the
                floating IP feature, you must enable IP forwarding.</para>
            <note>
                <para>You must enable IP forwarding only on the nodes that run the <systemitem
                        class="service">nova-network</systemitem> service. If you use
                        <literal>multi_host</literal> mode, ensure that you enable it on all compute
                    nodes. Otherwise, enable it on only the node that runs the <systemitem
                        class="service">nova-network</systemitem> service.</para>
            </note>
            <para>To check whether forwarding is enabled, run:</para>
            <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>cat /proc/sys/net/ipv4/ip_forward</userinput>
<computeroutput>0</computeroutput></screen>
            <para>Alternatively, you can run:</para>
            <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>sysctl net.ipv4.ip_forward</userinput>
<computeroutput>net.ipv4.ip_forward = 0</computeroutput></screen>
            <para>In the previous example, IP forwarding is <emphasis role="bold"
                    >disabled</emphasis>. To enable it dynamically, run:</para>
            <screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>sysctl -w net.ipv4.ip_forward=1</userinput></screen>
            <para>Or:</para>
            <screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>echo 1 > /proc/sys/net/ipv4/ip_forward</userinput></screen>
            <para>To make the changes permanent, edit the <filename>/etc/sysctl.conf</filename> file
                and update the IP forwarding setting:</para>
            <programlisting language="ini">net.ipv4.ip_forward = 1</programlisting>
            <para>Save the file and run the following command to apply the changes:</para>
            <screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>sysctl -p</userinput></screen>
            <para>You can also update the setting by restarting the network service:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>On Ubuntu, run:</para>
                    <screen><userinput><prompt>#</prompt>/etc/init.d/procps.sh restart</userinput></screen>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>On RHEL/Fedora/CentOS, run:</para>
                    <screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>service network restart</userinput></screen>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="create_list_of_available_floating_ips">
            <title>Create a list of available floating IP addresses</title>
            <para>Compute maintains a list of floating IP addresses that you can assign to
                instances. Use the <command>nova-manage floating create</command> command to add
                entries to this list.</para>
            <para>For example:</para>
            <screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>nova-manage floating create --pool=nova --ip_range=68.99.26.170/31</userinput></screen>
            <para>You can use the following <command>nova-manage</command> commands to perform
                floating IP operations:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>nova-manage floating list</userinput></screen>
                    <para>Lists the floating IP addresses in the pool.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>nova-manage floating create --pool=<replaceable>POOL_NAME</replaceable> --ip_range=<replaceable>CIDR</replaceable></userinput></screen>
                    <para>Creates specific floating IPs for either a single address or a
                        subnet.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>nova-manage floating delete <replaceable>CIDR</replaceable></userinput></screen>
                    <para>Removes floating IP addresses using the same parameters as the create
                        command.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>For information about how administrators can associate floating IPs with
                instances, see <link
                    xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/user-guide-admin/content/manage_ip_addresses.html"
                    >Manage IP addresses</link> in the <citetitle>OpenStack Admin User
                    Guide</citetitle>.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="Automatically_adding_floating_IPs">
            <title>Automatically add floating IPs</title>
            <para>You can configure the <systemitem class="service">nova-network</systemitem>
                service to automatically allocate and assign a floating IP address to virtual
                instances when they are launched. Add the following line to the
                    <filename>/etc/nova/nova.conf</filename> file and restart the <systemitem
                    class="service">nova-network</systemitem> service:</para>
            <programlisting language="ini">auto_assign_floating_ip=True</programlisting>
            <note>
                <para>If you enable this option and all floating IP addresses have already been
                    allocated, the <command>nova boot</command> command fails.</para>
            </note>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section_remove-network-from-project">
        <title>Remove a network from a project</title>
        <para>You cannot remove a network that has already been associated to a project by simply
            deleting it.</para>
        <para>To determine the project ID, you must have administrative rights. You can disassociate
            the project from the network with a scrub command and the project ID as the final
            parameter:</para>
        <screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>nova-manage project scrub --project=<replaceable>ID</replaceable></userinput></screen>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section_use-multi-nics">
        <title>Multiple interfaces for your instances (multinic)</title>
        <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
        <para>The multinic feature allows you to plug more than one interface to your instances,
            making it possible to make several use cases available:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>SSL Configurations (VIPs)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Services failover/ HA</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Bandwidth Allocation</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Administrative/ Public access to your instances</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>Each VIF is representative of a separate network with its own IP block. Every network
            mode introduces its own set of changes regarding the multinic usage:</para>
        <figure>
            <title>multinic flat manager</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata scale="40"
                        fileref="../../common/figures/SCH_5007_V00_NUAC-multi_nic_OpenStack-Flat-manager.jpg"
                    />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <figure>
            <title>multinic flatdhcp manager</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata scale="40"
                        fileref="../../common/figures/SCH_5007_V00_NUAC-multi_nic_OpenStack-Flat-DHCP-manager.jpg"
                    />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <figure>
            <title>multinic VLAN manager</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata scale="40"
                        fileref="../../common/figures/SCH_5007_V00_NUAC-multi_nic_OpenStack-VLAN-manager.jpg"
                    />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <section xml:id="using-multiple-nics-usage">
            <title>Use the multinic feature</title>
            <para>In order to use the multinic feature, first create two networks, and attach them
                to your tenant (still named 'project' on the command line):
                <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>nova network-create first-net --fixed-range-v4=20.20.0.0/24 --project-id=$your-project</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>nova network-create second-net --fixed-range-v4=20.20.10.0/24 --project-id=$your-project</userinput>              </screen>
                Now every time you spawn a new instance, it gets two IP addresses from the
                respective DHCP servers:</para>
            <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>nova list</userinput>
<computeroutput>+-----+------------+--------+----------------------------------------+
 |  ID |    Name    | Status |                Networks                |
 +-----+------------+--------+----------------------------------------+
 | 124 | Server 124 | ACTIVE | network2=20.20.0.3; private=20.20.10.14|
 +-----+------------+--------+----------------------------------------+</computeroutput></screen>
            <note>
                <para>Make sure to power up the second interface on the instance, otherwise that
                    last won't be reachable through its second IP. Here is an example of how to
                    setup the interfaces within the instance (this is the configuration that needs
                    to be applied inside the image):</para>
                <para><filename>/etc/network/interfaces</filename></para>
                <programlisting language="bash"># The loopback network interface
auto lo
iface lo inet loopback

auto eth0
iface eth0 inet dhcp

auto eth1
iface eth1 inet dhcp</programlisting>
            </note>
            <note>
                <para>If the Virtual Network Service Neutron is installed, it is possible to specify
                    the networks to attach to the respective interfaces by using the
                        <literal>--nic</literal> flag when invoking the <literal>nova</literal>
                    command:</para>
                <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>nova boot --image ed8b2a37-5535-4a5f-a615-443513036d71 --flavor 1 --nic net-id=<replaceable>NETWORK1_ID</replaceable> --nic net-id=<replaceable>NETWORK2_ID</replaceable> test-vm1</userinput></screen>
            </note>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section_network-troubleshoot">
        <title>Troubleshoot Networking</title>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Cannot reach floating IPs</title>
            <para>If you cannot reach your instances through the floating IP address, check the
                following:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Ensure the default security group allows ICMP (ping) and SSH (port 22), so
                        that you can reach the instances:</para>
                    <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>nova secgroup-list-rules default</userinput>
<computeroutput>+-------------+-----------+---------+-----------+--------------+
| IP Protocol | From Port | To Port |  IP Range | Source Group |
+-------------+-----------+---------+-----------+--------------+
| icmp        | -1        | -1      | 0.0.0.0/0 |              |
| tcp         | 22        | 22      | 0.0.0.0/0 |              |
+-------------+-----------+---------+-----------+--------------+</computeroutput></screen>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Ensure the NAT rules have been added to <systemitem>iptables</systemitem>
                        on the node that <systemitem>nova-network</systemitem> is running on, as
                        root:</para>
                    <screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>iptables -L -nv -t nat</userinput>
<computeroutput>-A nova-network-PREROUTING -d 68.99.26.170/32 -j DNAT --to-destination 10.0.0.3
-A nova-network-floating-snat -s 10.0.0.3/32 -j SNAT --to-source 68.99.26.170</computeroutput></screen>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Check that the public address, in this example "68.99.26.170", has been
                        added to your public interface. You should see the address in the listing
                        when you enter "ip addr" at the command prompt.</para>
                    <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>ip addr</userinput>
<computeroutput>2: eth0: &lt;BROADCAST,MULTICAST,UP,LOWER_UP&gt; mtu 1500 qdisc mq state UP qlen 1000
link/ether xx:xx:xx:17:4b:c2 brd ff:ff:ff:ff:ff:ff
inet 13.22.194.80/24 brd 13.22.194.255 scope global eth0
inet 68.99.26.170/32 scope global eth0
inet6 fe80::82b:2bf:fe1:4b2/64 scope link
valid_lft forever preferred_lft forever</computeroutput></screen>
                    <note>
                        <para>You cannot <command>ssh</command> to an instance with a public IP from
                            within the same server because the routing configuration does not allow
                            it.</para>
                    </note>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>You can use <command>tcpdump</command> to identify if packets are being
                        routed to the inbound interface on the compute host. If the packets are
                        reaching the compute hosts but the connection is failing, the issue may be
                        that the packet is being dropped by reverse path filtering. Try disabling
                        reverse-path filtering on the inbound interface. For example, if the inbound
                        interface is <literal>eth2</literal>, as root, run:</para>
                    <screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>sysctl -w net.ipv4.conf.<replaceable>ETH2</replaceable>.rp_filter=0</userinput></screen>
                    <para>If this solves your issue, add the following line to
                            <filename>/etc/sysctl.conf</filename> so that the reverse-path filter is
                        disabled the next time the compute host reboots:</para>
                    <programlisting language="ini">net.ipv4.conf.rp_filter=0</programlisting>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Disable firewall</title>
            <para>To help debug networking issues with reaching VMs, you can disable the firewall by
                setting the following option in <filename>/etc/nova/nova.conf</filename>:</para>
            <programlisting language="ini">firewall_driver=nova.virt.firewall.NoopFirewallDriver</programlisting>
            <para>We strongly recommend you remove this line to re-enable the firewall once your
                networking issues have been resolved.</para>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Packet loss from instances to nova-network server (VLANManager mode)</title>
            <para>If you can SSH to your instances but you find that the network interactions to
                your instance is slow, or if you find that running certain operations are slower
                than they should be (for example, <command>sudo</command>), then there may be packet
                loss occurring on the connection to the instance.</para>
            <para>Packet loss can be caused by Linux networking configuration settings related to
                bridges. Certain settings can cause packets to be dropped between the VLAN interface
                (for example, <literal>vlan100</literal>) and the associated bridge interface (for
                example, <literal>br100</literal>) on the host running the <systemitem
                    class="service">nova-network</systemitem> service.</para>
            <para>One way to check whether this is the issue in your setup, is to open up three
                terminals and run the following commands:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>In the first terminal, on the host running nova-network, use
                            <command>tcpdump</command> on the VLAN interface to monitor DNS-related
                        traffic (UDP, port 53). As root, run:</para>
                    <screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>tcpdump -K -p -i vlan100 -v -vv udp port 53</userinput></screen>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>In the second terminal, also on the host running nova-network, use
                            <command>tcpdump</command> to monitor DNS-related traffic on the bridge
                        interface. As root, run:</para>
                    <screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>tcpdump -K -p -i br100 -v -vv udp port 53</userinput></screen>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>In the third terminal, SSH inside of the instance and generate DNS
                        requests by using the <command>nslookup</command> command:</para>
                    <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>nslookup www.google.com</userinput></screen>
                    <para>The symptoms may be intermittent, so try running
                            <command>nslookup</command> multiple times. If the network configuration
                        is correct, the command should return immediately each time. If it is not
                        functioning properly, the command hangs for several seconds.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If the <command>nslookup</command> command sometimes hangs, and there are
                        packets that appear in the first terminal but not the second, then the
                        problem may be due to filtering done on the bridges. Try to disable
                        filtering, run the following commands as root:</para>
                    <screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>sysctl -w net.bridge.bridge-nf-call-arptables=0</userinput>
<prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>sysctl -w net.bridge.bridge-nf-call-iptables=0</userinput>
<prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>sysctl -w net.bridge.bridge-nf-call-ip6tables=0</userinput></screen>
                    <para>If this solves your issue, add the following line to
                            <filename>/etc/sysctl.conf</filename> so that these changes take effect
                        the next time the host reboots:</para>
                    <programlisting language="ini">net.bridge.bridge-nf-call-arptables=0
net.bridge.bridge-nf-call-iptables=0
net.bridge.bridge-nf-call-ip6tables=0</programlisting>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>KVM: Network connectivity works initially, then fails</title>
            <para>Some administrators have observed an issue with the KVM hypervisor where instances
                running Ubuntu 12.04 sometimes loses network connectivity after functioning properly
                for a period of time. Some users have reported success with loading the vhost_net
                kernel module as a workaround for this issue (see <link
                    xlink:href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/ubuntu/+source/libvirt/+bug/997978/">bug
                    #997978</link>) . This kernel module may also <link
                    xlink:href="http://www.linux-kvm.org/page/VhostNet">improve network performance
                    on KVM</link>. To load the kernel module, as root:</para>
            <screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>modprobe vhost_net</userinput></screen>
            <note>
                <para>Loading the module has no effect on running instances.</para>
            </note>
        </simplesect>
    </section>
</section>
