<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xml:id="root-wrap-reference"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <title>Secure with root wrappers</title>
    <para>The root wrapper enables an unprivileged user to run a number of Compute actions as the
        root user in the safest manner possible. Historically, Compute used a specific
            <filename>sudoers</filename> file that listed every command that the Compute user was
        allowed to run, and used <command>sudo</command> to run that command as
            <literal>root</literal>. However this was difficult to maintain (the
            <filename>sudoers</filename> file was in packaging), and did not enable complex
        filtering of parameters (advanced filters). The rootwrap was designed to solve those
        issues.</para>
    <simplesect>
        <title>How rootwrap works</title>
        <para>Instead of calling <command>sudo make me a sandwich</command>, Compute services start
            with a <command>nova-rootwrap</command> call; for example, <command>sudo nova-rootwrap
                /etc/nova/rootwrap.conf make me a sandwich</command>. A generic sudoers entry lets
            the Compute user run <command>nova-rootwrap</command> as root. The
                <command>nova-rootwrap</command> code looks for filter definition directories in its
            configuration file, and loads command filters from them. Then it checks if the command
            requested by Compute matches one of those filters, in which case it executes the command
            (as root). If no filter matches, it denies the request.</para>
        <note><para>To use <command>nova-rootwrap</command>, you must be aware of the issues with using NFS and
                root-owned files. The NFS share must be configured with the
                    <option>no_root_squash</option> option enabled.</para>
        </note>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>Security model</title>
        <para>The escalation path is fully controlled by the root user. A sudoers entry (owned by
            root) allows Compute to run (as root) a specific rootwrap executable, and only with a
            specific configuration file (which should be owned by root).
                <command>nova-rootwrap</command> imports the Python modules it needs from a cleaned
            (and system-default) <replaceable>PYTHONPATH</replaceable>. The configuration file (also
            root-owned) points to root-owned filter definition directories, which contain root-owned
            filters definition files. This chain ensures that the Compute user itself is not in
            control of the configuration or modules used by the <command>nova-rootwrap</command>
            executable.</para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>Details of rootwrap.conf</title>
        <para>You configure <command>nova-rootwrap</command> in the
                <filename>rootwrap.conf</filename> file. Because it's in the trusted security path,
            it must be owned and writable by only the root user. The file's location is specified
            both in the sudoers entry and in the <filename>nova.conf</filename> configuration file
            with the <code>rootwrap_config=entry</code>.</para>
        <para>The <filename>rootwrap.conf</filename> file uses an INI file format with these
            sections and parameters:</para>
        <table rules="all" frame="border"
            xml:id="rootwrap-conf-table-filter-path" width="100%">
            <caption>rootwrap.conf configuration options</caption>
            <col width="50%"/>
            <col width="50%"/>
            <thead>
                <tr>
                    <td><para>Configuration option=Default
                            value</para></td>
                    <td><para>(Type) Description</para></td>
                </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
                <tr>
                    <td><para>[DEFAULT]</para>
                        <para>filters_path=/etc/nova/rootwrap.d,/usr/share/nova/rootwrap
                        </para></td>
                    <td><para>(ListOpt) Comma-separated list of
                            directories containing filter definition
                            files. Defines where filters for root wrap
                            are stored. Directories defined on this
                            line should all exist, be owned and
                            writable only by the root
                        user.</para></td>
                </tr>
            </tbody>
        </table>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>Details of .filters files</title>
        <para>Filters definition files contain lists of filters that
                <command>nova-rootwrap</command> will use to allow or deny a specific command. They
            are generally suffixed by .filters. Since they are in the trusted security path, they
            need to be owned and writable only by the root user. Their location is specified in the
                <filename>rootwrap.conf</filename> file.</para>
        <para>Filter definition files use an INI file format with a [Filters] section and several
            lines, each with a unique parameter name (different for each filter that you
            define):</para>
        <table rules="all" frame="border"
            xml:id="rootwrap-conf-table-filter-name" width="100%">
            <caption>.filters configuration options</caption>
            <col width="50%"/>
            <col width="50%"/>
            <thead>
                <tr>
                    <td><para>Configuration option=Default
                            value</para></td>
                    <td><para>(Type) Description</para></td>
                </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
                <tr>
                    <td><para>[Filters]</para>
                        <para>filter_name=kpartx: CommandFilter,
                            /sbin/kpartx, root</para></td>
                    <td><para>(ListOpt) Comma-separated list
                            containing first the Filter class to use,
                            followed by that Filter arguments (which
                            vary depending on the Filter class
                            selected).</para></td>
                </tr>
            </tbody>
        </table>
    </simplesect>
</section>
