<section xml:id="GPFS-driver" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <title>IBM GPFS volume driver</title>
    <para>IBM General Parallel File System (GPFS) is a cluster file
        system that provides concurrent access to file systems from
        multiple nodes. The storage provided by these nodes can be
        direct attached, network attached, SAN attached, or a
        combination of these methods. GPFS provides many features
        beyond common data access, including data replication, policy
        based storage management, and space efficient file snapshot
        and clone operations.</para>
    <section xml:id="GPFS-driver-background">
        <title>How the GPFS driver works</title>
        <para>The GPFS driver enables the use of GPFS in a fashion
            similar to that of the NFS driver. With the GPFS driver, instances do not
            actually access a storage device at the block level.
            Instead, volume backing files are created in a GPFS file
            system and mapped to instances, which emulate a block
            device.</para>
        <para>
            <note>
                <para>GPFS software must be installed and running on
                    nodes where Block Storage and Compute
                    services run in the OpenStack environment.
                    A GPFS file system must also be created and
                    mounted on these nodes before starting the
                        <literal>cinder-volume</literal> service. The
                    details of these GPFS specific steps are covered
                    in <citetitle>GPFS: Concepts, Planning, and Installation Guide</citetitle>
                    and <citetitle>GPFS: Administration and Programming Reference</citetitle>.
                   </para>
            </note>
       </para>
        <para>Optionally, the Image Service can be configured to store images on
            a GPFS file system. When a Block Storage volume is created from
            an image, if both image data and volume data reside in the
            same GPFS file system, the data from image file is moved
            efficiently to the volume file using copy-on-write
            optimization strategy.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="GPFS-driver-options">
        <title>Enable the GPFS driver</title>
        <para>To use the Block Storage service with the GPFS driver, first set the
                <literal>volume_driver</literal> in
                <filename>cinder.conf</filename>:</para>
        <programlisting>volume_driver = cinder.volume.drivers.ibm.gpfs.GPFSDriver</programlisting>
        <para>The following table contains the configuration options
            supported by the GPFS driver.</para>
        <xi:include
            href="../../../common/tables/cinder-storage_gpfs.xml"/>
        <note>
            <para>The <literal>gpfs_images_share_mode</literal>
                flag is only valid if the Image Service is configured to
                use GPFS with the <literal>gpfs_images_dir</literal> flag.
                When the value of this flag is
                    <literal>copy_on_write</literal>, the paths
                specified by the
                    <literal>gpfs_mount_point_base</literal> and
                    <literal>gpfs_images_dir</literal> flags must both
                reside in the same GPFS file system and in the same
                GPFS file set.</para>
        </note>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="GPFS-volume-options">
        <title>Volume creation options</title>
        <para>It is possible to specify additional volume
            configuration options on a per-volume basis by specifying
            volume metadata. The volume is created using the specified
            options. Changing the metadata after the volume is created
            has no effect. The following table lists the volume
            creation options supported by the GPFS volume
            driver.</para>
        <table rules="all">
            <caption>Volume Create Options for GPFS Volume
                Drive</caption>
            <thead>
                <tr>
                    <th>Metadata Item Name</th>
                    <th>Description</th>
                </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
                <tr>
                    <td><literal>fstype</literal></td>
                    <td>Specifies whether to create a file system or a swap
                        area on the new volume. If
                            <literal>fstype=swap</literal> is
                        specified, the mkswap command is used to
                        create a swap area. Otherwise the mkfs command
                        is passed the specified file system type, for example
                        ext3, ext4 or ntfs.</td>

                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><literal>fslabel</literal></td>
                    <td>Sets the file system label for
                        the file system specified by <literal>fstype</literal> option.
                        This value is only used if <literal>fstype</literal> is
    specified.</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
      <td><literal>data_pool_name</literal></td>
      <td>
    <para>Specifies the GPFS storage pool to which the volume is to be assigned.
        Note: The GPFS storage pool must already have been
        created.</para>
      </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
      <td><literal>replicas</literal></td>
      <td>
    <para>Specifies how many copies of the volume
        file to create. Valid values are 1, 2,
        and, for GPFS V3.5.0.7 and later, 3. This
        value cannot be greater than the value of
        the <literal>MaxDataReplicas</literal> attribute of the file
        system.</para>
      </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
      <td><literal>dio</literal></td>
      <td>
    <para>Enables or disables the Direct I/O caching
        policy for the volume file. Valid values
        are <literal>yes</literal> and <literal>no</literal>.</para>
      </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
      <td><literal>write_affinity_depth</literal></td>
      <td>
    <para>Specifies the allocation policy to be used
        for the volume file. Note: This option
        only works if <literal>allow-write-affinity</literal> is
        set for the GPFS data pool.</para>
      </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
      <td><literal>block_group_factor</literal></td>
      <td>
    <para>Specifies how many blocks are laid out
        sequentially in the volume file to behave
        as a single large block. Note: This option
        only works if <literal>allow-write-affinity</literal> is
        set for the GPFS data pool.</para>
      </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
      <td><literal>write_affinity_failure_group</literal></td>
      <td>
    <para>Specifies the range of nodes (in GPFS
        shared nothing architecture) where
        replicas of blocks in the volume file are
        to be written. See <citetitle>GPFS: Administration and
        Programming Reference</citetitle> for more
        details on this option.</para>
      </td>
  </tr>
    </tbody>
</table>
<simplesect>
    <title>Example: Volume creation options</title>
    <para>This example shows the creation of a 50GB volume with an <systemitem>ext4</systemitem>
                file system labeled <literal>newfs</literal> and direct IO enabled:</para>
    <screen><prompt>$</prompt><userinput>cinder create --metadata fstype=ext4 fslabel=newfs dio=yes --display-name volume_1 50</userinput> </screen>
</simplesect>
</section>
<section xml:id="GPFS-operational-notes">
<title>Operational notes for GPFS driver</title>
<simplesect>
    <title>Snapshots and clones</title>
    <para>Volume snapshots are implemented using the GPFS file
        clone feature. Whenever a new snapshot is created, the
        snapshot file is efficiently created as a read-only
        clone parent of the volume, and the volume file uses
        copy-on-write optimization strategy to minimize data
        movement.</para>
    <para>Similarly when a new volume is created from a snapshot or from an existing volume, the
                same approach is taken. The same approach is also used when a new volume is created
                from an Image Service image, if the source image is in raw format, and
                    <literal>gpfs_images_share_mode</literal> is set to
                    <literal>copy_on_write</literal>.</para>
        </simplesect>
    </section>
</section>
