<section xml:id="netapp-volume-driver"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <title>NetApp unified driver</title>
    <para>The NetApp® unified driver is a block storage driver that
        supports multiple storage families and protocols. A storage
        family corresponds to storage systems built on different
        NetApp technologies such as clustered Data ONTAP® and Data
        ONTAP operating in 7-Mode. The storage protocol refers to the
        protocol used to initiate data storage and access operations
        on those storage systems like iSCSI and NFS. The NetApp
        unified driver can be configured to provision and manage
        OpenStack volumes on a given storage family using a specified
        storage protocol. The OpenStack volumes can then be used for
        accessing and storing data using the storage protocol on the
        storage family system. The NetApp unified driver is an
        extensible interface that can support new storage families and
        protocols.</para>
    <section xml:id="ontap-cluster-family">
        <title>NetApp clustered Data ONTAP storage family</title>
        <para>The NetApp clustered Data ONTAP storage family
            represents a configuration group which provides OpenStack
            compute instances access to clustered Data ONTAP storage
            systems. At present it can be configured in Cinder to work
            with iSCSI and NFS storage protocols.</para>
        <section xml:id="ontap-cluster-iscsi">
            <title>NetApp iSCSI configuration for clustered Data
                ONTAP</title>
            <para>The NetApp iSCSI configuration for clustered Data
                ONTAP is an interface from OpenStack to clustered Data
                ONTAP storage systems for provisioning and managing
                the SAN block storage entity; that is, a NetApp LUN
                which can be accessed using the iSCSI protocol.</para>
            <para>The iSCSI configuration for clustered Data ONTAP is
                a direct interface from Cinder to the clustered Data
                ONTAP instance and as such does not require additional
                management software to achieve the desired
                functionality. It uses NetApp APIs to interact with
                the clustered Data ONTAP instance.</para>
            <simplesect>
                <title>Configuration options for clustered Data ONTAP
                    family with iSCSI protocol</title>
                <para>Configure the volume driver, storage family and
                    storage protocol to the NetApp unified driver,
                    clustered Data ONTAP, and iSCSI respectively by
                    setting the <literal>volume_driver</literal>,
                        <literal>netapp_storage_family</literal> and
                        <literal>netapp_storage_protocol</literal>
                    options in <filename>cinder.conf</filename> as
                    follows:</para>
                <programlisting language="ini">
  volume_driver=cinder.volume.drivers.netapp.common.NetAppDriver
  netapp_storage_family=ontap_cluster
  netapp_storage_protocol=iscsi
  netapp_vserver=openstack-vserver
  netapp_server_hostname=myhostname
  netapp_server_port=80
  netapp_login=username
  netapp_password=password
               </programlisting>
                <note>
                    <para>You must override the default value of
                            <literal>netapp_storage_protocol</literal>
                        with <literal>iscsi</literal> in order to
                        utilize the iSCSI protocol.</para>
                </note>
                <xi:include
                    href="../../../common/tables/cinder-netapp_cdot_iscsi.xml"/>
                <note>
                    <para>If you specify an account in the
                            <literal>netapp_login</literal> that only
                        has virtual storage server (Vserver)
                        administration privileges (rather than
                        cluster-wide administration privileges), some
                        advanced features of the NetApp unified driver
                        will not work and you may see warnings in the
                        Cinder logs.</para>
                </note>
                <tip>
                    <para>For more information on these options and
                        other deployment and operational scenarios,
                        visit the <link
                            xlink:href="https://communities.netapp.com/groups/openstack"
                            > OpenStack NetApp
                        community</link>.</para>
                </tip>
            </simplesect>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="ontap-cluster-nfs">
            <title>NetApp NFS configuration for clustered Data
                ONTAP</title>
            <para>The NetApp NFS configuration for clustered Data
                ONTAP is an interface from OpenStack to a clustered
                Data ONTAP system for provisioning and managing
                OpenStack volumes on NFS exports provided by the
                clustered Data ONTAP system that are accessed using
                the NFS protocol.</para>
            <para>The NFS configuration for clustered Data ONTAP is a
                direct interface from Cinder to the clustered Data
                ONTAP instance and as such does not require any
                additional management software to achieve the desired
                functionality. It uses NetApp APIs to interact with
                the clustered Data ONTAP instance.</para>
            <simplesect>
                <title>Configuration options for the clustered Data
                    ONTAP family with NFS protocol</title>
                <para>Configure the volume driver, storage family and
                    storage protocol to NetApp unified driver,
                    clustered Data ONTAP, and NFS respectively by
                    setting the <literal>volume_driver</literal>,
                        <literal>netapp_storage_family</literal> and
                        <literal>netapp_storage_protocol</literal>
                    options in <filename>cinder.conf</filename> as
                    follows:</para>
                <programlisting language="ini">
  volume_driver=cinder.volume.drivers.netapp.common.NetAppDriver
  netapp_storage_family=ontap_cluster
  netapp_storage_protocol=nfs
  netapp_vserver=openstack-vserver
  netapp_server_hostname=myhostname
  netapp_server_port=80
  netapp_login=username
  netapp_password=password
               </programlisting>
                <xi:include
                    href="../../../common/tables/cinder-netapp_cdot_nfs.xml"/>
                <note>
                    <para>If you specify an account in the
                            <literal>netapp_login</literal> that only
                        has virtual storage server (Vserver)
                        administration privileges (rather than
                        cluster-wide administration privileges), some
                        advanced features of the NetApp unified driver
                        will not work and you may see warnings in the
                        Cinder logs.</para>
                </note>
            </simplesect>
            <simplesect>
                <title>NetApp NFS Copy Offload client</title>
                <para>A feature was added in the Icehouse release of the NetApp unified
                    driver that enables Image Service images to be efficiently copied to a
                    destination Block Storage volume. When the Block Storage and Image Service are
                    configured to use the NetApp NFS Copy Offload client, a controller-side copy
                    will be attempted before reverting to downloading the image from the
                    Image Service. This improves image provisioning times while reducing the
                    consumption of bandwidth and CPU cycles on the host(s) running the Image
                    and Block Storage services. This is due to the copy operation being performed
                    completely within the storage cluster.</para>
                <para>The NetApp NFS Copy Offload client can be used in either of the following
                    scenarios:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The Image Service is configured to store images in an NFS share that
                            is exported from a NetApp FlexVol volume <emphasis>and</emphasis>
                            the destination for the new Block Storage volume will be on an NFS share
                            exported from a different FlexVol volume than the one used by
                            the Image Service. Both FlexVols must be located within the same cluster.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The source image from the Image Service has already been cached in an NFS
                            image cache within a Block Storage backend. The cached image resides on a
                            different FlexVol volume than the destination for the new Block Storage
                            volume. Both FlexVols must be located within the same cluster.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>In order to use this feature, the Image Service must be configured as follows:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The <literal>default_store</literal> configuration option should be set to
                            <literal>file</literal></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The <literal>filesystem_store_datadir</literal> configuration option should be set to
                            the path to the the Image Service NFS export</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The <literal>show_image_direct_url</literal> configuration option should be set to
                            <literal>True</literal></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The <literal>show_multiple_locations</literal> configuration option should be set to
                            <literal>True</literal></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The <literal>filesystem_store_metadata_file</literal> configuration option
                            should refer to a metadata file. The metadata file should contain a
                            JSON object that contains the correct information about the NFS export
                            used by the Image Service, similar to:</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <programlisting language="ini">
{
    "share_location": "<replaceable>nfs://192.168.0.1/myGlanceExport</replaceable>",
    "mount_point": "<replaceable>/var/lib/glance/images</replaceable>",
    "type": "nfs"
}
                </programlisting>
                <para>In order to use this feature, the Block Storage Service must be configured as follows:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The <literal>netapp_copyoffload_tool</literal> configuration option should be set to
                            the path to the NetApp Copy Offload binary</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The <literal>glance_api_version</literal> configuration option should be set to
                            <literal>2</literal></para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <important>
                    <para>This feature requires that:</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The storage system must have Data ONTAP v8.2 or greater
                                installed.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The vStorage feature must be enabled on each storage virtual
                                machine (SVM, also known as a Vserver) that is permitted to
                                interact with the copy offload client.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>NFS v4.0 or greater must be enabled and correctly exported
                                from the SVM in order for the copy offload workflow to succeed.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </important>
                <tip>
                    <para>To download the NetApp copy offload binary to be utilized
                        in conjunction with the <literal>netapp_copyoffload_tool_path</literal>
                        configuration option, please visit the Downloads section of
                        the <link xlink:href="http://support.netapp.com/">NetApp
                        support site</link>.</para>
                </tip>
                <tip>
                    <para>For more information on these options and other deployment
                        and operational scenarios, visit the <link
                        xlink:href="https://communities.netapp.com/groups/openstack">
                        OpenStack NetApp community</link>.</para>
                </tip>
            </simplesect>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="ontap-cluster-extraspecs">
            <title>NetApp-supported extra specs for clustered Data
                ONTAP</title>
            <para>Extra specs enable vendors to specify extra filter
                criteria that the Block Storage scheduler uses when it
                determines which volume node should fulfill a volume
                provisioning request. When you use the NetApp unified
                driver with a clustered Data ONTAP storage system, you
                can leverage extra specs with Cinder volume types to
                ensure that Cinder volumes are created on storage back
                ends that have certain properties. For example, when
                you configure QoS, mirroring, or compression for a
                storage back end.</para>
            <para>Extra specs are associated with Cinder volume types,
                so that when users request volumes of a particular
                volume type, the volumes are created on storage back
                ends that meet the list of requirements. For example,
                the back ends have the available space or extra specs.
                You can use the specs in the following table when you
                define Cinder volume types by using the
                    <command>cinder type-key</command> command.</para>
            <xi:include
                href="../../../common/tables/cinder-netapp_cdot_extraspecs.xml"/>
            <note>
                <para>It is recommended to only set the value of extra
                    specs to <literal>True</literal> when combining
                    multiple specs to enforce a certain logic set. If
                    you desire to remove volumes with a certain
                    feature enabled from consideration from the Cinder
                    volume scheduler, be sure to use the negated spec
                    name with a value of <literal>True</literal>
                    rather than setting the positive spec to a value
                    of <literal>False</literal>.</para>
            </note>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ontap-7mode-family">
        <title>NetApp Data ONTAP operating in 7-Mode storage
            family</title>
        <para>The NetApp Data ONTAP operating in 7-Mode storage family
            represents a configuration group which provides OpenStack
            compute instances access to 7-Mode storage systems. At
            present it can be configured in Cinder to work with iSCSI
            and NFS storage protocols.</para>
        <section xml:id="ontap-7mode-iscsi">
            <title>NetApp iSCSI configuration for Data ONTAP operating
                in 7-Mode</title>
            <para>The NetApp iSCSI configuration for Data ONTAP
                operating in 7-Mode is an interface from OpenStack to
                Data ONTAP operating in 7-Mode storage systems for
                provisioning and managing the SAN block storage
                entity, that is, a LUN which can be accessed using
                iSCSI protocol.</para>
            <para>The iSCSI configuration for Data ONTAP operating in
                7-Mode is a direct interface from OpenStack to Data
                ONTAP operating in 7-Mode storage system and it does
                not require additional management software to achieve
                the desired functionality. It uses NetApp ONTAPI to
                interact with the Data ONTAP operating in 7-Mode
                storage system.</para>
            <simplesect>
                <title>Configuration options for the Data ONTAP
                    operating in 7-Mode storage family with iSCSI
                    protocol</title>
                <para>Configure the volume driver, storage family and
                    storage protocol to the NetApp unified driver,
                    Data ONTAP operating in 7-Mode, and iSCSI
                    respectively by setting the
                        <literal>volume_driver</literal>,
                        <literal>netapp_storage_family</literal> and
                        <literal>netapp_storage_protocol</literal>
                    options in <filename>cinder.conf</filename> as
                    follows:</para>
                <programlisting language="ini">
  volume_driver=cinder.volume.drivers.netapp.common.NetAppDriver
  netapp_storage_family=ontap_7mode
  netapp_storage_protocol=iscsi
  netapp_server_hostname=myhostname
  netapp_server_port=80
  netapp_login=username
  netapp_password=password
               </programlisting>
                <note>
                    <para>You must override the default value of
                            <literal>netapp_storage_protocol</literal>
                        with <literal>iscsi</literal> in order to
                        utilize the iSCSI protocol.</para>
                </note>
                <xi:include
                    href="../../../common/tables/cinder-netapp_7mode_iscsi.xml"/>
                <tip>
                    <para>For more information on these options and
                        other deployment and operational scenarios,
                        visit the <link
                            xlink:href="https://communities.netapp.com/groups/openstack"
                            >OpenStack NetApp community</link>.</para>
                </tip>
            </simplesect>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="ontap-7mode-nfs">
            <title>NetApp NFS configuration for Data ONTAP operating
                in 7-Mode</title>
            <para>The NetApp NFS configuration for Data ONTAP
                operating in 7-Mode is an interface from OpenStack to
                Data ONTAP operating in 7-Mode storage system for
                provisioning and managing OpenStack volumes on NFS
                exports provided by the Data ONTAP operating in 7-Mode
                storage system which can then be accessed using NFS
                protocol.</para>
            <para>The NFS configuration for Data ONTAP operating in
                7-Mode is a direct interface from Cinder to the Data
                ONTAP operating in 7-Mode instance and as such does
                not require any additional management software to
                achieve the desired functionality. It uses NetApp
                ONTAPI to interact with the Data ONTAP operating in
                7-Mode storage system.</para>
            <simplesect>
                <title>Configuration options for the Data ONTAP
                    operating in 7-Mode family with NFS
                    protocol</title>
                <para>Configure the volume driver, storage family and
                    storage protocol to the NetApp unified driver,
                    Data ONTAP operating in 7-Mode, and NFS
                    respectively by setting the
                        <literal>volume_driver</literal>,
                        <literal>netapp_storage_family</literal> and
                        <literal>netapp_storage_protocol</literal>
                    options in <filename>cinder.conf</filename> as
                    follows:</para>
                <programlisting language="ini">
  volume_driver=cinder.volume.drivers.netapp.common.NetAppDriver
  netapp_storage_family=ontap_7mode
  netapp_storage_protocol=nfs
  netapp_server_hostname=myhostname
  netapp_server_port=80
  netapp_login=username
  netapp_password=password
               </programlisting>
                <xi:include
                    href="../../../common/tables/cinder-netapp_7mode_nfs.xml"/>
                <tip>
                    <para>For more information on these options and
                        other deployment and operational scenarios,
                        visit the <link
                            xlink:href="https://communities.netapp.com/groups/openstack"
                            >OpenStack NetApp community</link>.</para>
                </tip>
            </simplesect>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ontap-unified-upgrade-deprecated">
        <title>Upgrading prior NetApp drivers to the NetApp unified
            driver</title>
        <para>NetApp introduced a new unified block storage driver in
            Havana for configuring different storage families and
            storage protocols. This requires defining upgrade path for
            NetApp drivers which existed in releases prior to Havana.
            This section covers the upgrade configuration for NetApp
            drivers to the new unified configuration and a list of
            deprecated NetApp drivers.</para>
        <section xml:id="ontap-unified-upgrade">
            <title>Upgraded NetApp drivers</title>
            <para>This section describes how to update Cinder
                configuration from a pre-Havana release to the new
                unified driver format.</para>
            <simplesect>
                <title>Driver upgrade configuration</title>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>NetApp iSCSI direct driver for Clustered
                            Data ONTAP in Grizzly (or earlier)</para>
                        <programlisting language="ini">
volume_driver=cinder.volume.drivers.netapp.iscsi.NetAppDirectCmodeISCSIDriver
               </programlisting>
                        <para>NetApp Unified Driver
                            configuration</para>
                        <programlisting language="ini">
volume_driver=cinder.volume.drivers.netapp.common.NetAppDriver
netapp_storage_family=ontap_cluster
netapp_storage_protocol=iscsi
               </programlisting>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>NetApp NFS direct driver for Clustered
                            Data ONTAP in Grizzly (or earlier)</para>
                        <programlisting language="ini">
volume_driver=cinder.volume.drivers.netapp.nfs.NetAppDirectCmodeNfsDriver
               </programlisting>
                        <para>NetApp Unified Driver
                            configuration</para>
                        <programlisting language="ini">
volume_driver=cinder.volume.drivers.netapp.common.NetAppDriver
netapp_storage_family=ontap_cluster
netapp_storage_protocol=nfs
               </programlisting>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>NetApp iSCSI direct driver for Data
                            ONTAP operating in 7-Mode storage
                            controller in Grizzly (or earlier)</para>
                        <programlisting language="ini">
volume_driver=cinder.volume.drivers.netapp.iscsi.NetAppDirect7modeISCSIDriver
               </programlisting>
                        <para>NetApp Unified Driver
                            configuration</para>
                        <programlisting language="ini">
volume_driver=cinder.volume.drivers.netapp.common.NetAppDriver
netapp_storage_family=ontap_7mode
netapp_storage_protocol=iscsi
               </programlisting>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>NetApp NFS direct driver for Data ONTAP
                            operating in 7-Mode storage controller in
                            Grizzly (or earlier)</para>
                        <programlisting language="ini">
volume_driver=cinder.volume.drivers.netapp.nfs.NetAppDirect7modeNfsDriver
               </programlisting>
                        <para>NetApp Unified Driver
                            configuration</para>
                        <programlisting language="ini">
volume_driver=cinder.volume.drivers.netapp.common.NetAppDriver
netapp_storage_family=ontap_7mode
netapp_storage_protocol=nfs
               </programlisting>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>

            </simplesect>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="ontap-driver-deprecate">
            <title>Deprecated NetApp drivers</title>
            <para>This section lists the NetApp drivers in previous
                releases that are deprecated in Havana.</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>NetApp iSCSI driver for clustered Data
                        ONTAP.</para>
                    <programlisting language="ini">
volume_driver=cinder.volume.drivers.netapp.iscsi.NetAppCmodeISCSIDriver
   </programlisting>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>NetApp NFS driver for clustered Data
                        ONTAP.</para>
                    <programlisting language="ini">
volume_driver=cinder.volume.drivers.netapp.nfs.NetAppCmodeNfsDriver
   </programlisting>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>NetApp iSCSI driver for Data ONTAP operating
                        in 7-Mode storage controller.</para>
                    <programlisting language="ini">
volume_driver=cinder.volume.drivers.netapp.iscsi.NetAppISCSIDriver
   </programlisting>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>NetApp NFS driver for Data ONTAP operating
                        in 7-Mode storage controller.</para>
                    <programlisting language="ini">
volume_driver=cinder.volume.drivers.netapp.nfs.NetAppNFSDriver
   </programlisting>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <note>
                <para>See the <link
                        xlink:href="https://communities.netapp.com/groups/openstack"
                        >OpenStack NetApp community</link> for support
                    information on deprecated NetApp drivers in the
                    Havana release.</para>
            </note>
        </section>
    </section>
</section>
