<section xml:id="nexenta-driver" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <title>Nexenta drivers</title>
    <para>NexentaStor Appliance is NAS/SAN software platform designed
        for building reliable and fast network storage arrays. The
        Nexenta Storage Appliance uses ZFS as a disk management
        system. NexentaStor can serve as a storage node for the
        OpenStack and for the virtual servers through iSCSI and NFS
        protocols.</para>
    <para>With the NFS option, every Compute volume is represented by
        a directory designated to be its own file system in the ZFS
        file system. These file systems are exported using NFS.</para>
    <para>With either option some minimal setup is required to tell
        OpenStack which NexentaStor servers are being used, whether
        they are supporting iSCSI and/or NFS and how to access each of
        the servers.</para>
    <para>Typically the only operation required on the NexentaStor
        servers is to create the containing directory for the iSCSI or
        NFS exports. For NFS this containing directory must be
        explicitly exported via NFS. There is no software that must be
        installed on the NexentaStor servers; they are controlled
        using existing management plane interfaces.</para>
    <!-- iSCSI driver section -->
    <section xml:id="nexenta-iscsi-driver">
        <title>Nexenta iSCSI driver</title>
        <para>The Nexenta iSCSI driver allows you to use NexentaStor
            appliance to store Compute volumes. Every Compute volume
            is represented by a single zvol in a predefined Nexenta
            namespace. For every new volume the driver creates a iSCSI
            target and iSCSI target group that are used to access it
            from compute hosts.</para>
        <para>The Nexenta iSCSI volume driver should work with all
            versions of NexentaStor. The NexentaStor appliance must be
            installed and configured according to the relevant Nexenta
            documentation. A pool and an enclosing namespace must be
            created for all iSCSI volumes to be accessed through the
            volume driver. This should be done as specified in the
            release specific NexentaStor documentation.</para>
        <para>The NexentaStor Appliance iSCSI driver is selected using
            the normal procedures for one or multiple back-end volume
            drivers. You must configure these items
            for each NexentaStor appliance that the iSCSI volume
            driver controls:</para>
        <section xml:id="nexenta-iscsi-driver-options">
            <title>Enable the Nexenta iSCSI driver and related
                options</title>
            <para>This table contains the options supported
                by the Nexenta iSCSI driver.</para>
            <xi:include
                href="../../../common/tables/cinder-storage_nexenta_iscsi.xml"/>
            <para>To use Compute with the Nexenta iSCSI driver, first
                set the <code>volume_driver</code>:</para>
            <programlisting language="ini">volume_driver=cinder.volume.drivers.nexenta.iscsi.NexentaISCSIDriver
</programlisting>
            <para>Then, set the <code>nexenta_host</code> parameter and
                other parameters from the table, if needed.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <!-- / iSCSI driver section -->
    <!-- NFS driver section -->
    <section xml:id="nexenta-nfs-driver">
        <title>Nexenta NFS driver</title>
        <para>The Nexenta NFS driver allows you to use NexentaStor
            appliance to store Compute volumes via NFS. Every Compute
            volume is represented by a single NFS file within a shared
            directory.</para>
        <para>While the NFS protocols standardize file access for
            users, they do not standardize administrative actions such
            as taking snapshots or replicating file systems. The
            Openstack Volume Drivers bring a common interface to these
            operations. The Nexenta NFS driver implements these
            standard actions using the ZFS management plane that
            already is deployed on NexentaStor appliances.</para>
        <para>The Nexenta NFS volume driver should work with all
            versions of NexentaStor. The NexentaStor appliance must be
            installed and configured according to the relevant Nexenta
            documentation. A single parent file system must be created
            for all virtual disk directories supported for OpenStack.
            This directory must be created and exported on each
            NexentaStor appliance. This should be done as specified in
            the release specific NexentaStor documentation.</para>
        <section xml:id="nexenta-nfs-driver-options">
            <title>Enable the Nexenta NFS driver and related
                options</title>
            <para>To use Compute with the Nexenta NFS driver, first
                set the <code>volume_driver</code>:</para>
            <programlisting language="ini">
volume_driver = cinder.volume.drivers.nexenta.nfs.NexentaNfsDriver
</programlisting>
            <para>The following table contains the options supported
                by the Nexenta NFS driver.</para>
            <xi:include
                href="../../../common/tables/cinder-storage_nexenta_nfs.xml"/>
            <para>Add your list of Nexenta NFS servers to the file you
                specified with the <code>nexenta_shares_config</code>
                option. For example, if the value of this option was
                set to <filename>/etc/cinder/nfs_shares</filename>,
                then:</para>
            <screen>
<prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>cat /etc/cinder/nfs_shares</userinput>
<computeroutput>192.168.1.200:/storage http://admin:nexenta@192.168.1.200:2000
192.168.1.201:/storage http://admin:nexenta@192.168.1.201:2000
192.168.1.202:/storage http://admin:nexenta@192.168.1.202:2000</computeroutput></screen>
            <para>Comments are allowed in this file. They begin with a
                    <code>#</code>.</para>
            <para>Each line in this file represents a NFS share. The
                first part of the line is the NFS share URL, the
                second is the connection URL to the NexentaStor
                Appliance.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <!-- / NFS driver section -->
</section>
