<section xml:id="solidfire-volume-driver"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <title>SolidFire</title>
    <para>The SolidFire Cluster is a high performance all SSD iSCSI
        storage device that provides massive scale out capability and
        extreme fault tolerance. A key feature of the SolidFire
        cluster is the ability to set and modify during operation
        specific QoS levels on a volume for volume basis. The
        SolidFire cluster offers this along with de-duplication,
        compression, and an architecture that takes full advantage of
        SSDs.</para>
    <para>To configure the use of a SolidFire cluster with Block
        Storage, modify your <filename>cinder.conf</filename> file as
        follows:</para>
    <programlisting language="ini">volume_driver = cinder.volume.drivers.solidfire.SolidFireDriver
san_ip = 172.17.1.182         # the address of your MVIP
san_login = sfadmin           # your cluster admin login
san_password = sfpassword     # your cluster admin password
sf_account_prefix = ''        # prefix for tenant account creation on solidfire cluster (see warning below)</programlisting>
    <warning>
        <para>The SolidFire driver creates a unique account prefixed
            with
                <literal>$cinder-volume-service-hostname-$tenant-id</literal>
            on the SolidFire cluster for each tenant that accesses the
            cluster through the Volume API. Unfortunately, this
            account formation results in issues for High Availability
            (HA) installations and installations where the <systemitem
                class="service">cinder-volume</systemitem> service can
            move to a new node. HA installations can return an
                <errortext>Account Not Found</errortext> error because
            the call to the SolidFire cluster is not always going to
            be sent from the same node. In installations where the
                <systemitem class="service">cinder-volume</systemitem>
            service moves to a new node, the same issue can occur when
            you perform operations on existing volumes, such as clone,
            extend, delete, and so on.</para>
    </warning>
    <note>
        <para>Set the <option>sf_account_prefix</option> option to an empty string ('') in the
                <filename>cinder.conf</filename> file. This setting results in unique accounts being
            created on the SolidFire cluster, but the accounts are prefixed with the
                <systemitem>tenant-id</systemitem> or any unique identifier that you choose and are
            independent of the host where the <systemitem class="service">cinder-volume</systemitem>
            service resides.</para>
    </note>
    <xi:include href="../../../common/tables/cinder-solidfire.xml"/>
</section>
