<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xml:id="vmware-vmdk-driver"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <title>VMware VMDK driver</title>
    <para>Use the VMware VMDK driver to enable management of the
        OpenStack Block Storage volumes on vCenter-managed data
        stores. Volumes are backed by VMDK files on data stores using
        any VMware-compatible storage technology such as NFS, iSCSI,
        FiberChannel, and vSAN.</para>
    <simplesect>
        <title>Functional context</title>
        <para>The VMware VMDK driver connects to vCenter, through
            which it can dynamically access all the datastores visible
            from the ESX hosts in the managed cluster.</para>
        <para>When you create a volume, the VMDK driver creates a VMDK
            file on demand. The creation of this VMDK file is
            completed only when the volume is subsequently attached to
            an instance, because the set of datastores visible to the
            instance determines where to place the volume.</para>
        <para>The running vSphere VM is then automatically
            reconfigured to attach the VMDK file as an extra disk.
            Once attached, you can log in to the running vSphere VM to
            rescan and discover this extra disk.</para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>Configuration</title>
        <para>The recommended volume driver for OpenStack Block Storage is
            the VMware vCenter VMDK driver. When you configure the
            driver, you must match it with the appropriate OpenStack
            Compute driver from VMware and both drivers must point to
            the same server.</para>
        <para>For example, in the <filename>nova.conf</filename> file,
            use this option to define the Compute driver:</para>
        <programlisting>compute_driver=vmwareapi.VMwareVCDriver</programlisting>
        <para>In the <filename>cinder.conf</filename> file, use this
            option to define the volume driver:</para>
        <programlisting>volume_driver=cinder.volume.drivers.vmware.vmdk.VMwareVcVmdkDriver</programlisting>
        <para>The following table lists various options that the
            drivers support for the OpenStack Block Storage
            configuration (<filename>cinder.conf</filename>):</para>
        <xi:include href="../../../common/tables/cinder-vmware.xml"/>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>VMDK disk type</title>
        <para>The VMware VMDK drivers support the creation of VMDK
            disk files of type <literal>thin</literal>, <literal>thick</literal>,
            or <literal>eagerZeroedThick</literal>. Use the
            <code>vmware:vmdk_type</code> extra spec key with the
            appropriate value to specify the VMDK disk file type.
            The following table captures the mapping between the extra
            spec entry and the VMDK disk file type:</para>
        <table rules="all">
            <caption>Extra spec entry to VMDK disk file type
                mapping</caption>
            <thead>
                <tr>
                    <td>Disk file type</td>
                    <td>Extra spec key</td>
                    <td>Extra spec value</td>
                </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
                <tr>
                    <td>thin</td>
                    <td>vmware:vmdk_type</td>
                    <td>thin</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>thick</td>
                    <td>vmware:vmdk_type</td>
                    <td>thick</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>eagerZeroedThick</td>
                    <td>vmware:vmdk_type</td>
                    <td>eagerZeroedThick</td>
                </tr>
            </tbody>
        </table>
        <para>If no <code>vmdk_type</code> extra spec entry is
            specified, the default disk file type is
                <literal>thin</literal>.</para>
        <para>The example below shows how to create a
                <code>thick</code> VMDK volume using the appropriate
                <code>vmdk_type</code>:</para>
        <screen>
        <prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>cinder type-create thick_volume</userinput>
        <prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>cinder type-key thick_volume set vmware:vmdk_type=thick</userinput>
        <prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>cinder create --volume-type thick_volume --display-name volume1 1</userinput>
</screen>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>Clone type</title>
        <para>With the VMware VMDK drivers, you can create a volume
            from another source volume or from a snapshot point. The
            VMware vCenter VMDK driver supports clone types
                <literal>full</literal> and
                <literal>linked/fast</literal>. The clone type is
            specified using the <code>vmware:clone_type</code> extra
            spec key with the appropriate value. The following table
            captures the mapping for clone types:</para>
        <table rules="all">
            <caption>Extra spec entry to clone type mapping</caption>
            <thead>
                <tr>
                    <td>Clone type</td>
                    <td>Extra spec key</td>
                    <td>Extra spec value</td>
                </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
                <tr>
                    <td>full</td>
                    <td>vmware:clone_type</td>
                    <td>full</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>linked/fast</td>
                    <td>vmware:clone_type</td>
                    <td>linked</td>
                </tr>
            </tbody>
        </table>
        <para>If not specified, the default clone type is
                <literal>full</literal>.</para>
        <para>The following is an example of linked cloning from
            another source volume:</para>
        <screen>
        <prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>cinder type-create fast_clone</userinput>
        <prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>cinder type-key fast_clone set vmware:clone_type=linked</userinput>
        <prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>cinder create --volume-type fast_clone --source-volid 25743b9d-3605-462b-b9eb-71459fe2bb35 --display-name volume1 1</userinput>
</screen>
        <para>Note: The VMware ESX VMDK driver ignores the extra spec
            entry and always creates a <literal>full</literal>
            clone.</para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>Supported operations</title>
        <para>The following operations are supported by the VMware
            vCenter and ESX VMDK drivers:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Create volume</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Create volume from another source volume.
                    (Supported only if source volume is not attached
                    to an instance.)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Create volume from snapshot</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Create volume from glance image</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Attach volume (When a volume is attached to an
                    instance, a reconfigure operation is performed on
                    the instance to add the volume's VMDK to it. The
                    user must manually rescan and mount the device
                    from within the guest operating system.)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Detach volume</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Create snapshot (Allowed only if volume is not
                    attached to an instance.)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Delete snapshot (Allowed only if volume is not
                    attached to an instance.)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Upload as image to glance (Allowed only if
                    volume is not attached to an instance.)</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <note>
            <para>Although the VMware ESX VMDK driver supports these
                operations, it has not been extensively tested.</para>
        </note>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>Data store selection</title>
        <para>When creating a volume, the driver chooses a data store
            which is connected to maximum number of hosts. This is
            meant to reduce the number of volume migrations while
            attaching the volume to instances. The volume needs to be
            migrated if the instance's ESX host cannot access the
            data store containing the volume. In case of ties, the
            data store with lowest space utilization is selected, where
            space utilization is defined by the metric
            <literal>(1 - freespace/totalspace)</literal>.</para>
    </simplesect>
</section>
