<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="arch-design-architecture-hardware">
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
  <title>Architecture</title>
    <para>The hardware selection covers three areas:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Compute</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Network</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Storage</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
  <para>Compute-focused OpenStack clouds have high demands on processor and
    memory resources, and requires hardware that can handle these demands.
    Consider the following factors when selecting compute (server) hardware:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Server density</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Resource capacity</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Expandability</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Cost</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  <para>Weigh these considerations against each other to determine the
    best design for the desired purpose. For example, increasing server density
    means sacrificing resource capacity or expandability.</para>
  <para>A compute-focused cloud should have an emphasis on server hardware
    that can offer more CPU sockets, more CPU cores, and more RAM. Network
    connectivity and storage capacity are less critical.</para>
  <para>When designing a compute-focused OpenStack architecture, you must
    consider whether you intend to scale up or scale out.
    Selecting a smaller number of larger hosts, or a
    larger number of smaller hosts, depends on a combination of factors:
    cost, power, cooling, physical rack and floor space, support-warranty,
    and manageability.</para>
  <para>Considerations for selecting hardware:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Most blade servers can support dual-socket multi-core CPUs. To
          avoid this CPU limit, select <literal>full width</literal>
          or <literal>full height</literal> blades.
          Be aware, however, that this also decreases server density. For example,
          high density blade servers such as HP BladeSystem or Dell PowerEdge
          M1000e support up to 16 servers in only ten rack units. Using
          half-height blades is twice as dense as using full-height blades,
          which results in only eight servers per ten rack units.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>1U rack-mounted servers that occupy only a single rack
          unit may offer greater server density than a blade server
          solution. It is possible to place forty 1U servers in a rack, providing
          space for the top of rack (ToR) switches, compared to 32 full width
          blade servers.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>2U rack-mounted servers provide quad-socket, multi-core CPU
          support, but with a corresponding decrease in server density (half
          the density that 1U rack-mounted servers offer).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Larger rack-mounted servers, such as 4U servers, often provide
          even greater CPU capacity, commonly supporting four or even eight CPU
          sockets. These servers have greater expandability, but such servers
          have much lower server density and are often more expensive.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><literal>Sled servers</literal> are rack-mounted servers that
          support multiple
          independent servers in a single 2U or 3U enclosure. These deliver higher
          density as compared to typical 1U or 2U rack-mounted servers. For
          example, many sled servers offer four independent dual-socket
          nodes in 2U for a total of eight CPU sockets in 2U.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  <para>Consider these when choosing server hardware for a compute-
    focused OpenStack design architecture:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Instance density</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Host density</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Power and cooling density</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section xml:id="selecting-networking-hardware-arch">
      <title>Selecting networking hardware</title>
        <para>Some of the key considerations for networking hardware selection
          include:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Port count</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Port density</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Port speed</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Redundancy</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Power requirements</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        <para>We recommend designing the network architecture using
          a scalable network model that makes it easy to add capacity and
          bandwidth. A good example of such a model is the leaf-spline model. In
          this type of network design, it is possible to easily add additional
          bandwidth as well as scale out to additional racks of gear. It is
          important to select network hardware that supports the required
          port count, port speed, and port density while also allowing for future
          growth as workload demands increase. It is also important to evaluate
          where in the network architecture it is valuable to provide redundancy.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="os-and-hypervisor-arch">
      <title>Operating system and hypervisor</title>
        <para>The selection of operating system (OS) and hypervisor has a
          significant impact on the end point design.</para>
        <para>OS and hypervisor selection impact the following areas:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Cost</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Supportability</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Management tools</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Scale and performance</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Security</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Supported features</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Interoperability</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="openstack-components-arch">
      <title>OpenStack components</title>
        <para>The selection of OpenStack components is important.
          There are certain components that are required, for example the compute
          and image services, but others, such as the Orchestration service, may not
          be present.</para>
        <para>For a compute-focused OpenStack design architecture, the
          following components may be present:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Identity (keystone)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Dashboard (horizon)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Compute (nova)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Object Storage (swift)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Image (glance)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Networking (neutron)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Orchestration (heat)</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        <note>
          <para>A compute-focused design is less likely to include OpenStack Block
            Storage. However, there may be some situations where the need for
            performance requires a block storage component to improve data I-O.</para>
        </note>
        <para>The exclusion of certain OpenStack components might also limit the
          functionality of other components. If a design includes
          the Orchestration service but excludes the Telemetry service, then
          the design cannot take advantage of Orchestration's auto
          scaling functionality as this relies on information from Telemetry.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="networking-software-arch">
        <title>Networking software</title>
          <para>OpenStack Networking provides a wide variety of networking services
            for instances. There are many additional networking software packages
            that might be useful to manage the OpenStack components themselves.
            The <citetitle>OpenStack High Availability Guide</citetitle>
            (<link xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/ha-guide/">http://docs.openstack.org/ha-guide/</link>)
            describes some of these software packages in more detail.
          </para>
          <para>For a compute-focused OpenStack cloud, the OpenStack infrastructure
            components must be highly available. If the design does not
            include hardware load balancing, you must add networking software packages,
            for example, HAProxy.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="management-software-arch">
        <title>Management software</title>
          <para>The selected supplemental software solution impacts and affects
            the overall OpenStack cloud design. This includes software for
            providing clustering, logging, monitoring and alerting.</para>
          <para>The availability of design requirements is the main determiner
            for the inclusion of clustering software, such as Corosync or Pacemaker.</para>
          <para>Operational considerations determine the requirements for logging,
            monitoring, and alerting. Each of these sub-categories include
            various options.</para>
          <para>Some other potential design impacts include:</para>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>OS-hypervisor combination</term>
              <listitem>
               <para>Ensure that the selected logging,
                 monitoring, or alerting tools support the proposed OS-hypervisor
                 combination.</para>
              </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Network hardware</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>The logging, monitoring, and alerting software
                  must support the network hardware selection.</para>
              </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="database-software-arch">
        <title>Database software</title>
          <para>A large majority of OpenStack components require access to
            back-end database services to store state and configuration
            information. Select an appropriate back-end database that
            satisfies the availability and fault tolerance requirements of the
            OpenStack services. OpenStack services support connecting
            to any database that the SQLAlchemy Python drivers support,
            however most common database deployments make use of MySQL or some
            variation of it. We recommend that you make the database that provides
            back-end services within a general-purpose cloud highly
            available. Some of the more common software solutions include Galera,
            MariaDB, and MySQL with multi-master replication.</para>
    </section>

</section>
