<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="user-requirements-compute-focus">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>User requirements</title>
    <para>Compute intensive workloads are defined by their high
        utilization of CPU, RAM, or both. User requirements will
        determine if a cloud must be built to accommodate anticipated
        performance demands.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Cost: Cost is not generally a primary concern for a
                compute-focused cloud, however some organizations
                might be concerned with cost avoidance. Repurposing
                existing resources to tackle compute-intensive tasks
                instead of needing to acquire additional resources may
                offer cost reduction opportunities.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Time to Market: Compute-focused clouds can be used
                to deliver products more quickly, for example,
                speeding up a company's software development life cycle
                (SDLC) for building products and applications.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Revenue Opportunity: Companies that are interested
                in building services or products that rely on the
                power of the compute resources will benefit from a
                compute-focused cloud. Examples include the analysis
                of large data sets (via Hadoop or Cassandra) or
                completing computational intensive tasks such as
                rendering, scientific computation, or
                simulations.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <section xml:id="legal-requirements-compute-focus">
      <title>Legal requirements</title>
    <para>Many jurisdictions have legislative and regulatory
        requirements governing the storage and management of data in
        cloud environments. Common areas of regulation include:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Data retention policies ensuring storage of
                persistent data and records management to meet data
                archival requirements.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Data ownership policies governing the possession and
                responsibility for data.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Data sovereignty policies governing the storage of
                data in foreign countries or otherwise separate
                jurisdictions.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Data compliance - certain types of information needs
                to reside in certain locations due to regular issues -
                and more important cannot reside in other locations
                for the same reason.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Examples of such legal frameworks include the data
        protection framework of the European Union
        (http://ec.europa.eu/justice/data-protection/ ) and the
        requirements of the Financial Industry Regulatory Authority
        (http://www.finra.org/Industry/Regulation/FINRARules/ ) in the
        United States. Consult a local regulatory body for more
        information.</para></section>
    <section xml:id="technical-considerations-compute-focus-user">
      <title>Technical considerations</title>
    <para>The following are some technical requirements that need to
        be incorporated into the architecture design.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Performance: If a primary technical concern is for
                the environment to deliver high performance
                capability, then a compute-focused design is an
                obvious choice because it is specifically designed to
                host compute-intensive workloads.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Workload persistence: Workloads can be either
                short-lived or long running. Short-lived workloads
                might include continuous integration and continuous
                deployment (CI-CD) jobs, where large numbers of
                compute instances are created simultaneously to
                perform a set of compute-intensive tasks. The results
                or artifacts are then copied from the instance into
                long-term storage before the instance is destroyed.
                Long-running workloads, like a Hadoop or
                high-performance computing (HPC) cluster, typically
                ingest large data sets, perform the computational work
                on those data sets, then push the results into long
                term storage. Unlike short-lived workloads, when the
                computational work is completed, they will remain idle
                until the next job is pushed to them. Long-running
                workloads are often larger and more complex, so the
                effort of building them is mitigated by keeping them
                active between jobs. Another example of long running
                workloads is legacy applications that typically are
                persistent over time.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Storage: Workloads targeted for a compute-focused
                OpenStack cloud generally do not require any
                persistent block storage (although some usages of
                Hadoop with HDFS may dictate the use of persistent
                block storage). A shared filesystem or object store
                will maintain the initial data set(s) and serve as the
                destination for saving the computational results. By
                avoiding the input-output (IO) overhead, workload
                performance is significantly enhanced. Depending on
                the size of the data set(s), it might be necessary to
                scale the object store or shared file system to match
                the storage demand.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>User Interface: Like any other cloud architecture, a
                compute-focused OpenStack cloud requires an on-demand
                and self-service user interface. End users must be
                able to provision computing power, storage, networks
                and software simply and flexibly. This includes
                scaling the infrastructure up to a substantial level
                without disrupting host operations.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Security: Security is going to be highly dependent
                on the business requirements. For example, a
                computationally intense drug discovery application
                will obviously have much higher security requirements
                than a cloud that is designed for processing market
                data for a retailer. As a general start, the security
                recommendations and guidelines provided in the
                OpenStack Security Guide are applicable.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></section>
    <section xml:id="operational-considerations-compute-focus-user">
      <title>Operational considerations</title>
    <para>The compute intensive cloud from the operational perspective
        is similar to the requirements for the general-purpose cloud.
        More details on operational requirements can be found in the
        general-purpose design section.</para></section>
</section>
