<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
<!ENTITY % openstack SYSTEM "../../common/entities/openstack.ent">
%openstack;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="user-requirements-compute-focus">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>User requirements</title>
    <para>High utilization of CPU, RAM, or both defines compute
        intensive workloads. User requirements determine the performance
        demands for the cloud.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Cost</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>Cost is not generally a primary concern for a
                compute-focused cloud, however some organizations
                might be concerned with cost avoidance. Repurposing
                existing resources to tackle compute-intensive tasks
                instead of acquiring additional resources may
                offer cost reduction opportunities.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Time to market</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>Compute-focused clouds can deliver products more quickly,
                for example by speeding up a company's software development
                life cycle (SDLC) for building products and applications.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Revenue opportunity</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>Companies that want to build services or products that
                rely on the power of compute resources benefit from a
                compute-focused cloud. Examples include the analysis
                of large data sets (via Hadoop or Cassandra) or
                completing computational intensive tasks such as
                rendering, scientific computation, or
                simulations.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <section xml:id="legal-requirements-compute-focus">
      <title>Legal requirements</title>
    <para>Many jurisdictions have legislative and regulatory
        requirements governing the storage and management of data in
        cloud environments. Common areas of regulation include:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Data retention policies ensuring storage of
                persistent data and records management to meet data
                archival requirements.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Data ownership policies governing the possession and
                responsibility for data.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Data sovereignty policies governing the storage of
                data in foreign countries or otherwise separate
                jurisdictions.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Data compliance: certain types of information need
                to reside in certain locations due to regular issues and,
                more importantly, cannot reside in other locations
                for the same reason.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      Examples of such legal frameworks include the <link
      xlink:href="http://ec.europa.eu/justice/data-protection/">data
      protection framework</link> of the European Union and the
      requirements of the <link
      xlink:href="http://www.finra.org/Industry/Regulation/FINRARules/">Financial
      Industry Regulatory Authority</link> in the United
      States. Consult a local regulatory body for more
      information.</para></section>
    <section xml:id="technical-considerations-compute-focus-user">
      <title>Technical considerations</title>
    <para>The following are some technical requirements you must consider
      in the architecture design:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Performance</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>If a primary technical concern is to deliver high performance
                capability, then a compute-focused design is an
                obvious choice because it is specifically designed to
                host compute-intensive workloads.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Workload persistence</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>Workloads can be either
                short-lived or long-running. Short-lived workloads
                can include continuous integration and continuous
                deployment (CI-CD) jobs, which create large numbers of
                compute instances simultaneously to
                perform a set of compute-intensive tasks. The environment then
                copies the results or artifacts from each instance into
                long-term storage before destroying the instance.
                Long-running workloads, like a Hadoop or
                high-performance computing (HPC) cluster, typically
                ingest large data sets, perform the computational work
                on those data sets, then push the results into long-term
                storage. When the computational work finishes, the instances
                remain idle until they receive another job. Environments
                for long-running workloads are often larger and more complex,
                but you can offset the cost of building them by keeping them
                active between jobs. Another example of long-running
                workloads is legacy applications that are
                persistent over time.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Storage</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>Workloads targeted for a compute-focused
                OpenStack cloud generally do not require any
                persistent block storage, although some uses of
                Hadoop with HDFS may require persistent
                block storage. A shared filesystem or object store
                maintains the initial data sets and serves as the
                destination for saving the computational results. By
                avoiding the input-output (IO) overhead, you can significantly
                enhance workload performance. Depending on
                the size of the data sets, it may be necessary to
                scale the object store or shared file system to match
                the storage demand.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>User interface</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>Like any other cloud architecture, a
                compute-focused OpenStack cloud requires an on-demand
                and self-service user interface. End users must be
                able to provision computing power, storage, networks,
                and software simply and flexibly. This includes
                scaling the infrastructure up to a substantial level
                without disrupting host operations.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Security</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>Security is highly dependent
                on business requirements. For example, a
                computationally intense drug discovery application
                has much higher security requirements
                than a cloud for processing market
                data for a retailer. As a general rule, the security
                recommendations and guidelines provided in the
                OpenStack Security Guide are applicable.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
    <section xml:id="operational-considerations-compute-focus-user">
      <title>Operational considerations</title>
    <para>From an operational perspective, a compute intensive cloud
        is similar to a general-purpose cloud. See the general-purpose
        design section for more details on operational requirements.</para>
    </section>
</section>
