<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0"
    xml:id="arch-guide-intro-compute-focus">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>A compute-focused cloud is a specialized subset of the
        general purpose OpenStack cloud architecture. Unlike the
        general purpose OpenStack architecture, which is built to host
        a wide variety of workloads and applications and does not
        heavily tax any particular computing aspect, a compute-focused
        cloud is built and designed specifically to support compute
        intensive workloads. As such, the design must be specifically
        tailored to support hosting compute intensive workloads.
        Compute intensive workloads may be CPU intensive, RAM
        intensive, or both. However, they are not typically storage
        intensive or network intensive. Compute-focused workloads may
        include the following use cases:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>High performance computing (HPC)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Big data analytics using Hadoop or other distributed
                data stores</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Continuous integration/continuous deployment
                (CI/CD)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Platform-as-a-Service (PaaS)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Signal processing for Network Function
                Virtualization (NFV)</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Based on the use case requirements, such clouds might need
        to provide additional services such as a virtual machine disk
        library, file or object storage, firewalls, load balancers, IP
        addresses, and network connectivity in the form of overlays or
        virtual Local Area Networks (VLANs). A compute-focused
        OpenStack cloud will not typically use raw block storage
        services since the applications hosted on a compute-focused
        OpenStack cloud generally do not need persistent block
        storage.</para>
</section>
