<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="ch_introduction-to-openstack-compute">
    <title>Introduction to OpenStack Compute</title>
    <para>OpenStack Compute gives you a tool to orchestrate a cloud, including running instances,
        managing networks, and controlling access to the cloud through users and projects. The
        underlying open source project's name is Nova, and it provides the software that can control
        an Infrastructure as a Service (IaaS) cloud computing platform. It is similar in scope to
        Amazon EC2 and Rackspace Cloud Servers. OpenStack Compute does not include any
        virtualization software; rather it defines drivers that interact with underlying
        virtualization mechanisms that run on your host operating system, and exposes functionality
        over a web-based API.</para>
    
    <section xml:id="hypervisors">
        <title>Hypervisors</title>
    
    <para>OpenStack Compute requires a hypervisor and Compute controls the hypervisors through an
            API server. The process for selecting a hypervisor usually means prioritizing and making
            decisions based on budget and resource constraints as well as the inevitable list of
            supported features and required technical specifications. The majority of development is
            done with the KVM and Xen-based hypervisors. Refer to <link
                xlink:href="http://wiki.openstack.org/HypervisorSupportMatrix"
                >http://wiki.openstack.org/HypervisorSupportMatrix</link> for a detailed list of
        features and support across the hypervisors.  </para>
        <para>With OpenStack Compute, you can orchestrate clouds using multiple hypervisors in
            different zones. The types of virtualization standards that may be used with Compute
            include:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><link xlink:href="http://www.linux-kvm.org/page/Main_Page">KVM</link> -
                    Kernel-based Virtual Machine</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><link xlink:href="http://lxc.sourceforge.net/">LXC</link> - Linux Containers
                    (through libvirt)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><link xlink:href="http://wiki.qemu.org/Manual">QEMU</link> - Quick
                    EMUlator</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><link xlink:href="http://user-mode-linux.sourceforge.net/">UML</link> - User
                    Mode Linux</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><link
                        xlink:href="http://www.vmware.com/products/vsphere-hypervisor/support.html"
                        >VMWare ESX/ESXi</link> 4.1 update 1</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><link xlink:href="http://www.xen.org/support/documentation.html">Xen</link> -
                    XenServer 5.5, Xen Cloud Platform (XCP)</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="users-and-projects">
        <title>Users and Tenants (Projects)</title>
        <para>The OpenStack Compute system is designed to be used by many different cloud computing
            consumers or customers, basically tenants on a shared system, using role-based access
            assignments. Roles control the actions that a user is allowed to perform. In the default
            configuration, most actions do not require a particular role, but this is configurable
            by the system administrator editing the appropriate <filename>policy.json</filename>
            file that maintains the rules. For example, a rule can be defined so that a user cannot
            allocate a public IP without the admin role. A user's access to particular images is
            limited by tenant, but the username and password are assigned per user. Key pairs
            granting access to an instance are enabled per user, but quotas to control resource
            consumption across available hardware resources are per tenant. <note>
                <para>Earlier versions of OpenStack used the term "project" instead of "tenant".
                    Because of this legacy terminology, some command-line tools use
                        <literal>--project_id</literal> when a tenant ID is expected.</para>
            </note></para>
<para>While the original EC2 API supports users, OpenStack Compute adds the concept of tenants.
            Tenants are isolated resource containers forming the principal organizational structure
            within the Compute service. They consist of a separate VLAN, volumes, instances, images,
            keys, and users. A user can specify which tenant he or she wishes to be known as by
            appending <literal>:project_id</literal> to his or her access key. If no tenant is
            specified in the API request, Compute attempts to use a tenant with the same ID as the
            user. </para>
        <para>For tenants, quota controls are available to limit the:<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Number of volumes which may be created</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Total size of all volumes within a project as measured in GB</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Number of instances which may be launched</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Number of processor cores which may be allocated</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Publicly accessible IP addresses</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        
    </section><section xml:id="images-and-instances">
            <title>Images and Instances</title>
        
        <para>An image is a file containing information about a virtual disk that completely
            replicates all information about a working computer at a point in time including
            operating system information and file system information. Compute can use certificate
            management for decrypting bundled images. With the deprecated auth system, you can use
            the euca2ools command-line tools distributed by the Eucalyptus Team for adding,
            bundling, and deleting images. When using the Image Service (Keystone), you can use the
            nova-client command-line tool for working with images and the glance-client command-line
            tool for uploading images to the Image Service. </para>
        <para>There are two methods for managing images. Images can be served through the OpenStack
            Image Service, a project that is named Glance, or use the nova-objectstore service.
            Compute defaults to being configured to use the Image Service. With an OpenStack Image
            Service server in place, the Image Service fetches the image on to the host machine and
            then OpenStack Compute boots the image from the host machine. To place images into the
            service, you would use a REST interface to stream them, and the service, in turn,
            streams that into a back end which could be S3, OpenStack Object Storage (which can use
            an S3), or the local file system on the server where OpenStack Image Service is
            installed.</para>
        <para>An instance is a running virtual machine within the cloud. An instance has a life
            cycle that is controlled by OpenStack Compute. Compute creates the instances and it is
            responsible for building a disk image, launching it, reporting the state, attaching
            persistent storage, and terminating it. </para>
    </section><section xml:id="system-architecture">
        <title>System Architecture</title><para>OpenStack Compute consists of several main components. A "cloud controller" contains many of
            these components, and it represents the global state and interacts with all other
            components. An API Server acts as the web services front end for the cloud controller.
            The compute controller provides compute server resources and typically contains the
            compute service, The Object Store component optionally provides storage services. An
            auth manager provides authentication and authorization services when used with the
            Compute system, or you can use the Identity Service (keystone) as a separate
            authentication service. A volume controller provides fast and permanent block-level
            storage for the compute servers. A network controller provides virtual networks to
            enable compute servers to interact with each other and with the public network. A
            scheduler selects the most suitable compute controller to host an instance. </para><para>OpenStack Compute is built on a shared-nothing, messaging-based architecture. You can run all
            of the major components on multiple servers including a compute controller, volume
            controller, network controller, and object store (or image service). A cloud controller
            communicates with the internal object store via HTTP (Hyper Text Transfer Protocol), but
            it communicates with a scheduler, network controller, and volume controller via AMQP
            (Advanced Message Queue Protocol). To avoid blocking each component while waiting for a
            response, OpenStack Compute uses asynchronous calls, with a call-back that gets
            triggered when a response is received.</para>
        
        <para>To achieve the shared-nothing property with multiple copies of the same component, OpenStack Compute keeps all the cloud system state in a database.</para></section>
    <section xml:id="storage-and-openstack-compute">
            <title>Block Storage and OpenStack Compute</title><para>A ‘volume’ is a detachable block storage device. You can think of it as a USB hard drive. It
            can only be attached to one instance at a time, so it does not work like a SAN. If you
            wish to expose the same volume to multiple instances, you will have to use an NFS or
            SAMBA share from an existing instance. </para><para>Every instance larger than m1.tiny starts with some local storage (up to 160GB for m1.xlarge).
            This storage is currently the second partition on the root drive. </para></section></chapter>
