<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!-- Some useful entities borrowed from HTML -->
<!ENTITY ndash  "&#x2013;">
<!ENTITY mdash  "&#x2014;">
<!ENTITY hellip "&#x2026;">
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
<!ENTITY CHECK  '<inlinemediaobject xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="img/Check_mark_23x20_02.svg"
format="SVG" scale="60"/>
</imageobject>
</inlinemediaobject>'>

<!ENTITY ARROW  '<inlinemediaobject xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="img/Arrow_east.svg"
format="SVG" scale="60"/>
</imageobject>
</inlinemediaobject>'>
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="ch_system-administration-for-openstack-compute">

    <title>System Administration</title>
    <para>By understanding how the different installed nodes interact with each other you can
        administer the OpenStack Compute installation. OpenStack Compute offers many ways to install
        using multiple servers but the general idea is that you can have multiple compute nodes that
        control the virtual servers and a cloud controller node that contains the remaining Nova services. </para>
    <para>The OpenStack Compute cloud works via the interaction of a series of daemon processes
        named nova-* that reside persistently on the host machine or machines. These binaries can
        all run on the same machine or be spread out on multiple boxes in a large deployment. The
        responsibilities of Services, Managers, and Drivers, can be a bit confusing at first. Here
        is an outline the division of responsibilities to make understanding the system a little bit
        easier. </para>
    <para>Currently, Services are nova-api, nova-objectstore (which can be replaced with Glance, the
        OpenStack Image Service), nova-compute, nova-volume, and nova-network. Managers and Drivers
        are specified by configuration options and loaded using utils.load_object(). Managers are responsible for a
        certain aspect of the system. It is a logical grouping of code relating to a portion of the
        system. In general other components should be using the manager to make changes to the
        components that it is responsible for. </para>
    <para>For example, other components that need to deal with volumes in some way, should do so by
        calling methods on the VolumeManager instead of directly changing fields in the database.
        This allows us to keep all of the code relating to volumes in the same place. </para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>nova-api - The nova-api service receives xml requests and sends them to the rest
                of the system. It is a wsgi app that routes and authenticate requests. It supports
                the EC2 and OpenStack APIs. There is a nova-api.conf file created when you install
                Compute.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>nova-objectstore - The nova-objectstore service is an ultra simple file-based
                storage system for images that replicates most of the S3 API. It can be replaced
                with OpenStack Image Service and a simple image manager or use OpenStack Object
                Storage as the virtual machine image storage facility. It must reside on the same
                node as nova-compute.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>nova-compute - The nova-compute service is responsible for managing virtual
                machines. It loads a Service object which exposes the public methods on
                ComputeManager via Remote Procedure Call (RPC).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>nova-volume - The nova-volume service is responsible for managing attachable block
                storage devices. It loads a Service object which exposes the public methods on
                VolumeManager via RPC.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>nova-network - The nova-network service is responsible for managing floating and
                fixed IPs, DHCP, bridging and VLANs. It loads a Service object which exposes the
                public methods on one of the subclasses of NetworkManager. Different networking
                strategies are available to the service by changing the network_manager configuration option to
                FlatManager, FlatDHCPManager, or VlanManager (default is VLAN if no other is
                specified).</para>

        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <section xml:id="understanding-the-compute-service-architecture">

        <title>Understanding the Compute Service Architecture</title>
        <para>These basic categories describe the service architecture and what's going on within the cloud controller.</para>
        <simplesect><title>API Server</title>

            <para>At the heart of the cloud framework is an API Server. This API Server makes command and control of the hypervisor, storage, and networking programmatically available to users in realization of the definition of cloud computing.
            </para>
            <para>The API endpoints are basic http web services which handle authentication, authorization, and basic command and control functions using various API interfaces under the Amazon, Rackspace, and related models. This enables API compatibility with multiple existing tool sets created for interaction with offerings from other vendors. This broad compatibility prevents vendor lock-in.
            </para> </simplesect>
        <simplesect><title>Message Queue</title>
            <para>
            A messaging queue brokers the interaction between compute nodes (processing), volumes (block storage), the networking controllers (software which controls network infrastructure), API endpoints, the scheduler (determines which physical hardware to allocate to a virtual resource), and similar components. Communication to and from the cloud controller is by HTTP requests through multiple API endpoints.</para>

<para>            A typical message passing event begins with the API server receiving a request from a user. The API server authenticates the user and ensures that the user is permitted to issue the subject command. Availability of objects implicated in the request is evaluated and, if available, the request is routed to the queuing engine for the relevant workers. Workers continually listen to the queue based on their role, and occasionally their type hostname. When such listening produces a work request, the worker takes assignment of the task and begins its execution. Upon completion, a response is dispatched to the queue which is received by the API server and relayed to the originating user. Database entries are queried, added, or removed as necessary throughout the process.
</para>
</simplesect>
        <simplesect><title>Compute Worker</title>

            <para>Compute workers manage computing instances on host machines. Through the API, commands are dispatched to compute workers to:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>Run instances</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Terminate instances</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Reboot instances</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Attach volumes</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Detach volumes</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Get console output</para></listitem></itemizedlist>
            </simplesect>
            <simplesect><title>Network Controller</title>

            <para>The Network Controller manages the networking resources on host machines. The API server dispatches commands through the message queue, which are subsequently processed by Network Controllers. Specific operations include:</para>

            <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Allocate fixed IP addresses</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Configuring VLANs for projects</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Configuring networks for compute nodes</para></listitem></itemizedlist>
            </simplesect>
<simplesect><title>Volume Workers</title>

            <para>Volume Workers interact with iSCSI storage to manage LVM-based instance volumes. Specific functions include:
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>Create volumes</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Delete volumes</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Establish Compute volumes</para></listitem></itemizedlist>

    <para>Volumes may easily be transferred between instances, but may be attached to only a single instance at a time.</para></simplesect></section>
    <section xml:id="managing-compute-users">
        <title>Managing Compute Users</title>
        <para>Access to the Euca2ools (ec2) API is controlled by an access and secret key. The
            user’s access key needs to be included in the request, and the request must be signed
            with the secret key. Upon receipt of API requests, Compute will verify the signature and
            execute commands on behalf of the user. </para>
        <para>In order to begin using nova, you will need to create a
            user with the Identity Service.  </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="managing-the-cloud">

        <title>Managing the Cloud</title><para>There are three main tools that a system administrator will find useful to manage their cloud;
            the nova-manage command, and the novaclient or the Euca2ools commands. </para>
        <para>The nova-manage command may only be run by users with admin privileges. Both
            novaclient and euca2ools can be used by all users, though specific commands may be
            restricted by Role Based Access Control in the deprecated nova auth system or in the Identity Management service. </para>
        <simplesect><title>Using the nova-manage command</title>
        <para>The nova-manage command may be used to perform many essential functions for
                administration and ongoing maintenance of nova, such as network creation.</para>

        <para>The standard pattern for executing a nova-manage command is: </para>
            <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>nova-manage category command <replaceable>[args]</replaceable></userinput>
            </screen>

            <para>For example, to obtain a list of all projects:
                    <command>nova-manage project list</command></para>

            <para>Run without arguments to see a list of available command categories: nova-manage</para>
            <para>You can also run with a category argument such as user to see a list of all commands in that category: nova-manage user</para>
        </simplesect><simplesect><title>Using the nova command-line tool</title>
            <para>Installing the python-novaclient gives you a <code>nova</code> shell command that enables
                Compute API interactions from the command line. You install the client, and then provide
                your username and password, set as environment variables for convenience, and then you
                can have the ability to send commands to your cloud on the command-line.</para>
            <para>To install python-novaclient, download the tarball from
                <link xlink:href="http://pypi.python.org/pypi/python-novaclient/2.6.3#downloads">http://pypi.python.org/pypi/python-novaclient/2.6.3#downloads</link> and then install it in your favorite python environment. </para>
            <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>curl -O http://pypi.python.org/packages/source/p/python-novaclient/python-novaclient-2.6.3.tar.gz</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>tar -zxvf python-novaclient-2.6.3.tar.gz</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>cd python-novaclient-2.6.3</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>sudo python setup.py install</userinput>
    </screen>
            <para>Now that you have installed the python-novaclient, confirm the installation by entering:</para>
<screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>nova help</userinput>
</screen>
<programlisting>
usage: nova [--debug] [--os_username OS_USERNAME] [--os_password OS_PASSWORD]
            [--os_tenant_name OS_TENANT_NAME] [--os_auth_url OS_AUTH_URL]
            [--os_region_name OS_REGION_NAME] [--service_type SERVICE_TYPE]
            [--service_name SERVICE_NAME] [--endpoint_type ENDPOINT_TYPE]
            [--version VERSION]
            &lt;subcommand&gt; ...
</programlisting>
            <para>In return, you will get a listing of all the
                commands and parameters for the nova command line
                client. By setting up the required parameters as
                environment variables, you can fly through these
                commands on the command line. You can add
                    <literal>--os_username</literal> on the nova
                command, or set them as environment variables: </para>
            <para>
<screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>export OS_USERNAME=joecool</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>export OS_PASSWORD=coolword</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>export OS_TENANT_NAME=coolu</userinput>
</screen>
            </para><para>Using the Identity Service, you are supplied with an
                authentication endpoint, which nova recognizes as the
                    <literal>OS_AUTH_URL</literal>. </para>
            <para>
                <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>export OS_AUTH_URL=http://hostname:5000/v2.0</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>export NOVA_VERSION=1.1</userinput>
</screen>
            </para></simplesect>
        <simplesect><title>Using the euca2ools commands</title>
            <para>For a command-line interface to EC2 API calls, use
                the euca2ools command line tool. It is documented at
                    <link
                    xlink:href="http://open.eucalyptus.com/wiki/Euca2oolsGuide_v1.3"
                    >http://open.eucalyptus.com/wiki/Euca2oolsGuide_v1.3</link></para>
        </simplesect>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="managing-volumes">
        <title>Managing Volumes</title>
        <para>Nova-volume is the service that allows you to give extra block level storage to your
            OpenStack Compute instances. You may recognize this as a similar offering from Amazon
            EC2 known as Elastic Block Storage (EBS). However, nova-volume is not the same
            implementation that EC2 uses today. Nova-volume is an iSCSI solution that employs the
            use of Logical Volume Manager (LVM) for Linux. Note that a volume may only be attached
            to one instance at a time. This is not a ‘shared storage’ solution like a SAN of NFS on
            which multiple servers can attach to.</para>
        <para>Before going any further; let's discuss the nova-volume implementation in OpenStack: </para>
        <para>The nova-volumes service uses iSCSI-exposed LVM volumes to the compute nodes which run
            instances. Thus, there are two components involved: </para>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>lvm2, which works with a VG called "nova-volumes" (Refer to <link
                            xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logical_Volume_Manager_(Linux)"
                            >http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logical_Volume_Manager_(Linux)</link> for
                        further details)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>open-iscsi, the iSCSI implementation which manages iSCSI sessions on the
                        compute nodes </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
        <para>Here is what happens from the volume creation to its attachment: </para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>The volume is created via <command>nova volume-create</command>; which creates an LV into the
                    volume group (VG) "nova-volumes" </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The volume is attached to an instance via <command>nova volume-attach</command>; which creates a
                    unique iSCSI IQN that will be exposed to the compute node </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The compute node which run the concerned instance has now an active ISCSI
                    session; and a new local storage (usually a /dev/sdX disk) </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>libvirt uses that local storage as a storage for the instance; the instance
                    get a new disk (usually a /dev/vdX disk) </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>For this particular walkthrough, there is one cloud controller running nova-api,
            nova-scheduler, nova-objectstore, nova-network and nova-volume services. There are two
            additional compute nodes running nova-compute. The walkthrough uses a custom
            partitioning scheme that carves out 60GB of space and labels it as LVM. The network is a
            /28 .80-.95, and FlatManger is the NetworkManager setting for OpenStack Compute (Nova). </para>
        <para>Please note that the network mode doesn't interfere at all with the way nova-volume
            works, but networking must be set up for for nova-volumes to work. Please refer to <link linkend="ch_networking">Networking</link> for more details.</para>
        <para>To set up Compute to use volumes, ensure that nova-volume is installed along with
            lvm2. The guide will be split in four parts : </para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A- Installing the nova-volume service on the cloud controller.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>B- Configuring the "nova-volumes" volume group on the compute
                        nodes.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>C- Troubleshooting your nova-volume installation.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>D- Backup your nova volumes.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <simplesect>
            <title>A- Install nova-volume on the cloud controller.</title>
            <para> This is simply done by installing the two
                components on the cloud controller :</para> 
            <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>apt-get install lvm2 nova-volume</userinput>
            </screen>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <emphasis role="bold">Configure Volumes for use with
                                nova-volume</emphasis></para>
                        <para> If you do not already have LVM volumes on hand, but have free drive
                            space, you will need to create a LVM volume before proceeding. Here is a
                            short run down of how you would create a LVM from free drive space on
                            your system. Start off by issuing an fdisk command to your drive with
                            the free space:
                            <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>fdisk /dev/sda</userinput>
                            </screen>
                            Once in fdisk, perform the following commands: <orderedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Press <command>n</command>
                                   to create a new disk
                                   partition,</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Press <command>p</command>
                                   to create a primary disk
                                   partition,</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Press <command>1</command>
                                   to denote it as 1st disk
                                   partition,</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Either press ENTER twice to
                                   accept the default of 1st and last
                                   cylinder – to convert the remainder
                                   of hard disk to a single disk
                                   partition -OR- press ENTER once to
                                   accept the default of the 1st, and
                                   then choose how big you want the
                                   partition to be by specifying
                                   <literal>+size<replaceable>[K,M,G]</replaceable></literal>
                                   e.g. +5G or +6700M.</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Press <command>t</command>
                                   and select the new partition that
                                   you have created.</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Press <command>8e</command>
                                   change your new partition to 8e,
                                   i.e. Linux LVM partition
                                   type.</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Press <command>p</command>
                                   to display the hard disk partition
                                   setup. Please take note that the
                                   first partition is denoted as
                                   <filename>/dev/sda1</filename> in
                                   Linux.</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Press <command>w</command>
                                   to write the partition table and
                                   exit fdisk upon completion.</para>
                                    <para>Refresh your partition table
                                   to ensure your new partition shows
                                   up, and verify with
                                   <command>fdisk</command>. We then
                                   inform the OS about the table
                                   partition update : </para>
                                        <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>partprobe</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>fdisk -l</userinput>
                                         </screen>
<para>You should see your new partition in this listing.</para>
                                    
                                    <para>Here is how you can set up partitioning during the OS
                                        install to prepare for this nova-volume
                                        configuration:</para>
                                    <screen>
<prompt>root@osdemo03:~#</prompt> <userinput>fdisk -l</userinput> 
                                    </screen>
                                    <para>
                                        <programlisting>
Device Boot Start End Blocks Id System

/dev/sda1 * 1 12158 97280 83 Linux
/dev/sda2 12158 24316 97655808 83 Linux

/dev/sda3 24316 24328 97654784 83 Linux
/dev/sda4 24328 42443 145507329 5 Extended

<emphasis role="bold">/dev/sda5 24328 32352 64452608 8e Linux LVM</emphasis>
<emphasis role="bold">/dev/sda6 32352 40497 65428480 8e Linux LVM</emphasis>

/dev/sda7 40498 42443 15624192 82 Linux swap / Solaris
</programlisting>
                                    </para>
                                    <para>Now that you have identified a partition has been labeled
                                        for LVM use, perform the following steps to configure LVM
                                        and prepare it as nova-volumes. <emphasis role="bold">You
                                            must name your volume group ‘nova-volumes’ or things
                                            will not work as expected</emphasis>:</para>
                                    <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>pvcreate /dev/sda5</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>vgcreate nova-volumes /dev/sda5</userinput> 
                                    </screen>
                                </listitem>
                            </orderedlist></para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>B- Configuring nova-volume on the compute
                nodes</title>
            <para>Since you have created the volume group, you will be
                able to use the following tools for managing your
                volumes: </para>
            <simpara>nova volume-create</simpara>
            <simpara>nova volume-attach</simpara>
            <simpara>nova volume-detach</simpara>
            <simpara>nova volume-delete</simpara>
            <note><para>If you are using KVM as your hypervisor, then the actual
             device name in the guest will be different than the one specified in 
             the nova volume-attach command. You can specify a device name to 
             the KVM hypervisor, but the actual means of attaching to the guest 
             is over a virtual PCI bus. When the guest sees a new device on the
             PCI bus, it picks the next available name (which in most cases is 
             /dev/vdc) and the disk shows up there on the guest. </para></note>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Installing and configuring the iSCSI
                            initiator</emphasis></para>
                    <para> Remember that every node will act as the iSCSI initiator while the server
                        running nova-volumes will act as the iSCSI target. So make sure, before
                        going further that your nodes can communicate with you nova-volumes server.
                        If you have a firewall running on it, make sure that the port 3260 (tcp)
                        accepts incoming connections. </para>
                    <para>First install the open-iscsi package on the initiators, so on the
                        compute-nodes <emphasis role="bold">only</emphasis></para>
                    <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>apt-get install open-iscsi</userinput> 
                    </screen>
                        <para>Then on the target, which is in our case the cloud-controller, the iscsitarget package :</para>
                        <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>apt-get install iscsitarget</userinput> 
                        </screen>
                        <para>This package could refuse to start with a "FATAL: Module iscsi_trgt not found" error. </para>
                        <para>This error is caused by the kernel which does not contain the iscsi module's source into it ;
                            you can install the kernel modules by installing an extra package : </para>
                        <screen> 
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>apt-get install iscsitarget-dkms</userinput>
                        </screen>
                        <para>(the Dynamic Kernel Module Support is a framework used for created modules with non-existent sources into the current kernel)</para>
                        <para>You have to enable it so the startut script (/etc/init.d/iscsitarget) can start the daemon:</para>
                        <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>sed -i 's/false/true/g' /etc/default/iscsitarget</userinput>
                        </screen>
                        <para>Then run on the nova-controller (iscsi target) :</para>
                            <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>service iscsitarget start</userinput>
                            </screen>
                            <para>And on the compute-nodes (iscsi initiators) :</para>
                            <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>service open-iscsi start</userinput>
                            </screen>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Start nova-volume and create volumes</emphasis></para>
                    <para>You are now ready to fire up nova-volume, and start creating
                        volumes!</para>
                    <para>
                        <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>service nova-volume start</userinput></screen>
                    </para>
                    <para>Once the service is started, login to your controller and ensure you’ve
                        properly sourced your ‘novarc’ file.</para>
                    <para>One of the first things you should do is make sure that nova-volume is
                        checking in as expected. You can do so using nova-manage:</para>
                    <para>
                        <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>nova-manage service list</userinput>
                        </screen>
                    </para>
                    <para>If you see a smiling ‘nova-volume’ in there, you are looking good. Now
                        create a new volume:</para>
                    <para>
                        <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>nova volume-create --display_name myvolume 10</userinput>  
                        </screen>
                        --display_name sets a readable name for the volume, while
                         the final argument refers to the size of the volume in GB.</para>
                    <para>You should get some output similar to this:</para>
                    <para>
                        <programlisting>
                        +----+-----------+--------------+------+-------------+--------------------------------------+
                        | ID |   Status  | Display Name | Size | Volume Type |             Attached to              |
                        +----+-----------+--------------+------+-------------+--------------------------------------+
                        | 1  | available | myvolume     | 10   | None        |                                      |
                        +----+-----------+--------------+------+-------------+--------------------------------------+
                        </programlisting>
                    </para>
                    <para>You can view that status of the volumes creation using
                        <command>nova volume-list</command>. Once that status is ‘available,’ it is ready to be
                        attached to an instance:</para>
                    <para><screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>nova volume-attach 857d70e4-35d5-4bf6-97ed-bf4e9a4dcf5a 1 /dev/vdb</userinput>
                    </screen>
                        The first argument refers to the instance
                        you will attach the volume to;
                            The second is the volume ID;
                            The third is the mountpoint<emphasis role="bold"> on the
                            compute-node</emphasis> that the volume will be attached to</para>
                    <para>By doing that, the compute-node which runs the instance basically performs
                        an iSCSI connection and creates a session. You can ensure that the session
                        has been created by running : </para>
                    <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>iscsiadm -m session</userinput>
                    </screen>
                    <para>Which should output : </para>
                    <para>
                        <programlisting>root@nova-cn1:~# iscsiadm -m session
tcp: [1] 172.16.40.244:3260,1 iqn.2010-10.org.openstack:volume-1</programlisting>
                    </para>
                    <para>If you do not get any errors, you can login
                        to the instance and see if the new space is there. <emphasis
                            role="italic"/></para>
                    <para><emphasis role="italic">KVM changes the device name, since it's not
                            considered to be the same type of device as the instances uses as it's
                            local one, you will find the nova-volume will be designated as
                            "/dev/vdX" devices, while local are named "/dev/sdX". </emphasis></para>
                    <para>You can check the volume attachment by running : </para>
                    <para><screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>dmesg | tail</userinput>
                    </screen>
                        You should from there see a new disk. Here is
                        the output from <command>fdisk -l</command>:</para>
                    <programlisting>
Disk /dev/vda: 10.7 GB, 10737418240 bytes
16 heads, 63 sectors/track, 20805 cylinders
Units = cylinders of 1008 * 512 = 516096 bytes
Sector size (logical/physical): 512 bytes / 512 bytes
I/O size (minimum/optimal): 512 bytes / 512 bytes
Disk identifier: 0×00000000
Disk /dev/vda doesn’t contain a valid partition table
<emphasis role="bold">Disk /dev/vdb: 21.5 GB, 21474836480 bytes &lt;—–Here is our new volume!</emphasis>
16 heads, 63 sectors/track, 41610 cylinders
Units = cylinders of 1008 * 512 = 516096 bytes
Sector size (logical/physical): 512 bytes / 512 bytes
I/O size (minimum/optimal): 512 bytes / 512 bytes Disk identifier: 0×00000000 
                    </programlisting>
                    <para>Now with the space presented, let’s configure it for use:</para>
                    <para>
                        <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>fdisk /dev/vdb</userinput>
                        </screen>
                    </para>
                    <orderedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Press <command>n</command> to create
                                a new disk partition.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Press <command>p</command> to create
                                a primary disk partition.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Press <command>1</command> to
                                designated it as the first disk
                                partition.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Press ENTER twice to accept the
                                default of first and last cylinder –
                                to convert the remainder of hard disk
                                to a single disk partition.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Press <command>t</command>, then
                                select the new partition you
                                made.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Press <command>83</command> change
                                your new partition to 83, i.e. Linux
                                partition type.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Press <command>p</command> to
                                display the hard disk partition setup.
                                Please take note that the first
                                partition is denoted as /dev/vda1 in
                                your instance.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Press <command>w</command> to write
                                the partition table and exit fdisk
                                upon completion.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Lastly, make a file system on the
                                partition and mount it.
                                <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>mkfs.ext3 /dev/vdb1</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>mkdir /extraspace</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>mount /dev/vdb1 /extraspace</userinput> 
                                </screen></para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                    <para>Your new volume has now been successfully
                        mounted, and is ready for use! The
                        commands are
                        pretty self-explanatory, so play around with
                        them and create new volumes, tear them down,
                        attach and reattach, and so on. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>C- Troubleshoot your nova-volume installation</title>
            <para>If the volume attachment doesn't work, you should be able to perform different
                checks in order to see where the issue is. The nova-volume.log and nova-compute.log
                will help you to diagnosis the errors you could encounter : </para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">nova-compute.log / nova-volume.log</emphasis></para>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="italic">ERROR "Cannot
                                resolve host"</emphasis>
                            <programlisting>
(nova.root): TRACE: ProcessExecutionError: Unexpected error while running command.
(nova.root): TRACE: Command: sudo iscsiadm -m discovery -t sendtargets -p ubuntu03c
(nova.root): TRACE: Exit code: 255
(nova.root): TRACE: Stdout: ''
(nova.root): TRACE: Stderr: 'iscsiadm: Cannot resolve host ubuntu03c. getaddrinfo error: [Name or service not known]\n\niscsiadm:
cannot resolve host name ubuntu03c\niscsiadm: Could not perform SendTargets discovery.\n'
(nova.root): TRACE:
                            </programlisting>This
                            error happens when the compute node is
                            unable to resolve the nova-volume server
                            name. You could either add a record for
                            the server if you have a DNS server; or
                            add it into the
                                <filename>/etc/hosts</filename> file
                            of the nova-compute. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="italic">ERROR "No route to host"</emphasis>
                            <programlisting>
iscsiadm: cannot make connection to 172.29.200.37: No route to host\niscsiadm: cannot make connection to 172.29.200.37
                            </programlisting>
                            This error could be caused by several things, but<emphasis role="bold">
                                it means only one thing : openiscsi is unable to establish a
                                communication with your nova-volumes server</emphasis>.</para>
                        <para>The first thing you could do is running a telnet session in order to
                            see if you are able to reach the nova-volume server. From the
                            compute-node, run :</para>
                        <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>telnet $ip_of_nova_volumes  3260</userinput>
                        </screen>
                        <para>If the session times out, check the
                            server firewall ; or try to ping it. You
                            could also run a tcpdump session which may
                            also provide extra information : </para>
                        <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>tcpdump -nvv -i $iscsi_interface port dest $ip_of_nova_volumes</userinput>
                        </screen>
                        <para> Again, try to manually run an iSCSI discovery via : </para>
                        <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>iscsiadm -m discovery -t st -p $ip_of_nova-volumes</userinput>
                        </screen>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="italic">"Lost connectivity between nova-volumes and
                                node-compute ; how to restore a clean state ?"</emphasis>
                        </para>
                        <para>Network disconnection can happens, from an "iSCSI view", losing
                            connectivity could be seen as a physical removal of a server's disk. If
                            the instance runs a volume while you loose the network between them, you
                            won't be able to detach the volume. You would encounter several errors.
                            Here is how you could clean this : </para>
                        <para>First, from the nova-compute, close the active (but stalled) iSCSI
                            session, refer to the volume attached to get the session, and perform
                            the following command : </para>
                        <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>iscsiadm -m session -r $session_id -u</userinput>
                        </screen>
                        <para>Here is an <command>iscsi -m</command>
                            session output : </para>
                        <programlisting>
tcp: [1] 172.16.40.244:3260,1 iqn.2010-10.org.openstack:volume-1
tcp: [2] 172.16.40.244:3260,1 iqn.2010-10.org.openstack:volume-2
tcp: [3] 172.16.40.244:3260,1 iqn.2010-10.org.openstack:volume-3
tcp: [4] 172.16.40.244:3260,1 iqn.2010-10.org.openstack:volume-4
tcp: [5] 172.16.40.244:3260,1 iqn.2010-10.org.openstack:volume-5
tcp: [6] 172.16.40.244:3260,1 iqn.2010-10.org.openstack:volume-6
tcp: [7] 172.16.40.244:3260,1 iqn.2010-10.org.openstack:volume-7
tcp: [9] 172.16.40.244:3260,1 iqn.2010-10.org.openstack:volume-9
                        </programlisting>
                        <para>For example, to free volume 9,
                            close the session number 9. </para>
                        <para>The cloud-controller is actually unaware
                            of the iSCSI session closing, and will
                            keeps the volume state as
                                <literal>in-use</literal>:
                            <programlisting>
                            +----+-----------+--------------+------+-------------+--------------------------------------+
                            | ID |   Status  | Display Name | Size | Volume Type |             Attached to              |
                            +----+-----------+--------------+------+-------------+--------------------------------------+
                            | 9  | in-use    | New Volume   | 20   | None        | 7db4cb64-7f8f-42e3-9f58-e59c9a31827d |
                            </programlisting>You
                            now have to inform the cloud-controller
                            that the disk can be used. Nova stores the
                            volumes info into the "volumes" table. You
                            will have to update four fields into the
                            database nova uses (eg. MySQL). First,
                            conect to the database : </para>
                        <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>mysql -uroot -p$password nova</userinput>
                        </screen>
                        <para> Using the volume id, you will
                            have to run the following sql queries
                            </para>
                        <programlisting>
mysql> update volumes set mountpoint=NULL where id=9;
mysql> update volumes set status="available" where status "error_deleting" where id=9;
mysql> update volumes set attach_status="detached" where id=9;
mysql> update volumes set instance_id=0 where id=9;
                        </programlisting>
                        <para>Now if you run again <command>nova volume-list</command> from the cloud
                            controller, you should see an available volume now : </para>
                        <programlisting>
                            +----+-----------+--------------+------+-------------+--------------------------------------+
                            | ID |   Status  | Display Name | Size | Volume Type |             Attached to              |
                            +----+-----------+--------------+------+-------------+--------------------------------------+
                            | 9  | available  | New Volume   | 20   | None       |                                      |
                        </programlisting>
                        <para>You can now proceed to the volume attachment again!</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>D- Backup your nova-volume disks</title>
            <para>While Diablo provides the snapshot functionality
                (using LVM snapshot), you can also back up your
                volumes. The advantage of this method is that it
                reduces the size of the backup; only existing data
                will be backed up, instead of the entire volume. For
                this example, assume that a 100 GB nova-volume has been
                created for an instance, while only 4 gigabytes are
                used. This process will back up only those 4
                giga-bytes, with the following tools: </para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><command>lvm2</command>, directly
                        manipulates the volumes. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><command>kpartx</command> discovers the
                        partition table created inside the instance. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><command>tar</command> creates a
                        minimum-sized backup </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><command>sha1sum</command> calculates the
                        backup checksum, to check its consistency </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">1- Create a snapshot of a used volume</emphasis></para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>In order to backup our volume, we first need
                        to create a snapshot of it. An LVM snapshot is
                        the exact copy of a logical volume, which
                        contains data in a frozen state. This prevents
                        data corruption, because data will not be
                        manipulated during the process of creating the
                        volume itself. Remember the volumes
                        created through a
                            <command>nova volume-create</command>
                        exist in an LVM's logical volume. </para>
                    <para>Before creating the
                            snapshot, ensure that you have enough
                            space to save it. As a precaution, you
                            should have at least twice as much space
                            as the potential snapshot size. If
                            insufficient space is available, there is
                            a risk that the snapshot could become
                            corrupted.</para>
                    <para>Use the following command to obtain a list
                        of all
                        volumes.<screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>lvdisplay</userinput>
                        </screen>In
                        this example, we will refer to a volume called
                            <literal>volume-00000001</literal>, which
                        is a 10GB volume. This process can be applied
                        to all volumes, not matter their size. At the
                        end of the section, we will present a script
                        that you could use to create scheduled
                        backups. The script itself exploits what we
                        discuss here. </para>
                    <para>First, create the snapshot; this can be
                        achieved while the volume is attached to an
                        instance :</para>
                    <para>
                        <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>lvcreate --size 10G --snapshot --name volume-00000001-snapshot /dev/nova-volumes/volume-00000001</userinput>
                        </screen>
                    </para>
                    <para>We indicate to LVM we want a snapshot of an
                        already existing volume with the
                            <literal>--snapshot</literal>
                        configuration option. The command includes the
                        size of the space reserved for the snapshot
                        volume, the name of the snapshot, and the path
                        of an already existing volume (In most cases,
                        the path will be
                                <filename>/dev/nova-volumes/<replaceable>$volume_name</replaceable></filename>).</para>
                    <para>The size doesn't have to be the same as the
                        volume of the snapshot. The size parameter
                        designates the space that LVM will reserve for
                        the snapshot volume. As a precaution, the size
                        should be the same as that of the original
                        volume, even if we know the whole space is not
                        currently used by the snapshot. </para>
                    <para>We now have a full snapshot, and it only took few seconds ! </para>
                    <para>Run <command>lvdisplay</command> again to
                        verify the snapshot. You should see now your
                        snapshot : </para>
                    <para>
                        <programlisting>
                  --- Logical volume ---
  LV Name                /dev/nova-volumes/volume-00000001
  VG Name                nova-volumes
  LV UUID                gI8hta-p21U-IW2q-hRN1-nTzN-UC2G-dKbdKr
  LV Write Access        read/write
  LV snapshot status     source of
                         /dev/nova-volumes/volume-00000026-snap [active]
  LV Status              available
  # open                 1
  LV Size                15,00 GiB
  Current LE             3840
  Segments               1
  Allocation             inherit
  Read ahead sectors     auto
  - currently set to     256
  Block device           251:13

  --- Logical volume ---
  LV Name                /dev/nova-volumes/volume-00000001-snap
  VG Name                nova-volumes
  LV UUID                HlW3Ep-g5I8-KGQb-IRvi-IRYU-lIKe-wE9zYr
  LV Write Access        read/write
  LV snapshot status     active destination for /dev/nova-volumes/volume-00000026
  LV Status              available
  # open                 0
  LV Size                15,00 GiB
  Current LE             3840
  COW-table size         10,00 GiB
  COW-table LE           2560
  Allocated to snapshot  0,00%
  Snapshot chunk size    4,00 KiB
  Segments               1
  Allocation             inherit
  Read ahead sectors     auto
  - currently set to     256
  Block device           251:14
            </programlisting>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">2- Partition table discovery </emphasis></para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If we want to exploit that snapshot with the
                            <command>tar</command> program, we first
                        need to mount our partition on the
                        nova-volumes server. </para>
                    <para><command>kpartx</command> is a small utility
                        which performs table partition discoveries,
                        and maps it. It can be used to view partitions
                        created inside the instance. Without using the
                        partitions created inside instances, we won' t
                        be able to see its content and create
                        efficient backups. </para>
                    <para>
                        <programlisting>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>kpartx -av /dev/nova-volumes/volume-00000001-snapshot</userinput>
                        </programlisting>
                    </para>
                    <para>If no errors are displayed, it means the
                        tools has been able to find it, and map the
                        partition table. Note that on a Debian flavor
                        distro, you could also use <command>apt-get
                            install kpartx</command>.</para>
                    <para>You can easily check the partition table map
                        by running the following command: </para>
                    <para><programlisting>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>ls /dev/mapper/nova*</userinput>
                    </programlisting>You
                        should now see a partition called
                            <literal>nova--volumes-volume--00000001--snapshot1</literal>
                    </para>
                    <para>If you created more than one partition on
                        that volumes, you should have accordingly
                        several partitions; for example.
                            <literal>nova--volumes-volume--00000001--snapshot2</literal>,
                            <literal>nova--volumes-volume--00000001--snapshot3</literal>
                        and so forth. </para>
                    <para>We can now mount our partition : </para>
                    <para>
                        <programlisting>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>mount /dev/mapper/nova--volumes-volume--volume--00000001--snapshot1 /mnt</userinput>
                        </programlisting>
                    </para>
                    <para>If there are no errors, you have
                        successfully mounted the partition.</para>
                    <para>You should now be able to directly access
                        the data that were created inside the
                        instance. If you receive a message asking you
                        to specify a partition, or if you are unable
                        to mount it (despite a well-specified
                        filesystem) there could be two causes :</para>
                    <para><itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para> You didn't allocate enough
                                   space for the snapshot </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                   <command>kpartx</command> was
                                   unable to discover the partition
                                   table. </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>Allocate more space to the
                        snapshot and try the process again. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>
                <emphasis role="bold"> 3- Use tar in order to create archives</emphasis>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> Now that the volume has been mounted,
                            you can create a backup of it : </para>
                        <para>
                            <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>tar --exclude={"lost+found","some/data/to/exclude"} -czf volume-00000001.tar.gz -C /mnt/ /backup/destination</userinput>
                            </screen>
                        </para>
                        <para>This command will create a tar.gz file
                            containing the data, <emphasis
                                role="italic">and data
                            only</emphasis>. This ensures that you do
                            not waste space by backing up empty
                            sectors.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
            <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">4- Checksum calculation I</emphasis>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>You should always have the checksum for
                            your backup files. The checksum is a
                            unique identifier for a file. </para>
                        <para>When you transfer that same file over
                            the network, you can run another checksum
                            calculation. If the checksums are
                            different, this indicates that the file is
                            corrupted; thus, the checksum provides a
                            method to ensure your file has not been
                            corrupted during its transfer.</para>
                        <para>The following command runs a checksum
                            for our file, and saves the result to a
                            file :</para>
                        <para><screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>sha1sum volume-00000001.tar.gz > volume-00000001.checksum</userinput>
                        </screen><emphasis
                                role="bold">Be aware</emphasis> the
                                <command>sha1sum</command> should be
                            used carefully, since the required time
                            for the calculation is directly
                            proportional to the file's size. </para>
                        <para>For files larger than ~4-6 gigabytes,
                            and depending on your CPU, the process may
                            take a long time.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <emphasis role="bold">5- After work cleaning</emphasis>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Now that we have an efficient and
                            consistent backup, the following commands
                            will clean up the file system.<orderedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                   <para>Unmount the volume:
                                   <command>unmount
                                   /mnt</command></para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                   <para>Delete the partition table:
                                   <command>kpartx -dv
                                   /dev/nova-volumes/volume-00000001-snapshot</command></para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                   <para>Remove the snapshot:
                                   <command>lvremove -f
                                   /dev/nova-volumes/volume-00000001-snapshot</command></para>
                                </listitem>
                            </orderedlist></para>
                        <para>And voila :) You can now repeat these
                            steps for every volume you have.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <emphasis role="bold">6- Automate your backups</emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>Because you can expect that more and more volumes
                will be allocated to your nova-volume service, you may
                want to automate your backups. This script <link
                    xlink:href="https://github.com/Razique/Bash-stuff/blob/master/SCR_5005_V01_NUAC-OPENSTACK-EBS-volumes-backup.sh"
                    >here</link> will assist you on this task. The
                script performs the operations from the previous
                example, but also provides a mail report and runs the
                backup based on the
                    <literal>backups_retention_days</literal> setting.
                It is meant to be launched from the server which runs
                the nova-volumes component.</para>
            <para>Here is an example of a mail report: </para>
            <programlisting>
Backup Start Time - 07/10 at 01:00:01
Current retention - 7 days

The backup volume is mounted. Proceed...
Removing old backups...  : /BACKUPS/EBS-VOL/volume-00000019/volume-00000019_28_09_2011.tar.gz
	 /BACKUPS/EBS-VOL/volume-00000019 - 0 h 1 m and 21 seconds. Size - 3,5G

The backup volume is mounted. Proceed...
Removing old backups...  : /BACKUPS/EBS-VOL/volume-0000001a/volume-0000001a_28_09_2011.tar.gz
	 /BACKUPS/EBS-VOL/volume-0000001a - 0 h 4 m and 15 seconds. Size - 6,9G
---------------------------------------
Total backups size - 267G - Used space : 35%
Total execution time - 1 h 75 m and 35 seconds
            </programlisting>
            <para>The script also provides the ability to SSH to your
                instances and run a mysqldump into them. In order to
                make this to work, ensure the connection via the
                nova's project keys is enabled. If you don't want to
                run the mysqldumps, you can turn off this
                functionality by adding
                    <literal>enable_mysql_dump=0</literal> to the
                script.</para>
        </simplesect>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="volume-drivers">
        <title>Volume drivers</title>
        <para>The default nova-volume behaviour can be altered by
            using different volume drivers that are included in Nova
            codebase. To set volume driver, use
                <literal>volume_driver</literal> flag. The default is
            as follows:</para>
        <programlisting>
--volume_driver=nova.volume.driver.ISCSIDriver
        </programlisting>

        <section xml:id="rados">
            <title>Ceph RADOS block device (RBD)</title>
            <para>If you are using KVM or QEMU as your hypervisor, the
                Compute service can be configured to use
                <link xlink:href="http://ceph.com/ceph-storage/block-storage/">
                    Ceph's RADOS block devices (RBD)</link> for volumes. Add
                    the following lines to nova.conf on the host the runs the
                    <command>nova-volume</command> service to enable the RBD
                    driver:
<programlisting>
volume_driver=nova.volume.driver.RBDDriver
rbd_pool=nova
</programlisting>
            </para>
            <para></para>
        </section>


        <section xml:id="nexenta-driver">
            <title>Nexenta</title>
            <para>NexentaStor Appliance is NAS/SAN software platform designed for building reliable and fast network storage arrays. The NexentaStor is based on
                the OpenSolaris and uses ZFS as a disk management system. NexentaStor can serve as a storage node for the OpenStack and provide block-level volumes
                for the virtual servers via iSCSI protocol. </para>
            <para>The Nexenta driver allows you to use Nexenta SA to
                store Nova volumes. Every Nova volume is represented
                by a single zvol in a predefined Nexenta volume. For
                every new volume the driver creates a iSCSI target and
                iSCSI target group that are used to access it from
                compute hosts.</para>
            <para>To use Nova with Nexenta Storage Appliance, you should:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem><para>set
                            <literal>--volume_driver=nova.volume.nexenta.volume.NexentaDriver</literal>.</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>set <literal>--nexenta_host</literal> flag to the hostname or IP
                        of your NexentaStor</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>set <literal>--nexenta_user</literal> and
                            <literal>--nexenta_password</literal> to
                        the username and password of the user with all
                        necessary privileges on the appliance,
                        including the access to REST API</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>set <literal>--nexenta_volume</literal> to the name of the
                        volume on the appliance that you would like to
                        use in Nova, or create a volume named
                            <literal>nova</literal> (it will be used
                        by default)</para></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            <para>Nexenta driver has a lot of tunable flags. Some of them you might want to change:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem><para><literal>nexenta_target_prefix</literal> defines the prefix that
                        will be prepended to volume id to form target
                        name on Nexenta</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para><literal>nexenta_target_group_prefix</literal> defines the
                        prefix for target groups</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para><literal>nexenta_blocksize</literal> can be set to the size of
                        the blocks in newly created zvols on
                        appliance, with the suffix; for example, the
                        default 8K means 8 kilobytes</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para><literal>nexenta_sparse</literal> is boolean and can be set to
                        use sparse zvols to save space on
                        appliance</para></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            <para>Some flags that you might want to keep with the
                default values:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem><para><literal>nexenta_rest_port</literal> is the port where Nexenta
                        listens for REST requests (the same port where
                        the NMV works)</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para><literal>nexenta_rest_protocol</literal> can be set to
                            <literal>http</literal> or
                            <literal>https</literal>, but the default
                        is <literal>auto</literal> which makes the
                        driver try to use HTTP and switch to HTTPS in
                        case of failure</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para><literal>nexenta_iscsi_target_portal_port</literal> is the port
                        to connect to Nexenta over iSCSI</para></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="xensm">
            <title>Using the Xen Storage Manager Volume Driver</title>
            <para>The Xen Storage Manager Volume driver (xensm) is a
                Xen hypervisor specific volume driver, and can be used
                to provide basic storage functionality, including
                volume creation and destruction, on a number of
                different storage back-ends. It also enables the
                capability of using more sophisticated storage
                back-ends for operations like cloning/snapshots, etc.
                The list below shows some of the storage plugins
                already supported in XenServer/Xen Cloud Platform
                (XCP): </para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>NFS VHD: Storage repository (SR) plugin which stores disks as Virtual Hard Disk (VHD)
                        files on a remote Network File System (NFS).
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Local VHD on LVM: SR plugin which represents disks as VHD disks on Logical Volumes (LVM)
                        within a locally-attached Volume Group.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>HBA LUN-per-VDI driver: SR plugin which represents Logical Units (LUs)
                        as Virtual Disk Images (VDIs) sourced by host bus adapters (HBAs).
                        E.g. hardware-based iSCSI or FC support.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>NetApp: SR driver for mapping of LUNs to VDIs on a NETAPP server,
                        providing use of fast snapshot and clone features on the filer.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>LVHD over FC: SR plugin which represents disks as VHDs on Logical Volumes
                        within a Volume Group created on an HBA LUN. E.g. hardware-based iSCSI or FC support.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>iSCSI: Base ISCSI SR driver, provides a LUN-per-VDI.
                        Does not support creation of VDIs but accesses existing LUNs on a target.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>LVHD over iSCSI: SR plugin which represents disks as
                        Logical Volumes within a Volume Group created on an iSCSI LUN.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>EqualLogic: SR driver for mapping of LUNs to VDIs on a
                        EQUALLOGIC array group, providing use of fast snapshot and clone features on the array.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <section xml:id="xensmdesign">
                <title>Design and Operation</title>
                <simplesect>
                    <title>Definitions</title>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold"
                                   >Backend:</emphasis> A term for a
                                particular storage backend. This could
                                be iSCSI, NFS, Netapp etc. </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold"
                                   >Backend-config:</emphasis> All the
                                parameters required to connect to a
                                specific backend. For e.g. For NFS,
                                this would be the server, path, etc. </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold"
                                   >Flavor:</emphasis> This term is
                                equivalent to volume "types". A
                                user0friendly term to specify some
                                notion of quality of service. For
                                example, "gold" might mean that the
                                volumes will use a backend where
                                backups are possible. A flavor can be
                                associated with multiple backends. The
                                volume scheduler, with the help of the
                                driver, will decide which backend will
                                be used to create a volume of a
                                particular flavor. Currently, the
                                driver uses a simple "first-fit"
                                policy, where the first backend that
                                can successfully create this volume is
                                the one that is used. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </simplesect>
                <simplesect>
                    <title>Operation</title>
                    <para>The admin uses the the nova-manage command
                        detailed below to add flavors and backends. </para>
                    <para>One or more nova-volume service instances
                        will be deployed per availability zone. When
                        an instance is started, it will create storage
                        repositories (SRs) to connect to the backends
                        available within that zone. All nova-volume
                        instances within a zone can see all the
                        available backends. These instances are
                        completely symmetric and hence should be able
                        to service any
                            <literal>create_volume</literal> request
                        within the zone. </para>
                </simplesect>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="xensmconfig">
                <title>Configuring Xen Storage Manager</title>
                <simplesect>
                    <title>Prerequisites
                    </title>
                    <orderedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>xensm requires that you use either Xenserver or XCP as the hypervisor.
                                The Netapp and EqualLogic backends are not supported on XCP.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Ensure all <emphasis role="bold">hosts</emphasis> running volume and compute services
                                have connectivity to the storage system.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                </simplesect>
                <simplesect>
                    <title>Configuration
                    </title>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                <emphasis role="bold">Set the following configuration options for the nova volume service:
                                    (nova-compute also requires the volume_driver configuration option.)
                                </emphasis>
                            </para>
                            <programlisting>
--volume_driver="nova.volume.xensm.XenSMDriver"
--use_local_volumes=False
                                </programlisting>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                <emphasis role="bold">The backend configs that the volume driver uses need to be
                                    created before starting the volume service.
                                </emphasis>
                            </para>
                            <programlisting>
<prompt>$</prompt> nova-manage sm flavor_create &lt;label> &lt;description>

<prompt>$</prompt> nova-manage sm flavor_delete &lt;label>

<prompt>$</prompt> nova-manage sm backend_add &lt;flavor label> &lt;SR type> [config connection parameters]

Note: SR type and config connection parameters are in keeping with the Xen Command Line Interface. http://support.citrix.com/article/CTX124887

<prompt>$</prompt> nova-manage sm backend_delete &lt;backend-id>

                               </programlisting>
                            <para> Example: For the NFS storage manager plugin, the steps
                                below may be used.
                            </para>
                            <programlisting>
<prompt>$</prompt> nova-manage sm flavor_create gold "Not all that glitters"

<prompt>$</prompt> nova-manage sm flavor_delete gold

<prompt>$</prompt> nova-manage sm backend_add gold nfs name_label=mybackend server=myserver serverpath=/local/scratch/myname

<prompt>$</prompt> nova-manage sm backend_remove 1
                                </programlisting>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                <emphasis role="bold">Start nova-volume and nova-compute with the new configuration options.
                                </emphasis>
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </simplesect>
                <simplesect>
                    <title>Creating and Accessing the volumes from VMs </title>
                    <para>Currently, the flavors have not been tied to
                        the volume types API. As a result, we simply
                        end up creating volumes in a "first fit" order
                        on the given backends. </para>
                    <para>The standard euca-* or openstack API
                        commands (such as volume extensions) should be
                        used for creating, destroying, attaching, or
                        detaching volumes. </para>
                </simplesect>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="boot-from-volume">
        <title>Boot From Volume</title>
        <para>The Compute service has preliminary support for booting an instance from a
            volume.</para>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Creating a bootable volume</title>
            <para>To create a bootable volume, mount the volume to an existing instance, and then
                build a volume-backed image. Here is an example based on <link
                    xlink:href="https://github.com/openstack-dev/devstack/blob/master/exercises/boot_from_volume.sh"
                    >exercises/boot_from_volume.sh</link>. This example assumes that you have a
                running instance with a 1GB volume mounted at <literal>/dev/vdc</literal>. These
                commands will make the mounted volume bootable using a CirrOS image. As
                root:<screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>mkfs.ext3 -b 1024 /dev/vdc 1048576</userinput>
<prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>mkdir /tmp/stage</userinput>
<prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>mount /dev/vdc /tmp/stage</userinput>

<prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>cd /tmp</userinput>
<prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>wget https://launchpad.net/cirros/trunk/0.3.0/+download/cirros-0.3.0-x86_64-rootfs.img.gz</userinput>
<prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>gunzip cirros-0.3.0-x86_64-rootfs.img.gz</userinput>
<prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>mkdir /tmp/cirros</userinput>
<prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>mount /tmp/cirros-0.3.0-x86_64-rootfs.img /tmp/cirros</userinput>

<prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>cp -pr /tmp/cirros/* /tmp/stage</userinput>
<prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>umount /tmp/cirros</userinput>
<prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>sync</userinput>
<prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>umount /tmp/stage</userinput></screen></para>
            <para>Detach the volume once you are done.</para>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Booting an instance from the volume</title>
            <para>To boot a new instance from the volume, use the
                    <command>nova boot</command> command with the
                    <literal>--block_device_mapping</literal> flag.
                The output for <command>nova help boot</command> shows
                the following documentation about this
                flag:<screen><computeroutput> --block_device_mapping &lt;dev_name=mapping>
                        Block device mapping in the format &lt;dev_name=&lt;id>:&lt;typ
                        e>:&lt;size(GB)>:&lt;delete_on_terminate>.
 </computeroutput></screen></para>
            <para>The command arguments are:<variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><literal>dev_name</literal></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>A device name where the volume will be attached in the system at
                                        <filename>/dev/<replaceable>dev_name</replaceable></filename>.
                                This value is typically <literal>vda</literal>.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><literal>id</literal></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The ID of the volume to boot from, as shown in the output of
                                    <command>nova volume-list</command>.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><literal>type</literal></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>This is either <literal>snap</literal>, which means that the
                                volume was created from a snapshot, or anything other than
                                    <literal>snap</literal> (a blank string is valid). In the
                                example above, the volume was not created from a snapshot, so we
                                will leave this field blank in our example below.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><literal>size (GB)</literal></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The size of the volume, in GB. It is safe to leave this blank and
                                have the Compute service infer the size.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><literal>delete_on_terminate</literal></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>A boolean to indicate whether the volume should be deleted when
                                the instance is terminated. True can be specified as
                                    <literal>True</literal> or <literal>1</literal>. False can be
                                specified as <literal>False</literal> or
                                <literal>0</literal>.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist></para>
            <para><note>
                    <para>Because of bug <link
                            xlink:href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/nova/+bug/1008622"
                            >#1008622</link>, you must specify an image when booting from a volume,
                        even though this image will not be used.</para>
                </note>The following example will attempt boot from volume with
                    ID=<literal>13</literal>, it will not delete on terminate. Replace the
                    <literal>--image</literal> flag with a valid image on your system, and the
                    <literal>--key_name</literal> with a valid keypair
                name:<screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>nova boot --image <replaceable>f4addd24-4e8a-46bb-b15d-fae2591f1a35</replaceable> --flavor 2 --key_name <replaceable>mykey</replaceable> --block_device_mapping vda=13:::0 boot-from-vol-test</userinput></screen></para>
        </simplesect>

    </section>
    <section xml:id="live-migration-usage">

        <title>Using Live Migration</title>
        <para>Before starting live migration, review the "Configuring
            Live Migration" section.</para>
        <para>Live migration provides a scheme to migrate running instances from one OpenStack
            Compute server to another OpenStack Compute server. No visible downtime and no
            transaction loss is the ideal goal. This feature can be used as described below. </para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>First, look at the running instances, to get the ID of the instance you wish
to live migrate.</para>
                <programlisting>
<prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>nova-list</userinput>
<![CDATA[+--------------------------------------+------+--------+-----------------+
|                  ID                  | Name | Status |Networks         |
+--------------------------------------+------+--------+-----------------+
| d1df1b5a-70c4-4fed-98b7-423362f2c47c | vm1  | ACTIVE | private=a.b.c.d |
| d693db9e-a7cf-45ef-a7c9-b3ecb5f22645 | vm2  | ACTIVE | private=e.f.g.h |
+--------------------------------------+------+--------+-----------------+
                 ]]></programlisting>
               <para>Second, look at information associated with that instance - our example is vm1
from above.</para>
                <programlisting>
<prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>nova show d1df1b5a-70c4-4fed-98b7-423362f2c47c</userinput>
<![CDATA[+-------------------------------------+----------------------------------------------------------+
|               Property              |                          Value                           |
+-------------------------------------+----------------------------------------------------------+
...
| OS-EXT-SRV-ATTR:host                | HostB                                                    |
...
| flavor                              | m1.tiny                                                  |
| id                                  | d1df1b5a-70c4-4fed-98b7-423362f2c47c                     |
| name                                | vm1                                                      |
| private network                     | a.b.c.d                                                  |
| status                              | ACTIVE                                                   |
...
+-------------------------------------+----------------------------------------------------------+
                 ]]></programlisting>
                 <para> In this example, vm1 is running on HostB.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Third, select the server to migrate instances to.</para>
                <programlisting>
<prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>nova-manage service list</userinput>
<![CDATA[HostA nova-scheduler enabled  :-) None
HostA nova-volume enabled  :-) None
HostA nova-network enabled  :-) None
HostB nova-compute enabled  :-) None
HostC nova-compute enabled  :-) None
                 ]]></programlisting>
                 <para> In this example, HostC can be picked up because nova-compute is running on it.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Third, ensure that  HostC has enough resource
                    for live migration.</para>
                <programlisting>
<prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>nova-manage service describe_resource HostC</userinput>
<![CDATA[HOST             PROJECT     cpu   mem(mb)     hdd
HostC(total)                  16     32232     878
HostC(used_now)               13     21284     442
HostC(used_max)               13     21284     442
HostC            p1            5     10240     150
HostC            p2            5     10240     150
.....
                 ]]></programlisting>
                 <itemizedlist>
                     <listitem>
                         <para><emphasis role="bold">cpu:</emphasis>the nuber of cpu</para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem>
                         <para><emphasis role="bold">mem(mb):</emphasis>total amount of memory (MB)</para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem>
                         <para><emphasis role="bold">hdd</emphasis>total amount of NOVA-INST-DIR/instances(GB)</para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem>
                         <para><emphasis role="bold">1st line shows </emphasis>total amount of resource physical server has.</para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem>
                         <para><emphasis role="bold">2nd line shows </emphasis>current used resource.</para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem>
                         <para><emphasis role="bold">3rd line shows </emphasis>maximum used resource.</para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem>
                         <para><emphasis role="bold">4th line and under</emphasis> is used resource per project.</para>
                     </listitem>
                 </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Finally, live migration</para>
                <programlisting>
<prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>nova live-migration bee83dd3-5cc9-47bc-a1bd-6d11186692d0 HostC</userinput>
<![CDATA[Migration of bee83dd3-5cc9-47bc-a1bd-6d11186692d0 initiated.
                 ]]></programlisting>
                 <para>Make sure instances are migrated successfully
                    with <command>nova list</command>. If instances
                    are still running on HostB, check logfiles
                    (src/dest nova-compute and nova-scheduler) to
                    determine why.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>


    </section>
    <section xml:id="nova-disaster-recovery-process">
        <title>Nova Disaster Recovery Process</title>
        <para>Sometimes, things just don't go right. An incident is
            never planned, by its definition. </para>
        <para>In this section, we will review managing your cloud
            after a disaster, and how to easily backup the persistent
            storage volumes, which is another approach when you face a
            disaster. Even apart from the disaster scenario, backup
            ARE mandatory. While the Diablo release includes the
            snapshot functions, both the backup procedure and the
            utility do apply to the Cactus release. </para>
        <para>For reference, you cand find a DRP definition here : <link
                xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Disaster_Recovery_Plan"
                >http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Disaster_Recovery_Plan</link>. </para>
            <simplesect>
                <title>A- The disaster Recovery Process presentation</title>
           <para>A disaster could happen to several components of your
                architecture : a disk crash, a network loss, a power
                cut, etc. In this example, we suppose the following
                setup : <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> A cloud controller (nova-api,
                            nova-objecstore, nova-volume,
                            nova-network) </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> A compute node (nova-compute) </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> A Storage Area Network used by
                            nova-volumes (aka SAN) </para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>The example disaster will be the worst
                one : a power loss. That power loss applies to the
                three components. <emphasis role="italic">Let's see
                    what runs and how it runs before the
                    crash</emphasis> : <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>From the SAN to the cloud controller, we
                            have an active iscsi session (used for the
                            "nova-volumes" LVM's VG). </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>From the cloud controller to the compute
                            node we also have active iscsi sessions
                            (managed by nova-volume). </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>For every volume an iscsi session is
                            made (so 14 ebs volumes equals 14
                            sessions). </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>From the cloud controller to the compute
                            node, we also have iptables/ ebtables
                            rules which allows the acess from the
                            cloud controller to the running instance.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>And at least, from the cloud controller
                            to the compute node ; saved into database,
                            the current state of the instances (in
                            that case "running" ), and their volumes
                            attachment (mountpoint, volume id, volume
                            status, etc..) </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist> Now, after the power loss occurs and
                all hardware components restart, the situation is as
                follows: </para>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>From the SAN to the cloud, the ISCSI
                            session no longer exists. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>From the cloud controller to the compute
                            node, the ISCSI sessions no longer exist.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>From the cloud controller to the compute
                            node, the iptables and ebtables are
                            recreated, since, at boot, nova-network
                            reapply the configurations. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>From the cloud controller, instances
                            turn into a shutdown state (because they
                            are no longer running) </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Into the database, data was not updated
                            at all, since nova could not have guessed
                            the crash. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>Before going further, and in order to
                prevent the admin to make fatal mistakes,<emphasis
                    role="bold"> the instances won't be
                    lost</emphasis>, since no "<command role="italic"
                    >destroy</command>" or "<command role="italic"
                    >terminate</command>" command had been invoked, so
                the files for the instances remain on the compute
                node. </para>
            <para>The plan is to perform the following tasks, in that
                exact order. <emphasis role="underline">Any extra step
                    would be dangerous at this stage</emphasis>
                :</para>
            <para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
               <para>We need to get the current relation from a volume to its instance, since we
                            will recreate the attachment.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>We need to update the database in order to clean the stalled state.
                            (After that, we won't be able to perform the first step). </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>We need to restart the instances (so go from a "shutdown" to a
                            "running" state). </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>After the restart, we can reattach the volumes to their respective
                            instances. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> That step, which is not a mandatory one, exists in an SSH into the
                            instances in order to reboot them. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </para>
            </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>B - The Disaster Recovery Process itself</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold"> Instance to
                                Volume relation </emphasis>
                        </para>
                        <para>We need to get the current relation from
                            a volume to its instance, since we will
                            recreate the attachment : </para>
                        <para>This relation could be figured by
                            running
                                <command>nova volume-list</command>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold"> Database Update
                            </emphasis>
                        </para>
                        <para>Second, we need to update the database
                            in order to clean the stalled state. Now
                            that we have saved the attachments we need
                            to restore for every volume, the database
                            can be cleaned with the following queries:
                            <programlisting>
<prompt>mysql></prompt> <userinput>use nova;</userinput>
<prompt>mysql></prompt> <userinput>update volumes set mountpoint=NULL;</userinput>
<prompt>mysql></prompt> <userinput>update volumes set status="available" where status &lt;&gt;"error_deleting";</userinput>
<prompt>mysql></prompt> <userinput>update volumes set attach_status="detached";</userinput>
<prompt>mysql></prompt> <userinput>update volumes set instance_id=0;</userinput>
                </programlisting>Now,
                            when running
                                <command>nova volume-list</command>
                            all volumes should be available. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold"> Instances Restart
                            </emphasis>
                        </para>
                        <para>We need to restart the instances. This
                            can be done via a simple
                                <command>nova reboot
                                   <replaceable>$instance</replaceable></command>
                        </para>
                        <para>At that stage, depending on your image,
                            some instances will completely reboot and
                            become reacheable, while others will stop
                            on the "plymouth" stage. </para>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">DO NOT reboot a
                                second time</emphasis> the ones which
                            are stopped at that stage (<emphasis
                                role="italic">see below, the fourth
                                step</emphasis>). In fact it depends
                            on whether you added an
                                <filename>/etc/fstab</filename> entry
                            for that volume or not. Images built with
                            the <emphasis role="italic"
                                >cloud-init</emphasis> package will
                            remain on a pending state, while others
                            will skip the missing volume and start.
                            (More information is available on <link
                                xlink:href="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/CloudInit"
                                >help.ubuntu.com</link>) But remember
                            that the idea of that stage is only to ask
                            nova to reboot every instance, so the
                            stored state is preserved. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold"> Volume Attachment
                            </emphasis>
                        </para>
                        <para>After the restart, we can reattach the
                            volumes to their respective instances. Now
                            that nova has restored the right status,
                            it is time to performe the attachments via
                            a <command>nova volume-attach</command></para>
                        <para>Here is a simple snippet that uses the
                            file we created :
                            <programlisting>
#!/bin/bash

while read line; do
    volume=`echo $line | $CUT -f 1 -d " "`
    instance=`echo $line | $CUT -f 2 -d " "`
    mount_point=`echo $line | $CUT -f 3 -d " "`
        echo "ATTACHING VOLUME FOR INSTANCE - $instance"
    nova volume-attach $instance $volume $mount_point
    sleep 2
done &lt; $volumes_tmp_file
                </programlisting>At
                            that stage, instances which were pending
                            on the boot sequence (<emphasis
                                role="italic">plymouth</emphasis>)
                            will automatically continue their boot,
                            and restart normally, while the ones which
                            booted will see the volume. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold"> SSH into
                                instances </emphasis>
                        </para>
                        <para>If some services depend on the volume,
                            or if a volume has an entry into fstab, it
                            could be good to simply restart the
                            instance. This restart needs to be made
                            from the instance itself, not via nova.
                            So, we SSH into the instance and perform a
                            reboot :
                            <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>shutdown -r now</userinput>
                             </screen></para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>Voila! You successfully recovered your
                cloud after that. </para>
            <para>Here are some suggestions : </para>
            <para><itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> Use the <literal>parameter
                                errors=remount</literal> in the
                                <filename>fstab</filename> file, which
                            will prevent data corruption.</para>
                        <para> The system would lock any write to the
                            disk if it detects an I/O error. This
                            configuration option should be added into
                            the nova-volume server (the one which
                            performs the ISCSI connection to the SAN),
                            but also into the instances'
                                <filename>fstab</filename>
                            file.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Do not add the entry for the SAN's disks
                            to the nova-volume's
                                <filename>fstab</filename> file. </para>
                        <para>Some systems will  hang on that step,
                            which means you could lose access to your
                            cloud-controller. In order to re-run the
                            session manually, you would run the
                            following command before performing the
                            mount:
                            <screen>
<prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>iscsiadm -m discovery -t st -p $SAN_IP $ iscsiadm -m node --target-name $IQN -p $SAN_IP -l</userinput>
 </screen></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> For your instances, if you have the
                            whole <filename>/home/</filename>
                            directory on the disk, instead of emptying
                            the <filename>/home</filename> directory
                            and map the disk on it, leave a user's
                            directory with the user's bash files and
                            the <filename>authorized_keys</filename>
                            file. </para>
                        <para>This will allow you to connect to the
                            instance, even without the volume
                            attached, if you allow only connections
                            via public keys. </para>
                    </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
                </para>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
                    <title>C- Scripted DRP</title>
            <para>You can download from <link
                    xlink:href="https://github.com/Razique/Bash-stuff/blob/master/SCR_5006_V00_NUAC-OPENSTACK-DRP-OpenStack.sh"
                    >here</link> a bash script which performs these
                five steps : </para>
            <para>The "test mode" allows you to perform that whole sequence for only one
                instance.</para>
            <para>To reproduce the power loss,  connect to the compute
                node which runs that same instance and close the iscsi
                session. <emphasis role="underline">Do not dettach the
                    volume via
                    <command>nova volume-detach</command></emphasis>, but
                instead manually close the iscsi session. </para>
            <para>In the following example, the iscsi session is
                number 15 for that instance :
                    <screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>iscsiadm -m session -u -r 15</userinput>
                    </screen><emphasis
                    role="bold">Do not forget the flag
                        -<literal>r</literal>; otherwise, you will
                    close ALL sessions</emphasis>.</para>
        </simplesect>
    </section>

</chapter>
