<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="ch_installing-openstack-compute"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Installing OpenStack Compute</title>

  <para>The OpenStack system has several key projects that are separate
  installations but can work together depending on your cloud needs: OpenStack
  Compute, OpenStack Object Storage, and OpenStack Image Service. You can
  install any of these projects separately and then configure them either as
  standalone or connected entities. </para>

  <xi:include href="../openstack-install/compute-sys-requirements.xml"/>

  <section xml:id="example-installation-architecture">
    <title>Example Installation Architectures</title>

    <para>OpenStack Compute uses a shared-nothing, messaging-based
    architecture. While very flexible, the fact that you can install each
    nova- service on an independent server means there are many possible
    methods for installing OpenStack Compute. Here are the types of
    installation architectures:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Single node: Only one server runs all nova- services and also
        drives all the virtual instances. Use this configuration only for
        trying out OpenStack Compute, or for development purposes.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Two nodes: A cloud controller node runs the nova- services
        except for <command>nova-compute</command>, and a compute node runs
        <command>nova-compute</command>. A client computer is likely needed to
        bundle images and interfacing to the servers, but a client is not
        required. Use this configuration for proof of concepts or development
        environments.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Multiple nodes: You can add more compute nodes to the two node
        installation by simply installing <command>nova-compute</command> on
        an additional server and copying a <filename>nova.conf</filename> file
        to the added node. This would result in a multiple node installation.
        You can also add a volume controller and a network controller as
        additional nodes in a more complex multiple node installation. A
        minimum of 4 nodes is best for running multiple virtual instances that
        require a lot of processing power.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>This is an illustration of one possible multiple server installation
    of OpenStack Compute; virtual server networking in the cluster may
    vary.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/NOVA_install_arch.png" scale="80"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject></para>

    <para>An alternative architecture would be to add more messaging servers
    if you notice a lot of back up in the messaging queue causing performance
    problems. In that case you would add an additional RabbitMQ server in
    addition to or instead of scaling up the database server. Your
    installation can run any nova- service on any server as long as the
    <filename>nova.conf</filename> is configured to point to the RabbitMQ
    server and the server can send messages to the server.</para>

    <para>Multiple installation architectures are possible, here is another
    example illustration.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/NOVA_compute_nodes.png" scale="40"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject></para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="service-architecture">
    <title>Service Architecture</title>

    <para>Because Compute has multiple services and many configurations are
    possible, here is a diagram showing the overall service architecture and
    communication systems between the services.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/NOVA_ARCH.png" scale="80"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject></para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="installing-openstack-compute-on-debian">
    <title>Installing OpenStack Compute on Debian</title>
    <para>Starting with Debian 7.0 "Wheezy", the OpenStack packages are 
      provided as part of the distribution.</para>
    <para>
      For the management or controller node install the following packages: (via <command>apt-get install</command>)
      
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para><literal>nova-api</literal></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><literal>nova-scheduler</literal></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><literal>glance</literal></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><literal>keystone</literal></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><literal>mysql-server</literal></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><literal>rabbitmq</literal></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><literal>memcached</literal></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><literal>openstack-dashboard</literal></para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
        
    </para>
    <para>
      For the compute node(s) install the following packages:
      <itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><literal>nova-compute</literal></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><literal>nova-network</literal></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><literal>nova-api</literal></para></listitem>            
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        Because this manual takes active advantage of the "sudo" command,
        it would be easier for you to add to it your Debian system, by doing:</para>
        
<screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>usermod -a -G sudo "myuser"</userinput></screen>
              
        <para>then re-login.
        Otherwise you will have to replace every "<command>sudo</command>" call by executing from
        root account.
      </para>
    </note>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="installing-openstack-compute-on-rhel6">
    <title>Installing on Fedora or Red Hat Enterprise Linux 6</title>
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <para>The Fedora project provides OpenStack packages in Fedora 16 and
    later. Fedora also provides packages for RHEL6 via the EPEL (Extra
    Packages for Enterprise Linux) 6 repository. If you would like to install
    OpenStack on RHEL6, see this page for more information on enabling the use
    of EPEL: <link
    xlink:href="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/EPEL">http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/EPEL</link>.</para>

    <para>Detailed instructions for installing OpenStack Compute on Fedora or
    RHEL6 can be found on the Fedora wiki. See these pages for more
    information:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><link
        xlink:href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Getting_started_with_OpenStack_on_Fedora_17">Getting
        Started with OpenStack on Fedora 17</link></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>The Essex release is in Fedora 17. This page discusses the
          installation of Essex on Fedora 17. Once EPEL 6 has been updated to
          include Essex, these instructions should be used if installing on
          RHEL 6. The main difference between the Fedora 17 instructions and
          what must be done on RHEL 6 is that RHEL 6 does not use systemd, so
          the <command>systemctl</command> commands will have to substituted
          with the RHEL 6 equivalent.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><link
        xlink:href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Getting_started_with_OpenStack_Nova">Getting
        Started with OpenStack Nova</link></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>This page was originally written as instructions for getting
          started with OpenStack on Fedora 16, which includes the Diablo
          release. At the time of writing, While EPEL 6 still includes Diablo,
          these instructions should be used if installing on RHEL 6.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="installing-openstack-compute-on-ubuntu">
    <title>Installing on Ubuntu</title>
    
    <para>How you go about installing OpenStack Compute depends on your goals
      for the installation. You can use an ISO image, you can use a scripted
      installation, and you can manually install with a step-by-step
      installation.</para>
    
    <section xml:id="iso-ubuntu-installation">
      <title>ISO Distribution Installation</title>
      
      <para>You can download and use an ISO image that is based on a Ubuntu
        Linux Server 10.04 LTS distribution containing only the components
        needed to run OpenStack Compute. See <link
          xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/stackops/files/">http://sourceforge.net/projects/stackops/files/</link>
        for download files and information, license information, and a
        <filename>README</filename> file. For documentation on the StackOps
        distro, see <link
          xlink:href="http://docs.stackops.org">http://docs.stackops.org</link>.
        For free support, go to <link
          xlink:href="http://getsatisfaction.com/stackops">http://getsatisfaction.com/stackops</link>.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section xml:id="scripted-ubuntu-installation">
      <title>Scripted Installation</title>
      
      <para>You can download a script for a standalone install for
        proof-of-concept, learning, or for development purposes for Ubuntu 11.04
        at <link
          xlink:href="http://devstack.org">https://devstack.org</link>.</para>
      
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Install Ubuntu 11.04 (Natty):</para>
          
          <para>In order to correctly install all the dependencies, we assume
            a specific version of Ubuntu to make it as easy as possible.
            OpenStack works on other flavors of Linux (and some folks even run
            it on Windows!) We recommend using a minimal install of Ubuntu
            server in a VM if this is your first time.</para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>Download DevStack:</para>
          
          <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>git clone git://github.com/openstack-dev/devstack.git</userinput></screen>
          
          <para>The devstack repo contains a script that installs OpenStack
            Compute, the Image Service and the Identity Service and offers
            templates for configuration files plus data scripts.</para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>Start the install:</para>
          
          <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>cd devstack; ./stack.sh</userinput></screen>
          
          <para>It takes a few minutes, we recommend <link
            xlink:href="http://devstack.org/stack.sh.html">reading the
            well-documented script</link> while it is building to learn more
            about what is going on.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    
    <section xml:id="manual-ubuntu-installation">
      <title>Manual Installation on Ubuntu</title>
      
      <para>The manual installation involves installing from packages
        shipped on Ubuntu 12.04 as a user with root (or sudo)
        permission. The <link
          xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/diablo/openstack-compute/starter/content/"
          >Oneiric OpenStack Starter Guide</link> provides
        instructions for a manual installation using the packages
        shipped with Ubuntu 11.10. The <link
          xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/essex/openstack-compute/install/content/"
          >OpenStack Install and Deploy Manual</link> provides
        instructions for installing using Ubuntu 12.04 packages. Refer
        to those manuals for detailed instructions by going to <link
          xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org"
          >http://docs.openstack.org</link> and clicking the links
        next to the manual title.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
