<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!-- Some useful entities borrowed from HTML -->
<!ENTITY ndash  "&#x2013;">
<!ENTITY mdash  "&#x2014;">
<!ENTITY hellip "&#x2026;">
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#xB1;">

<!-- Useful for describing APIs -->
<!ENTITY GET    '<command xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">GET</command>'>
<!ENTITY PUT    '<command xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">PUT</command>'>
<!ENTITY POST   '<command xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">POST</command>'>
<!ENTITY DELETE '<command xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">DELETE</command>'>

<!ENTITY CHECK  '<inlinemediaobject xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
<imageobject role="fo">
<imagedata fileref="figures/Check_mark_23x20_02.svg"
format="SVG" scale="60"/>
</imageobject>
<imageobject role="html">
<imagedata fileref="../figures/Check_mark_23x20_02.png"
format="PNG" />
</imageobject>
</inlinemediaobject>'>

<!ENTITY ARROW  '<inlinemediaobject xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
<imageobject role="fo">
<imagedata fileref="figures/Arrow_east.svg"
format="SVG" scale="60"/>
</imageobject>
<imageobject role="html">
<imagedata fileref="../figures/Arrow_east.png"
format="PNG" />
</imageobject>
</inlinemediaobject>'>
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="ch_limitations">
    <title>Limitations</title>
    <para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>Quantum overlapping IPs do not work with
                Nova security groups or Nova metadata server:</emphasis>
                Nova was designed assuming that a particular IP address will
                only ever be used by a single VM at any time.  Quantum supports
                overlapping IPs if the allow_overlapping_ips config value is
                set to 'True'.  We default this value to false to prevent
                unintentionally running Nova security groups or metadata
                server with overlapping IPs.  If you enable this flag,
                you must disable both Nova security groups and the Nova
                metadata service.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>No equivalent for nova-network --multi_host
                flag:</emphasis> Nova-network has a model where the L3,
                NAT, and DHCP processing happen on the compute node itself,
                rather than a dedicated networking node.  Quantum does not
                has an equivalent configuration, but is likely to add a similar
                capability in the future.  However, since the nova-network
                multi_host design has some significant limitations in terms of
                deployment scale (limited to a single physical L2) and L3
                forwarding behavior (does not map to a single L3 router for
                traffic between instances on separate networks), the Quantum
                feature may not be an exact match, or may be limited to
                a subnet of all Quantum deployment scenarios.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>Linux network namespace required on
                nodes running quantum-l3-agent or quantum-dhcp-agent:
                </emphasis>.  In order to support overlapping IP addresses,
                the Quantum DHCP and L3 agents uses Linux network namespaces
                by default.  The hosts running these processes must support
                network namespaces. To support network namespaces,
                the following are required:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem><para>Linux kernel 2.6.24 or newer
                  (with CONFIG_NET_NS=y in kernel configuration) and
                  </para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>iproute2 utilities ('ip' command)
                  version 3.1.0 (aka 20111117) or newer
                  </para></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>To check whether your host supports
                namespaces try running the following as root:</para>
                <screen><computeroutput>ip netns create test-ns
ip netns exec test-ns ifconfig</computeroutput></screen>
                <para>If the preceding commands do not produce errors, your
                platform is likely sufficient to use the dhcp-agent or l3-agent
                with namespace.  In our experience, Ubuntu 12.04 or later
                support namespaces as does Fedora 17 and new, but some older
                RHEL platforms do not by default. It may be possible to upgrade
                the iproute2 package on a platform that does not support
                namespaces by default.
            </para>
            <para> If you need to disable namespaces, make sure the quantum.conf
            used by quantum-server has the following setting:</para>
            <screen><computeroutput>allow_overlapping_ips=False</computeroutput></screen>
            <para>and that the dhcp_agent.ini and l3_agent.ini have the
            following setting:</para>
            <screen><computeroutput>use_namespaces=False</computeroutput></screen>

            </listitem>
            <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>No IPv6 support for L3 agent:</emphasis>
            The quantum-l3-agent supports only IPv4 forwarding.  Currently,
            There are no errors provided if you configure IPv6 addresses
            via the API.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>L3 Agent supports limited scale for Quantum Routers:</emphasis>
            The L3 agent polls the Quantum API to learn about changes to L3
            configuration.  If there are a large number of routers or router
            ports, this can lead to heavy load on the database used by a
            Quantum plugin.  The suggested work-around is to increase the
            polling_interval value in l3_agent.ini .  This will increase the
            possible time between when a L3 configuration change happens via
            the API and when it affects data forwarding.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>ZeroMQ support is experimental</emphasis>:
                    Some agents, including quantum-dhcp-agent,
                    quantum-openvswitch-agent, and quantum-linuxbridge-agent
                    use RPC to communicate.  ZeroMQ is an available option
                    in the configuration file, but has not been tested and
                    should be considered experimental.  In particular, there
                    are believed to be issues with ZeroMQ and the dhcp agent.
                    </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>MetaPlugin is experimental</emphasis>:
                This release includes a "MetaPlugin" that is intended to
                support multiple plugins at the same time for different
                API requests, based on the content of those API requests.
                This functionality has not been widely reviewed or tested
                by the core team, and should be considered experimental
                until further validation is performed. </para>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Horizon does not support Routers/Floating IPs
                  with Quantum:</emphasis> Horizon support is limited to
                  operations on Quantum Networks, Subnets, and Ports.
                  Routers and Floating IPs must be configured via CLI.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
            <para>L3 Router Extension does not support IPv6.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>
</chapter>

