<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<preface xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="ch_preface">
    <title>Preface</title>
    <para>OpenStack Networking was created to provide a rich 
        API for defining network connectivity and addressing in the cloud. 
        The service, code-named "Neutron" (formerly known as "Quantum"), gives 
        operators the ability to leverage different networking technologies to 
        power their cloud networking. </para>
    <para>The Board of Directors and Technical Committee members involved in 
        networking-related development and documentation have decided to change 
        the code name to "Neutron", as part of a legal agreement with Quantum 
        Corporation (the owner of the "Quantum" trademark).</para>
    <para>Any references to the previous code name have been removed in this guide wherever
        possible; all configuration files have been changed in the Havana release and this guide 
        updated respectively.</para>
    <section xml:id="Intended_Audience-d1e85">
        <title>Intended Audience</title>
        <para>This guide assists OpenStack administrators in
            leveraging different networking technologies to power
            their cloud networking. This document covers how to
            install, configure, and run OpenStack Networking. </para>
        <para>You must have access to a plugin providing
            the implementation of the OpenStack Networking service. Plugins are
            distributed both within and externally to the OpenStack Networking distribution.
            For more information, see the <link linkend="flexibility">plugin listing</link>.
            </para>
        <para>You should also be familiar with running the OpenStack
            Compute service as described in the operator's documentation. 
            </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="Document_Change_History-d1e118">
        <title>Document Change History</title>
        <para>The most recent changes are described in the table
            below:</para>
        <?rax revhistory?>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="resources">
        <title>Resources</title>
        <para>For more information on OpenStack Networking and other network-related projects,
            see the project page on the OpenStack wiki (<link
                xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Neutron"
                >wiki.openstack.org/Neutron</link>). </para>
        <para>For information about programming against the OpenStack
            Networking API, see the <link
                xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/api/openstack-network/2.0/content/"
                    ><citetitle>OpenStack Networking API Guide
                (v2.0)</citetitle></link>.</para>
        <para>We welcome feedback, comments, and bug reports at <link
                xlink:href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/neutron">bugs.launchpad.net/Neutron</link>. </para>
    </section>
    <?hard-pagebreak?>
</preface>
