<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="section_telemetry-troubleshooting-guide">
  <title>Troubleshoot Telemetry</title>
  <section xml:id="section_telemetry-logging">
    <title>Logging in Telemetry</title>
    <para>The Telemetry module has similar log settings as the other
      OpenStack services. Multiple options are available to change the
      target of logging, the format of the log entries and the log
      levels.</para>
    <para>The log settings can be changed in
      <filename>ceilometer.conf</filename>. The list of configuration
      options are listed in the logging configuration options table in
      the <link xlink:href=
      "http://docs.openstack.org/juno/config-reference/content/ch_configuring-openstack-telemetry.html">
      Telemetry section</link> in the <citetitle>OpenStack Configuration
      Reference</citetitle>.</para>
    <para>By default <literal>stderr</literal> is used as standard
      output for the log messages. It can be changed to either a log file
      or syslog. The <option>debug</option> and <option>verbose</option>
      options are also set to false in the default settings, the default
      log levels of the corresponding modules can be found in the table
      referred above.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section_telemetry-order-of-service-startup">
    <title>Recommended order of starting services</title>
    <para>As it can be seen in <link xlink:href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/devstack/+bug/1355809">
      Bug 1355809</link>, the wrong ordering of service startup can result
      in data loss.</para>
    <para>When the services are started for the first time or in line with
      the message queue service restart, it takes time while the
      <systemitem class="service">ceilometer-collector</systemitem> services
      establishes the connection and joins or rejoins to the configured
      exchanges. Therefore, if the <systemitem class="service">
      ceilometer-agent-compute</systemitem>, <systemitem class="service">
      ceilometer-agent-central</systemitem> and the <systemitem class="service">
      ceilometer-agent-notification</systemitem> services are started before
      <systemitem class="service">ceilometer-collector</systemitem>, it can
      loose some messages sent by these services, while connecting to the
      message queue service.</para>
    <para>The possibility of this issue to happen is higher, when the polling
      interval is set to a relatively short period. In order to avoid this
      situation, the recommended order of service startup is to start or restart the
      <systemitem class="service">ceilometer-collector</systemitem> service
      after the message queue. All the other Telemetry services should
      be started or restarted after and the <systemitem class="service">
      ceilometer-agent-compute</systemitem> should be the last in the
      sequence, as this component emits metering messages in order to send
      the samples to the collector.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section_telemetry-notification-agent">
    <title>Notification agent</title>
    <para>In the Icehouse release of OpenStack a new service was introduced
      to be responsible for consuming notifications that are coming from
      other OpenStack services.</para>
    <para>If the <systemitem class="service">ceilometer-agent-notification</systemitem>
      service is not installed and started, samples originating from
      notifications will not be generated. In case of the lack
      of notification based samples, the state of this service and the log
      file of Telemetry should be checked first.</para>
    <para>For the list of meters that are originated from notifications, see
      the <link xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/developer/ceilometer/measurements.html">
      Telemetry Measurements Reference</link>.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section_telemetry-auth-url-ports">
    <title>Recommended <option>auth_url</option> to be used</title>
    <para>When using the commandline client of Telemetry, the credentials
      and the <option>os_auth_url</option> has to be set in order to
      provide the possibility to the client to authenticate against
      OpenStack Identity. For further details about the credentials
      that has to be provided see the
      <link xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/developer/python-ceilometerclient/">
       Python API</link> reference of Telemetry.</para>
    <para>The service catalog provided by OpenStack Identity contains the
      available URLs that are available for authentication.
      The URLs contain different <parameter>port</parameter>s, based on
      that the type of the given URL is <literal>public</literal>,
      <literal>internal</literal> or <literal>admin</literal>.</para>
    <para>OpenStack Identity is about to change API version from v2 to v3.
      The <literal>adminURL</literal> endpoint (which is available via the
      port: <literal>35357</literal>) supports only the v3 version,
      while the other two supports both.</para>
    <para>The commandline client of Telemetry is not adapted to the v3 version
      of the OpenStack Identity API. If the <literal>adminURL</literal>
      is used as <option>os_auth_url</option>, the <command>ceilometer</command>
      command results in the following error message:
      <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>ceilometer meter-list</userinput>
<?db-font-size 75%?><computeroutput>Unable to determine the Keystone version to authenticate with using the given
auth_url: http://10.0.2.15:35357/v2.0</computeroutput></screen></para>
    <para>Therefore when specifying the <option>os_auth_url</option>
      parameter on the command line or by using environment variable, use
      the <literal>internalURL</literal> or <literal>publicURL</literal>.</para>
    <para>For more details check the bug report
      <link xlink:href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/python-ceilometerclient/+bug/1351841">
      Bug 1351841</link>.</para>
  </section>
</section>
