<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="basic-install_architecture">
    <title>Architecture</title>
           <figure><title>Physical network diagram</title> <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata width="6in" fileref="figures/Quantum-PhysNet-Diagram.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                        <!-- Edit link: http://docs.google.com/drawings/d/19qtlB_EeG9TM_jpeX5DprHRd9ShngXgfpt_t5mlrUMo/edit -->
            </mediaobject></figure>
    <para>This guide assists administrators with the process of creating the following types of OpenStack servers:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">The Cloud
                    Controller</emphasis>. Provides all functionality
                of the cloud except actually hosting virtual machines
                or providing network services. See the "Compute Node"
                and "Network Controller" for details about those
                roles. This server will host the OpenStack Image
                Service, the OpenStack Block Storage Service, the
                OpenStack Identity Service, and the OpenStack
                Dashboard. It will also run portions of the OpenStack
                Compute service such as the API server, the scheduler,
                conductor, console authenticator, and VNC service.
                Finally, it hosts the API endpoint for the OpenStack
                Network service. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">The Network
                    Controller</emphasis>. Provides the bulk of the
                OpenStack Network services such as DHCP, layer 2
                switching, layer 3 routing, floating IPs (which this
                guide does not configure), and metadata connectivity. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Compute Node</emphasis>. Runs
                the OpenStack Compute service as well as the OpenStack
                Network service agent (in this case, the Open vSwitch
                plugin agent). This server also manages an
                OpenStack-compatible hypervisor such as KVM or Xen.
                This server will host the actual virtual machines
                (instances). </para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <note><para>OpenStack provides great flexibility with regard to how its
        individual services can be hosted. For example, the services
        that run on the Network Controller can easily be installed on
        the Cloud Controller. As another example, the OpenStack Image
        service can be installed on its own server (or many servers to
        provide a more highly available service). </para>
    </note>
    <para>With regard to cloud networking, a standard OpenStack
        Network setup can have up to four distinct physical data
        center networks. Note that these networks can be combined and
        re-used. For example, the Management, Data, and API networks
        are commonly the same network. For simplicity, this will be
        done in this guide.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Management
                    network</emphasis>. Used for internal
                communication between OpenStack components. The IP
                addresses on this network should be reachable only
                within the data center.  </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Data
                    network</emphasis>. Used for VM data communication
                within the cloud deployment. The IP addressing
                requirements of this network depend on the OpenStack
                Networking plugin in use.  </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">External
                    network</emphasis>. Provides VMs with Internet
                access in some deployment scenarios. The IP addresses
                on this network should be reachable by anyone on the
                Internet.  </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">API
                network</emphasis>. Exposes all OpenStack APIs,
                including the OpenStack Networking API, to
                tenants. The IP addresses on this network should be
                reachable by anyone on the Internet. This may be the
                same network as the external network, as it is
                possible to create a quantum subnet for the external
                network that uses IP allocation ranges to use only
                less than the full range of IP addresses in an IP
                block. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
</chapter>
