<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<preface xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="basic-install_intro">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Preface</title>
    <para>This document helps you deploy OpenStack Grizzly for
        development purposes with <phrase os="ubuntu">Ubuntu 12.04 LTS
            (using the Ubuntu Cloud Archive)</phrase><phrase
            os="rhel;centos;fedora">Fedora 18 (using the
            fedora-openstack-grizzly repo)</phrase>.</para>
    <note os="ubuntu">
        <para>The Grizzly version is available on the current
            Ubuntu development series, which is 13.04 (Raring
            Ringtail) and the most recent LTS (Long Term Support)
            version which is 12.04 (Precise Pangolin), via the
            Ubuntu Cloud Archive. At this time, there are not
            packages available for 12.10. </para>
    </note>
    <para>We are going to install a three-node setup with one
        controller, one network and one compute node.</para>
    <para>Of course, you can setup as many computes nodes as you want. 
        Use this document to learn to install a testing infrastructure.</para> 
    <para>The OpenStack configuration files contain several commented
        options. These options specify the default setting. You only
        need to uncomment these lines if you are changing the setting
        to a non-default value. Additionally, the only options that
        will be shown throughout this guide are options that are being
        modified from their default value. </para>   
    <para>Finally, please be aware that the use of <literal>password</literal> 
        as a password throughout this guide is for simplicity and
        testing purposes. Please ensure you use proper passwords when 
        configuring your OpenStack environment in production.
    </para>
    <para>At this time, this guide does not cover floating IPs.</para> 
    <section xml:id="doc_change_history">
        <title>Document Change History</title>
        <para>This version of the guide replaces and
            obsoletes all previous versions. The following table
            describes the latest changes:
            The most recent
            changes:</para>
        <?rax revhistory?>
        <!-- Table generated in output from revision element in the book element -->
    </section>
</preface>

