<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="ch_admin-openstack-orchestration">
  <title>Orchestration</title>
  <para>Orchestration is an orchestration engine that provides possibility
      to launch multiple composite cloud applications based on templates in
      the form of text files that can be treated like code. A native
      Heat Orchestration Template (HOT) format is evolving, but it also
      endeavours to provide compatibility with the AWS CloudFormation template
      format, so that many existing CloudFormation templates can be launched
      on OpenStack.</para>
  <section xml:id="section_orchestration-introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>Orchestration is a tool for orchestrating clouds that
        automatically configures and deploys resources in stacks.
        Such deployments can be simple — like deploying WordPress on Ubuntu
        with an SQL back-end. And they can be quite complex, like launching
        a group of servers that autoscale: starting and stopping based on
        realtime CPU loading information from Telemetry module.</para>
    <para>Orchestration stacks are defined with templates, which are
        non-procedural documents describing tasks in terms of resources,
        parameters, inputs, constraints and dependencies. When
        Orchestration module was originally introduced, it worked with
        AWS CloudFormation templates, which are in JSON format.</para>
    <para>Now, Orchestration also executes HOT (Heat Orchestration
        Template) templates, written in YAML: a terse notation that loosely
        follows Python/Ruby-type structural conventions (colons, returns,
        indentation) so it’s more easily to write, parse, grep, generate with
        tools, and maintain with source-code management systems.</para>
    <para>Orchestration can be accessed via the CLI, and using RESTful queries.
        Orchestration module provides both an OpenStack-native ReST API
        and a CloudFormation-compatible Query API. Orchestration is also
        integrated with OpenStack dashboard in order to launching stacks from
        templates through web-interface.</para>
    <para>For more details how to use Orchestration module command-line see
        <link xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/cli-reference/content/">
            OpenStack Command line interface reference</link>
    </para>
  </section>
  <xi:include href="orchestration/section_orchestration-auth-model.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="orchestration/section_orchestration-stack-domain-users.xml"/>
</chapter>
