<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="ch_admin-openstack-telemetry">
  <title>Telemetry</title>
  <para>The Telemetry module is the metering service in OpenStack.</para>
  <section xml:id="section_telemetry-introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>Even in the cloud industry, providers must use a multi-step
      process for billing. The required steps to bill for usage in a
      cloud environment are metering, rating, and billing. Because the
      provider's requirements may be far too specific for a shared
      solution, rating and billing solutions cannot be designed a
      common module that satisfies all. Providing users with measurements
      on cloud services is required to meet the "measured service"
      definition of cloud computing.</para>
    <para>The Telemetry module was originally designed to support billing
      systems for OpenStack cloud resources. This project only covers the
      metering portion of the required processing for billing. This module
      collects information about the system and stores it in the form of
      samples in order to provide data about anything that can be billed.
    </para>
    <para>The list of meters is continuously growing, which makes it
      possible to use the data collected by Telemetry for different
      purposes, other than billing. For example, the autoscaling feature
      in the Orchestration module can be triggered by alarms this module
      sets and then gets notified within Telemetry.</para>
    <para>The sections in this document contain information about the
      architecture and usage of Telemetry. The first section contains a
      brief summary about the system architecture used in a typical
      OpenStack deployment. The second section describes the data collection
      mechanisms. You can also read about alarming to understand how alarm
      definitions can be posted to Telemetry and what actions can happen if
      an alarm is raised. The last section contains a troubleshooting
      guide, which mentions error situations and possible solutions for the
      problems.</para>
    <para>You can retrieve the collected samples three different ways: with
      the REST API, with the command line interface, or with the Metering tab
      on an OpenStack dashboard.</para>
  </section>
  <xi:include href="telemetry/section_telemetry-system-architecture.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="telemetry/section_telemetry-data-collection.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="telemetry/section_telemetry-data-retrieval.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="telemetry/section_telemetry-alarms.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="telemetry/section_telemetry-troubleshooting-guide.xml"/>
</chapter>
