<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xml:id="section_ts_cinder_config" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="1.0" linkend="section_ts_cinder_config">
    <title xml:id="ts_block_config">Troubleshooting your Block Storage Configuration</title>
    <para>This section is intended to help solve some basic and common errors that are encountered
        during setup and configuration of  the Cinder block storage service. The focus here is on
        failed creation of volumes. The most important thing to know is where to look in case of a
        failure.</para>
    <para>There are two log files that are especially helpful for solving volume creation failures,
        the <systemitem class="service">cinder-api</systemitem> log and the <systemitem
            class="service">cinder-volume</systemitem> log. The <systemitem class="service"
            >cinder-api</systemitem> log is useful for determining if you have endpoint or
        connectivity issues. If you send a request to create a volume and it fails, it's a good idea
        to look in the <systemitem class="service">cinder-api</systemitem> log first and see if the
        request even made it to the Cinder service. If the request is logged and there are no errors
        or trace-backs, then you can check the <systemitem class="service"
            >cinder-volume</systemitem> log for errors or trace-backs.</para>
    <para>
        <note>
            <para>Create commands are listed in the <systemitem class="service"
                    >cinder-api</systemitem> log.</para>
        </note>
    </para>
    <para>Here are some common issues discovered during configuration, and some suggested solutions
        .</para>
    <para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Isusues with <literal>state_path</literal> and <literal>volumes_dir</literal>
                    settings.</para>
                <para>Cinder uses <command>tgtd</command> as the default iscsi helper and implements
                    persistent targets. This means that in the case of a tgt restart or even a node
                    reboot your existing volumes on that node will be restored automatically with
                    their original IQN.</para>
                <para>In order to make this possible the iSCSI target information needs to be stored
                    in a file on creation that can be queried in case of restart of the tgt daemon.
                    By default, Cinder uses a <literal>state_path</literal> variable, which if
                    installing with Yum or APT should be set to
                        <filename>/var/lib/cinder/</filename>. The next part is the
                        <literal>volumes_dir</literal> variable, by default this just simply appends
                    a "<literal>volumes</literal>" directory to the <literal>state_path</literal>.
                    The result is a file-tree <filename>/var/lib/cinder/volumes/</filename>.</para>
                <para>While this should all be handled by the installer, it can go wrong. If you are
                    having trouble creating volumes and this directory does not exist you should see
                    an error message in the <systemitem class="service">cinder-volume</systemitem>
                    log indicating that the <literal>volumes_dir</literal> doesn't exist, and it
                    should give you information to specify what path exactly it was looking
                    for.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The persistent tgt include file.</para>
                <para>Along with the <literal>volumes_dir</literal> mentioned above, the iSCSI
                    target driver also needs to be configured to look in the correct place for the
                    persist files. This is a simple entry in <filename>/etc/tgt/conf.d</filename>,
                    and you should have created this when you went through the install guide. If you
                    haven't or you're running into issues, verify that you have a file
                        <filename>/etc/tgt/conf.d/cinder.conf</filename>.</para>
                <para>If the file is not there, you can create with the following
                    command:<programlisting>
sudo sh -c "echo 'include /var/lib/cinder/volumes/*' >> /etc/tgt/conf.d/cinder.conf"
                    </programlisting></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>No sign of attach call in the <systemitem class="service"
                        >cinder-api</systemitem> log.</para>
                <para>This is most likely going to be a minor adjustment to your
                        <filename>nova.conf</filename> file. Make sure that your
                        <filename>nova.conf</filename> has the following
                    entry:<programlisting>
volume_api_class=nova.volume.cinder.API
        </programlisting></para>
                <caution>
                    <para>Make certain that you explicitly set <filename>enabled_apis</filename>
                        because the default will include
                        <filename>osapi_volume</filename>:<programlisting>
enabled_apis=ec2,osapi_compute,metadata
    </programlisting>
                    </para>
                </caution>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Failed to create iscsi target error in the
                        <filename>cinder-volume.log</filename> file.</para>
                <programlisting language="bash">2013-03-12 01:35:43 1248 TRACE cinder.openstack.common.rpc.amqp ISCSITargetCreateFailed: Failed to create iscsi target for volume volume-137641b2-af72-4a2f-b243-65fdccd38780.
</programlisting>
                <para>You may see this error in <filename>cinder-volume.log</filename> after trying
                    to create a volume that is 1 GB. To fix this issue:</para>
                <para>Change content of the <filename>/etc/tgt/targets.conf</filename> from "include
                    /etc/tgt/conf.d/*.conf" to: include /etc/tgt/conf.d/cinder_tgt.conf:</para>
                <programlisting language="bash">
            include /etc/tgt/conf.d/cinder_tgt.conf
            include /etc/tgt/conf.d/cinder.conf
            default-driver iscsi</programlisting>
                <para>Then restart tgt and <literal>cinder-*</literal> services so they pick up the
                    new configuration.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>
</section>
