<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0"
    xml:id="ch_introduction-to-openstack-object-storage-monitoring">
    <!-- ... Based on a blog, should be replaced with original material... -->
    <title>Object Storage monitoring</title>
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <para>Excerpted from a blog post by <link
            xlink:href="http://swiftstack.com/blog/2012/04/11/swift-monitoring-with-statsd"
            >Darrell Bishop</link></para>
    <para>An OpenStack Object Storage cluster is a complicated beast—a
        collection of many daemons across many nodes, all working
        together. With so many “moving parts” it’s important to be
        able to tell what’s going on inside the cluster. Tracking
        server-level metrics like CPU utilization, load, memory
        consumption, disk usage and utilization, etc. is necessary,
        but not sufficient. We need to know what the different daemons
        are doing on each server. What’s the volume of object
        replication on node8? How long is it taking? Are there errors?
        If so, when did they happen?</para>
    <para>In such a complex ecosystem, it’s no surprise that there are
        multiple approaches to getting the answers to these kinds of
        questions. Let’s examine some of the existing approaches to
        OpenStack Object Storage monitoring.</para>
    <section xml:id="monitoring-swiftrecon">
        <title>Swift Recon</title>
        <para>The <link
                xlink:href="http://swift.openstack.org/admin_guide.html#cluster-telemetry-and-monitoring"
                >Swift Recon middleware</link> can provide general
            machine stats (load average, socket stats,
                <code>/proc/meminfo</code> contents, etc.) as well as
            Swift-specific metrics:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>The MD5 sum of each ring file.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The most recent object replication time.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Count of each type of quarantined file: account,
                    container, or object.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Count of “async_pendings” (deferred container
                    updates) on disk.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>Swift Recon is middleware installed in the object
            server’s pipeline and takes one required option: a local
            cache directory. Tracking of async_pendings requires an
            additional cron job per object server. Data is then
            accessed by sending HTTP requests to the object server
            directly, or by using the swift-recon command-line
            tool.</para>
        <para>There are some good Object Storage cluster stats in
            there, but the general server metrics overlap with
            existing server monitoring systems and to get the
            Swift-specific metrics into a monitoring system, they must
            be polled. Swift Recon is essentially acting as a
            middle-man metrics collector. The process actually feeding
            metrics to your stats system, like collectd, gmond, etc.,
            is probably already running on the storage node. So it
            could either talk to Swift Recon or just collect the
            metrics itself.</para>
        <para>There’s an <link
                xlink:href="https://review.openstack.org/#change,6074"
                >upcoming update</link> to Swift Recon which broadens
            support to the account and container servers. The
            auditors, replicators, and updaters can also report
            statistics, but only for the most recent run.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="monitoring-swift-informant">
        <title>Swift-Informant</title>
        <para>Florian Hines developed the <link
                xlink:href="http://pandemicsyn.posterous.com/swift-informant-statsd-getting-realtime-telem"
                >Swift-Informant middleware</link> to get real-time
            visibility into Object Storage client requests. It sits in
            the proxy server’s pipeline and after each request to the
            proxy server, sends three metrics to a <link
                xlink:href="http://codeascraft.etsy.com/2011/02/15/measure-anything-measure-everything/"
                >StatsD</link> server:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>A counter increment for a metric like <code>obj.GET.200</code> or
                        <code>cont.PUT.404</code>.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Timing data for a metric like <code>acct.GET.200</code> or <code>obj.GET.200</code>. [The README says the metrics will look
                    like <code>duration.acct.GET.200</code>, but I don’t see
                    the “duration” in the code. I’m not sure what Etsy’s server does, but our StatsD
                    server turns timing metrics into 5 derivative metrics with new segments
                    appended, so it probably works as coded. The first metric above would turn into
                        <code>acct.GET.200.lower</code>, <code>acct.GET.200.upper</code>, <code>acct.GET.200.mean</code>, <code>acct.GET.200.upper_90</code>, and <code>acct.GET.200.count</code>]</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>A counter increase by the bytes transferred for a metric like <code>tfer.obj.PUT.201</code>.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>This is good for getting a feel for the quality of
            service clients are experiencing with the timing metrics,
            as well as getting a feel for the volume of the various
            permutations of request server type, command, and response
            code. Swift-Informant also requires no change to core
            Object Storage code since it is implemented as middleware.
            However, because of this, it gives you no insight into the
            workings of the cluster past the proxy server. If one
            storage node’s responsiveness degrades for some reason,
            you’ll only see that some of your requests are bad—either
            as high latency or error status codes. You won’t know
            exactly why or where that request tried to go. Maybe the
            container server in question was on a good node, but the
            object server was on a different, poorly-performing
            node.</para>

    </section>
    <section xml:id="monitoring-statsdlog">
        <title>Statsdlog</title>
        <para>Florian’s <link
                xlink:href="https://github.com/pandemicsyn/statsdlog"
                >Statsdlog</link> project increments StatsD counters
            based on logged events. Like Swift-Informant, it is also
            non-intrusive, but statsdlog can track events from all
            Object Storage daemons, not just proxy-server. The daemon
            listens to a UDP stream of syslog messages and StatsD
            counters are incremented when a log line matches a regular
            expression. Metric names are mapped to regex match
            patterns in a JSON file, allowing flexible configuration
            of what metrics are extracted from the log stream.</para>
        <para>Currently, only the first matching regex triggers a
            StatsD counter increment, and the counter is always
            incremented by 1. There’s no way to increment a counter by
            more than one or send timing data to StatsD based on the
            log line content. The tool could be extended to handle
            more metrics per line and data extraction, including
            timing data. But even then, there would still be a
            coupling between the log textual format and the log
            parsing regexes, which would themselves be more complex in
            order to support multiple matches per line and data
            extraction. Also, log processing introduces a delay
            between the triggering event and sending the data to
            StatsD. We would prefer to increment error counters where
            they occur, send timing data as soon as it is known, avoid
            coupling between a log string and a parsing regex, and not
            introduce a time delay between events and sending data to
            StatsD. And that brings us to the next method of gathering
            Object Storage operational metrics.</para>
    </section>
 <section xml:id="monitoring-statsD">
     <title>Swift StatsD Logging</title>
     <para><link xlink:href="http://codeascraft.etsy.com/2011/02/15/measure-anything-measure-everything/">StatsD</link> was designed for application code to be deeply instrumented; metrics are sent in real-time by the code which just noticed something or did something. The overhead of sending a metric is extremely low: a <code>sendto</code> of one UDP packet. If that overhead is still too high, the StatsD client library can send only a random portion of samples and StatsD will approximate the actual number when flushing metrics upstream.</para>
     <para>To avoid the problems inherent with middleware-based
            monitoring and after-the-fact log processing, the sending
            of StatsD metrics is integrated into Object Storage
            itself. The <link
                xlink:href="https://review.openstack.org/#change,6058"
                >submitted change set</link> currently reports 124
            metrics across 15 Object Storage daemons and the tempauth
            middleware. Details of the metrics tracked are in the
                <link
                    xlink:href="http://swift.openstack.org/admin_guide.html"
                >Swift Administration Guide</link>.</para>
     <para>The sending of metrics is integrated with the logging framework. To enable, configure <code>log_statsd_host</code> in the relevant config file. You can also specify the port and a default sample rate. The specified default sample rate is used unless a specific call to a statsd logging method (see the list below) overrides it. Currently, no logging calls override the sample rate, but it’s conceivable that some metrics may require accuracy (sample_rate == 1) while others may not.</para>
     <literallayout class="monospaced">[DEFAULT]
     ...
log_statsd_host = 127.0.0.1
log_statsd_port = 8125
log_statsd_default_sample_rate = 1</literallayout>
     <para>Then the LogAdapter object returned by <code>get_logger()</code>, usually stored in <code>self.logger</code>, has the following new methods:</para>
     <itemizedlist>
         <listitem><para><code>set_statsd_prefix(self, prefix)</code> Sets the client library’s stat prefix value which gets prepended to every metric. The default prefix is the “name” of the logger (eg. “object-server”, “container-auditor”, etc.). This is currently used to turn “proxy-server” into one of “proxy-server.Account”, “proxy-server.Container”, or “proxy-server.Object” as soon as the Controller object is determined and instantiated for the request.</para></listitem>
         <listitem><para><code>update_stats(self, metric, amount, sample_rate=1)</code> Increments the supplied metric by the given amount. This is used when you need to add or subtract more that one from a counter, like incrementing “suffix.hashes” by the number of computed hashes in the object replicator.</para></listitem>
         <listitem><para><code>increment(self, metric, sample_rate=1)</code> Increments the given counter metric by one.</para></listitem>
         <listitem><para><code>decrement(self, metric, sample_rate=1)</code> Lowers the given counter metric by one.</para></listitem>
         <listitem><para><code>timing(self, metric, timing_ms, sample_rate=1)</code> Record that the given metric took the supplied number of milliseconds.</para></listitem>
         <listitem><para><code>timing_since(self, metric, orig_time, sample_rate=1)</code> Convenience method to record a timing metric whose value is “now” minus an existing timestamp.</para></listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
        <para>Note that these logging methods may safely be called
            anywhere you have a logger object. If StatsD logging has
            not been configured, the methods are no-ops. This avoids
            messy conditional logic each place a metric is recorded.
            Here’s two example usages of the new logging
            methods:</para>
     <programlisting language="bash"># swift/obj/replicator.py
def update(self, job):
    # ...
    begin = time.time()
    try:
        hashed, local_hash = tpool.execute(tpooled_get_hashes, job['path'],
                do_listdir=(self.replication_count % 10) == 0,
                reclaim_age=self.reclaim_age)
        # See tpooled_get_hashes "Hack".
        if isinstance(hashed, BaseException):
            raise hashed
        self.suffix_hash += hashed
        self.logger.update_stats('suffix.hashes', hashed)
        # ...
    finally:
        self.partition_times.append(time.time() - begin)
        self.logger.timing_since('partition.update.timing', begin)</programlisting>
        <programlisting language="bash"># swift/container/updater.py
def process_container(self, dbfile):
    # ...
    start_time = time.time()
    # ...
        for event in events:
            if 200 &lt;= event.wait() &lt; 300:
                successes += 1
            else:
                failures += 1
        if successes > failures:
            self.logger.increment('successes')
            # ...
        else:
            self.logger.increment('failures')
            # ...
        # Only track timing data for attempted updates:
        self.logger.timing_since('timing', start_time)
    else:
        self.logger.increment('no_changes')
        self.no_changes += 1</programlisting>
     <para>The development team of StatsD wanted to use the <link
                xlink:href="https://github.com/sivy/py-statsd"
                >pystatsd</link> client library (not to be confused
            with a <link
                xlink:href="https://github.com/sivy/py-statsd"
                >similar-looking project</link> also hosted on
            GitHub), but the released version on PyPi was missing two
            desired features the latest version in GitHub had: the
            ability to configure a metrics prefix in the client object
            and a convenience method for sending timing data between
            “now” and a “start” timestamp you already have. So they
            just implemented a simple StatsD client library from
            scratch with the same interface. This has the nice fringe
            benefit of not introducing another external library
            dependency into Object Storage.</para>
    </section>
</section>
