<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="section_networking-scenarios">
    <title>Networking scenarios</title>
    <para>This chapter describes two networking scenarios and how the Open vSwitch plug-in and the
        Linux Bridge plug-in implement these scenarios.</para>
    <section xml:id="under_the_hood_openvswitch">
        <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
        <title>Open vSwitch</title>
        <para>This section describes how the Open vSwitch plug-in implements the Networking
            abstractions.</para>
        <section xml:id="under_the_hood_openvswitch_configuration">
            <title>Configuration</title>
            <para>This example uses VLAN segmentation on the switches to isolate tenant networks.
                This configuration labels the physical network associated with the public network as
                    <literal>physnet1</literal>, and the physical network associated with the data
                network as <literal>physnet2</literal>, which leads to the following configuration
                options in <filename>ovs_neutron_plugin.ini</filename>:</para>
            <programlisting language="ini">[ovs]
tenant_network_type = vlan
network_vlan_ranges = physnet1,physnet2:100:110
integration_bridge = br-int
bridge_mappings = physnet2:br-eth1</programlisting>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="under_the_hood_openvswitch_scenario1">
            <title>Scenario 1: one tenant, two networks, one router</title>
            <para>The first scenario has two private networks (<literal>net01</literal>, and
                    <literal>net02</literal>), each with one subnet
                    (<literal>net01_subnet01</literal>: 192.168.101.0/24,
                    <literal>net02_subnet01</literal>, 192.168.102.0/24). Both private networks are
                attached to a router that connects them to the public network
                (10.64.201.0/24).</para>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../../common/figures/under-the-hood-scenario-1.png"
                        contentwidth="6in"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            <para>Under the <literal>service</literal> tenant, create the shared router, define the
                public network, and set it as the default gateway of the
                router<screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>tenant=$(keystone tenant-list | awk '/service/ {print $2}')</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron router-create router01</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron net-create --tenant-id $tenant public01 \
          --provider:network_type flat \
          --provider:physical_network physnet1 \
          --router:external True</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron subnet-create --tenant-id $tenant --name public01_subnet01 \
          --gateway 10.64.201.254 public01 10.64.201.0/24 --disable-dhcp</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron router-gateway-set router01 public01</userinput></screen></para>
            <para>Under the <literal>demo</literal> user tenant, create the private network
                    <literal>net01</literal> and corresponding subnet, and connect it to the
                    <literal>router01</literal> router. Configure it to use VLAN ID 101 on the
                physical
                switch.<screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>tenant=$(keystone tenant-list|awk '/demo/ {print $2}'</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron net-create --tenant-id $tenant net01 \
          --provider:network_type vlan \
          --provider:physical_network physnet2 \
          --provider:segmentation_id 101</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron subnet-create --tenant-id $tenant --name net01_subnet01 net01 192.168.101.0/24</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron router-interface-add router01 net01_subnet01</userinput></screen></para>
            <para>Similarly, for <literal>net02</literal>, using VLAN ID 102 on the physical
                switch:<screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron net-create --tenant-id $tenant net02 \
          --provider:network_type vlan \
          --provider:physical_network physnet2 \
          --provider:segmentation_id 102</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron subnet-create --tenant-id $tenant --name net02_subnet01 net02 192.168.102.0/24</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron router-interface-add router01 net02_subnet01</userinput></screen></para>
            <section xml:id="under_the_hood_openvswitch_scenario1_compute">
                <title>Scenario 1: Compute host config</title>
                <para>The following figure shows how to configure various Linux networking devices
                    on the compute host:</para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata
                            fileref="../../common/figures/under-the-hood-scenario-1-ovs-compute.png"
                            contentwidth="6in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
                <simplesect>
                    <title>Types of network devices</title>
                    <note>
                        <para>There are four distinct type of virtual networking devices: TAP
                            devices, veth pairs, Linux bridges, and Open vSwitch bridges. For an
                            Ethernet frame to travel from <literal>eth0</literal> of virtual machine
                                <literal>vm01</literal> to the physical network, it must pass
                            through nine devices inside of the host: TAP <literal>vnet0</literal>,
                            Linux bridge <literal>qbr<replaceable>NNN</replaceable></literal>, veth
                            pair <literal>(qvb<replaceable>NNN</replaceable>,
                                    qvo<replaceable>NNN</replaceable>)</literal>, Open vSwitch
                            bridge <literal>br-int</literal>, veth pair <literal>(int-br-eth1,
                                phy-br-eth1)</literal>, and, finally, the physical network interface
                            card <literal>eth1</literal>.</para>
                    </note>
                    <para>A <emphasis role="italic">TAP device</emphasis>, such as
                            <literal>vnet0</literal> is how hypervisors such as KVM and Xen
                        implement a virtual network interface card (typically called a VIF or vNIC).
                        An Ethernet frame sent to a TAP device is received by the guest operating
                        system.</para>
                    <para>A <emphasis role="italic">veth pair</emphasis> is a pair of directly
                        connected virtual network interfaces. An Ethernet frame sent to one end of a
                        veth pair is received by the other end of a veth pair. Networking uses veth
                        pairs as virtual patch cables to make connections between virtual
                        bridges.</para>
                    <para>A <emphasis role="italic">Linux bridge</emphasis> behaves like a simple
                        MAC learning switch: you can connect multiple (physical or virtual) network
                        interfaces devices to a Linux bridge. The Linux bridge uses a MAC caching
                        table to record which interface on the bridge is used to communicate with a
                        host on the link. For any Ethernet frames that come in from one interface
                        attached to the bridge, the host MAC address and port on which the frame was
                        received is recorded in the MAC caching table for a limited time. When the
                        bridge needs to forward a frame, it will check to see if the frame's
                        destination MAC address is recorded in the table. If so, the Linux bridge
                        forwards the frame through only that port. If not, the frame is flooded to
                        all network ports in the bridge, with the exception of the port where the
                        frame was received.</para>
                    <para>An <emphasis role="italic">Open vSwitch bridge</emphasis> behaves like a
                        virtual switch: network interface devices connect to Open vSwitch bridge's
                        ports, and the ports can be configured much like a physical switch's ports,
                        including VLAN configurations.</para>
                </simplesect>
                <simplesect>
                    <title>Integration bridge</title>
                    <para>The <literal>br-int</literal> Open vSwitch bridge is the integration
                        bridge: all guests running on the compute host connect to this bridge.
                        Networking implements isolation across these guests by configuring the
                            <literal>br-int</literal> ports.</para>
                </simplesect>
                <simplesect>
                    <title>Physical connectivity bridge</title>
                    <para>The <literal>br-eth1</literal> bridge provides connectivity to the
                        physical network interface card, <literal>eth1</literal>. It connects to the
                        integration bridge by a veth pair: <literal>(int-br-eth1,
                            phy-br-eth1)</literal>.</para>
                </simplesect>
                <simplesect>
                    <title>VLAN translation</title>
                    <para>In this example, net01 and net02 have VLAN ids of 1 and 2, respectively.
                        However, the physical network in our example only supports VLAN IDs in the
                        range 101 through 110. The Open vSwitch agent is responsible for configuring
                        flow rules on <literal>br-int</literal> and <literal>br-eth1</literal> to do
                        VLAN translation. When <literal>br-eth1</literal> receives a frame marked
                        with VLAN ID 1 on the port associated with <literal>phy-br-eth1</literal>,
                        it modifies the VLAN ID in the frame to 101. Similarly, when
                            <literal>br-int</literal> receives a frame marked with VLAN ID 101 on
                        the port associated with <literal>int-br-eth1</literal>, it modifies the
                        VLAN ID in the frame to 1.</para>
                </simplesect>
                <simplesect>
                    <title>Security groups: iptables and Linux bridges</title>
                    <para>Ideally, the TAP device <literal>vnet0</literal> would be connected
                        directly to the integration bridge, <literal>br-int</literal>.
                        Unfortunately, this isn't possible because of how OpenStack security groups
                        are currently implemented. OpenStack uses iptables rules on the TAP devices
                        such as <literal>vnet0</literal> to implement security groups, and Open
                        vSwitch is not compatible with iptables rules that are applied directly on
                        TAP devices that are connected to an Open vSwitch port.</para>
                    <para>Networking uses an extra Linux bridge and a veth pair as a workaround for
                        this issue. Instead of connecting <literal>vnet0</literal> to an Open
                        vSwitch bridge, it is connected to a Linux bridge,
                                <literal>qbr<replaceable>XXX</replaceable></literal>. This bridge is
                        connected to the integration bridge, <literal>br-int</literal>, through the
                                <literal>(qvb<replaceable>XXX</replaceable>,
                                qvo<replaceable>XXX</replaceable>)</literal> veth pair.</para>
                </simplesect>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="under_the_hood_openvswitch_scenario1_network">
                <title>Scenario 1: Network host config</title>
                <para>The network host runs the neutron-openvswitch-plugin-agent, the
                    neutron-dhcp-agent, neutron-l3-agent, and neutron-metadata-agent
                    services.</para>
                <para>On the network host, assume that eth0 is connected to the external network,
                    and eth1 is connected to the data network, which leads to the following
                    configuration in the <filename>ovs_neutron_plugin.ini</filename> file:</para>
                <programlisting language="bash">[ovs]
tenant_network_type = vlan
network_vlan_ranges = physnet1,physnet2:101:110
integration_bridge = br-int
bridge_mappings = physnet1:br-ex,physnet2:br-eth1</programlisting>
                <para>The following figure shows the network devices on the network host:</para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata
                            fileref="../../common/figures/under-the-hood-scenario-1-ovs-network.png"
                            contentwidth="6in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
                <para>As on the compute host, there is an Open vSwitch integration bridge
                        (<literal>br-int</literal>) and an Open vSwitch bridge connected to the data
                    network (<literal>br-eth1</literal>), and the two are connected by a veth pair,
                    and the neutron-openvswitch-plugin-agent configures the ports on both switches
                    to do VLAN translation.</para>
                <para>An additional Open vSwitch bridge, <literal>br-ex</literal>, connects to the
                    physical interface that is connected to the external network. In this example,
                    that physical interface is <literal>eth0</literal>.</para>
                <note>
                    <para>While the integration bridge and the external bridge are connected by a
                        veth pair <literal>(int-br-ex, phy-br-ex)</literal>, this example uses layer
                        3 connectivity to route packets from the internal networks to the public
                        network: no packets traverse that veth pair in this example.</para>
                </note>
                <simplesect>
                    <title>Open vSwitch internal ports</title>
                    <para>The network host uses Open vSwitch <emphasis role="italic">internal
                            ports</emphasis>. Internal ports enable you to assign one or more IP
                        addresses to an Open vSwitch bridge. In previous example, the
                            <literal>br-int</literal> bridge has four internal ports:
                                <literal>tap<replaceable>XXX</replaceable></literal>,
                                <literal>qr-<replaceable>YYY</replaceable></literal>,
                                <literal>qr-<replaceable>ZZZ</replaceable></literal>, and
                                <literal>tap<replaceable>WWW</replaceable></literal>. Each internal
                        port has a separate IP address associated with it. An internal port,
                                <literal>qg-<replaceable>VVV</replaceable></literal>, is on the
                            <literal>br-ex</literal> bridge.</para>
                </simplesect>
                <simplesect>
                    <title>DHCP agent</title>
                    <para>By default, the Networking DHCP agent uses a process called dnsmasq to
                        provide DHCP services to guests. Networking must create an internal port for
                        each network that requires DHCP services and attach a dnsmasq process to
                        that port. In the previous example, the
                                <literal>tap<replaceable>XXX</replaceable></literal> interface is on
                            <literal>net01_subnet01</literal>, and the
                                <literal>tap<replaceable>WWW</replaceable></literal> interface is on
                            <literal>net02_subnet01</literal>.</para>
                </simplesect>
                <simplesect>
                    <title>L3 agent (routing)</title>
                    <para>The Networking L3 agent uses Open vSwitch internal ports to implement
                        routing and relies on the network host to route the packets across the
                        interfaces. In this example, the
                            <literal>qr-<replaceable>YYY</replaceable></literal> interface is on
                            <literal>net01_subnet01</literal> and has the IP address
                        192.168.101.1/24. The <literal>qr-<replaceable>ZZZ</replaceable></literal>,
                        interface is on <literal>net02_subnet01</literal> and has the IP address
                            <literal>192.168.102.1/24</literal>. The
                                <literal>qg-<replaceable>VVV</replaceable></literal> interface has
                        the IP address <literal>10.64.201.254/24</literal>. Because each of these
                        interfaces is visible to the network host operating system, the network host
                        routes the packets across the interfaces, as long as an administrator has
                        enabled IP forwarding.</para>
                    <para>The L3 agent uses iptables to implement floating IPs to do the network
                        address translation (NAT).</para>
                </simplesect>
                <simplesect>
                    <title>Overlapping subnets and network namespaces</title>
                    <para>One problem with using the host to implement routing is that one of the
                        Networking subnets might overlap with one of the physical networks that the
                        host uses. For example, if the management network is implemented on
                            <literal>eth2</literal> and also happens to be on the
                            <literal>192.168.101.0/24</literal> subnet, routing problems will occur
                        because the host can't determine whether to send a packet on this subnet to
                                <literal>qr-<replaceable>YYY</replaceable></literal> or
                            <literal>eth2</literal>. If end users are permitted to create their own
                        logical networks and subnets, you must design the system so that such
                        collisions do not occur.</para>
                    <para>Networking uses Linux <emphasis role="italic">network namespaces
                        </emphasis>to prevent collisions between the physical networks on the
                        network host, and the logical networks used by the virtual machines. It also
                        prevents collisions across different logical networks that are not routed to
                        each other, as the following scenario shows.</para>
                    <para>A network namespace is an isolated environment with its own networking
                        stack. A network namespace has its own network interfaces, routes, and
                        iptables rules. Consider it a chroot jail, except for networking instead of
                        for a file system. LXC (Linux containers) use network namespaces to
                        implement networking virtualization.</para>
                    <para>Networking creates network namespaces on the network host to avoid subnet
                        collisions.</para>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata
                                fileref="../../common/figures/under-the-hood-scenario-1-ovs-netns.png"
                                contentwidth="6in"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                    <para>In this example, there are three network namespaces, as shown in the
                        figure above:<itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para><literal>qdhcp-<replaceable>AAA</replaceable></literal>:
                                    contains the
                                        <literal>tap<replaceable>XXX</replaceable></literal>
                                    interface and the dnsmasq process that listens on that interface
                                    to provide DHCP services for <literal>net01_subnet01</literal>.
                                    This allows overlapping IPs between
                                        <literal>net01_subnet01</literal> and any other subnets on
                                    the network host.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para><literal>qrouter-<replaceable>BBBB</replaceable></literal>:
                                    contains the
                                        <literal>qr-<replaceable>YYY</replaceable></literal>,
                                            <literal>qr-<replaceable>ZZZ</replaceable></literal>,
                                    and <literal>qg-<replaceable>VVV</replaceable></literal>
                                    interfaces, and the corresponding routes. This namespace
                                    implements <literal>router01</literal> in our example.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para><literal>qdhcp-<replaceable>CCC</replaceable></literal>:
                                    contains the
                                        <literal>tap<replaceable>WWW</replaceable></literal>
                                    interface and the dnsmasq process that listens on that
                                    interface, to provide DHCP services for
                                        <literal>net02_subnet01</literal>. This allows overlapping
                                    IPs between <literal>net02_subnet01</literal> and any other
                                    subnets on the network host.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist></para>
                </simplesect>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="under_the_hood_openvswitch_scenario2">
            <title>Scenario 2: two tenants, two networks, two routers</title>
            <para>In this scenario, tenant A and tenant B each have a network with one subnet and
                one router that connects the tenants to the public Internet.</para>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../../common/figures/under-the-hood-scenario-2.png"
                        contentwidth="6in"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            <para>Under the <literal>service</literal> tenant, define the public
                network:<screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>tenant=$(keystone tenant-list | awk '/service/ {print $2}')</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron net-create --tenant-id $tenant public01 \
          --provider:network_type flat \
          --provider:physical_network physnet1 \
          --router:external True</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron subnet-create --tenant-id $tenant --name public01_subnet01 \
          --gateway 10.64.201.254 public01 10.64.201.0/24 --disable-dhcp</userinput></screen></para>
            <para>Under the <literal>tenantA</literal> user tenant, create the tenant router and set
                its gateway for the public
                network.<screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>tenant=$(keystone tenant-list|awk '/tenantA/ {print $2}')</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron router-create --tenant-id $tenant router01</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron router-gateway-set router01 public01</userinput></screen>
                Then, define private network <literal>net01</literal> using VLAN ID 101 on the
                physical switch, along with its subnet, and connect it to the router.
                <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron net-create --tenant-id $tenant net01 \
          --provider:network_type vlan \
          --provider:physical_network physnet2 \
          --provider:segmentation_id 101</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron subnet-create --tenant-id $tenant --name net01_subnet01 net01 192.168.101.0/24</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron router-interface-add router01 net01_subnet01</userinput></screen></para>
            <para>Similarly, for <literal>tenantB</literal>, create a router and another network,
                using VLAN ID 102 on the physical
                switch:<screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>tenant=$(keystone tenant-list|awk '/tenantB/ {print $2}')</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron router-create --tenant-id $tenant router02</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron router-gateway-set router02 public01</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron net-create --tenant-id $tenant net02 \
          --provider:network_type vlan \
          --provider:physical_network physnet2 \
          --provider:segmentation_id 102</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron subnet-create --tenant-id $tenant --name net02_subnet01 net01 192.168.102.0/24</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron router-interface-add router02 net02_subnet01</userinput></screen></para>
            <section xml:id="under_the_hood_openvswitch_scenario2_compute">
                <title>Scenario 2: Compute host config</title>
                <para>The following figure shows how to configure Linux networking devices on the
                    compute host:</para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata
                            fileref="../../common/figures/under-the-hood-scenario-2-ovs-compute.png"
                            contentwidth="6in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
                <note>
                    <para>The compute host configuration resembles the configuration in scenario 1.
                        However, in scenario 1, a guest connects to two subnets while in this
                        scenario, the subnets belong to different tenants.</para>
                </note>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="under_the_hood_openvswitch_scenario2_network">
                <title>Scenario 2: Network host config</title>
                <para>The following figure shows the network devices on the network host for the
                    second scenario.</para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata
                            fileref="../../common/figures/under-the-hood-scenario-2-ovs-network.png"
                            contentwidth="6in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
                <para>In this configuration, the network namespaces are organized to isolate the two
                    subnets from each other as shown in the following figure.</para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata
                            fileref="../../common/figures/under-the-hood-scenario-2-ovs-netns.png"
                            contentwidth="6in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
                <para>In this scenario, there are four network namespaces
                            (<literal>qhdcp-<replaceable>AAA</replaceable></literal>,
                            <literal>qrouter-<replaceable>BBBB</replaceable></literal>,
                            <literal>qrouter-<replaceable>CCCC</replaceable></literal>, and
                            <literal>qhdcp-<replaceable>DDDD</replaceable></literal>), instead of
                    three. Because there is no connectivity between the two networks, each router is
                    implemented by a separate namespace.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="under_the_hood_openvswitch_tunneling">
            <title>Configure Open vSwitch tunneling</title>
            <para>Tunneling encapsulates network traffic between physical Networking hosts and
                allows VLANs to span multiple physical hosts. Instances communicate as if they share
                the same layer 2 network. Open vSwitch supports tunneling with the VXLAN and GRE
                encapsulation protocols.</para>
            <figure>
                <title>Example VXLAN tunnel</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="../../common/figures/OVStunneling.png"
                            contentwidth="6in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                        <phrase>Example VXLAN tunnel</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>This diagram shows two instances running on separate hosts connected by a VXLAN
                tunnel. The required physical and virtual components are also illustrated. The
                following procedure creates a VXLAN or GRE tunnel between two Open vSwitches running
                on separate Networking hosts:</para>
            <procedure>
                <title>Example tunnel configuration</title>
                <step>
                    <para>Create a virtual bridge named OVS-BR0 on each participating host:</para>
                    <programlisting>ovs-vsctl add-br OVS-BR0</programlisting>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Create a tunnel to link the OVS-BR0 virtual bridges. Run the ovs-vsctl
                        command on HOST1 to create the tunnel and link it to the bridge on
                        HOST2:</para>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold"> GRE tunnel command: </emphasis></para>
                    <programlisting>ovs-vsctl add-port OVS-BR0 gre1 -- set Interface gre1 type=gre options:remote_ip=192.168.1.11</programlisting>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">VXLAN tunnel command: </emphasis></para>
                    <programlisting>ovs-vsctl add-port OVS-BR0 vxlan1 -- set Interface vxlan1 type=vxlan options:remote_ip=192.168.1.11</programlisting>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Run the ovs-vsctl command on HOST2 to create the tunnel and link it to the
                        bridge on HOST1.</para>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold"> GRE tunnel command: </emphasis></para>
                    <programlisting>
ovs-vsctl add-port OVS-BR0 gre1 -- set Interface gre1 type=gre options:remote_ip=192.168.1.10
                </programlisting>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold"> VXLAN tunnel command: </emphasis></para>
                    <programlisting>
ovs-vsctl add-port OVS-BR0 vxlan1 -- set Interface vxlan1 type=vxlan options:remote_ip=192.168.1.10
                </programlisting>
                </step>
            </procedure>
            <para>Successful completion of these steps results in the two instances sharing a layer
                2 network.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="under_the_hood_linuxbridge">
        <title>Linux Bridge</title>
        <para>This section describes how the Linux Bridge plug-in implements the Networking
            abstractions. For information about DHCP and L3 agents, see <xref
                linkend="under_the_hood_openvswitch_scenario1"/>.</para>
        <section xml:id="under_the_hood_linuxbridge_configuration">
            <title>Configuration</title>
            <para>This example uses VLAN isolation on the switches to isolate tenant networks. This
                configuration labels the physical network associated with the public network as
                    <literal>physnet1</literal>, and the physical network associated with the data
                network as <literal>physnet2</literal>, which leads to the following configuration
                options in <filename>linuxbridge_conf.ini</filename>:</para>
            <programlisting language="ini">[vlans]
tenant_network_type = vlan
network_vlan_ranges = physnet1,physnet2:100:110

[linux_bridge]
physical_interface_mappings = physnet2:eth1</programlisting>
            <note>
               <para>In this configuration there isn't a bridge mapping for <literal>physnet1</literal> as it is only needed on
                   the network host, which maps it to the Open vSwitch bridge <literal>br-ex</literal> connected to
                   the external network as seen below.</para>
            </note>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="under_the_hood_linuxbridge_scenario1">
            <title>Scenario 1: one tenant, two networks, one router</title>
            <para>The first scenario has two private networks (<literal>net01</literal>, and
                    <literal>net02</literal>), each with one subnet
                    (<literal>net01_subnet01</literal>: 192.168.101.0/24,
                    <literal>net02_subnet01</literal>, 192.168.102.0/24). Both private networks are
                attached to a router that connects them to the public network
                (10.64.201.0/24).</para>

            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../../common/figures/under-the-hood-scenario-1.png"
                        contentwidth="6in"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            <para>Under the <literal>service</literal> tenant, create the shared router, define the
                public network, and set it as the default gateway of the
                router<screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>tenant=$(keystone tenant-list | awk '/service/ {print $2}')</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron router-create router01</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron net-create --tenant-id $tenant public01 \
          --provider:network_type flat \
          --provider:physical_network physnet1 \
          --router:external True</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron subnet-create --tenant-id $tenant --name public01_subnet01 \
          --gateway 10.64.201.254 public01 10.64.201.0/24 --disable-dhcp</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron router-gateway-set router01 public01</userinput></screen></para>
            <para>Under the <literal>demo</literal> user tenant, create the private network
                    <literal>net01</literal> and corresponding subnet, and connect it to the
                    <literal>router01</literal> router. Configure it to use VLAN ID 101 on the
                physical
                switch.<screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>tenant=$(keystone tenant-list|awk '/demo/ {print $2}'</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron net-create --tenant-id $tenant net01 \
          --provider:network_type vlan \
          --provider:physical_network physnet2 \
          --provider:segmentation_id 101</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron subnet-create --tenant-id $tenant --name net01_subnet01 net01 192.168.101.0/24</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron router-interface-add router01 net01_subnet01</userinput></screen></para>
            <para>Similarly, for <literal>net02</literal>, using VLAN ID 102 on the physical
                switch:<screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron net-create --tenant-id $tenant net02 \
          --provider:network_type vlan \
          --provider:physical_network physnet2 \
          --provider:segmentation_id 102</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron subnet-create --tenant-id $tenant --name net02_subnet01 net02 192.168.102.0/24</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron router-interface-add router01 net02_subnet01</userinput></screen></para>

            <section xml:id="under_the_hood_linuxbridge_scenario1_compute">
                <title>Scenario 1: Compute host config</title>
                <para>The following figure shows how to configure the various Linux networking
                    devices on the compute host.</para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata
                            fileref="../../common/figures/under-the-hood-scenario-1-linuxbridge-compute.png"
                            contentwidth="6in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>

                <simplesect>
                    <title>Types of network devices</title>
                    <note>
                        <para>There are three distinct type of virtual networking devices: TAP
                            devices, VLAN devices, and Linux bridges. For an Ethernet frame to
                            travel from <literal>eth0</literal> of virtual machine
                                <literal>vm01</literal>, to the physical network, it must pass
                            through four devices inside of the host: TAP <literal>vnet0</literal>,
                            Linux bridge <literal>brq<replaceable>XXX</replaceable></literal>, VLAN
                                <literal>eth1.101)</literal>, and, finally, the physical network
                            interface card <literal>eth1</literal>.</para>
                    </note>
                    <para>A <emphasis role="italic">TAP device</emphasis>, such as
                            <literal>vnet0</literal> is how hypervisors such as KVM and Xen
                        implement a virtual network interface card (typically called a VIF or vNIC).
                        An Ethernet frame sent to a TAP device is received by the guest operating
                        system.</para>
                    <para>A <emphasis role="italic">VLAN device</emphasis> is associated with a VLAN
                        tag attaches to an existing interface device and adds or removes VLAN tags.
                        In the preceding example, VLAN device <literal>eth1.101</literal> is
                        associated with VLAN ID 101 and is attached to interface
                            <literal>eth1</literal>. Packets received from the outside by
                            <literal>eth1</literal> with VLAN tag 101 will be passed to device
                            <literal>eth1.101</literal>, which will then strip the tag. In the other
                        direction, any Ethernet frame sent directly to eth1.101 will have VLAN tag
                        101 added and will be forward to <literal>eth1</literal> for sending out to
                        the network.</para>
                    <para>A <emphasis role="italic">Linux bridge</emphasis> behaves like a hub: you
                        can connect multiple (physical or virtual) network interfaces devices to a
                        Linux bridge. Any Ethernet frames that come in from one interface attached
                        to the bridge is transmitted to all of the other devices.</para>
                </simplesect>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="under_the_hood_linuxbridge_scenario1_network">
                <title>Scenario 1: Network host config</title>
                <para>The following figure shows the network devices on the network host.</para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata
                            fileref="../../common/figures/under-the-hood-scenario-1-linuxbridge-network.png"
                            contentwidth="6in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
                <para>The following figure shows how the Linux Bridge plug-in uses network
                    namespaces to provide isolation.</para>
                <note>
                    <para>veth pairs form connections between the Linux bridges and the network
                        namespaces.</para>
                </note>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata
                            fileref="../../common/figures/under-the-hood-scenario-1-linuxbridge-netns.png"
                            contentwidth="6in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="under_the_hood_linuxbridge_scenario2">
            <title>Scenario 2: two tenants, two networks, two routers</title>
            <para>The second scenario has two tenants (A, B). Each tenant has a network with one
                subnet, and each one has a router that connects them to the public Internet.</para>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../../common/figures/under-the-hood-scenario-2.png"
                        contentwidth="6in"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            <para>Under the <literal>service</literal> tenant, define the public
                network:<screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>tenant=$(keystone tenant-list | awk '/service/ {print $2}')</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron net-create --tenant-id $tenant public01 \
          --provider:network_type flat \
          --provider:physical_network physnet1 \
          --router:external True</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron subnet-create --tenant-id $tenant --name public01_subnet01 \
          --gateway 10.64.201.254 public01 10.64.201.0/24 --disable-dhcp</userinput></screen></para>
            <para>Under the <literal>tenantA</literal> user tenant, create the tenant router and set
                its gateway for the public
                network.<screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>tenant=$(keystone tenant-list|awk '/tenantA/ {print $2}')</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron router-create --tenant-id $tenant router01</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron router-gateway-set router01 public01</userinput></screen>
                Then, define private network <literal>net01</literal> using VLAN ID 102 on the
                physical switch, along with its subnet, and connect it to the router.
                <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron net-create --tenant-id $tenant net01 \
          --provider:network_type vlan \
          --provider:physical_network physnet2 \
          --provider:segmentation_id 101</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron subnet-create --tenant-id $tenant --name net01_subnet01 net01 192.168.101.0/24</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron router-interface-add router01 net01_subnet01</userinput></screen></para>
            <para>Similarly, for <literal>tenantB</literal>, create a router and another network,
                using VLAN ID 102 on the physical
                switch:<screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>tenant=$(keystone tenant-list|awk '/tenantB/ {print $2}')</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron router-create --tenant-id $tenant router02</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron router-gateway-set router02 public01</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron net-create --tenant-id $tenant net02 \
          --provider:network_type vlan \
          --provider:physical_network physnet2 \
          --provider:segmentation_id 102</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron subnet-create --tenant-id $tenant --name net02_subnet01 net01 192.168.101.0/24</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>neutron router-interface-add router02 net02_subnet01</userinput></screen></para>

            <section xml:id="under_the_hood_linuxbridge_scenario2_compute">
                <title>Scenario 2: Compute host config</title>
                <para>The following figure shows how the various Linux networking devices would be
                    configured on the compute host under this scenario.</para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata
                            fileref="../../common/figures/under-the-hood-scenario-2-linuxbridge-compute.png"
                            contentwidth="6in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
                <note>
                    <para>The configuration on the compute host is very similar to the configuration
                        in scenario 1. The only real difference is that scenario 1 had a guest
                        connected to two subnets, and in this scenario the subnets belong to
                        different tenants.</para>
                </note>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="under_the_hood_linuxbridge_scenario2_network">
                <title>Scenario 2: Network host config</title>
                <para>The following figure shows the network devices on the network host for the
                    second scenario.</para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata
                            fileref="../../common/figures/under-the-hood-scenario-2-linuxbridge-network.png"
                            contentwidth="6in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
                <para>The main difference between the configuration in this scenario and the
                    previous one is the organization of the network namespaces, in order to provide
                    isolation across the two subnets, as shown in the following figure.</para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata
                            fileref="../../common/figures/under-the-hood-scenario-2-linuxbridge-netns.png"
                            contentwidth="6in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
                <para>In this scenario, there are four network namespaces
                            (<literal>qhdcp-<replaceable>AAA</replaceable></literal>,
                            <literal>qrouter-<replaceable>BBBB</replaceable></literal>,
                            <literal>qrouter-<replaceable>CCCC</replaceable></literal>, and
                            <literal>qhdcp-<replaceable>DDDD</replaceable></literal>), instead of
                    three. Each router is implemented by a separate namespace, since there is no
                    connectivity between the two networks.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ml2_scenarios">
        <title>ML2</title>
        <para>The Modular Layer 2 plug-in allows OpenStack Networking to simultaneously utilize the
            variety of layer 2 networking technologies found in complex real-world data centers. It
            currently includes drivers for the local, flat, VLAN, GRE and VXLAN network types and
            works with the existing <emphasis>Open vSwitch</emphasis>, <emphasis>Linux Bridge
            </emphasis>, and <emphasis>HyperV</emphasis> L2 agents. The <emphasis>ML2</emphasis>
            plug-in can be extended through mechanism drivers, allowing multiple mechanisms to be
            used simultaneously. This section describes different <emphasis>ML2</emphasis> plug-in
            and agent configurations with different type drivers and mechanism drivers.</para>
        <para>Previously, Networking deployments were only able to use the plug-in that had been
            selected at implementation time. For example, a deployment running the Open vSwitch
            plug-in was only able to use Open vSwitch exclusively; it wasn't possible to
            simultaneously run another plug-in such as Linux Bridge. This was found to be a
            limitation in environments with heterogeneous requirements.</para>
        <warning>
            <para>Disabling a ML2 type driver and re-enabling it later may lead to database
                inconsistencies if ML2 is reconfigured without support for that type.</para>
        </warning>
        <section xml:id="ml2_l2pop_scenarios">
            <title>ML2 with L2 population mechanism driver</title>
            <para>The L2 Population driver enables broadcast, multicast, and unicast traffic to
                scale out on large overlay networks. This traffic is sent to the relevant agent via
                encapsulation as a targeted unicast.</para>
            <para>Current <emphasis>Open vSwitch</emphasis> and <emphasis>Linux Bridge</emphasis>
                tunneling implementations broadcast to every agent, even if they don’t host the
                corresponding network as illustrated below.</para>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../../common/figures/ml2_without_l2pop_full_mesh.png"
                        contentwidth="6in"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            <para>As broadcast emulation on overlay is costly, it may be better to avoid its use for
                MAC learning and ARP resolution. This supposes the use of proxy ARP on the agent to
                answer VM requests, and to populate forwarding table. Currently only the
                    <emphasis>Linux Bridge</emphasis> Agent implements an ARP proxy. The
                pre-population limits L2 broadcasts in overlay, however it may anyway be necessary
                to provide broadcast emulation. This is achieved by broadcasting packets via unicast
                only to the relevant agents as illustrated below.<mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="../../common/figures/ml2_without_l2pop_partial_mesh.png"
                            contentwidth="6in"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>The partial-mesh is available with the <emphasis>Open
                    vSwitch</emphasis> and <emphasis>Linux Bridge</emphasis> agents. The following
                scenarios will use the L2 population mechanism driver with an <emphasis>Open
                    vSwitch</emphasis> agent and a <emphasis>Linux Bridge</emphasis> agent. Enable
                the l2 population driver by adding it to the list of mechanism drivers. In addition,
                a tunneling driver must be selected. Supported options are GRE, VXLAN, or a
                combination of both. Configuration settings are enabled in
                    <filename>ml2_conf.ini</filename>:</para>
            <programlisting language="ini">[ml2]
type_drivers = local,flat,vlan,gre,vxlan
mechanism_drivers = openvswitch,linuxbridge,l2population</programlisting>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="ml2_l2pop_ovs_scenarios">
            <title>Scenario 1: L2 population with Open vSwitch agent</title>
            <para>Enable the l2 population extension in the <emphasis>Open vSwitch</emphasis> agent,
                and configure the <option>local_ip</option> and <option>tunnel_types</option>
                parameters in the <filename>ml2_conf.ini</filename> file:</para>
            <programlisting language="ini">[ovs]
local_ip = <replaceable>192.168.1.10</replaceable>

[agent]
tunnel_types = <replaceable>GRE</replaceable>,<replaceable>VXLAN</replaceable>
l2_population = True</programlisting>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="ml2_l2pop_lb_scenarios">
            <title>Scenario 2: L2 population with <emphasis>Linux Bridge</emphasis> agent</title>
            <para>Enable the l2 population extension on the <emphasis>Linux Bridge</emphasis> agent.
                Enable VXLAN and configure the local_ip parameter in
                    <filename>ml2_conf.ini</filename>.</para>
            <programlisting language="ini">[vxlan]
enable_vxlan = True
local_ip = <replaceable>192.168.1.10</replaceable>
l2_population = True</programlisting>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="ml2_l2_security_group">
            <title>Enable security group API</title>
            <para>The ML2 plug-in can concurrently support different L2 agents (or other
                mechanisms) with different configuration files, so each L2 agent
                configuration file (such as
                    <filename>ovs_neutron_plugin.ini</filename> or
                    <filename>linuxbridge_conf.ini</filename>) should contain the appropriate
                    <option>firewall_driver</option> value for that
                 agent in addition to setting <option>enable_security_group</option> to
                 <literal>True</literal> (which is the default).</para>

                <para>The <option>firewall_driver</option> value in the API server's <filename>ml2_conf.ini</filename> file
                 does not matter.</para>

            <para>To disable the securitygroup API, edit the <filename>ml2_conf.ini</filename> file
            on the API server, and <filename>ovs_neutron_plugin.ini</filename>,
                    <filename>linuxbridge_conf.ini</filename> or other L2 agent
configuration files on the agent servers :</para>
            <programlisting language="ini">[securitygroup]
enable_security_group = False
firewall_driver = neutron.agent.firewall.NoopFirewallDriver</programlisting>
        </section>
    </section>
</section>
