<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="specialized-hardware">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Specialized hardware</title>
    <para>Certain workloads require specialized hardware devices that
        are either difficult to virtualize or impossible to share.
        Applications such as load balancers, highly parallel brute
        force computing, and direct to wire networking may need
        capabilities that basic OpenStack components do not
        provide.</para>
    <section xml:id="challenges-specialized-hardware"><title>Challenges</title>
    <para>Some applications need access to hardware devices to either
        improve performance or provide capabilities that are not
        virtual CPU, RAM, network or storage. These can be a shared
        resource, such as a cryptography processor, or a dedicated
        resource such as a Graphics Processing Unit. OpenStack has
        ways of providing some of these, while others may need extra
        work.</para></section>
    <section xml:id="solutions-specialized-hardware"><title>Solutions</title>
    <para>In order to provide cryptography offloading to a set of
        instances, it is possible to use Glance configuration options
        to assign the cryptography chip to a device node in the guest.
        The documentation at
        http://docs.openstack.org/cli-reference/content/chapter_cli-glance-property.html
        contains further information on configuring this solution, but
        it allows all guests using the configured images to access the
        hypervisor cryptography device.</para>
    <para>If direct access to a specific device is required, it can be
        dedicated to a single instance per hypervisor through the use
        of PCI pass-through. The OpenStack administrator needs to
        define a flavor that specifically has the PCI device in order
        to properly schedule instances. More information regarding PCI
        pass-through, including instructions for implementing and
        using it, is available at
        https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Pci_passthrough#How_to_check_PCI_status_with_PCI_api_patches.</para>
    <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/Specialized_Hardware2.png"/>
        </imageobject>
    </mediaobject></section>
</section>
