<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="software-defined-networking-sdn">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Software Defined Networking</title>
    <para>Software Defined Networking (SDN) is the separation of the data
        plane and control plane. SDN has become a popular method of
        managing and controlling packet flows within networks. SDN
        uses overlays or directly controlled layer 2 devices to
        determine flow paths, and as such presents challenges to a
        cloud environment. Some designers may wish to run their
        controllers within an OpenStack installation. Others may wish
        to have their installations participate in an SDN-controlled
        network.</para>
    <section xml:id="challenges-sdn"><title>Challenges</title>
    <para>SDN is a relatively new concept that is not yet
        standardized, so SDN systems come in a variety of different
        implementations. Because of this, a truly prescriptive
        architecture is not feasible. Instead, examine the differences
        between an existing or intended OpenStack design and determine
        where the potential conflict and gaps can be found.</para></section>
    <section xml:id="possible-solutions-sdn">
      <title>Possible solutions</title>
    <para>If an SDN implementation requires layer 2 access because it
        directly manipulates switches, then running an overlay network
        or a layer 3 agent may not be advisable. If the controller
        resides within an OpenStack installation, it may be necessary
        to build an ML2 plug-in and schedule the controller instances
        to connect to tenant VLANs that then talk directly to the
        switch hardware. Alternatively, depending on the external
        device support, use a tunnel that terminates at the switch
        hardware itself.</para></section>
    <section xml:id="diagram-sdn"><title>Diagram</title>
    <para>OpenStack hosted SDN controller:
    <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/Special_case_SDN_hosted.png"
            />
        </imageobject>
    </mediaobject></para>
    <para>OpenStack participating in an SDN controller network:
    <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
            <imagedata
                fileref="../images/Special_case_SDN_external.png"/>
        </imageobject>
    </mediaobject></para></section>
</section>
