<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="desktop-as-a-service">
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
  <title>Desktop-as-a-Service</title>
  <para>Virtual Desktop Infrastructure (VDI) is a service that hosts
    user desktop environments on remote servers. This application
    is very sensitive to network latency and requires a high
    performance compute environment. Traditionally these types of
    services do not use cloud environments because
    few clouds support such a demanding workload for user-facing
    applications. As cloud environments become more robust,
    vendors are starting to provide services
    that provide virtual desktops in the cloud. OpenStack
    may soon provide the infrastructure for these types of
    deployments.</para>
  <section xml:id="challenges">
    <title>Challenges</title>
    <para>Designing an infrastructure that is suitable to host virtual
      desktops is a very different task to that of most virtual
      workloads. For example, the design must consider:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Boot storms, when a high volume of logins occur
        in a short period of time</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The performance of the applications running on
          virtual desktops</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Operating systems and their compatibility with the
          OpenStack hypervisor</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="broker">
    <title>Broker</title>
    <para>The connection broker determines which remote desktop host
      users can access. Medium and large scale environments require a broker
      since its service represents a central component of the architecture.
      The broker is a complete management product, and enables automated
      deployment and provisioning of remote desktop hosts.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="possible-solutions">
    <title>Possible solutions</title>
    <para>
      There are a number of commercial products currently available that
      provide a broker solution. However, no native OpenStack projects
      provide broker services. Not providing a broker is also
      an option, but managing this manually would not suffice for a
      large scale, enterprise solution.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="diagram">
    <title>Diagram</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="../figures/Specialized_VDI1.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </section>
</section>
