<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="desktop-as-a-service">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Desktop-as-a-Service</title>
    <para>Virtual Desktop Infrastructure (VDI) is a service that hosts
        user desktop environments on remote servers. This application
        is very sensitive to network latency and requires a high
        performance compute environment. Traditionally these types of
        environments have not been put on cloud environments because
        few clouds are built to support such a demanding workload that
        is so exposed to end users. Recently, as cloud environments
        become more robust, vendors are starting to provide services
        that allow virtual desktops to be hosted in the cloud. In the
        not too distant future, OpenStack could be used as the
        underlying infrastructure to run a virtual infrastructure
        environment, either in-house or in the cloud.</para>
    <section xml:id="challenges"><title>Challenges</title>
    <para>Designing an infrastructure that is suitable to host virtual
        desktops is a very different task to that of most virtual
        workloads. The infrastructure will need to be designed, for
        example:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Boot storms - What happens when hundreds or
                thousands of users log in during shift changes,
                affects the storage design.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>The performance of the applications running in these
                virtual desktops</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Operating system and compatibility with the
                OpenStack hypervisor</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></section>
    <section xml:id="broker"><title>Broker</title>
    <para>The Connection Broker is a central component of the
        architecture that determines which Remote Desktop Host will be
        assigned or connected to the user. The broker is often a
        full-blown management product allowing for the automated
        deployment and provisioning of Remote Desktop Hosts.</para></section>
    <section xml:id="possible-solutions">
      <title>Possible solutions</title>
    <para>There a number of commercial products available today that
        provide such a broker solution but nothing that is native in
        the OpenStack project. There of course is also the option of
        not providing a broker and managing this manually - but this
        would not suffice as a large scale, enterprise
        solution.</para></section>
    <section xml:id="diagram"><title>Diagram</title>
    <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
            <imagedata
                fileref="../images/Specialized_VDI1.png"
            />
        </imageobject>
    </mediaobject></section>
</section>
