<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
<!ENTITY % openstack SYSTEM "../../common/entities/openstack.ent">
%openstack;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="arch-guide-openstack-on-openstack">
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
  <title>OpenStack on OpenStack</title>
  <para>In some cases it is necessary to run OpenStack nested on top
    of another OpenStack cloud. This scenario allows for complete
    OpenStack cloud environments to be managed and provisioned on
    instances running on hypervisors and servers controlled by the
    underlying OpenStack cloud. Public cloud providers can use
    this technique to effectively manage the upgrade and
    maintenance process on complete OpenStack-based clouds.
    Developers and those testing OpenStack can also use the
    guidance to provision their own OpenStack environments on
    available OpenStack Compute resources, whether public or
    private.</para>
  <section xml:id="challenges-for-nested-cloud">
    <title>Challenges</title>
    <para>The network aspect of deploying a nested cloud is the most
      complicated aspect of this architecture. When using VLANs,
      these will need to be exposed to the physical ports on which
      the undercloud runs, as the bare metal cloud owns all the
      hardware, but they also need to be exposed to the nested
      levels as well. Alternatively, network overlay technologies
      can be used on the overcloud (the OpenStack cloud running on
      OpenStack) to provide the required software defined networking
      for the deployment.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="hypervisor-nested-cloud">
    <title>Hypervisor</title>
    <para>A key question to address in this scenario is the decision
      about which approach should be taken to provide a nested
      hypervisor in OpenStack. This decision influences which
      operating systems can be used for the deployment of the nested
      OpenStack deployments.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="possible-solutions-nested-cloud-deployment">
    <title>Possible solutions: deployment</title>
    <para>Deployment of a full stack can be challenging but this
      difficulty can be readily be mitigated by creating a Heat
      template to deploy the entire stack or a configuration
      management system. Once the Heat template is created,
      deploying additional stacks will be a trivial thing and can be
      performed in an automated fashion.</para>
    <para>The OpenStack-on-OpenStack project (<glossterm>TripleO</glossterm>)
      addresses this issue&mdash;currently, however, the project does
      not completely cover nested stacks. For more information, see
      <link
      xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/TripleO">
      https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/TripleO</link>.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="possible-solutions-nested-cloud-hypervisor">
    <title>Possible solutions: hypervisor</title>
    <para>In the case of running TripleO, the underlying OpenStack
      cloud deploys the Compute nodes as bare-metal. OpenStack would
      then be deployed on these Compute bare-metal servers with the
      appropriate hypervisor, such as KVM.</para>
    <para>In the case of running smaller OpenStack clouds for testing
      purposes, and performance would not be a critical factor, QEMU
      can be utilized instead. It is also possible to run a KVM
      hypervisor in an instance
      (see <link xlink:href="http://davejingtian.org/2014/03/30/nested-kvm-just-for-fun/">
      http://davejingtian.org/2014/03/30/nested-kvm-just-for-fun/</link>),
      though this is not a supported configuration, and could be a
      complex solution for such a use case.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="nested-cloud-diagram">
    <title>Diagram</title>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="4in" fileref="../figures/Specialized_OOO.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
