<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
<!ENTITY % openstack SYSTEM "../../common/entities/openstack.ent">
%openstack;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="arch-guide-openstack-on-openstack">
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
  <title>OpenStack on OpenStack</title>
  <para>In some cases it is necessary to run OpenStack nested on top
    of another OpenStack cloud. This scenario enables you to manage
    and provision complete OpenStack cloud environments on
    instances running on hypervisors and servers that the underlying
    OpenStack cloud controls. Public cloud providers can use
    this technique to manage the upgrade and
    maintenance process on complete OpenStack-based clouds.
    Developers and those testing OpenStack can also use this
    guidance to provision their own OpenStack environments on
    available OpenStack Compute resources, whether public or
    private.</para>
  <section xml:id="challenges-for-nested-cloud">
    <title>Challenges</title>
    <para>The network aspect of deploying a nested cloud is the most
    complicated aspect of this architecture. You must expose VLANs
    to the physical ports on which the underlying cloud runs,
    as the bare metal cloud owns all the
    hardware, but you must also expose them to the nested
    levels as well. Alternatively, you can use the network overlay
    technologies on the OpenStack cloud running on OpenStack to provide
    the required software defined networking for the deployment.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="hypervisor-nested-cloud">
    <title>Hypervisor</title>
    <para>A key question to address in this scenario is which
    approach you should take to provide a nested
    hypervisor in OpenStack. This decision influences which
    operating systems you use for the deployment of the nested
    OpenStack deployments.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="possible-solutions-nested-cloud-deployment">
    <title>Possible solutions: deployment</title>
    <para>Deployment of a full stack can be challenging but you can mitigate
    this difficulty by creating a Heat template to deploy the
    entire stack or a configuration management system. After creating
    the Heat template, you can automate the deployment of additional stacks.</para>
    <para>The OpenStack-on-OpenStack project (<glossterm>TripleO</glossterm>)
    addresses this issue. Currently, however, the project does
    not completely cover nested stacks. For more information, see
    <link xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/TripleO">
    https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/TripleO</link>.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="possible-solutions-nested-cloud-hypervisor">
    <title>Possible solutions: hypervisor</title>
    <para>In the case of running TripleO, the underlying OpenStack
    cloud deploys the Compute nodes as bare-metal. You then deploy
    OpenStack on these Compute bare-metal servers with the
    appropriate hypervisor, such as KVM.</para>
    <para>In the case of running smaller OpenStack clouds for testing
    purposes, where performance is not a critical factor, you can use
    QEMU instead. It is also possible to run a KVM hypervisor in an instance
    (see <link xlink:href="http://davejingtian.org/2014/03/30/nested-kvm-just-for-fun/">
    http://davejingtian.org/2014/03/30/nested-kvm-just-for-fun/</link>),
    though this is not a supported configuration, and could be a
    complex solution for such a use case.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="nested-cloud-diagram">
    <title>Diagram</title>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="4in" fileref="../figures/Specialized_OOO.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
