<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
  xml:id="ch_overview">
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
  <title>Architecture</title>
  <para>This install guide offers a few of the many ways to install
    OpenStack components and have them work together. It is meant as a
    "choose your own adventure" guide, not a comprehensive guide. The
      <citetitle>OpenStack Configuration Reference</citetitle> lists
    every option in all OpenStack services. Before you begin an
    installation adventure, here are some things you should know about
    OpenStack concepts.</para>
  <xi:include href="../common/ch_getstart.xml"
    xpointer="element(para1)"/>
  <xi:include href="../common/ch_getstart.xml"
    xpointer="element(para2)"/>
  <xi:include href="../common/ch_getstart.xml"
    xpointer="element(para3)"/>
  <xi:include href="../common/ch_getstart.xml"
    xpointer="element(table1)"/>
  <xi:include href="../common/section_getstart_conceptual_arch.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="../common/section_getstart_logical_arch.xml"/>
  <section xml:id="overview-architecture">
    <title>Sample architectures</title>
    <para>This guide enables you to choose your own OpenStack
      adventure. OpenStack is highly configurable to meet different
      needs with various storage and networking options.</para>
    <para>This guide offers the following sample architecture
      examples:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Example basic architecture. This architecture has two
          nodes. A cloud controller node runs the control services,
          such as database, message queue, and API services for the
          Identity Service, Image Service, and Compute. A compute node
          runs the hypervisor where virtual machines live.</para>
        <figure xml:id="basic-architecture">
          <title>Basic architecture</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata contentwidth="6in"
                fileref="figures/basic-architecture.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>Technical details: Compute with KVM, local ephemeral
          storage, <systemitem class="service">nova-network</systemitem> in multi-host flatDHCP mode, MySQL,
          nova-api, default scheduler, <phrase os="fedora;rhel;centos"
            >Qpid for messaging,</phrase><phrase
            os="ubuntu;debian;opensuse">RabbitMQ for
            messaging,</phrase> Identity Service  with SQL back end, Image Service with
          local storage, Dashboard (optional extra). Uses as many
          default options as possible.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Example architecture from the <link
            xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/trunk/openstack-ops/content/"
              ><citetitle>OpenStack Operations
            Guide</citetitle></link>. Same as the basic architecture
          but with the Block Storage Service LVM/iSCSI back end, <systemitem class="service">nova-network</systemitem> in
          multi-host with FlatDHCP, Live Migration back end, shared
          storage with NFS, and Object Storage. One controller node
          and multiple compute nodes.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Example architecture with Identity Service and Object
          Storage: Four-node installation with Identity Service on the
          proxy node and three replications of object servers.
          Dashboard does not support this configuration so examples
          are with CLI.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Example architecture with OpenStack Networking.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
