<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         version="5.0"
         xml:id="ch_overview">
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
  <title>Overview and Architecture</title>
  <section xml:id="overview-concepts">
    <title>OpenStack Overview</title>
    <para>The OpenStack project is an open source cloud computing
    platform for all types of clouds, which aims to be simple to
    implement, massively scalable, and feature rich. Developers and
    cloud computing technologists from around the world create the
    OpenStack project.</para>
    <xi:include href="../common/section_getstart_architecture.xml"/>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="overview-architecture">
    <title>Sample Architectures</title>
   <para>This guide is written so that you can choose your own
      OpenStack adventure. Because OpenStack is highly configurable to
      meet different use cases, with many storage choices and
      underlying software-defined networking scenarios, this guide
      offers these main examples with the intention of expanding on
      each:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Example architecture for simplicity:  the most basic
   architecture you can have: one node to run the "control" services, such
   as database, message queue and API services for the Identity Service,
   Image Service and Compute Service; and a second node to be our
   Compute node that runs the hypervisor where our virtual machines will live.</para>
  <figure xml:id="basic-architecture">
  <title>Basic Architecture</title>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata contentwidth="6in" fileref="figures/basic-architecture.svg"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  </figure>
         <para os="fedora;rhel;centos">Technical details: Compute with KVM,
          local ephemeral storage, nova-networks in multi-host flatDHCP,
          MySQL, nova-api, default scheduler, Qpid for messaging,
          Identity with SQL backend, Image with local storage,
          Dashboard (optional extra). Use as many default options as possible.
          </para>
         <para os="ubuntu;debian;opensuse;sles">Technical details: Compute with KVM,
          local ephemeral storage, nova-networks in multi-host flatDHCP,
          MySQL, nova-api, default scheduler, RabbitMQ for messaging,
          Identity with SQL backend, Image with local storage, Dashboard (optional extra).
          Use as many default options as possible.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Example architecture from the OpenStack Operations
          Guide: Same as above but with Block Storage backend
          LVM/iSCSI, nova-network in multi-host with FlatDHCP, Live
          Migration backend shared storage with NFS, and Object
          Storage. One controller node and multiple compute
          nodes.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Example architecture with Identity and Object Storage
          only (no Dashboard): Five node installation with Identity on
          the proxy node and three replications of object servers.
          Dashboard does not support this configuration so examples
          are with CLI.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Example architecture with OpenStack Networking
          (Neutron)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
