<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xml:id="neutron-concepts"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
  <title>Networking concepts</title>
  <para>OpenStack Networking (neutron) manages all of the networking
    facets for the Virtual Networking Infrastructure (VNI) in your
    OpenStack environment. OpenStack Networking also manages the access
    layer aspects of the Physical Networking Infrastructure (PNI).
    Tenants can create advanced virtual network topologies using
    OpenStack Networking. These topologies include services such as
    <glossterm baseform="firewall">firewalls</glossterm>,
    <glossterm baseform="load balancer">load balancers</glossterm>, and
    <glossterm baseform="virtual private network (VPN)">
      virtual private networks (VPNs)</glossterm>.</para>
  <para>Networking provides the following object abstractions: networks,
    routers, and subnets. Each has a functionality that mimics its
    physical counterpart: networks contain subnets, and routers route
    traffic between different subnet and networks.</para>
  <para>Each router has one gateway that connects to a network, and many
    interfaces connected to subnets. Subnets can access machines on
    other subnets connected to the same router.</para>
  <para>Any given Networking set up has at least one external network.
    This external network, unlike the other networks, is not solely a
    virtually defined network. It instead provides a view into a slice
    of the network accessible outside the OpenStack installation, which
    is the outside network. IP addresses on the external network are
    accessible by anybody physically on the outside network. DHCP is
    disabled on this network.</para>
  <para>Machines can access the outside network through the gateway
    for the router. For the outside network to access VMs, and for VM's
    to access the outside network, routers between the networks are
    needed.</para>
  <para>In addition to external networks, any Networking set up has one
    or more internal networks. These software-defined networks connect
    directly to the VMs. Only the VMs on any given internal network,
    or those on subnets connected through interfaces to a similar
    router, can access VMs connected to that network directly.</para>
   <para>Additionally, you can allocate IP addresses on external
    networks to ports on the internal network. Whenever something is
    connected to a subnet, that connection is called a port.You can
    associate external network IP addresses with ports to VMs.
    This way, entities on the outside network can access VMs.</para>
  <para>Networking also supports <emphasis role="italic">security
    groups</emphasis>, which enable administrators to define
    firewall rules in groups. A VM can belong to one or more
    security groups. Networking applies the rules in those security
    groups to block or unblock ports, port ranges, or traffic types
    for that VM.</para>
  <simplesect><title>Networking plug-ins</title>
  <para>Each plug-in that Networking uses has its own concepts. These
    plug-in concepts are not vital to operating Networking.
    Understanding these concepts can help you set up the Openstack
    Networking service, however. All Networking installations use a core
    plug-in and a security group plug-in (or just the No-Op security
    group plug-in). Additionally, Firewall-as-a-service (FWaaS) and
    Load-balancing-as-a-service (LBaaS) plug-ins are available.</para>
  </simplesect>
</section>
