<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xml:id="install-neutron"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
  xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
  version="5.0">
  <title>Neutron concepts</title>
  <para>Like Nova Networking, Neutron manages software-defined networking for your OpenStack
    installation. However, unlike Nova Networking, Neutron can be configured for advanced virtual
    network topologies, such as per-tenant private networks, and more.</para>
  <para>Neutron has three main object abstractions: networks, subnets, and routers. Each has
    functionality that mimics its physical counterpart: networks contain subnets, and routers route
    traffic between different subnet and networks.</para>
  <para>In any given Neutron setup, there is at least one external network. This network, unlike the
    other networks, is not merely an virtually defined network. Instead, it represents the view into
    a slice of the external network, accessible outside the OpenStack installation. IP addresses on
    Neutron's external network are in fact accessible by anybody physically on the outside network.
    Because this network merely represents a slice of the outside network, DHCP is disabled on this
    network.</para>
  <para>In addition external networks, any Neutron setup will have one or more internal networks.
    These software-defined networks connect directly to the VMs. Only the VMs on any given internal
    network, or those on subnets connected via interfaces to a similar router, can access VMs
    connected to that network directly.</para>
  <para>In order for the outside network to be able to access VMs, and vice versa, routers between
    the networks are needed. Each router has one gateway, connected to a network, and many
    interfaces, connected to subnets. Like a physical router, subnets can access machines on other
    subnets connected to the same router, and machines can access the outside network through the
    router's gateway.</para>
  <para>Additionally, IP addresses on an external networks can be allocated to ports on the internal
    network. Whenever something is connected to a subnet, that connection is called a port. External
    network IP addresses can be associated with ports to VMs. This way, entities on the outside
    network can access VMs.</para>
  <para>Neutron also supports "security groups." Security groups allow administrators to define
    firewall rules in groups. Then, a given VM can have one or more security groups to which it
    belongs, and Neutron will apply those rules to block or unblock ports, port ranges, or traffic
    types for that VM.</para>
  <para>Each of the plugins that Neutron uses has its own concepts as well. While not vital to
    operating Neutron, these concepts can be useful to help with setting up Neutron. All Neutron
    installations use a core plugin, as well as a security group plugin (or just the No-Op security
    group plugin). Additionally, Firewall-as-a-service (FWaaS) and Load-balancing-as-a-service
    (LBaaS) plugins are available.</para>
  <section xml:id="concepts-neutron.openvswitch">
    <title>Open vSwitch Concepts</title>
    <para>The Open vSwitch plugin is one of the most popular core plugins. Open vSwitch
      configurations consists of bridges and ports. Ports represent connections to other things,
      such as physical interfaces and patch cables. Packets from any given port on a bridge is
      shared with all other ports on that bridge. Bridges can be connected through Open vSwitch
      virtual patch cables, or through Linux virtual Ethernet cables (<literal>veth</literal>).
      Additionally, bridges appear as network interfaces to Linux, so they can be assigned IP
      addresses.</para>
    <para>In Neutron, there are several main bridges. The integration bridge, called
        <literal>br-int</literal>, connects directly to the VMs and associated services. The
      external bridge, called <literal>br-ex</literal>, connects to the external network. Finally,
      the VLAN configuration of the Open vSwitch plugin uses bridges associated with each physical
      network.</para>
    <para>In addition to defining bridges, Open vSwitch has OpenFlow, which allows you to define
      networking flow rules. These rules are used in certain configurations to transfer packets
      between VLANs.</para>
    <para>Finally, some configurations of Open vSwitch use network namespaces. This allows linux to
      group adapters into unique namespaces that are not visible to other namespaces, allowing
      multiple Neutron routers to be managed by the same network node.</para>
    <para>With Open vSwitch, there are two different technologies that can be used to create the
      virtual networks: GRE or VLANs.</para>
    <para>Generic Routing Encapsulation, or GRE for short, is the technology used in many VPNs. In
      essence, it works by wrapping IP packets and entirely new packets with different routing
      information. When the new packet reaches its destination, it is unwrapped, and the underlying
      packet is routed. To use GRE with Open vSwitch, Neutron creates GRE Tunnels. This tunnels are
      ports on a bridge, and allow bridges on different systems to act as though they were in fact
      one bridge, allowing the compute node and network node to act as one for the purposes of
      routing.</para>
    <para>Virtual LANs, or VLANs for short, on the other hand, use a special modification to the
      Ethernet header. They add a 4-byte VLAN tag that ranges between 1 and 4094 (the 0 tag is
      special, and the 4095 tag, made of all ones, is equivalent to an untagged packet). Special
      NICs, switches, and routers know how to interpret the VLAN tags, as does Open vSwitch. Packets
      tagged for one VLAN will only be shared with other devices configured to be on that VLAN,
      despite the fact that all of the devices are on the same physical network.</para>
    <para>The most common security group driver used with Open vSwitch is the Hybrid IPTables/Open
      vSwitch plugin. It uses a combination for IPTables and OpenFlow rules. IPTables is a tool used
      for creating firewalls and setting up NATs on Linux. It uses a complex rule system and
      "chains" of rules to allow for the complex rules required by Neutron's security groups.</para>
  </section>
</section>
