<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="debconf-concepts">
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
  <title>debconf concepts</title>
  <para>This chapter explains how to use the Debian <systemitem
      class="library">debconf</systemitem> and <systemitem
      class="library">dbconfig-common</systemitem> packages to
    configure OpenStack services. These packages enable users to
    perform configuration tasks. When users install OpenStack
    packages, <package>debconf</package> prompts the user for
    responses, which seed the contents of configuration files
    associated with that package. After package installation, users
    can update the configuration of a package by using the
      <command>dpkg-reconfigure</command> program.</para>
  <para>If you are familiar with these packages and pre-seeding, you
    can proceed to <xref linkend="ch_keystone"/>.</para>
  <section xml:id="debian_packages">
    <title>The Debian packages</title>
    <para>The rules described here are from the <link
        xlink:href="http://www.debian.org/doc/debian-policy/"
          ><citetitle>Debian Policy Manual</citetitle></link>. If any
      rule described in this chapter is not respected, you have found
      a serious bug that must be fixed.</para>
    <para>When you install or upgrade a Debian package, all
      configuration file values are preserved. Using the <systemitem
        class="library">debconf</systemitem> database as a registry is
      considered a bug in Debian. If you edit something in any
      OpenStack configuration file, the <systemitem class="library"
        >debconf</systemitem> package reads that value when it
      prepares to prompt the user. For example, to change the log in
      name for the RabbitMQ messaging queue for a service, you can
      edit its value in the corresponding configuration file.</para>
    <para>To opt out of using the <systemitem class="library"
        >debconf</systemitem> package, run the
        <command>dpkg-reconfigure</command> command and select
      non-interactive mode:</para>
    <screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>dpkg-reconfigure -plow debconf</userinput></screen>
    <para>Then, <systemitem class="library">debconf</systemitem> does
      not prompt you.</para>
    <para>Another way to disable the <systemitem class="library"
        >debconf</systemitem> package is to prefix the
        <command>apt</command> command with
        <literal>DEBIAN_FRONTEND=noninteractive</literal>, as
      follows:</para>
    <screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>DEBIAN_FRONTEND=noninteractive apt-get install nova-api</userinput></screen>
    <para>If you configure a package with <systemitem class="library"
        >debconf</systemitem> incorrectly, you can re-configure it, as
      follows:</para>
    <screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>dpkg-reconfigure <replaceable>PACKAGE-NAME</replaceable></userinput></screen>
    <para>This calls the post-installation script for the
        <replaceable>PACKAGE-NAME</replaceable> package after the user
      responds to all prompts. If you cannot install a Debian package
      in a non-interactive way, you have found a release-critical bug
      in Debian. Report it to the Debian bug tracking system.</para>
    <para>Generally, the <systemitem class="library"
        >-common</systemitem> packages install the configuration
      files. For example, the <literal>glance-common</literal> package
      installs the <filename>glance-api.conf</filename> and
        <filename>glance-registry.conf</filename> files. So, for the
      Image Service, you must re-configure the
        <literal>glance-common</literal> package. The same applies for
        <literal>cinder-common</literal>,
        <literal>nova-common</literal>, and
        <literal>heat-common</literal> packages.</para>
    <para>In <systemitem class="library">debconf</systemitem>, the
      higher the priority for a screen, the
      greater the chance that the user sees that screen. If a
        <systemitem class="library">debconf</systemitem> screen has
        <literal>medium</literal> priority and you configure the
      Debian system to show only <literal>critical</literal> prompts,
      which is the default in Debian, the user does not see that
        <systemitem class="library">debconf</systemitem> screen.
      Instead, the default for the related package is used. In the
      Debian OpenStack packages, a number of <systemitem
        class="library">debconf</systemitem> screens are set with
        <literal>medium</literal> priority. Consequently, if you want
      to respond to all <systemitem class="library"
        >debconf</systemitem> screens from the Debian OpenStack
      packages, you must run the following command and select the
        <literal>medium</literal> priority before you install any
      packages:</para>
    <screen><prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>dpkg-reconfigure debconf</userinput></screen>
    <note>
      <para>The packages do not require pre-depends. If <systemitem
          class="library">dbconfig-common</systemitem> is already
        installed on the system, the user sees all prompts. However,
        you cannot define the order in which the <systemitem
          class="library">debconf</systemitem> screens appear. The
        user must make sense of it even if the prompts appear in an
        illogical order.</para>
    </note>
  </section>
  <xi:include href="section_debconf-preseeding.xml"/>
</section>
