<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
  xml:id="basics-prerequisites">
  <?dbhtml-stop-chunking?>
  <title>Before you begin</title>
  <para>For a functional environment, OpenStack doesn't require a
    significant amount of resources. We recommend that your environment meets
    or exceeds the following minimum requirements which can support several
    minimal <glossterm>CirrOS</glossterm> instances:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Controller Node: 1 processor, 2 GB memory, and 5 GB
        storage</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Network Node: 1 processor, 512 MB memory, and 5 GB
        storage</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Compute Node: 1 processor, 2 GB memory, and 10 GB
        storage</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>To minimize clutter and provide more resources for OpenStack, we
    recommend a minimal installation of your Linux distribution. Also, we
    strongly recommend that you install a 64-bit version of your distribution
    on at least the compute node. If you install a 32-bit version of your
    distribution on the compute node, attempting to start an instance using
    a 64-bit image will fail.</para>
  <note>
    <para>A single disk partition on each node works for most basic
      installations. However, you should consider
      <glossterm>Logical Volume Manager (LVM)</glossterm> for installations
      with optional services such as Block Storage.</para>
  </note>
  <para>Many users build their test environments on
    <glossterm baseform="virtual machine (VM)">virtual machines
    (VMs)</glossterm>. The primary benefits of VMs include the
    following:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>One physical server can support multiple nodes, each with almost
        any number of network interfaces.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Ability to take periodic "snap shots" throughout the installation
        process and "roll back" to a working configuration in the event of
        a problem.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>However, VMs will reduce performance of your instances, particularly
    if your hypervisor and/or processor lacks support for hardware
    acceleration of nested VMs.</para>
  <note>
    <para>If you choose to install on VMs, make sure your hypervisor
      permits <glossterm>promiscuous mode</glossterm> on the
      <glossterm>external network</glossterm>.</para>
  </note>
  <para>For more information about system requirements, see the <link
    xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/ops/">OpenStack Operations
    Guide</link>.</para>
</section>
