<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xml:id="install-neutron"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
  xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" version="5.0">
  <title>Neutron concepts</title>
  <para>Like Nova Networking, Neutron manages software-defined
    networking for your OpenStack installation. However, unlike Nova
    Networking, you can configure Neutron for advanced virtual network
    topologies, such as per-tenant private networks and more.</para>
  <para>Neutron has the following object abstractions: networks,
    subnets, and routers. Each has functionality that mimics its
    physical counterpart: networks contain subnets, and routers route
    traffic between different subnet and networks.</para>
  <para>Any given Neutron set up has at least one external network.
    This network, unlike the other networks, is not merely a virtually
    defined network. Instead, it represents the view into a slice of
    the external network that is accessible outside the OpenStack
    installation. IP addresses on the Neutron external network are
    accessible by anybody physically on the outside network. Because
    this network merely represents a slice of the outside network,
    DHCP is disabled on this network.</para>
  <para>In addition to external networks, any Neutron set up has one
    or more internal networks. These software-defined networks connect
    directly to the VMs. Only the VMs on any given internal network,
    or those on subnets connected through interfaces to a similar
    router, can access VMs connected to that network directly.</para>
  <para>For the outside network to access VMs, and vice versa, routers
    between the networks are needed. Each router has one gateway that
    is connected to a network and many interfaces that are connected
    to subnets. Like a physical router, subnets can access machines on
    other subnets that are connected to the same router, and machines
    can access the outside network through the gateway for the
    router.</para>
  <para>Additionally, you can allocate IP addresses on external
    networks to ports on the internal network. Whenever something is
    connected to a subnet, that connection is called a port. You can
    associate external network IP addresses with ports to VMs. This
    way, entities on the outside network can access VMs.</para>
  <para>Neutron also supports <emphasis role="italic">security
      groups</emphasis>. Security groups enable administrators to
    define firewall rules in groups. A VM can belong to one or more
    security groups, and Neutron applies the rules in those security
    groups to block or unblock ports, port ranges, or traffic types
    for that VM.</para>
  <para>Each plug-in that Neutron uses has its own concepts. While not
    vital to operating Neutron, understanding these concepts can help
    you set up Neutron. All Neutron installations use a core plug-in
    and a security group plug-in (or just the No-Op security group
    plug-in). Additionally, Firewall-as-a-service (FWaaS) and
    Load-balancing-as-a-service (LBaaS) plug-ins are available.</para>
  <section xml:id="concepts-neutron.openvswitch">
    <title>Open vSwitch concepts</title>
    <para>The Open vSwitch plug-in is one of the most popular core
      plug-ins. Open vSwitch configurations consists of bridges and
      ports. Ports represent connections to other things, such as
      physical interfaces and patch cables. Packets from any given
      port on a bridge are shared with all other ports on that bridge.
      Bridges can be connected through Open vSwitch virtual patch
      cables or through Linux virtual Ethernet cables
        (<literal>veth</literal>). Additionally, bridges appear as
      network interfaces to Linux, so you can assign IP addresses to
      them.</para>
    <para>In Neutron, the integration bridge, called
        <literal>br-int</literal>, connects directly to the VMs and
      associated services. The external bridge, called
        <literal>br-ex</literal>, connects to the external network.
      Finally, the VLAN configuration of the Open vSwitch plug-in uses
      bridges associated with each physical network.</para>
    <para>In addition to defining bridges, Open vSwitch has OpenFlow,
      which enables you to define networking flow rules. Certain
      configurations use these rules to transfer packets between
      VLANs.</para>
    <para>Finally, some configurations of Open vSwitch use network
      namespaces that enable Linux to group adapters into unique
      namespaces that are not visible to other namespaces, which
      allows the same network node to manage multiple Neutron
      routers.</para>
    <para>With Open vSwitch, you can use two different technologies to
      create the virtual networks: GRE or VLANs.</para>
    <para>Generic Routing Encapsulation (GRE) is the technology used
      in many VPNs. It wraps IP packets to create entirely new packets
      with different routing information. When the new packet reaches
      its destination, it is unwrapped, and the underlying packet is
      routed. To use GRE with Open vSwitch, Neutron creates GRE
      tunnels. These tunnels are ports on a bridge and enable bridges
      on different systems to act as though they were one bridge,
      which allows the compute and network nodes to act as one for the
      purposes of routing.</para>
    <para>Virtual LANs (VLANs), on the other hand, use a special
      modification to the Ethernet header. They add a 4-byte VLAN tag
      that ranges from 1 to 4094 (the 0 tag is special, and the 4095
      tag, made of all ones, is equivalent to an untagged packet).
      Special NICs, switches, and routers know how to interpret the
      VLAN tags, as does Open vSwitch. Packets tagged for one VLAN are
      only shared with other devices configured to be on that VLAN,
      even though all devices are on the same physical
      network.</para>
    <para>The most common security group driver used with Open vSwitch
      is the Hybrid IPTables/Open vSwitch plug-in. It uses a
      combination for IPTables and OpenFlow rules. Use the IPTables
      tool to create firewalls and set up NATs on Linux. This tool
      uses a complex rule system and chains of rules to accommodate
      the complex rules required by Neutron security groups.</para>
  </section>
</section>
