<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section xml:id="debconf-api-endpoints"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
  <title>API end-points registration</title>
  <para>Every Debian package that contains an API service contains the
    debconf logic to register themselves into the Keystone end-point
    catalogue (at the exception of the Orchestration service, which is
    configured within the <systemitem class="service">heat-common</systemitem>
    package and not in the <systemitem class="service">heat-api</systemitem>
    package). This is very useful because the URLs and ports of each API
    are difficult to remember.</para>
    <para>When installing a package containing an API server, the first
    debconf screen prompts users whether to register the service.
    However, after the package is installed (or upgraded), the answer
    to this prompt is immediately removed form the debconf database.
    As a consequence, this debconf screen displays every time, which
    enables the user to re-register the API in the Identity Service,
    but making sure that it is registered only once.</para>
  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata scale="50" fileref="figures/debconf-screenshots/api-endpoint_1_register_endpoint.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
  <para>If you answer <literal>yes</literal> to the previous prompt
    and the API service is already registered in the Identity Service
    database, do not answer <literal>yes</literal> again when you
    upgrade.</para>
  <para>The following debconf screens are necessary for the package to
    reach Keystone and register itself in the catalog.</para>
  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata scale="50" fileref="figures/debconf-screenshots/api-endpoint_2_keystone_server_ip.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
  <para>The following screen prompts for the value in the admin_token
    of Keystone, which is necessary for registering an API server in
    the Identity Service. This admin_token is normally configured
    automatically when setting-up the <systemitem class="library">keystone</systemitem>
    package.</para>
  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata scale="50" fileref="figures/debconf-screenshots/api-endpoint_3_keystone_authtoken.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
  <para>The following screen is the IP addresses of the service that
    the user is configuring. The configuration script automatically
    detects the IP address by using <code>/sbin/route</code> and
      <code>/sbin/ip</code> (detecting the IP address used by the
    interface that is connected to the default route). So in most
    cases, and unless you have a very specific network set up, you
    simply press ENTER.</para>
  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata scale="50" fileref="figures/debconf-screenshots/api-endpoint_4_service_endpoint_ip_address.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
  <para>The last parameter is the region name for the service you are
    currently configuring. For example, <code>us-east-coast</code> or
      <code>europe-paris</code>.</para>
  <informalfigure>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata scale="50" fileref="figures/debconf-screenshots/api-endpoint_5_region_name.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
</section>
