<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
 <!-- Some useful entities borrowed from HTML -->
<!ENTITY ndash  "&#x2013;">
<!ENTITY mdash  "&#x2014;">
<!ENTITY hellip "&#x2026;">
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#xB1;">
        

]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="section_arch_provision">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Provisioning and Deployment</title>
    <para>A critical part of a cloud's scalability is the amount of
        effort that it takes to run your cloud. To minimize the
        operational cost of running your cloud, set up and use an
        automated deployment and configuration infrastructure. </para>
    <para>This infrastructure includes systems to automatically
        install the operating system's initial configuration and later
        coordinate the configuration of all services automatically and
        centrally, which reduces both manual effort and chance for
        error.</para>
    <section xml:id="automated_deploy">
        <title>Automated Deployment</title>
        <para>An automated deployment system installs and configures
            operating systems on new servers, without intervention,
            after the absolute minimum amount of manual work,
            including physical racking, MAC to IP assignment, power
            configuration, and so on. Typically solutions rely on
            wrappers around PXE boot and TFTP servers for the basic
            operating system install, then hand off to an automated
            configuration management system.</para>
        <para>Ubuntu and Red Hat Linux both include mechanisms for
            configuring the operating system, including preseed and
            kickstart, that you can use after a network boot.
            Typically these are used to bootstrap an automated
            configuration system. Alternatively, you can use an
            image-based approach for deploying the operating system,
            such as systemimager. You can use both approaches with a
            virtualized infrastructure, such as when you run VMs to
            separate your control services and physical
            infrastructure.</para>
        <para>When you create a deployment plan, focus on a few vital
            areas because they are very hard to modify
            post-deployment.</para>
        <?hard-pagebreak?>
        <section xml:id="disk_partition_raid">
            <title>Disk Partitioning and RAID</title>
            <para>At the very base of any operating system are the
                hard drives on which the OS is installed.</para>
            <para>You must complete the following configurations on
                the server's hard drives:</para>
            <itemizedlist role="compact">
                <listitem>
                    <para>Partitioning</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Adding to a RAID array</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>The simplest option is to use one hard drive with
                two partitions:</para>
            <itemizedlist role="compact">
                <listitem>
                    <para>File system</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Swap space</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>RAID is not used in this setup.</para>
            <note>
                <para>This option is not recommended for production
                    because if the hard drive fails, that entire
                    server is down. Instead, we recommend that you use
                    more than one disk. The number of disks determine
                    what types of RAID arrays to build.</para>
            </note>
            <?hard-pagebreak?>
            <para>We recommend that you choose one of the following
                multiple disk options:</para>
            <itemizedlist role="compact">
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Option 1:</emphasis>
                        Partition all drives in the same way in a
                        horizontal fashion, as shown in the following
                        diagram: <informalfigure>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject>
                                   <imagedata width="5in"
                                   fileref="figures/os_disk_partition.png"
                                   />
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </informalfigure></para>
                    <para>With this option, you can assign different
                        partitions to different RAID arrays. You can
                        allocate partition 1 of disk one and two to
                        the <code>/boot</code> partition mirror. You
                        can make partition 2 of all disks the root
                        partition mirror. You can use partition 3 of
                        all disks for a <code>cinder-volumes</code>
                        LVM partition running on a RAID 10
                        array.</para>
                    <para>While you might end up with unused
                        partitions, such as partition 1 in disk three
                        and four of this example, it allows for
                        maximum utilization of disk space. I/O
                        performance might be an issue due to all disks
                        being used for all tasks.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Option 2:</emphasis>
                        Add all raw disks to one large RAID array,
                        either hardware or software based. You can
                        partition this large array with the boot,
                        root, swap, and LVM areas. This option is
                        simple to implement and uses all partitions.
                        However, disk I/O might suffer.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Option 3:</emphasis>
                        Dedicate entire disks to certain partitions.
                        For example, you could allocate disk one and
                        two entirely to the boot, root, and swap
                        partitions under a RAID 1 mirror. Then,
                        allocate disk 3 and 4 entirely to the LVM
                        partition, also under a RAID 1 mirror. Disk
                        I/O should be better because I/O is focused on
                        dedicated tasks. However, the LVM partition is
                        much smaller.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>As with most architecture choices, the right answer
                depends on your environment.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="network_config">
            <title>Network Configuration</title>
            <para>Network configuration is a very large topic that
                spans multiple areas of this book. For now, make sure
                that your servers can PXE boot and successfully
                communicate with the deployment server.</para>
            <para>For example, you usually cannot configure NICs for
                VLANs when PXE booting. Additionally, you usually
                cannot PXE boot with bonded NICs. If you run into this
                scenario, consider using a simple 1 GB switch in a
                private network on which only your cloud
                communicates.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="auto_config">
        <title>Automated Configuration</title>
        <para>The purpose of automatic configuration management is to
            establish and maintain the consistency of a system with no
            human intervention. You want to maintain consistency in
            your deployments so you can have the same cloud every
            time, repeatably. Proper use of automatic configuration
            management tools ensures that components of the cloud
            systems are in particular states, in addition to
            simplifying deployment, and configuration change
            propagation. </para>
        <para>These tools also make it possible to test and roll back
            changes, as they are fully repeatable. Conveniently, a
            large body of work has been done by the OpenStack
            community in this space. Puppet – a configuration
            management tool – even provides official modules for
            OpenStack.</para>
        <para>An integral part of a configuration management system is
            the items that it controls. You should carefully consider
            all of the items that you want, or do not want, to be
            automatically managed.</para>
    </section>
    <?hard-pagebreak?>
    <section xml:id="remote_mgmt">
        <title>Remote Management</title>
        <para>In our experience, most operators don't sit right next
            to the servers running the cloud, and many don't
            necessarily enjoy visiting the data center. OpenStack
            should be entirely remotely configurable, but sometimes
            not everything goes according to plan. </para>
        <para>In this instance, having an out-of-band access into
            nodes running OpenStack components, is a boon. The IPMI
            protocol is the de-facto standard here, and acquiring
            hardware that supports it is highly recommended to achieve
            that lights-out data center aim.</para>
        <para>In addition, consider remote power control as well.
            While IPMI usually controls the server's power state,
            having remote access to the PDU that the server is plugged
            into can really be useful for situations when everything
            seems wedged.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
