<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!-- Some useful entities borrowed from HTML -->
<!ENTITY ndash  "&#x2013;">
<!ENTITY mdash  "&#x2014;">
<!ENTITY hellip "&#x2026;">
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#xB1;">
        
        
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="whats_next">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>What's Next?</title>
    <para>Congratulations! By now, you should have a solid design for
        your cloud. We now recommend that you turn to the <link
            xlink:title="OpenStack Install and Deploy Manual - Ubuntu"
            xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/folsom/openstack-compute/install/apt/content/"
            >OpenStack Install and Deploy Manual - Ubuntu</link>
        (http://docs.openstack.org/folsom/openstack-compute/install/apt/content/),
        which contains a step-by-step guide on how to manually install
        the OpenStack packages and dependencies on your cloud. </para>
    <para>While it is important for an operator to be familiar with
        the steps involved in deploying OpenStack, we also strongly
        encourage you to evaluate configuration management tools such
        as <glossterm>Puppet</glossterm> or
            <glossterm>Chef</glossterm> that can help automate this
        deployment process.</para>
    <para>In the remainder of the guide, we assume that you have
        successfully deployed an OpenStack cloud and are able to
        perform basic operations such as adding images, booting
        instances, and attaching volumes.</para>
    <para>As your focus turns to stable operations, we recommend you
        do an initial skim of the remainder of the book to get a sense
        of the content. Some of this content is useful to read in
        advance, so that you can put best practices into effect to
        simplify your life in the long run. Other content is more
        useful as a reference that you might refer when an unexpected
        event occurs, such a power failure or troubleshooting a
        particular problem.</para>
</chapter>
