<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
<!-- Some useful entities borrowed from HTML -->
<!ENTITY ndash  "&#x2013;">
<!ENTITY mdash  "&#x2014;">
<!ENTITY hellip "&#x2026;">
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#xB1;">

]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="example_architecture">
    <title>Example Architecture</title>
    <para>Because OpenStack is highly configurable, with many
        different back-ends and network configuration options, it is
        difficult to write documentation that covers all possible
        OpenStack deployments. Therefore, in this guide we have
        defined an <emphasis>example architecture</emphasis> to
        simplify the task of documenting, as well as to scope this
        guide so that it is focused on a configuration where the
        authors have direct deployment experience.</para>
    <section xml:id="overview">
        <title>Overview</title>
        <informaltable rules="all">
            <col width="40%"/>
            <col width="60%"/>
            <tbody>
                <tr>
                    <td><para>OpenStack release</para></td>
                    <td><para>Folsom</para></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><para>Host operating system</para></td>
                    <td><para>Ubuntu 12.04 LTS</para></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><para>OpenStack package repository</para></td>
                    <td><para><link
                                xlink:href="https://wiki.ubuntu.com/ServerTeam/CloudArchive"
                                >Ubuntu Cloud Archive</link>
                            (https://wiki.ubuntu.com/ServerTeam/CloudArchive)
                            *</para></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><para>Hypervisor</para></td>
                    <td><para>KVM</para></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><para>Database</para></td>
                    <td><para>MySQL*</para></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><para>Message queue</para></td>
                    <td><para>RabbitMQ</para></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><para>Networking service</para></td>
                    <td><para>nova-network</para></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><para>Network manager</para></td>
                    <td><para>FlatDHCP</para></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><para>Single nova-network or
                            multi-host?</para></td>
                    <td><para>multi-host*</para></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><para>Image Service (glance)
                        back-end</para></td>
                    <td><para>file</para></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><para>Identity Service (keystone)
                            driver</para></td>
                    <td><para>SQL</para></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><para>Block Storage Service (cinder)
                            back-end</para></td>
                    <td><para>LVM/iSCSI</para></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><para>Live Migration back-end</para></td>
                    <td><para>shared storage using NFS *</para></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><para>Object storage</para></td>
                    <td><para>OpenStack Object Storage
                        (swift)</para></td>
                </tr>
            </tbody>
        </informaltable>
        <para>An asterisk (*) indicates when the example architecture
            deviates from the settings of a default
            installation.</para>
        <note>
            <para>The following features of OpenStack are supported by
                the example architecture documented in this guide, but
                are optional: <itemizedlist role="compact">
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Dashboard</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Block storage</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Floating IPs</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Live migration</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Object storage</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
        </note>
    </section>
    <?hard-pagebreak?>
    <section xml:id="rationale">
        <title>Rationale</title>
        <para>This example architecture has been selected based on the
            current default feature set of OpenStack Folsom, with an
            emphasis on stability. In particular, if none of the guide
            authors had experience deploying the Folsom release of
            OpenStack with a specific back-end or configuration, we
            did not consider it for the example architecture. We
            believe that many clouds currently running OpenStack in
            production will have made similar choices.</para>
        <para>The first selection to make is the Operating System that
            will run on all of the physical nodes. While OpenStack is
            supported on several distributions of Linux, we used
                <emphasis role="bold">Ubuntu 12.04 LTS (Long Term
                Support)</emphasis>. This is due to several factors,
            including its use by the majority of the development
            community, feature completeness compared with other
            distributions and clear future support plans.</para>
        <para>We recommend that you do not use the default Ubuntu
            OpenStack install packages and instead use the <link
                xlink:href="https://wiki.ubuntu.com/ServerTeam/CloudArchive"
                >Ubuntu Cloud Archive</link>
            (https://wiki.ubuntu.com/ServerTeam/CloudArchive). The
            Cloud Archive is a package repository supported by
            Canonical that will allow you to upgrade to future
            OpenStack releases while still remaining on Ubuntu
            12.04.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">KVM</emphasis> as a hypervisor
            complements the choice of Ubuntu - being a matched pair in
            terms of support, and also because of the significant
            degree of attention it garners from the OpenStack
            development community (including the authors, who mostly
            use KVM). It is also feature complete, free from licensing
            charges and restrictions.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">MySQL</emphasis> follows a similar
            trend. Despite its recent change of ownership, this
            database is the most tested for use with OpenStack and is
            heavily documented for running on Ubuntu. We deviate from
            the default database, <emphasis>SQLite</emphasis>, because
            SQLite is not an appropriate database for production
            usage.</para>
        <para>The choice of <emphasis role="bold"> RabbitMQ</emphasis>
            over other AMQP compatible options that are gaining
            support in OpenStack, such as ZeroMQ and Qpid is due to
            its ease of use with Ubuntu and significant testing in
            production. It also is the only option which supports
            features such as Compute Cells. We recommend clustering
            with RabbitMQ, as it is an integral component of the
            system, and fairly simple to implement due to its inbuilt
            nature.</para>
        <para>As discussed in previous chapters, there are several
            options for networking in OpenStack Compute. We recommend
                <emphasis role="bold">FlatDHCP</emphasis> and to use
                <emphasis role="bold">Multi-Host</emphasis> networking
            mode for high availability, running one
                <code>nova-network</code> daemon per OpenStack Compute
            host. This provides a robust mechanism for ensuring
            network interruptions are isolated to individual compute
            hosts, and allows for the direct use of hardware network
            gateways.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Live Migration</emphasis> is
            supported by way of shared storage, with <emphasis
                role="bold">NFS</emphasis> as the distributed file
            system.</para>
        <para>Acknowledging that many small-scale deployments see
            running an Object Storage service just for the storage of
            virtual machine images as too costly, we opted for the
            file back-end in the OpenStack Image Catalog and Delivery
            Service (Glance). If the cloud you are designing also
            intends to run Object Storage, it is trivial to enable
            this as the back-end instead, and a recommended
            approach.</para>
        <?hard-pagebreak?>
        <para>The <emphasis role="bold">SQL back-end for Identify
                Service (keystone)</emphasis> was selected over
            others, such as LDAP, as it is the simplest to install and
            has a large degree of robustness. The authors acknowledge
            that many installations will desire binding with an
            existing directory services, and caution careful
            understanding of the <link
                xlink:title="LDAP config options"
                xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/folsom/openstack-compute/admin/content/reference-for-ldap-config-options.html"
                >array of options available</link>
            (http://docs.openstack.org/folsom/openstack-compute/admin/content/reference-for-ldap-config-options.html)</para>
        <para>The Block Storage service (Cinder) will be installed
            natively on external storage nodes and will use the
                <emphasis role="bold">LVM/iSCSI plugin</emphasis>.
            Most Block Storage Service plugins are tied to particular
            vendor products and implementations limiting their use to
            consumers of those hardware platforms, but LVM/iSCSI is
            known to be robust and stable on commodity
            hardware.</para>
        <para>While the cloud can be run without the <emphasis
                role="bold">OpenStack Dashboard</emphasis>, we
            consider it to be indispensable, not just for user
            interaction with the cloud, but also as a tool for
            operators. Additionally, the dashboard's use of Django
            makes it a flexible framework for extension.</para>

        <section xml:id="quantum">
            <title>Why Not Use the OpenStack Network Service
                (quantum)?</title>
            <para>We do not discuss the OpenStack Network Service
                (quantum) in this guide, because the authors of this
                guide only have production deployment experience using
                    <code>nova-network</code>. Additionally, it does
                not yet support multi-host networking.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="multi-host-networking">
            <title>Why Use Multi-host Networking?</title>
            <para>In a default OpenStack deployment, there is a single
                    <code>nova-network</code> service that runs within
                the cloud (usually on the cloud controller) that
                provides services such as network address translation
                (NAT), DHCP, and DNS to the guest instances. If the
                single node that runs the <code>nova-network</code>
                service goes down, then you will not be able to access
                your instances nor will the instances be able to
                access the Internet. There is also the risk that the
                single node that runs the nova-network service can
                become a bottleneck if there is excessive network
                traffic coming in and out of the cloud.</para>
            <para>
                <link xlink:title="Multi-host"
                    xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/folsom/openstack-compute/admin/content/existing-ha-networking-options.html#d6e8906"
                    >Multi-host</link>
                (http://docs.openstack.org/folsom/openstack-compute/admin/content/existing-ha-networking-options.html#d6e8906)
                is a high-availability option for the network
                configuration where the nova-network service is run on
                every compute node instead of running on only a single
                node.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <?hard-pagebreak?>
    <section xml:id="detailed_desc">
        <title>Detailed Description</title>
        <para>The reference architecture consists of multiple compute
            nodes, a cloud controller, an external NFS storage server
            for instance storage and an OpenStack Block Storage server
            for volume storage. A network time service (Network Time
            Protocol, NTP) synchronizes time for all the nodes.
            FlatDHCPManager in multi-host mode is used for the
            networking.</para>
        <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="5in"
                        fileref="figures/os-ref-arch.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
        <para>The cloud controller runs: the Dashboard, the API
            services, the database (MySQL), a message queue server
            (RabbitMQ), the scheduler for choosing compute resources
            (nova-scheduler), Identity services (keystone,
                <code>nova-consoleauth</code>), Image services
                (<code>glance-api</code>,
            <code>glance-registry</code>), services for console access
            of guests, and block storage services including the
            scheduler for storage resources (<code>cinder-api</code>
            and <code>cinder-scheduler</code>).</para>
        <?hard-pagebreak?>
        <para>Compute nodes are where the computing resources are
            held, and in our example architecture they run the
            hypervisor (KVM), libvirt (the driver for the hypervisor
            which enables live migration node to node),
                <code>nova-compute</code>,
                <code>nova-api-metadata</code> (generally only used
            when running in multi-host mode, it retrieves
            instance-specific metadata), nova-vncproxy, and
                <code>nova-network.</code>
        </para>
        <para>The network consists of two switches, one for the
            management or private traffic, and one which covers public
            access including Floating IPs. To support this, the cloud
            controller and the compute nodes have two network cards.
            The OpenStack Block Storage and NFS storage servers only
            need to access the private network and therefore only need
            one network card, but multiple cards run in a bonded
            configuration are recommended if possible. Floating IP
            access is direct to the internet, whereas Flat IP access
            goes through a NAT.</para>
        <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="5in"
                        fileref="figures/os_physical_network_1.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
    </section>
    <?hard-pagebreak?>
    <section xml:id="optional_extensions">
        <title>Optional Extensions</title>
        <para>You can extend this reference architecture as
            follows:</para>
        <itemizedlist role="compact">
            <listitem>
                <para>Add additional cloud controllers (see <emphasis
                        role="bold">Maintenance, Debugging and
                        Failures</emphasis>)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Add an OpenStack Storage service
                    (http://docs.openstack.org/folsom/openstack-object-storage/admin/)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Add additional OpenStack Block Storage hosts
                    (see <emphasis role="bold">Maintenance, Debugging
                        and Failures</emphasis>)</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
</section>
