<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!-- Some useful entities borrowed from HTML -->
<!ENTITY ndash  "&#x2013;">
<!ENTITY mdash  "&#x2014;">
<!ENTITY hellip "&#x2026;">
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#xB1;">

]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="projects_users">
    <title>Managing Projects and Users</title>
    <para>An OpenStack cloud does not have much value without users.
        This chapter covers topics that relate to managing users,
        projects, and quotas.</para>
    <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">Projects or tenants?</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>In OpenStack user interfaces and documentation, you will
        sometimes see the term "project" to refer to a group of users,
        and other times you will see the term "tenant". These terms
        are interchangeable.</para>
    <para>The reason behind this bifurcation is historical. The
        initial implementation of the OpenStack Compute Service (nova)
        had its own authentication system and used the term "project".
        When authentication was broken out into the OpenStack Identity
        Service (keystone) project, the new project used the term
        "tenant" to refer to a group of users. Because of this legacy,
        some of the OpenStack tools refer to "projects" and some refer
        to "tenants".</para>
    <para>In this guide, we will use the term "project" unless we are
        showing an example interaction with a tool that uses the term
        "tenant".</para>
    <section xml:id="managing_projects">
        <title>Managing Projects</title>
        <para>Users must be associated with at least one project,
            though they may belong to many. Therefore, you should add
            at least one project before adding users.</para>
        <section xml:id="add_projects">
            <title>Adding Projects</title>
            <para>To create a project through the dashboard:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Log in as an administrative user.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Select the "Projects" link in the left hand
                        navigation bar.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Click on the "Create Project" button at the
                        top right.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>This will pop up a form asking from asking for a
                project name and an optional, but recommended,
                description. There is also a check box at the bottom
                of the form to enable this project, by default this is
                enabled.</para>
            <informalfigure>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata width="5in"
                            fileref="figures/horizon-add-project.png"
                        />
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
            <para>As you can see from here, it is also possible to add
                project members and adjust the project quotas. We'll
                discuss those later, but in practice it can be quite
                convenient to deal with all these operations at one
                time.</para>
            <para>To create a project through the command-line
                interface (CLI):</para>
            <para>To add a project through the command line, you must
                use the keystone utility, which uses "tenant" in place
                of "project": </para>
            <programlisting># keystone tenant-create --name=demo</programlisting>
            <para>This will create a new project named "demo".
                Optionally, you can add a description string by
                appending <code>--description
                    &lt;tenant-description&gt;,</code> which can be
                very useful. It is also possible to create a group in
                a disabled state by appending <code>--enabled
                    false</code>. By default, projects are created in
                an enabled state.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <?hard-pagebreak?>
    <section xml:id="quotas">
        <title>Quotas</title>
        <para>OpenStack provides a number of quotas which are all
            enforced at the project (rather than user) level. As an
            administrative user in the Dashboard you can see (but not
            edit) the default quotas using the "Quotas" link in the
            navigation sidebar. These default project quotas are
            specified in the <code>nova.conf</code> file on your cloud
            controller.</para>
        <para>If you do not make quota-related changes, the system
            uses the following defaults.</para>
        <table xml:id="nova_conf" rules="all">
            <caption>Description of nova.conf file configuration
                options for
                quotas<!--<superscript
                    xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
                    <link xlink:href="#InsertNoteID_1">???? </link>
                </superscript> -->
            </caption>
            <colgroup>
                <col width="50%"/>
                <col width="50%"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
                <tr>
                    <th>Configuration option=Default value </th>
                    <th>(Type) Description </th>
                </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <para>quota_cores=20</para>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                        <para>(IntOpt) number of instance cores
                            allowed per project (tenant)</para>
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <para>quota_floating_ips=10</para>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                        <para>(IntOpt) number of floating ips allowed
                            per project (tenant)</para>
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <para>quota_gigabytes=1000</para>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                        <para>(IntOpt) number of volume gigabytes
                            allowed per project (tenant)</para>
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <para>quota_injected_file_content_bytes=10240</para>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                        <para>(IntOpt) number of bytes allowed per
                            injected file</para>
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <para>quota_injected_file_path_bytes=255</para>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                        <para>(IntOpt) number of bytes allowed per
                            injected file path</para>
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <para>quota_injected_files=5</para>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                        <para>(IntOpt) number of injected files
                            allowed</para>
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <para>quota_instances=10</para>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                        <para>(IntOpt) number of instances allowed per
                            project (tenant)</para>
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <para>quota_key_pairs=100</para>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                        <para>(IntOpt) number of key pairs allowed per
                            user</para>
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <para>quota_metadata_items=128</para>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                        <para>(IntOpt) number of metadata items
                            allowed per instance</para>
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <para>quota_ram=51200</para>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                        <para>(IntOpt) megabytes of instance ram
                            allowed per project (tenant)</para>
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <para>quota_security_group_rules=20</para>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                        <para>(IntOpt) number of security rules per
                            security group</para>
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <para>quota_security_groups=10</para>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                        <para>(IntOpt) number of security groups per
                            project (tenant)</para>
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <para>quota_volumes=10</para>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                        <para>(IntOpt) number of volumes allowed per
                            project (tenant)</para>
                    </td>
                </tr>
            </tbody>
        </table>
        <para>Configuration
            (http://docs.openstack.org/folsom/openstack-compute/admin/content/list-of-compute-config-options.html)</para>
        <para>The simplest way to change the default project quotas is
            to edit the <code>nova.conf</code> file on your cloud
            controller. Quotas are enforced by the
                <code>nova-scheduler</code> service, so you must
            restart that service once you change these options.</para>
        <para>If your site implementation varies from our example
            architecture, ensure any changes you make to quota default
            options in <code>/etc/nova/nova.conf</code> are applied to
            the host(s) running the <code>nova-scheduler</code>
            service. It is critical for consistent quota enforcement
            that all schedulers have identical quotas. Assuming you
            are following the best practices recommended in this
            guide, your configuration management system will
            automatically ensure all your schedulers have consistent
            configurations.</para>
        <para>To view and edit quotas for an individual project via
            Dashboard:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Use the "Projects" navigation link to get a list
                    of your existing projects.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Locate the project you want to modify and select
                    "Modify Quotas" from the "Actions" drop down menu
                    a the end of the line.  </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>To view and edit quotas for an individual project via
            CLI, follow these steps:</para>
        <para>You can access and modify quotas from the command line
            but it is a bit complicated. This is done using Keystone
            to get the ID and then <code>nova-manage.</code>
        </para>
        <para>1. To list a project's quota, you must first find its ID
            using the Keystone CLI tool.</para>
        <programlisting><?db-font-size 65%?># keystone tenant-list | grep &lt;tenant-name&gt;
 
      
| 98333a1a28e746fa8c629c83a818ad57 | &lt;tenant-name&gt; | True | </programlisting>
        <para>2. Recall that the Keystone CLI tool uses "tenant" where
            the Nova CLI tool uses "project" for the same concept. To
            show the quota for the project, for the example above, we
            must use the ID
                <code>98333a1a28e746fa8c629c83a818ad57</code>:</para>
        <programlisting language="bash"># nova-manage project quota 98333a1a28e746fa8c629c83a818ad57</programlisting>
        <programlisting language="bash">metadata_items: 128
volumes: 10
gigabytes: 1000
ram: 6291456
security_group_rules: 20
instances: 1024
security_groups: 10
injected_file_content_bytes: 10240
floating_ips: 10
injected_files: 5
cores: 2048</programlisting>
        <para>Note: Confusingly, <code>nova-manage project
                quota</code> will silently accept any string at the
            end of the command and report the default quotas. In
            particular, if you enter the project name rather than the
            ID, <code>nova-manage</code> won't complain, it will just
            lie.</para>
        <para>To change these values you append <code>--key</code> and
                <code>--value</code> flags to the above command. To
            increase the tenant quota of Floating IPs from 10 to
            20:</para>
        <programlisting><?db-font-size 65%?># nova-manage project quota 98333a1a28e746fa8c629c83a818ad57 --key floating_ips --value 20 </programlisting>
        <programlisting><?db-font-size 65%?>metadata_items: 128 
volumes: 10
gigabytes: 1000
ram: 6291456
security_group_rules: 20
instances: 1024
security_groups: 10
injected_file_content_bytes: 10240
floating_ips: 20
injected_files: 5
cores: 2048</programlisting>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="user_mgmt">
        <title>User Management</title>
        <para>The command line tools for managing users are
            inconvenient to use directly. They require issuing
            multiple commands to complete a single task, and they use
            UUIDs rather than symbolic names for many items. In
            practice, humans typically do not use these tools
            directly. Fortunately, the OpenStack Dashboard provides a
            reasonable interface to this. In addition, many sites
            write custom tools for local needs to enforce local
            policies and provide levels of self service to users that
            aren't currently available with packaged tools.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="create_new_users">
        <title>Creating New Users</title>
        <para>To create a new user you will need the following
            information:</para>
        <itemizedlist role="compact">
            <listitem>
                <para>Username</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Email address</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Password</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Primary project</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Role</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>Username and email address are self-explanatory, though
            your site may have local conventions you should observe.
            Setting and changing passwords in the Identity Service
            requires administrative privileges. As of the Folsom
            release, users cannot change their own passwords. This is
            a large driver for creating local custom tools, and must
            be kept in mind when assigning and distributing passwords.
            The primary project is simply the first project the user
            is associated with and must exist prior to creating the
            user. Role is almost always going to be "member". Out of
            the box, OpenStack comes with two roles defined:</para>
        <itemizedlist role="compact">
            <listitem>
                <para>"member":  a typical user.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>"admin":  an administrative super user which has
                    full permissions across all projects and should be
                    used with great care.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>It is possible to define other roles, but doing so is
            uncommon.</para>
        <para>Once you've gathered this information, creating the user
            in the Dashboard is just another web form similar to what
            we've seen before and can be found on the "Users" link in
            the "Admin" navigation bar and then clicking the "Create
            User" button at the top right.</para>
        <para>Modifying users is also done from this "Users" page. If
            you have a large number of users, this page can get quite
            crowded. The "Filter" search box at the top of the page
            can be used to limit the users listing. A form very
            similar to the user creation dialog can be pulled up by
            selecting "Edit" from the actions drop down menu at the
            end of the line for the user you are modifying.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="associate_users_with_projects">
        <title>Associating Users with Projects</title>
        <para>Many sites run with users being associated with only one
            project. This is a more conservative and simpler choice
            both for administration and for users. Administratively if
            a user reports a problem with an instance or quota it is
            obvious which project this relates to as well. Users
            needn't worry about what project they are acting in if
            they are only in one project. However, note that, by
            default, any user can affect the resources of any other
            user within their project. It is also possible to
            associate users with multiple projects if that makes sense
            for your organization.</para>
        <para>Associating existing users with an additional project or
            removing them from an older project is done from the
            "Projects" page of the Dashboard by selecting the "Modify
            Users" from the "Actions" column:</para>
        <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata width="5in"
                        fileref="figures/horizon-user-project.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
        <para>From this view you can do a number of useful and a few
            dangerous things.</para>
        <para>The first column of this form, titled "All Users", will
            include a list of all the users in your cloud who are not
            already associated with this project and the second all
            the users who are. These can be quite long, but can be
            limited by typing a substring of the user name you are
            looking for in the filter field at the top of the
            column.</para>
        <para>From here, clicking on the "+" will add users to the
            project and clicking the "-" will remove them.</para>
        <para>The dangerous possibility comes in the ability to change
            member roles. This is the drop down list after the user
            name in the "Project Members" list. In virtually all cases
            this value should be set to "Member". This example
            purposefully show and administrative user where this value
            is "admin". <emphasis role="bold">It is extremely
                important to note that the "admin" is global not per
                project so granting a user the admin role in any
                project gives the administrative rights across the
                whole cloud.</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para>Typical use is to only create administrative users in a
            single project, by convention the "admin" project which is
            created by default during cloud setup. If your
            administrative users also use the cloud to launch and
            manage instances it is strongly recommended that you use
            separate user accounts for administrative access and
            normal operations and that they be in distinct
            projects.</para>
        <section xml:id="customize_auth">
            <title>Customizing Authorization</title>
            <para>The default authorization settings only allow
                administrative users to create resources on behalf of
                a different project. OpenStack handles two kind of
                authorization policies:</para>
            <itemizedlist role="compact">
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis role="bold"
                            >Operation-based</emphasis>: policies
                        specify access criteria for specific
                        operations, possibly with fine-grained control
                        over specific attributes.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis role="bold"
                            >Resource-based</emphasis>: whether access
                        to a specific resource might be granted or not
                        according to the permissions configured for
                        the resource (currently available only for the
                        network resource). The actual authorization
                        policies enforced in an OpenStack service vary
                        from deployment to deployment.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>The policy engine reads entries from the
                    <code>policy.json</code> file. The actual location
                of this file might vary from distribution to
                distribution, for nova it is typically in
                    <code>/etc/nova/policy.json</code>. You can update
                entries while the system is running, and you do not
                have to restart services. Currently the only way of
                updating such policies is to edit the policy
                file.</para>
            <para>The OpenStack service's policy engine matches a
                policy directly. A rule indicates evaluation of the
                elements of such policies. For instance, in a
                    <code>compute:create:
                    [["rule:admin_or_owner"]]</code> statement, the
                policy is <code>compute:create</code>, and the rule is
                    <code>admin_or_owner</code>.</para>
            <para>Policies are triggered by an OpenStack policy engine
                whenever one of them matches an OpenStack API
                operation or a specific attribute being used in a
                given operation. For instance, the engine tests the
                    <code>create:compute</code> policy every time a
                user sends a <code>POST /v2/{tenant_id}servers</code>
                request to the OpenStack Compute API server. Policies
                can be also related to specific API extensions. For
                instance, if a user needs an extension like
                    <code>compute_extension:rescue</code> the
                attributes defined by the provider extensions trigger
                the rule test for that operation.</para>
            <para>An authorization policy can be composed by one or
                more rules. If more rules are specified, evaluation
                policy will be successful if any of the rules
                evaluates successfully; if an API operation matches
                multiple policies, then all the policies must evaluate
                successfully. Also, authorization rules are recursive.
                Once a rule is matched, the rule(s) can be resolved to
                another rule, until a terminal rule is reached. These
                are the rules defined:</para>
            <itemizedlist role="compact">
                <listitem>

                    <para>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Role-based
                            rules</emphasis>: evaluate successfully if
                        the user submitting the request has the
                        specified role. For instance
                            <code>"role:admin"</code>is successful if
                        the user submitting the request is an
                        administrator.</para>

                </listitem>
                <listitem>

                    <para>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Field-based rules:
                        </emphasis>evaluate successfully if a field of
                        the resource specified in the current request
                        matches a specific value. For instance
                            <code>"field:networks:shared=True"</code>
                        is successful if the attribute shared of the
                        network resource is set to true.</para>

                </listitem>
                <listitem>

                    <para>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Generic
                            rules:</emphasis> compare an attribute in
                        the resource with an attribute extracted from
                        the user's security credentials and evaluates
                        successfully if the comparison is successful.
                        For instance
                            <code>"tenant_id:%(tenant_id)s"</code> is
                        successful if the tenant identifier in the
                        resource is equal to the tenant identifier of
                        the user submitting the request.</para>

                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Here are snippets of the default nova policy.json
                file:</para>
            <programlisting><?db-font-size 65%?>{
	"context_is_admin":  [["role:admin"]],
	"admin_or_owner":  [["is_admin:True"], ["project_id:%(project_id)s"]], <emphasis role="bold">[1]</emphasis>
	"default": [["rule:admin_or_owner"]], <emphasis role="bold">[2]</emphasis>
	"compute:create": [],
	"compute:create:attach_network": [],
	"compute:create:attach_volume": [],
	"compute:get_all": [],
    "admin_api": [["is_admin:True"]],
	"compute_extension:accounts": [["rule:admin_api"]],
	"compute_extension:admin_actions": [["rule:admin_api"]],
	"compute_extension:admin_actions:pause": [["rule:admin_or_owner"]],
	"compute_extension:admin_actions:unpause": [["rule:admin_or_owner"]],
	"compute_extension:admin_actions:suspend": [["rule:admin_or_owner"]],
	"compute_extension:admin_actions:resume": [["rule:admin_or_owner"]],
	...
	"compute_extension:admin_actions:migrate": [["rule:admin_api"]],
	"compute_extension:aggregates": [["rule:admin_api"]],
	"compute_extension:certificates": [],
	"compute_extension:cloudpipe": [["rule:admin_api"]],
	...
	"compute_extension:flavorextraspecs": [],
	"compute_extension:flavormanage": [["rule:admin_api"]],  <emphasis role="bold">[3]</emphasis>
	}
	</programlisting>
            <para>[1] Shows a rule which evaluates successfully if the
                current user is an administrator or the owner of the
                resource specified in the request (tenant identifier
                is equal).</para>
            <para>[2] Shows the default policy which is always
                evaluated if an API operation does not match any of
                the policies in <code>policy.json</code>.</para>
            <para>[3] Shows a policy restricting the ability of
                manipulating flavors to administrators using the Admin
                API only.</para>
            <para>In some cases, some operations should be restricted
                to administrators only. Therefore, as a further
                example, let us consider how this sample policy file
                could be modified in a scenario where we enable users
                to create their own flavors:</para>
            <programlisting><?db-font-size 65%?>"compute_extension:flavormanage": [ ],</programlisting>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="problem_users">
            <title>Problematic Users (Users that Disrupt Other
                Users)</title>
            <para>Users on your cloud can disrupt other users,
                sometimes intentionally and maliciously and other
                times by accident. Understanding the situation allows
                you to make a better decision on how to handle the
                disruption.</para>
            <para>For example: A group of users have instances that
                are utilizing a large amount of compute resources for
                very compute-intensive tasks. This is driving the load
                up on compute nodes and affecting other users. In this
                situation, review your user use cases. You may find
                that high compute scenarios are common and should then
                plan for proper segregation in your cloud such as host
                aggregation or regions.</para>
            <para>Another example is a user consuming a very large
                amount of bandwidth. Again, the key is to understand
                what the user is doing. If they naturally need a high
                amount of bandwidth, you might have to limit their
                transmission rate as to not affect other users or move
                them to an area with more bandwidth available. On the
                other hand, maybe the user's instance has been hacked
                and is part of a botnet launching DDOS attacks.
                Resolution to this issue is the same as if any other
                server on your network has been hacked. Contact the
                user and give them time to respond. If they don't
                respond, shut the instance down.</para>
            <para>A final example is if a user is hammering cloud
                resources repeatedly. Contact the user and learn what
                they are trying to do. Maybe they don't understand
                that what they're doing is inappropriate or maybe
                there is an issue with the resource they are trying to
                access that is causing their requests to queue or
                lag.</para>
            <para>One key element of systems administration that is
                often overlooked is that end users are the reason why
                systems administrators exist. Don't go the BOFH route
                and terminate every user who causes an alert to go
                off. Work with them to understand what they're trying
                to accomplish and see how your environment can better
                assist them in achieving their goals.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
