<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!-- Some useful entities borrowed from HTML -->
<!ENTITY ndash  "&#x2013;">
<!ENTITY mdash  "&#x2014;">
<!ENTITY hellip "&#x2026;">
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#xB1;">
        
       
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="backup_and_recovery">
    <title>Backup and Recovery</title>
    <para>Standard backup best practices apply when creating your
        OpenStack backup policy. For example, how often to backup your
        data is closely related to how quickly you need to recover
        from data loss (side note: if you cannot have any data loss at
        all, you should be focusing on High Availability as well as
        backups).</para>
    <para>Other backup considerations include:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>How many backups to keep?</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Should backups be kept off-site?</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>How often should backups be tested?</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Just as important as a backup policy is a recovery policy
        (or at least recovery testing).</para>


    <section xml:id="what_to_backup">
        <title>What to Backup</title>
        <para>While OpenStack is composed of many components and
            moving parts, backing up the critical data is quite
            simple.</para>
        <para>Please note, though, that this chapter will only talk
            about backing up configuration files and databases that
            are needed for the various OpenStack components to run.
            This chapter will not talk about backing up objects inside
            Object Storage or data contained inside Block Storage.
            Generally these areas are left for the user to back up on
            their own.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="database_backups">
        <title>Database Backups</title>
        <para>The example OpenStack architecture designates the Cloud
            Controller as the MySQL server. This MySQL server hosts
            the databases for Nova, Glance, Cinder, and Keystone. With
            all of these databases in one place, it's very easy to
            create a database backup:</para>
        <para>
            <code># mysqldump --opt --all-databases &gt;
                openstack.sql</code>
        </para>
        <para>If you only want to backup a single database, you can
            instead run:</para>
        <para>
            <code># mysqldump --opt nova &gt; nova.sql</code>
        </para>
        <para>where <code>nova</code> is the database you want to back
            up.</para>
        <para>You can easily automate this process by creating a cron
            job that will run the following script once per
            day:</para>
        <programlisting>#!/bin/bash
backup_dir="/var/lib/backups/mysql"
filename="${backup_dir}/mysql-`hostname`-`eval date +%Y%m%d`.sql.gz"
# Dump the entire MySQL database
/usr/bin/mysqldump --opt --all-databases | gzip &gt; $filename 
# Delete backups older than 7 days
find $backup_dir -ctime +7 -type f -delete</programlisting>
        <para>This script will dump the entire MySQL database and
            delete any backups older than 7 days.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="file_system_backups">
        <title>File System Backups</title>
        <section xml:id="compute">
            <title>Compute</title>
            <para>The <code>/etc/nova</code> directory on both the
                cloud controller and compute nodes should be regularly
                backed up.</para>
            <para>
                <code>/var/log/nova</code> does not need backed up if
                you have all logs going to a central area. It is
                highly recommended to use a central logging server or
                backup the log directory.</para>
            <para>
                <code>/var/lib/nova</code> is another important
                directory to backup. The exception to this is the
                    <code>/var/lib/nova/instances</code> subdirectory
                on compute nodes. This subdirectory will contain the
                KVM images of running instances. You would only want
                to back up this directory if you need to maintain
                backup copies of all instances. Under most
                circumstances you will not need to do this, but this
                can vary from cloud to cloud and your service levels.
                Also be aware that making a backup of a live KVM
                instance will probably cause that instance to not boot
                properly if it is ever restored from a backup.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="image_catalog_delivery">
            <title>Image Catalog and Delivery</title>
            <para>
                <code>/etc/glance</code> and
                    <code>/var/log/glance</code> follow the same rules
                at the nova counterparts.</para>
            <para>
                <code>/var/lib/glance</code> should also be backed up.
                Take special notice of
                    <code>/var/lib/glance/images</code>. If you are
                using a file-based back-end of Glance,
                    <code>/var/lib/glance/images</code> is where the
                images will be stored and care should be taken.</para>
            <para>There are two ways to ensure stability with this
                directory. The first is to make sure this directory is
                run on a RAID array. This way if a disk fails, the
                directory will still be available. The second way is
                to use a tool such as rsync to replicate the images to
                another server:</para>
            <para># rsync -az --progress /var/lib/glance/images
                backup-server:/var/lib/glance/images/</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="identity">
            <title>Identity</title>
            <para>
                <code>/etc/keystone</code> and
                    <code>/var/log/keystone</code> follow the same
                rules as other components.</para>
            <para>
                <code>/var/lib/keystone</code>, while should not
                contain any data being used, can also be backed up
                just in case.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="ops_block_storage">
            <title>Block Storage</title>
            <para>
                <code>/etc/cinder</code> and
                    <code>/var/log/cinder</code> follow the same rules
                as other components.</para>
            <para>
                <code>/var/lib/cinder</code> should also be backed
                up.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="ops_object_storage">
            <title>Object Storage</title>
            <para>
                <code>/etc/swift</code> is very important to have
                backed up. This directory contains the Swift
                configuration files as well as the ring files and ring
                builder files, which if lost render the data on your
                cluster inaccessible. A best practice is to copy the
                builder files to all storage nodes along with the ring
                files. This way you will have multiple backups copies
                spread throughout your storage cluster.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="recovering_backups">
        <title>Recovering Backups</title>
        <para>Recovering backups is a fairly simple process. To begin,
            first ensure that the service you are recovering is not
            running. For example, to do a full recovery of nova on the
            cloud controller, first stop all <code>nova</code>
            services:</para>
        <programlisting># stop nova-api
      # stop nova-cert
      # stop nova-consoleauth
      # stop nova-novncproxy
      # stop nova-objectstore
      # stop nova-scheduler</programlisting>
        <para>Once that's done, stop MySQL:</para>
        <programlisting># stop mysql</programlisting>
        <para>Now you can import a previously backed up
            database:</para>
        <programlisting># mysql nova &lt; nova.sql</programlisting>
        <para>As well as restore backed up nova directories:</para>
        <programlisting># mv /etc/nova{,.orig}
      # cp -a /path/to/backup/nova /etc/</programlisting>
        <para>Once the files are restored, start everything back
            up:</para>
        <programlisting># start mysql
      # for i in nova-api nova-cert nova-consoleauth nova-novncproxy nova-objectstore nova-scheduler
      &gt; do
      &gt; start $i
      &gt; done
      </programlisting>
        <para>Other services follow the same process, with their
            respective directories and databases.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
