<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!-- Some useful entities borrowed from HTML -->
<!ENTITY ndash  "&#x2013;">
<!ENTITY mdash  "&#x2014;">
<!ENTITY hellip "&#x2026;">
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#xB1;">
        
        
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="lay_of_the_land">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Lay of the Land</title>
    <para>From this point forward in the guide, we assume that you
        have an OpenStack cloud up and running. This section helps you
        set up your working environment and use it to take a look
        around your cloud.</para>
    <section xml:id="cli_tools">
        <title>Client Command Line Tools</title>
        <para>We recommend using a combination of the OpenStack
            command line interface (CLI) client tools and the
            OpenStack Dashboard. Some users with a background in other
            cloud technologies may be using the EC2 Compatibility API,
            which uses somewhat different naming conventions from the
            native API. We highlight those differences.</para>
        <para>We strongly suggest that you install the command-line
            clients from the <link
                xlink:href="https://pypi.python.org/">Python Package
                Index</link>(PyPI) (https://pypi.python.org/) instead
            of from the Ubuntu or Fedora packages. The clients are
            under heavy development and it is very likely at any given
            time the version of the packages distributed by your
            operating system vendor are out of date. </para>
        <para>The "pip" utility is used to manage package installation
            from the PyPI archive and is available in the "python-pip"
            package in most Linux distributions. Each OpenStack
            project has its own client, so depending on which services
            your site runs, install some or all of the following
            packages:</para>
        <itemizedlist role="compact">
            <listitem>
                <para>python-novaclient (<glossterm>nova</glossterm>
                    CLI)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>python-glanceclient
                        (<glossterm>glance</glossterm> CLI)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>python-keystoneclient
                        (<glossterm>keystone</glossterm> CLI)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>python-cinderclient
                        (<glossterm>cinder</glossterm> CLI)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>python-swiftclient (<glossterm>swift</glossterm>
                    CLI)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>python-quantumclient
                        (<glossterm>quantum</glossterm> CLI)</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <section xml:id="install_tools">
            <title>Installing the Tools</title>
            <para>To install (or upgrade) a package from the PyPI
                archive with pip, as root:</para>
            <programlisting><?db-font-size 60%?># pip install [--upgrade] &lt;package-name&gt;</programlisting>
            <para>To remove the package:</para>
            <programlisting><?db-font-size 60%?># pip uninstall &lt;package-name&gt;</programlisting>
            <para>If you need even newer versions of the clients, pip
                can install directly from the upstream git repository
                using the <code>-e</code> flag. You must specify a
                name for the Python egg that is installed. For
                example:</para>
            <programlisting><?db-font-size 60%?># pip install -e git+https://github.com/openstack/python-novaclient.git#egg=python-novaclient</programlisting>
            <para>If you support the EC2 API on your cloud you should
                also install the "euca2ools" package or some other EC2
                API tool so you can get the same view your users have.
                Using EC2 API based tools is mostly out of the scope
                of this guide, though we discuss getting credentials
                for use with it.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="admin_cli">
            <title>Administrative Command Line Tools</title>
            <para>There are also several <emphasis>*-</emphasis>manage
                command line tools:</para>
            <itemizedlist role="compact">
                <listitem>
                    <para>nova-manage</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>glance-manage</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>keystone-manage</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>cinder-manage</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Unlike the tools mentioned above, the
                    <code>*-manage</code> tools must be run from the
                cloud controller, as root, because they need read
                access to the config files such as
                    <code>/etc/nova/nova.conf</code> and make queries
                directly against the database rather than against the
                OpenStack <glossterm>API endpoint</glossterm>s.</para>
            <para>The existence of the <code>*-manage</code> tools is
                a legacy issue. It is a goal of the OpenStack project
                to eventually migrate all of the remaining
                functionality in the <code>*-manage</code> tools into
                the regular client tools. Until that day, you need to
                SSH into the <glossterm>cloud controller
                    node</glossterm> to perform some maintenance
                operations that require one of the
                    <code>*-manage</code> tools.</para>
        </section>
        <?hard-pagebreak?>
        <section xml:id="get_creds">
            <title>Getting Credentials</title>
            <para>You must have the appropriate credentials if you
                wish to use the command line tools to make queries
                against your OpenStack cloud. By far the easiest way
                to obtain <glossterm>authentication</glossterm>
                credentials to use with command line clients is to use
                the horizon dashboard. From the top right navigation
                row, select the <guilabel>Settings</guilabel> link to
                access the user settings page where you can set your
                language and timezone preferences for the dashboard
                view. More importantly, this action changes the left
                hand navigation column to include <guilabel>OpenStack
                    API</guilabel> and <guilabel>EC2
                    Credentials</guilabel> links, which let you to
                generate files you can source in your shell to
                populate the environment variables the command line
                tools need to know where your service endpoints are as
                well as your authentication information.</para>
            <para>For using the OpenStack native tools follow the
                    <guilabel>OpenStack API</guilabel> link. The top
                section lists the URLs of your service endpoints and
                below that is a section titled <guilabel>Download
                    OpenStack RC File</guilabel>. For looking at the
                cloud as an administrator, you can choose admin from
                the drop-down menu. In this section select the project
                you wish to get credentials for and click
                    <guibutton>Download RC</guibutton>. This generates
                a file called <code>openrc.sh</code>, which looks
                something like this:</para>
            <programlisting><?db-font-size 60%?>#!/bin/bash
      
# With the addition of Keystone, to use an openstack cloud you should
# authenticate against keystone, which returns a **Token** and **Service
# Catalog**. The catalog contains the endpoint for all services the
# user/tenant has access to - including nova, glance, keystone, swift.
#
# *NOTE*: Using the 2.0 *auth api* does not mean that compute api is 2.0. 
# We use the 1.1 *compute api*
export OS_AUTH_URL=http://203.0.113.10:5000/v2.0
      
# With the addition of Keystone we have standardized on the term **tenant**
# as the entity that owns the resources.
export OS_TENANT_ID=98333aba48e756fa8f629c83a818ad57
export OS_TENANT_NAME="test-project"
      
# In addition to the owning entity (tenant), openstack stores the entity
# performing the action as the **user**.
export OS_USERNAME=test-user
      
# With Keystone you pass the keystone password.
echo "Please enter your OpenStack Password: "
read -s OS_PASSWORD_INPUT
export OS_PASSWORD=$OS_PASSWORD_INPUT</programlisting>
            <note>
                <para>This does not save your password in plain text,
                    which is a good thing. But when you source or run
                    the script, it prompts for your password and then
                    stores your response in the environment variable
                        <code>OS_PASSWORD</code>. It is important to
                    note that this does require interactivity. It is
                    possible to store a value directly in the script
                    if you require a non interactive operation, but
                    you then need to be extremely cautious with the
                    security and permissions of this file.</para>
            </note>
            <para>EC2 compatibility credentials can be downloaded from
                the "EC2 Credentials" link in the left hand navigation
                bar, then selecting the project you want credentials
                for and clicking "Download EC2 Credentials". This
                generates a zip file with server x509 certificates and
                a shell script fragment. Create a new directory in a
                secure location as, unlike the default
                    <code>openrc</code>, these are live credentials
                containing all the authentication information required
                to access your cloud identity. Extract the zip file
                here. You should have cacert.pem, cert.pem, ec2rc.sh
                and pk.pem. The <code>ec2rc.sh</code> is similar to
                this:</para>
            <programlisting><?db-font-size 50%?>#!/bin/bash
      
NOVARC=$(readlink -f "${BASH_SOURCE:-${0}}" 2&gt;/dev/null) ||\
NOVARC=$(python -c 'import os,sys; print os.path.abspath(os.path.realpath(sys.argv[1]))' "${BASH_SOURCE:-${0}}")
NOVA_KEY_DIR=${NOVARC%/*}
export EC2_ACCESS_KEY=df7f93ec47e84ef8a347bbb3d598449a
export EC2_SECRET_KEY=ead2fff9f8a344e489956deacd47e818
export EC2_URL=http://203.0.113.10:8773/services/Cloud
export EC2_USER_ID=42 # nova does not use user id, but bundling requires it
export EC2_PRIVATE_KEY=${NOVA_KEY_DIR}/pk.pem
export EC2_CERT=${NOVA_KEY_DIR}/cert.pem
export NOVA_CERT=${NOVA_KEY_DIR}/cacert.pem
export EUCALYPTUS_CERT=${NOVA_CERT} # euca-bundle-image seems to require this set
      
alias ec2-bundle-image="ec2-bundle-image --cert $EC2_CERT --privatekey $EC2_PRIVATE_KEY --user 42 --ec2cert $NOVA_CERT"
alias ec2-upload-bundle="ec2-upload-bundle -a $EC2_ACCESS_KEY -s $EC2_SECRET_KEY --url $S3_URL --ec2cert $NOVA_CERT"</programlisting>
            <para>To put the EC2 credentials into your environment
                source the <code>ec2rc.sh</code> file.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="cli_tricks">
            <title>Command Line Tricks and Traps</title>
            <para>The command line tools can be made to show the
                OpenStack API calls it's making by passing it the
                    <code>--debug</code> flag for example:</para>
            <programlisting><?db-font-size 60%?><prompt>#</prompt> nova --debug list</programlisting>
            <para>This example shows the HTTP requests from the client
                and the responses from the endpoints, which can be
                helpful in creating custom tools written to the
                OpenStack API.</para>
            <para><link
                    xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/KeyringSupport"
                    >Keyring Support</link>
                (https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/KeyringSupport) can
                be a source of confusion to the point that, as of the
                time of this writing, there is a <link
                    xlink:href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/python-novaclient/+bug/1020238"
                    >bug report</link>
                (https://bugs.launchpad.net/python-novaclient/+bug/1020238)
                which has been open, closed as invalid, and reopened
                through a few cycles. </para>
            <para>The issue is that under some conditions the command
                line tools try to use a Python keyring as a credential
                cache and, under a subset of those conditions, another
                condition can arise where the tools prompt for a
                keyring password on each use. If you find yourself in
                this unfortunate subset, adding the
                    <code>--no-cache</code> flag or setting the
                environment variable <code>OS_NO_CACHE=1</code> avoids
                the credentials cache.</para>
            <note>
                <para>This causes the command line tool to
                    authenticate on each and every interaction with
                    the cloud.</para>
            </note>
            <section xml:id="curl">
                <title>cURL</title>

                <para>Underlying the use of the command line tools is
                    the OpenStack API, which is a RESTful API that
                    runs over HTTP. There may be cases where you want
                    to interact with the API directly or need to use
                    it because of a suspected bug in one of the CLI
                    tools. The best way to do this is use a
                    combination of <link
                        xlink:href="http://curl.haxx.se/">cURL</link>
                    (http://curl.haxx.se/) and another tool to parse
                    the JSON, such as <link
                        xlink:href="http://stedolan.github.com/jq/"
                        >jq</link> (http://stedolan.github.com/jq/),
                    from the responses.</para>

                <para>The first thing you must do is authenticate with
                    the cloud using your credentials to get an
                        <glossterm>authentication token</glossterm>. </para>
                <para>Your credentials are a combination of username,
                    password, and tenant (project). You can extract
                    these values from the <code>openrc.sh</code>
                    discussed above. The token allows you to interact
                    with your other service endpoints without needing
                    to re-authenticate for every request. Tokens are
                    typically good for 24 hours, and when the token
                    expires, you are alerted with a 401 (Unauthorized)
                    response and you can request another token.</para>
                <para>
                    <orderedlist>
                        <listitem>

                            <para>Look at your OpenStack service
                                   <glossterm>catalog</glossterm>:</para>
                            <programlisting language="bash"><?db-font-size 55%?><prompt>$</prompt> curl -s -X POST http://203.0.113.10:35357/v2.0/tokens \
    -d '{"auth": {"passwordCredentials": {"username":"test-user", "password":"test-password"}, "tenantName":"test-project"}}' \
    -H "Content-type: application/json" | jq .</programlisting>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Read through the JSON response to
                                get a feel for how the catalog is laid
                                out.</para>
                            <para>To make working with subsequent
                                requests easier, store the token in an
                                environment variable.</para>
                            <programlisting language="bash"><?db-font-size 55%?><prompt>$</prompt> TOKEN=`curl -s -X POST http://203.0.113.10:35357/v2.0/tokens \
    -d '{"auth": {"passwordCredentials": {"username":"test-user", "password":"test-password"}, "tenantName":"test-project"}}' \
    -H "Content-type: application/json" |  jq -r .access.token.id`</programlisting>
                            <para>Now you can refer to your token on
                                the command line as $TOKEN.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Pick a service endpoint from your
                                service catalog, such as compute, and
                                try out a request like listing
                                instances (servers).</para>
                            <programlisting><?db-font-size 60%?><prompt>$</prompt> curl -s \
                                  -H "X-Auth-Token: $TOKEN" \
                                   http://203.0.113.10:8774/v2/98333aba48e756fa8f629c83a818ad57/servers | jq .</programlisting>

</listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                </para>
                <para>To discover how API requests should be
                    structured, read the <link
                        xlink:href="http://api.openstack.org/api-ref.html"
                        >OpenStack API Reference</link>
                    (http://api.openstack.org/api-ref.html). To chew
                    through the responses using jq, see the <link
                        xlink:href="http://stedolan.github.com/jq/manual/"
                        >jq Manual</link>
                    (http://stedolan.github.com/jq/manual/).</para>
                <para>The <code>-s flag</code> used in the cURL
                    commands above are used to prevent the progress
                    meter from being shown. If you are having trouble
                    running cURL commands, you'll want to remove it.
                    Likewise, to help you troubleshoot cURL commands
                    you can include the <code>-v</code> flag to show
                    you the verbose output. There are many more
                    extremely useful features in cURL, refer to the
                    man page for all of the options.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="servers_services">
            <title>Servers and Services</title>
            <para>As an administrator, there are a few ways to
                discover what your OpenStack cloud looks like simply
                by using the OpenStack tools available. This section
                gives you an idea of how to get an overview of your
                cloud, its shape, size, and current state.</para>
            <para>First, you can discover what servers belong to your
                OpenStack cloud by running:</para>
            <programlisting><?db-font-size 60%?><prompt>$</prompt> nova-manage service list | sort</programlisting>
            <para>The output looks like the following:</para>
            <programlisting><?db-font-size 60%?>Binary           Host              Zone Status  State Updated_At
nova-cert        cloud.example.com nova enabled  :-)  2013-02-25 19:32:38
nova-compute     c01.example.com   nova enabled  :-)  2013-02-25 19:32:35
nova-compute     c02.example.com   nova enabled  :-)  2013-02-25 19:32:32
nova-compute     c03.example.com   nova enabled  :-)  2013-02-25 19:32:36
nova-compute     c04.example.com   nova enabled  :-)  2013-02-25 19:32:32
nova-compute     c05.example.com   nova enabled  :-)  2013-02-25 19:32:41
nova-consoleauth cloud.example.com nova enabled  :-)  2013-02-25 19:32:36
nova-network     cloud.example.com nova enabled  :-)  2013-02-25 19:32:32
nova-scheduler   cloud.example.com nova enabled  :-)  2013-02-25 19:32:33</programlisting>
            <para>The output shows that there are five compute nodes
                and one cloud controller. You see a smiley face like
                    <code>:-)</code> which indicates that the services
                are up and running and functional. If a service is no
                longer available, the <code>:-)</code> changes to an
                    <code>XXX</code>. This is an indication that you
                should troubleshoot why the service is down.</para>
            <para>If you are still using <code>nova-volume</code>
                (this service is deprecated after the Folsom release),
                you might also see entries for the nova-volume
                service.</para>
            <para>If you are using Cinder, run the following command
                to see a similar listing:</para>

            <programlisting><?db-font-size 60%?><prompt>$</prompt> cinder-manage host list | sort</programlisting>

            <programlisting><?db-font-size 60%?>host              zone
c01.example.com   nova
c02.example.com   nova
c03.example.com   nova
c04.example.com   nova
c05.example.com   nova
cloud.example.com nova</programlisting>
            <para>With these two tables, you now have a good overview
                of what servers and services make up your
                cloud.</para>
            <para>You can also use the Identity Service (Keystone), to
                see what services are available in your cloud as well
                as what endpoints have been configured for the
                services.</para>
            <para>The following commands require you to have your
                shell environment configured with the proper
                administrative variables.</para>

            <programlisting><?db-font-size 60%?><prompt>$</prompt> keystone service-list</programlisting>

            <programlisting><?db-font-size 60%?>+-----+----------+----------+----------------------------+
| id  | name     | type     | description                |
+-----+----------+----------+----------------------------+
| ... | cinder   | volume   | Cinder Service             |
| ... | glance   | image    | OpenStack Image Service    |
| ... | nova_ec2 | ec2      | EC2 Service                |
| ... | keystone | identity | OpenStack Identity Service |
| ... | nova     | compute  | OpenStack Compute Service  |
+-----+----------+----------+----------------------------+</programlisting>
            <para>The output above shows that there are five services
                configured.</para>
            <para>To see the endpoint of each service, run: </para>
            <programlisting><?db-font-size 60%?><prompt>$</prompt> keystone endpoint-list</programlisting>
            <programlisting><?db-font-size 55%?>+-----+-----------------------------------------+-/+-----------------------------------------+
| id  |            publicurl                    | \|               adminurl                  |
+-----+-----------------------------------------+-/+-----------------------------------------+
| ... | http://example.com:8774/v2/%(tenant_id)s| \| http://example.com:8774/v2/%(tenant_id)s|
| ... | http://example.com:8773/services/Cloud  | /| http://example.com:8773/services/Admin  |
| ... | http://example.com:9292/v1              | \| http://example.com:9292/v1              |
| ... | http://example.com:5000/v2.0            | /| http://example.com:35357/v2.0           |
| ... | http://example.com:8776/v1/%(tenant_id)s| \| http://example.com:8776/v1/%(tenant_id)s|
+-----+-----------------------------------------+-/+-----------------------------------------+</programlisting>
            <para>There should be a one-to-one mapping between a
                    <emphasis>service</emphasis> and
                    <emphasis>endpoint</emphasis>. Note the different
                URLs and ports between the public URL and the admin
                URL for some services.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="network">
        <title>Network</title>
        <para>Next, take a look at what Fixed IP networks are
            configured in your cloud:</para>

        <programlisting><?db-font-size 60%?><prompt>$</prompt> nova-manage network list</programlisting>

        <programlisting><?db-font-size 60%?>id IPv4        IPv6 start address DNS1 DNS2 VlanID project   uuid 
1  10.1.0.0/24 None 10.1.0.3      None None 300    2725bbd   beacb3f2
2  10.1.1.0/24 None 10.1.1.3      None None 301    none      d0b1a796</programlisting>
        <para>This output shows that two networks are configured, each
            network containing 255 IPs (a /24 subnet). The first
            network has been assigned to a certain project while the
            second network is still open for assignment. You can
            assign this network manually or it is automatically
            assigned when a project launches their first
            instance.</para>
        <para>To find out if any floating IPs are available in your
            cloud, run:</para>

        <programlisting><?db-font-size 60%?><prompt>$</prompt> nova-manage floating list</programlisting>

        <programlisting><?db-font-size 55%?>2725bbd458e2459a8c1bd36be859f43f 1.2.3.4 None                                 nova vlan20
None                             1.2.3.5 48a415e7-6f07-4d33-ad00-814e60b010ff nova vlan20</programlisting>
        <para>Here, two floating IPs are available. The first has been
            allocated to a project while the other is
            unallocated.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="users_projects">
        <title>Users and Projects</title>
        <para>To see a list of projects that have been added to the
            cloud, run:</para>

        <programlisting><?db-font-size 60%?><prompt>$</prompt> keystone tenant-list</programlisting>

        <programlisting><?db-font-size 60%?>+-----+----------+---------+
| id  | name     | enabled |
+-----+----------+---------+
| ... | jtopjian | True    |
| ... | alvaro   | True    |
| ... | everett  | True    |
| ... | admin    | True    |
| ... | services | True    |
| ... | jonathan | True    |
| ... | lorin    | True    |
| ... | anne     | True    |
| ... | rhulsker | True    |
| ... | tom      | True    |
| ... | adam     | True    |
+-----+----------+---------+</programlisting>
        <?hard-pagebreak?>
        <para>To see a list of users, run:</para>

        <programlisting><?db-font-size 60%?><prompt>$</prompt> keystone user-list</programlisting>

        <programlisting><?db-font-size 60%?>+-----+----------+---------+------------------------------+
| id  | name     | enabled | email                        |
+-----+----------+---------+------------------------------+
| ... | everett  | True    | everett.towne@backspace.com  |
| ... | jonathan | True    | jon@sfcu.edu                 |
| ... | nova     | True    | nova@localhost               |
| ... | rhulsker | True    | ryan.hulkster@cyberalbert.ca |
| ... | lorin    | True    | lorinhoch@nsservices.com     |
| ... | alvaro   | True    | Alvaro.Perry@cyberalbert.ca  |
| ... | anne     | True    | anne.green@backspace.com     |
| ... | admin    | True    | root@localhost               |
| ... | cinder   | True    | cinder@localhost             |
| ... | glance   | True    | glance@localhost             |
| ... | jtopjian | True    | joe.topjian@cyberalbert.com  |
| ... | adam     | True    | adam@ossmanuals.net          |
| ... | tom      | True    | fafield@univm.edu.au         |
+-----+----------+---------+------------------------------+</programlisting>
        <note>
            <para>Sometimes a user and a group have a one-to-one
                mapping. This happens for standard system accounts,
                such as cinder, glance, nova, and swift, or when only
                one user is ever part of a group. </para>
        </note>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="running_instances">
        <title>Running Instances</title>
        <para>To see a list of running instances, run:</para>

        <programlisting><?db-font-size 60%?><prompt>$</prompt> nova list --all-tenants</programlisting>

        <programlisting><?db-font-size 60%?>+-----+------------------+--------+-------------------------------------------+
| ID  | Name             | Status | Networks                                  |
+-----+------------------+--------+-------------------------------------------+
| ... | Windows          | ACTIVE | novanetwork_1=10.1.1.3, 199.116.232.39    |
| ... | cloud controller | ACTIVE | novanetwork_0=10.1.0.6; jtopjian=10.1.2.3 |
| ... | compute node 1   | ACTIVE | novanetwork_0=10.1.0.4; jtopjian=10.1.2.4 |
| ... | devbox           | ACTIVE | novanetwork_0=10.1.0.3                    |
| ... | devstack         | ACTIVE | novanetwork_0=10.1.0.5                    |
| ... | initial          | ACTIVE | nova_network=10.1.7.4, 10.1.8.4           |
| ... | lorin-head       | ACTIVE | nova_network=10.1.7.3, 10.1.8.3           |
+-----+------------------+--------+-------------------------------------------+</programlisting>
        <para>Unfortunately this command does not tell you various
            details about the running instances, such as what compute
            node the instance is running on, what flavor the instance
            is, and so on. You can use the following command to view
            details about individual instances:</para>

        <programlisting><?db-font-size 60%?><prompt>$</prompt> nova show &lt;uuid&gt;</programlisting>
        <?hard-pagebreak?>
        <para>For example:
            <programlisting><?db-font-size 60%?># nova show 81db556b-8aa5-427d-a95c-2a9a6972f630</programlisting><programlisting><?db-font-size 60%?>+-------------------------------------+-----------------------------------+
| Property                            | Value                             |
+-------------------------------------+-----------------------------------+
| OS-DCF:diskConfig                   | MANUAL                            |
| OS-EXT-SRV-ATTR:host                | c02.example.com                   |
| OS-EXT-SRV-ATTR:hypervisor_hostname | c02.example.com                   |
| OS-EXT-SRV-ATTR:instance_name       | instance-00000029                 |
| OS-EXT-STS:power_state              | 1                                 |
| OS-EXT-STS:task_state               | None                              |
| OS-EXT-STS:vm_state                 | active                            |
| accessIPv4                          |                                   |
| accessIPv6                          |                                   |
| config_drive                        |                                   |
| created                             | 2013-02-13T20:08:36Z              |
| flavor                              | m1.small (6)                      |
| hostId                              | ...                               |
| id                                  | ...                               |
| image                               | Ubuntu 12.04 cloudimg amd64 (...) |
| key_name                            | jtopjian-sandbox                  |
| metadata                            | {}                                |
| name                                | devstack                          |
| novanetwork_0 network               | 10.1.0.5                          |
| progress                            | 0                                 |
| security_groups                     | [{u'name': u'default'}]           |
| status                              | ACTIVE                            |
| tenant_id                           | ...                               |
| updated                             | 2013-02-13T20:08:59Z              |
| user_id                             | ...                               |
+-------------------------------------+-----------------------------------+</programlisting></para>
    </section>
</chapter>
