<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface [
<!-- Some useful entities borrowed from HTML -->
<!ENTITY ndash  "&#x2013;">
<!ENTITY mdash  "&#x2014;">
<!ENTITY hellip "&#x2026;">
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#xB1;">


]>
<preface xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="section_yk2_jpr_lj">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Preface</title>
    <para>OpenStack is an open source platform that lets you build an
        Infrastructure as a Service (IaaS) cloud that runs on
        commodity hardware. OpenStack is designed for scalability, so
        you can easily add new compute and storage resources to grow
        your cloud over time. Organizations such as HP and Rackspace
        have built massive public clouds on top of OpenStack.</para>
    <para>OpenStack is more than a software package that you run
        as-is. It lets you integrate a number of different
        technologies to construct a cloud. This approach provides
        great flexibility, but the number of options might be
        bewildering at first.</para>
    <para>This guide assumes that you are familiar with the Ubuntu
        distribution of Linux, SQL databases, and virtualization. You
        must be comfortable administering and configuring multiple
        Linux machines for networking. You must install and maintain a
        MySQL database, and occasionally run SQL queries against it.
        One of the most complex aspects of an OpenStack cloud is the
        networking configuration. You should be familiar with concepts
        such as DHCP, Linux bridges, VLANs, and iptables. You must
        also have access to a network hardware expert who can
        configure the switches and routers required in your OpenStack
        cloud. </para>
    <section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
        xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
        xml:id="chapter_gk2_jpr_lj">

        <title>Why and How We Wrote This Book</title>
        <para>We wrote this book because we have deployed and
            maintained OpenStack clouds for at least a year, and
            wanted to be able to distribute this knowledge to others.
            After months of being the point people for an OpenStack
            cloud, we also wanted to have a document to hand to our
            system administrators so they'd know how to operate the
            cloud on a daily basis — both reactively and proactively.
            We wanted to provide more detailed technical information
            about the decisions that deployers make along the
            way.</para>
        <para>We wrote this book to help you:<itemizedlist
                role="compact">
                <listitem>
                    <para>Design and create an architecture for your
                        first non-trivial OpenStack cloud. After you
                        read this guide, you'll know which questions
                        to ask and how to organize your compute,
                        networking, storage resources, and the
                        associated software packages. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Perform the day-to-day tasks required to
                        administer a cloud.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>

        <para>We wrote this book in a Book Sprint, which is a
            facilitated rapid development production method for books.
            For more information see the <link
                xlink:title="Foundation web site"
                xlink:href="http://www.booksprints.net">Book Sprint
                site</link>. Your authors cobbled this book together
            in five days during February 2013, fueled by caffeine and
            the best take-out food that Austin, Texas could offer. </para>
        <para>On the first day we filled white boards with colorful
            sticky notes to start to shape this nebulous book about
            how to architect and operate clouds. <informalfigure>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata width="5in"
                            fileref="figures/1-IMG_4895.JPG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure></para>
        <para>We wrote furiously from our own experiences and bounced
            ideas between each other. At regular intervals we reviewed
            the shape and organization of the book and further molded
            it, leading to what you see today.</para>
        <para>The team includes:</para>
        <itemizedlist role="compact">
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Tom Fifield</emphasis>.
                    After learning about scalability in computing from
                    particle physics experiments like ATLAS at the
                    LHC, Tom works on OpenStack clouds in production
                    to support the Australian public research sector.
                    He lives in Melbourne, Australia and works on
                    OpenStack documentation in his spare time.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Diane Fleming</emphasis>.
                    Diane works on the OpenStack API documentation
                    tirelessly. She helped out wherever she could on
                    this project.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Anne Gentle</emphasis>.
                    Anne is the documentation coordinator for
                    OpenStack and also served as an individual
                    contributor to the Google Doc Summit in 2011,
                    working with the Open Street Maps team. Anne has
                    worked on doc sprints in the past with FLOSS
                    Manuals’ Adam Hyde facilitating. Anne lives in
                    Austin, Texas.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Lorin
                    Hochstein</emphasis>. An academic turned software
                    developer-slash-operator, Lorin currently works as
                    the Lead Architect for Cloud Services at Nimbis
                    Services where he deploys OpenStack for technical
                    computing applications. He has been working with
                    OpenStack since the Cactus release. Previously, he
                    worked on high-performance computing extensions
                    for OpenStack at University of Southern
                    California's Information Sciences Institute
                    (USC-ISI).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Adam Hyde</emphasis>. Adam
                    facilitated this Book Sprint. He also founded the
                    Book Sprint methodology and is the most
                    experienced Book Sprint facilitator around. See
                    http://www.booksprints.net/ for more information.
                    Adam founded FLOSS Manuals—a community of some
                    3,000 individuals developing Free Manuals about
                    Free Software. He is also the founder and project
                    manager for Booktype, an open source project for
                    writing, editing, and publishing books online and
                    in print.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Jonathan
                    Proulx</emphasis>. Jon has been piloting an
                    OpenStack cloud as a senior system administrator
                    at the MIT Computer Science and Artificial
                    Intelligence Lab for his researchers to have as
                    much computing power as they need. He started
                    contributing to OpenStack documentation and
                    reviewing the documentation so that he could
                    accelerate his learning.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Everett Toews</emphasis>.
                    Everett is a Developer Advocate at Rackspace
                    making OpenStack and the Rackspace Cloud easy to
                    use. Sometimes developer, sometimes advocate, and
                    sometimes operator. He's built web applications,
                    taught workshops, given presentations around the
                    world, and deployed OpenStack for production use
                    by academia and business.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Joe Topjian</emphasis>.
                    Joe has designed and deployed several clouds at
                    Cybera, where, as a non-profit, they are building
                    e-infrastructure to support entrepreneurs and
                    local researchers in Alberta, Canada. He also
                    actively maintains and operates these clouds which
                    has generated a wealth of troubleshooting skills
                    for cloud environments.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="section_gl2_jpr_lj">
        <title>How to Contribute to This Book</title>
        <para>The genesis of this book was an in-person event, but now
            that the book is in your hands we want you to contribute
            to it. OpenStack documentation follows the coding
            principles of iterative work, with bug logging,
            investigating, and fixing.</para>
        <!--   <para>If you see a bug in this book or want to work on a
            section, you can edit it immediately by going to the <link
                xlink:title="OpenStack Operations Guide"
                xlink:href="http://openstack.booktype.pro">OpenStack
                Booktype site</link> (http://openstack.booktype.pro),
            creating a user account, and editing the section as you
            see fit. The book is located at <link
                xlink:title="OpenStack Operations Guide"
                xlink:href="http://openstack.booktype.pro/openstack-operations-guide"
                >OpenStack Operations Guide</link>
            (http://openstack.booktype.pro/openstack-operations-guide/).</para>-->
        <!--   <para>A member of the OpenStack doc-core team publishes this
            book periodically. We plan to have events at OpenStack
            summits to work in-person on this book.</para> -->
        <para>Learn more about how to contribute to the OpenStack docs
            at <link
                xlink:href="http://wiki.openstack.org/Documentation/HowTo"
                >Documentation How To</link>
            (http://wiki.openstack.org/Documentation/HowTo).</para>
        <para>If you find a bug and can't fix it or aren't sure it's
            really a doc bug, log a bug at <link
                xlink:href="http://bugs.launchpad.net/openstack-manuals"
                >OpenStack Manuals</link>
            (http://bugs.launchpad.net/openstack-manuals). Tag the bug
            under <guilabel>Extra</guilabel> options with
                <literal>ops-guide</literal> tag to indicate that the
            bug is in this guide. You can assign the bug to yourself
            if you know how to fix it. Also, a member of the OpenStack
            doc-core team can triage the doc bug. </para>
    </section>

</preface>
