<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="generalpurpose">
    <title>General purpose</title>
    <para>An OpenStack general purpose cloud is often considered a
        starting point for building a cloud deployment. They are designed
        to balance the components and do not emphasize any particular aspect
        of the overall computing environment.
        Cloud design must give equal weight to the compute, network, and
        storage components. General purpose clouds are
        found in private, public, and hybrid environments, lending
        themselves to many different use cases.
    </para>
      <note>
        <para>
          General purpose clouds are homogeneous deployments and are
          not suited to specialized environments or edge case situations.
        </para>
      </note>
    <para>
        Common uses of a general purpose cloud include:
    </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          Providing a simple database
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          A web application runtime environment
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          A shared application development platform
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          Lab test bed
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    <para>Use cases that benefit from scale-out rather than scale-up approaches
        are good candidates for general purpose cloud architecture.
    </para>
    <para>A general purpose cloud is designed to have a range of potential
        uses or functions; not specialized for specific use cases. General
        purpose architecture is designed to address 80% of potential use
        cases available. The infrastructure, in itself, is a specific use case,
        enabling it to be used as a base model for the design process.
        General purpose clouds are designed to be platforms that are suited
        for general purpose applications.</para>
    <para>General purpose clouds are limited to the most basic
        components, but they can include additional resources such
        as:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Virtual-machine disk image library</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Raw block storage</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>File or object storage</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Firewalls</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Load balancers</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>IP addresses</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Network overlays or virtual local area networks
                (VLANs)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Software bundles</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <xi:include href="generalpurpose/section_user_requirements_general_purpose.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="generalpurpose/section_tech_considerations_general_purpose.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="generalpurpose/section_operational_considerations_general_purpose.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="generalpurpose/section_architecture_general_purpose.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="generalpurpose/section_prescriptive_example_general_purpose.xml"/>

</chapter>
