<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="arch-design-glossary">
    <title>Glossary</title>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>6to4 - A mechanism that allows IPv6 packets to be
                transmitted over an IPv4 network, providing a strategy
                for migrating to IPv6.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>AAA - authentication, authorization and
                auditing.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Anycast - A network routing methodology that routes
                traffic from a single sender to the nearest node, in a
                pool of nodes.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>ARP - Address Resolution Protocol - the protocol by
                which layer 3 IP addresses are resolved into layer 2,
                link local addresses.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>BGP - Border Gateway Protocol is a dynamic routing
                protocol that connects autonomous systems together.
                Considered the backbone of the Internet, this protocol
                connects disparate networks together to form a larger
                network.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Boot Storm - When hundreds of users log in to and
                consume resources at the same time, causing
                significant performance degradation. This problem is
                particularly common in Virtual Desktop Infrastructure
                (VDI) environments.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Broadcast Domain - The layer 2 segment shared by a
                group of network connected nodes.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Bursting - The practice of utilizing a secondary
                environment to elastically build instances on-demand
                when the primary environment is resource
                constrained.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Capital Expenditure (CapEx) - A capital expense,
                capital expenditure, CapEx is an initial cost for
                building a product, business, or system.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Cascading Failure - A scenario where a single
                failure in a system creates a cascading effect, where
                other systems fail as load is transferred from the
                failing system.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>CDN - Content delivery network - a specialized
                network that is used to distribute content to clients,
                typically located close to the client for increased
                performance.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Cells - An OpenStack Compute (Nova) feature, where a
                compute deployment can be split into smaller clusters
                or cells with their own queue and database for
                performance and scalability, while still providing a
                single API endpoint.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>CI/CD - Continuous Integration / Continuous
                Deployment, a methodology where software is
                continually built and unit tests run for each change
                that is merged, or proposed for merge. Continuous
                Deployment is a software development methodology where
                changes are deployed into production as they are
                merged into source control, rather than being
                collected into a release and deployed at regular
                intervals</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Cloud Broker - A cloud broker is a third-party
                individual or business that acts as an intermediary
                between the purchaser of a cloud computing service and
                the sellers of that service. In general, a broker is
                someone who acts as an intermediary between two or
                more parties during negotiations.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Cloud Consumer - User that consumes cloud instances,
                storage, or other resources in a cloud environment.
                This user interacts with OpenStack or other cloud
                management tools.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Cloud Management Platform (CMP) - Products that
                provide a common interface to manage multiple cloud
                environments or platforms.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Connection Broker - In desktop virtualization, a
                connection broker is a software program that allows
                the end-user to connect to an available
                desktop.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Direct Attached Storage (DAS) - Data storage that is
                directly connected to a machine.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>DefCore - DefCore sets base requirements by defining
                capabilities, code and must-pass tests for all
                OpenStack products. This definition uses community
                resources and involvement to drive interoperability by
                creating the minimum standards for products labeled
                "OpenStack." See
                https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Governance/CoreDefinition
                for more information.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Desktop as a Service (DaaS) - A platform that
                provides a suite of desktop environments that users
                may log in to receive a desktop experience from any
                location. This may provide general use, development,
                or even homogenous testing environments.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Direct Server Return - A technique in load balancing
                where an initial request is routed through a load
                balancer, and the reply is sent from the responding
                node directly to the requester.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Denial of Service (DoS) - In computing, a
                denial-of-service or distributed denial-of-service
                attack is an attempt to make a machine or network
                resource unavailable to its intended users.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Distributed Replicated Block Device (DRBD) - The
                Distributed Replicated Block Device (DRBD) is a
                distributed replicated storage system for the Linux
                platform.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Differentiated Service Code Point (DSCP) - Defined
                in RFC 2474, this field in IPv4 and IPv6 headers is
                used to define classes of network traffic, for quality
                of service purposes.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>External Border Gateway Protocol (eBGP) - External
                Border Gateway Protocol describes a specific
                implementation of BGP designed for inter-autonomous
                system communication</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Elastic IP - An Amazon Web Services concept, which
                is an IP address that can be dynamically allocated and
                reassigned to running instances on the fly. The
                OpenStack equivalent is a Floating IP.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Encapsulation - The practice of placing one packet
                type within another for the purposes of abstracting or
                securing data. Examples include GRE, MPLS, or
                IPSEC.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>External Cloud - A cloud environment that exists
                outside of the control of an organization. Referred to
                for hybrid cloud to indicate a public cloud or an
                off-site hosted cloud.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Federated Cloud - A federated cloud describes a
                multiple sets of cloud resources, for example compute
                or storage, that are managed by a centralized
                endpoint.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Flow - A series of packets that are stateful in
                nature and represent a session. Usually represented by
                a TCP stream, but can also indicate other packet types
                that when combined comprise a connection between two
                points.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Golden Image - An operating system image that
                contains a set of pre-installed software packages and
                configurations. This may be used to build standardized
                instances that have the same base set of configuration
                to improve mean time to functional application</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Graphics Processing Unit (GPU) - A single chip
                processor with integrated transform, lighting,
                triangle setup/clipping, and rendering engines that is
                capable of processing a minimum of 10 million polygons
                per second. Traditional uses are any compute problem
                that can be represented as a vector or matrix
                operation.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Hadoop Distributed File System (HDFS) - A
                distributed file-system that stores data on commodity
                machines, providing very high aggregate bandwidth
                across the cluster.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>High Availability (HA) - High availability system
                design approach and associated service implementation
                that ensures a prearranged level of operational
                performance will be met during a contractual
                measurement period.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>High Performance Computing (HPC) - Also known as
                distributed computing - used for computation intensive
                processes run on a large number of instances</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Hierarchical Storage Management (HSM) - Hierarchical
                storage management is a data storage technique, which
                automatically moves data between high-cost and
                low-cost storage media</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Hot Standby Router Protocol (HSRP) - Hot Standby
                Router Protocol is a Cisco proprietary redundancy
                protocol for establishing a fault-tolerant default
                gateway, and has been described in detail in RFC
                2281.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Hybrid Cloud - Hybrid cloud is a composition of two
                or more clouds (private, community or public) that
                remain distinct entities but are bound together,
                offering the benefits of multiple deployment models.
                Hybrid cloud can also mean the ability to connect
                colocation, managed and/or dedicated services with
                cloud resources.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Interior Border Gateway Protocol (iBGP) - Interior
                Border Gateway Protocol is an interior gateway
                protocol designed to exchange routing and reachability
                information within autonomous systems.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Interior Gateway Protocol (IGP) - An Interior
                Gateway Protocol is a type of protocol used for
                exchanging routing information between gateways
                (commonly routers) within an Autonomous System (for
                example, a system of corporate local area networks).
                This routing information can then be used to route
                network-level protocols like IP.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Input/Output Operations Per Second (IOPS) - A common
                performance measurement used to benchmark computer
                storage devices like hard disk drives, solid state
                drives, and storage area networks.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>jClouds - An open source multi-cloud toolkit for the
                Java platform that gives you the freedom to create
                applications that are portable across clouds while
                giving you full control to use cloud-specific
                features.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Jitter - Is the deviation from true periodicity of a
                presumed periodic signal in electronics and
                telecommunications, often in relation to a reference
                clock source.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Jumbo Frame - Ethernet frames with more than 1500
                bytes of payload.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Kernel-based Virtual Machine (KVM) - A full
                virtualization solution for Linux on x86 hardware
                containing virtualization extensions (Intel VT or
                AMD-V). It consists of a loadable kernel module, that
                provides the core virtualization infrastructure and a
                processor specific module.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>LAG - Link aggregation group is a term to describe
                various methods of combining (aggregating) multiple
                network connections in parallel into a group to
                increase throughput beyond what a single connection
                could sustain, and to provide redundancy in case one
                of the links fail.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Layer 2 - The data link layer provides a reliable
                link between two directly connected nodes, by
                detecting and possibly correcting errors that may
                occur in the physical layer.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Layer 3 - The network layer provides the functional
                and procedural means of transferring variable length
                data sequences (called datagrams) from one node to
                another connected to the same network.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Legacy System - An old method, technology, computer
                system, or application program that is considered
                outdated.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Looking Glass - A tool that provides information on
                backbone routing and network efficiency.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Microsoft Azure - A cloud computing platform and
                infrastructure, created by Microsoft, for building,
                deploying and managing applications and services
                through a global network of Microsoft-managed
                datacenters.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>MongoDB - A cross-platform document-oriented
                database. Classified as a NoSQL database, MongoDB
                eschews the traditional table-based relational
                database structure in favor of JSON-like documents
                with dynamic schemas.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Mean Time Before Failures (MTBF) - Mean time before
                failures is the predicted elapsed time before inherent
                failures of a system during operation. MTBF can be
                calculated as the arithmetic mean (average) time
                between failures of a system.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Maximum Transmission Unit (MTU) - The maximum
                transmission unit of a communications protocol of a
                layer is the size (in bytes) of the largest protocol
                data unit that the layer can pass onwards.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>NAT64 - NAT64 is a mechanism to allow IPv6 hosts to
                communicate with IPv4 servers. The NAT64 server is the
                endpoint for at least one IPv4 address and an IPv6
                network segment of 32-bits.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Network Functions Virtualization (NFV) - Network
                Functions Virtualization is a network architecture
                concept that proposes using IT virtualization related
                technologies, to virtualize entire classes of network
                node functions into building blocks that may be
                connected, or chained, together to create
                communication services.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>NoSQL - A NoSQL or Not Only SQL database provides a
                mechanism for storage and retrieval of data that is
                modeled in means other than the tabular relations used
                in relational databases.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Open vSwitch - Open vSwitch is a production quality,
                multilayer virtual switch licensed under the open
                source Apache 2.0 license. It is designed to enable
                massive network automation through programmatic
                extension, while still supporting standard management
                interfaces and protocols (for example NetFlow, sFlow, SPAN,
                RSPAN, CLI, LACP, 802.1ag).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Operational Expenditure (OPEX) - An operating
                expense, operating expenditure, operational expense,
                operational expenditure or OPEX is an ongoing cost for
                running a product, business, or system.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Original Design Manufacturers (ODM) - Original
                Design Manufacturers, a company which designs and
                manufactures a product which is specified and
                eventually branded by another firm for sale.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Overlay Network - An overlay network is a computer
                network which is built on the top of another network.
                Nodes in the overlay can be thought of as being
                connected by virtual or logical links, each of which
                corresponds to a path, perhaps through many physical
                links, in the underlying network.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Packet Storm - A cause of degraded service or
                failure that occurs when a network system is
                overwhelmed by continuous multicast or broadcast
                traffic.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Platform-as-a-Service (PaaS) - Platform-as-a-Service
                is a category of cloud computing services that
                provides a computing platform and a solution stack as
                a service.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Power Usage Effectiveness (PUE) - Power usage
                effectiveness is a measure of how efficiently a
                computer data center uses energy; specifically, how
                much energy is used by the computing equipment (in
                contrast to cooling and other overhead).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Quality of Service (QoS) - Quality of Service is the
                overall performance of a telephony or computer
                network, particularly the performance seen by the
                users of the network.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Remote Desktop Host - A server that hosts Remote
                Applications as session-based desktops. Users can
                access a Remote Desktop Host server by using the
                Remote Desktop Connection client.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Renumbering - Network renumbering, the exercise of
                renumbering a network consists of changing the IP host
                addresses, and perhaps the network mask, of each
                device within the network that has an address
                associated with it.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Rollback - In database technologies, a rollback is
                an operation which returns the database to some
                previous state. Rollbacks are important for database
                integrity, because they mean that the database can be
                restored to a clean copy even after erroneous
                operations are performed.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Remote Procedure Call (RPC) - A powerful technique
                for constructing distributed, client-server based
                applications. The communicating processes may be on
                the same system, or they may be on different systems
                with a network connecting them.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Recovery Point Objective (RPO) - A recovery point
                objective is defined by business continuity planning.
                It is the maximum tolerable period in which data might
                be lost from an IT service due to a major incident.
                The RPO gives systems designers a limit to work
                to.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Recovery Time Objective (RTO) - The recovery time
                objective is the duration of time and a service level
                within which a business process must be restored after
                a disaster (or disruption) in order to avoid
                unacceptable consequences associated with a break in
                business continuity.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Software Development Kit (SDK) - A software
                development kit is typically a set of software
                development tools that allows for the creation of
                applications for a certain software package, software
                framework, hardware platform, computer system, video
                game console, operating system, or similar development
                platform.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Service Level Agreement (SLA) - A service-level
                agreement is a part of a service
                contract[disambiguation needed] where a service is
                formally defined. In practice, the term SLA is
                sometimes used to refer to the contracted delivery
                time (of the service or performance).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Software Development Lifecycle (SDLC) - Software
                development life cycle - A software development
                process, also known as a software development
                life-cycle (SDLC), is a structure imposed on the
                development of a software product.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Top of Rack Switch (ToR Switch) - A Top of the Rack
                or (TOR) switch is a small port count switch that sits
                on the very top or near the top of a Telco rack you
                see in Datacenters.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Traffic Shaping - Traffic shaping (also known as
                "packet shaping") is a computer network traffic
                management technique which delays some or all
                datagrams to bring them into compliance with a desired
                traffic profile. Traffic shaping is a form of rate
                limiting.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Tunneling - Computer networks use a tunneling
                protocol when one network protocol (the delivery
                protocol) encapsulates a different payload protocol.
                By using tunneling one can (for example) carry a
                payload over an incompatible delivery-network, or
                provide a secure path through an untrusted
                network.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Virtual Desktop Infrastructure (VDI) - Virtual
                Desktop Infrastructure is a desktop-centric service
                that hosts user desktop environments on remote
                servers, which are accessed over a network using a
                remote display protocol. A connection brokering
                service is used to connect users to their assigned
                desktop sessions.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Virtual Local Area Networks (VLAN) - In computer
                networking, a single layer-2 network may be
                partitioned to create multiple distinct broadcast
                domains, which are mutually isolated so that packets
                can only pass between them via one or more routers;
                such a domain is referred to as a virtual local area
                network, virtual LAN or VLAN.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Voice over Internet Protocol (VoIP) -
                Voice-over-Internet Protocol (VoIP) is a methodology
                and group of technologies for the delivery of voice
                communications and multimedia sessions over Internet
                Protocol (IP) networks, such as the Internet.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Virtual Router Redundancy Protocol (VRRP) - The
                Virtual Router Redundancy Protocol (VRRP) is a
                computer networking protocol that provides for
                automatic assignment of available Internet Protocol
                (IP) routers to participating hosts. This increases
                the availability and reliability of routing paths via
                automatic default gateway selections on an IP
                sub-network.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>VXLAN Tunnel Endpoint (VTEP) - VXLAN Tunnel Endpoint
                - Used for frame encapsulation. VTEP functionality can
                be implemented in software such as a virtual switch or
                in the form a physical switch.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Virtual Extensible Local Area Network (VXLAN) -
                Virtual Extensible LAN is a network virtualization
                technology that attempts to ameliorate the scalability
                problems associated with large cloud computing
                deployments. It uses a VLAN-like encapsulation
                technique to encapsulate MAC-based OSI layer 2
                Ethernet frames within layer 3 UDP packets.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Wide Area Network (WAN) - A wide area network is a
                network that covers a broad area using leased or
                private telecommunication lines.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Xen - Xen is a hypervisor using a microkernel
                design, providing services that allow multiple
                computer operating systems to execute on the same
                computer hardware concurrently.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</chapter>
