<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="hybrid">
    <title>Hybrid</title>

    <para><glossterm baseform="hybrid cloud">Hybrid cloud</glossterm>,
        by definition, means that the design spans
        more than one cloud. An example of this kind of architecture
        may include a situation in which the design involves more than
        one OpenStack cloud (for example, an OpenStack-based private
        cloud and an OpenStack-based public cloud), or it may be a
        situation incorporating an OpenStack cloud and a non-OpenStack
        cloud (for example, an OpenStack-based private cloud that
        interacts with Amazon Web Services).
        <glossterm baseform="bursting">Bursting</glossterm> into an external
        cloud is the practice of creating new instances to alleviate
        extra load where there is no available capacity in the private
        cloud.</para>
    <para>Some situations that could involve hybrid cloud architecture
        include:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Bursting from a private cloud to a public
                cloud</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Disaster recovery</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Development and testing</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Federated cloud, enabling users to choose resources
                from multiple providers</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Hybrid clouds built to support legacy systems as
                they transition to cloud</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>As a hybrid cloud design deals with systems that are outside
        of the control of the cloud architect or organization, a
        hybrid cloud architecture requires considering aspects of the
        architecture that might not have otherwise been necessary. For
        example, the design may need to deal with hardware, software,
        and APIs under the control of a separate organization.</para>
    <para>Similarly, the degree to which the architecture is
        OpenStack-based will have an effect on the cloud operator or
        cloud consumer's ability to accomplish tasks with native
        OpenStack tools. By definition, this is a situation in which
        no single cloud can provide all of the necessary
        functionality. In order to manage the entire system, users,
        operators and consumers will need an overarching tool known as
        a cloud management platform (CMP). Any organization that is
        working with multiple clouds already has a CMP, even if that
        CMP is the operator who logs into an external web portal and
        launches a public cloud instance.</para>
    <para>There are commercially available options, such as
        Rightscale, and open source options, such as ManageIQ
        (http://manageiq.org/), but there is no single CMP that can
        address all needs in all scenarios. Whereas most of the
        sections of this book talk about the aspects of OpenStack, an
        architect needs to consider when designing an OpenStack
        architecture. This section will also discuss the things the
        architect must address when choosing or building a CMP to run
        a hybrid cloud design, even if the CMP will be a manually
        built solution.</para>

    <xi:include href="hybrid/section_user_requirements_hybrid.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="hybrid/section_tech_considerations_hybrid.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="hybrid/section_operational_considerations_hybrid.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="hybrid/section_architecture_hybrid.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="hybrid/section_prescriptive_examples_hybrid.xml"/>

</chapter>
