<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>OpenStack is a leader in the cloud technology gold rush, as
        organizations of all stripes discover the increased
        flexibility and speed to market that self-service cloud and
        Infrastructure-as-a-Service (IaaS) provides. However, in order
        to reap those benefits, the cloud must be designed and
        architected properly.</para>
    <para>A well-architected cloud provides a stable IT environment
        that offers easy access to needed resources, usage-based
        expenses, extra capacity on demand, disaster recovery, and a
        secure environment. A well-architected cloud does not
        magically build itself. It requires careful consideration of a
        multitude of factors both technical and non-technical.</para>
    <para>There is no single architecture that is "right" for an
        OpenStack cloud deployment. OpenStack can be used for any
        number of different purposes, each with its own
        particular requirements and architectural
        peculiarities.</para>
    <para>This book is designed to examine some of the most common
        uses for OpenStack clouds (and some less common uses)
        and to provide knowledge and advice to help explain the
        issues that require consideration. These examples, coupled
        with a wealth of knowledge and advice will help an organization
        design and build a well-architected OpenStack cloud to fit its unique
        requirements.</para>

  <xi:include href="introduction/section_intended_audience.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="introduction/section_how_this_book_is_organized.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="introduction/section_how_this_book_was_written.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="introduction/section_methodology.xml"/>

</chapter>
