<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="network_focus">
    <title>Network focused</title>
    <para>All OpenStack deployments depend on network communication in order
    to function properly due to its service-based nature. In some cases,
    however, the network elevates beyond simple
    infrastructure. This chapter discusses architectures that are more
    reliant or focused on network services. These architectures depend
    on the network infrastructure and require
    network services that perform reliably in order to satisfy user and
    application requirements.</para>
    <para>Some possible use cases include:</para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Content delivery network</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>This includes streaming video, viewing photographs, or
            accessing any other cloud-based data repository distributed to
            a large number of end users. Network configuration affects
            latency, bandwidth, and the distribution of instances. Therefore,
            it impacts video streaming. Not all video streaming is
            consumer-focused. For example, multicast videos (used for media,
            press conferences, corporate presentations, and web conferencing
            services) can also use a content delivery network.
            The location of the video repository and its relationship to end
            users affects content delivery. Network throughput of the back-end
            systems, as well as the WAN architecture and the cache methodology,
            also affect performance.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Network management functions</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>Use this cloud to provide network service functions built to
            support the delivery of back-end network services such as DNS,
            NTP, or SNMP. A company can use these services for internal
            network management.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Network service offerings</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>Use this cloud to run customer-facing network tools to
            support services. Examples include VPNs, MPLS private networks,
            and GRE tunnels.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Web portals or web services</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>Web servers are a common application for cloud services,
            and we recommend an understanding of their network requirements.
            The network requires scaling out to meet user demand and deliver
            web pages with a minimum latency. Depending on the details of
            the portal architecture, consider the internal east-west and
            north-south network bandwidth.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>High speed and high volume transactional systems</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                These types of applications are sensitive to network
                configurations. Examples include financial systems,
                credit card transaction applications, and trading and other
                extremely high volume systems. These systems are sensitive
                to network jitter and latency. They must balance a high volume
                of East-West and North-South network traffic to
                maximize efficiency of the data delivery.
                Many of these systems must access large, high performance
                database back ends.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>High availability</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>These types of use cases are dependent on the proper sizing
            of the network to maintain replication of data between sites for
            high availability. If one site becomes unavailable, the extra
            sites can serve the displaced load until the original site
            returns to service. It is important to size network capacity
            to handle the desired loads.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Big data</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>Clouds used for the management and collection of big data
            (data ingest) have a significant demand on network resources.
            Big data often uses partial replicas of the data to maintain
            integrity over large distributed clouds. Other big data
            applications that require a large amount of network resources
            are Hadoop, Cassandra, NuoDB, Riak, and other NoSQL and
            distributed databases.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Virtual desktop infrastructure (VDI)</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>This use case is sensitive to network congestion, latency,
            jitter, and other network characteristics. Like video streaming,
            the user experience is important. However, unlike video
            streaming, caching is not an option to offset the network issues.
            VDI requires both upstream and downstream traffic and cannot rely
            on caching for the delivery of the application to the end user.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Voice over IP (VoIP)</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>This is sensitive to network congestion, latency, jitter,
            and other network characteristics. VoIP has a symmetrical traffic
            pattern and it requires network quality of service (QoS) for best
            performance. In addition, you can implement active queue management
            to deliver voice and multimedia content. Users are sensitive to
            latency and jitter fluctuations and can detect them at very low
            levels.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Video Conference or web conference</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>This is sensitive to network congestion, latency, jitter,
            and other network characteristics. Video Conferencing has a
            symmetrical traffic pattern, but unless the network is on an
            MPLS private network, it cannot use network quality of service
            (QoS) to improve performance. Similar to VoIP, users are
            sensitive to network performance issues even at low levels.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>High performance computing (HPC)</term>
        <listitem>
            <para>This is a complex use case that requires careful
            consideration of the traffic flows and usage patterns to address
            the needs of cloud clusters. It has high east-west traffic
            patterns for distributed computing, but there can be substantial
            north-south traffic depending on the specific application.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <xi:include href="network_focus/section_user_requirements_network_focus.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="network_focus/section_tech_considerations_network_focus.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="network_focus/section_operational_considerations_network_focus.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="network_focus/section_architecture_network_focus.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="network_focus/section_prescriptive_examples_network_focus.xml"/>

</chapter>
