<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="storage_focus">
    <title>Storage focused</title>

    <para>Cloud storage is a model of data storage that stores digital
        data in logical pools and physical storage that spans
        across multiple servers and locations. Cloud storage commonly
        refers to a hosted object storage service, however the term
        also includes other types of data storage that are
        available as a service, for example block storage.</para>
    <para>Cloud storage runs on virtualized infrastructure and
        resembles broader cloud computing in terms of accessible
        interfaces, elasticity, scalability, multi-tenancy, and
        metered resources. You can use cloud storage services from
        an off-premises service or deploy on-premises.</para>
    <para>Cloud storage consists of many distributed, synonymous
        resources, which are often referred to as integrated
        storage clouds. Cloud storage is highly fault tolerant through
        redundancy and the distribution of data. It is highly durable
        through the creation of versioned copies, and can be
        consistent with regard to data replicas.</para>
    <para>At large scale, management of data operations is
        a resource intensive process for an organization. Hierarchical
        storage management (HSM) systems and data grids help
        annotate and report a baseline data valuation to make
        intelligent decisions and automate data decisions. HSM enables
        automated tiering and movement, as well as orchestration
        of data operations. A data grid is an architecture, or set of
        services evolving technology, that brings together sets of
        services enabling users to manage large data sets.</para>
    <para>Example applications deployed with cloud
        storage characteristics:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Active archive, backups and hierarchical storage
                management.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>General content storage and synchronization. An
                example of this is private dropbox.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Data analytics with parallel file systems.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Unstructured data store for services. For example,
                social media back-end storage.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Persistent block storage.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Operating system and application image store.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Media streaming.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Databases.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Content distribution.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Cloud storage peering.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <xi:include href="storage_focus/section_user_requirements_storage_focus.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="storage_focus/section_tech_considerations_storage_focus.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="storage_focus/section_operational_considerations_storage_focus.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="storage_focus/section_architecture_storage_focus.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="storage_focus/section_prescriptive_examples_storage_focus.xml"/>

</chapter>
