<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0"
    xml:id="module002-ch001-networking-in-openstack">
    <title>Networking in OpenStack</title>
    <para><guilabel>Networking in OpenStack</guilabel></para>
        <para>OpenStack Networking provides a rich tenant-facing API
            for defining network connectivity and addressing in the
            cloud. The OpenStack Networking project gives operators
            the ability to leverage different networking technologies
            to power their cloud networking. It is a virtual network
            service that provides a powerful API to define the network
            connectivity and addressing used by devices from other
            services, such as OpenStack Compute. It has a rich API
            which consists of the following components.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Network:</emphasis> An
                isolated L2 segment, analogous to VLAN in the physical
                networking world.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Subnet:</emphasis> A block
                of v4 or v6 IP addresses and associated configuration
                state.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Port:</emphasis> A
                connection point for attaching a single device, such
                as the NIC of a virtual server, to a virtual network.
                Also describes the associated network configuration,
                such as the MAC and IP addresses to be used on that
                port.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>You can configure rich network topologies by creating
            and configuring networks and subnets, and then instructing
            other OpenStack services like OpenStack Compute to attach
            virtual devices to ports on these networks. In
            particular, OpenStack Networking supports each tenant
            having multiple private networks, and allows tenants to
            choose their own IP addressing scheme, even if those IP
            addresses overlap with those used by other tenants. This
            enables very advanced cloud networking use cases, such as
            building multi-tiered web applications and allowing
            applications to be migrated to the cloud without changing
            IP addresses.</para>
    <para><guilabel>Plugin Architecture: Flexibility to Choose
            Different Network Technologies</guilabel></para>
    <para>Enhancing traditional networking solutions to provide rich
        cloud networking is challenging. Traditional networking is not
        designed to scale to cloud proportions or to configure
        automatically.</para>
    <para>The original OpenStack Compute network implementation
        assumed a very basic model of performing all isolation through
        Linux VLANs and IP tables. OpenStack Networking introduces the
        concept of a plug-in, which is a pluggable back-end
        implementation of the OpenStack Networking API. A plug-in can
        use a variety of technologies to implement the logical API
        requests. Some OpenStack Networking plug-ins might use basic
        Linux VLANs and IP tables, while others might use more
        advanced technologies, such as L2-in-L3 tunneling or OpenFlow,
        to provide similar benefits.</para>
    <para>The current set of plug-ins include:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Big Switch, Floodlight REST
                    Proxy:</emphasis>
                <link
                    xlink:href="http://www.openflowhub.org/display/floodlightcontroller/Quantum+REST+Proxy+Plugin"
                    >http://www.openflowhub.org/display/floodlightcontroller/Quantum+REST+Proxy+Plugin</link></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Brocade
                Plugin</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Cisco:</emphasis> Documented
                externally at: <link
                    xlink:href="http://wiki.openstack.org/cisco-quantum"
                    >http://wiki.openstack.org/cisco-quantum</link></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Hyper-V
                Plugin</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Linux Bridge:</emphasis>
                Documentation included in this guide and <link
                    xlink:href="http://wiki.openstack.org/Quantum-Linux-Bridge-Plugin"
                    >http://wiki.openstack.org/Quantum-Linux-Bridge-Plugin</link>
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Midonet
                Plugin</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">NEC OpenFlow:</emphasis>
                <link
                    xlink:href="http://wiki.openstack.org/Quantum-NEC-OpenFlow-Plugin"
                    >http://wiki.openstack.org/Quantum-NEC-OpenFlow-Plugin</link></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Open vSwitch:</emphasis>
                Documentation included in this guide.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">PLUMgrid:</emphasis>
                <link
                    xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Plumgrid-quantum"
                    >https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Plumgrid-quantum</link></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Ryu:</emphasis>
                <link
                    xlink:href="https://github.com/osrg/ryu/wiki/OpenStack"
                    >https://github.com/osrg/ryu/wiki/OpenStack</link></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <!-- TODO: Update support link, when available -->
            <para><emphasis role="bold">VMware NSX:</emphasis>
                Documentation include in this guide, <link
                    xlink:href="http://www.vmware.com/products/nsx"
                    >NSX Product Overview </link>, and <link
                    xlink:href="http://www.nicira.com/support">NSX
                    Product Support</link>.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Plugins can have different properties in terms of hardware
        requirements, features, performance, scale, operator tools,
        etc. Supporting many plug-ins enables the cloud administrator
        to weigh different options and decide which networking
        technology is right for the deployment.</para>
    <para>Components of OpenStack Networking</para>
    <para>To deploy OpenStack Networking, it is useful to understand
        the different components that make up the solution and how
        those components interact with each other and with other
        OpenStack services.</para>
    <para>OpenStack Networking is a standalone service, just like
        other OpenStack services such as OpenStack Compute, OpenStack
        Image service, OpenStack Identity service, and the OpenStack
        Dashboard. Like those services, a deployment of OpenStack
        Networking often involves deploying several processes on a
        variety of hosts.</para>
    <para>The main process of the OpenStack Networking server is
        quantum-server, which is a Python daemon that exposes the
        OpenStack Networking API and passes user requests to the
        configured OpenStack Networking plug-in for additional
        processing. Typically, the plug-in requires access to a
        database for persistent storage, similar to other OpenStack
        services.</para>
    <para>If your deployment uses a controller host to run centralized
        OpenStack Compute components, you can deploy the OpenStack
        Networking server on that same host. However, OpenStack
        Networking is entirely standalone and can be deployed on its
        own server as well. OpenStack Networking also includes
        additional agents that might be required depending on your
        deployment:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">plugin agent
                    (quantum-*-agent):</emphasis>Runs on each
                hypervisor to perform local vswitch configuration.
                Agent to be run depends on which plug-in you are using,
                as some plug-ins do not require an agent.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">dhcp agent
                    (quantum-dhcp-agent):</emphasis>Provides DHCP
                services to tenant networks. This agent is the same
                across all plug-ins.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">l3 agent
                    (quantum-l3-agent):</emphasis>Provides L3/NAT
                forwarding to provide external network access for VMs
                on tenant networks. This agent is the same across all
                plug-ins.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>These agents interact with the main quantum-server process
        in the following ways:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Through RPC. For example, rabbitmq or qpid.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Through the standard OpenStack Networking
                API.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>OpenStack Networking relies on the OpenStack Identity
        Project (Keystone) for authentication and authorization of all
        API request.</para>
    <para>OpenStack Compute interacts with OpenStack Networking
        through calls to its standard API. As part of creating a VM,
        nova-compute communicates with the OpenStack Networking API to
        plug each virtual NIC on the VM into a particular
        network.</para>
    <para>The OpenStack Dashboard (Horizon) has integration with the
        OpenStack Networking API, allowing administrators and tenant
        users, to create and manage network services through the
        Horizon GUI.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Place Services on Physical
            Hosts</emphasis></para>
    <para>Like other OpenStack services, OpenStack Networking provides
        cloud administrators with significant flexibility in deciding
        which individual services should run on which physical
        devices. On one extreme, all service daemons can be run on a
        single physical host for evaluation purposes. On the other,
        each service could have its own physical hosts, and some cases
        be replicated across multiple hosts for redundancy.</para>
    <para>In this guide, we focus primarily on a standard architecture
        that includes a “cloud controller” host, a “network gateway”
        host, and a set of hypervisors for running VMs. The "cloud
        controller" and "network gateway" can be combined in simple
        deployments, though if you expect VMs to send significant
        amounts of traffic to or from the Internet, a dedicated
        network gateway host is suggested to avoid potential CPU
        contention between packet forwarding performed by the
        quantum-l3-agent and other OpenStack services.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Network Connectivity for Physical
            Hosts</emphasis></para>
    <figure>
        <title>Network Diagram</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/image33.png"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>A standard OpenStack Networking setup has up to four
        distinct physical data center networks:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Management
                network:</emphasis>Used for internal communication
                between OpenStack Components. The IP addresses on this
                network should be reachable only within the data
                center.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Data network:</emphasis>Used
                for VM data communication within the cloud deployment.
                The IP addressing requirements of this network depend
                on the OpenStack Networking plug-in in use.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">External
                network:</emphasis>Used to provide VMs with Internet
                access in some deployment scenarios. The IP addresses
                on this network should be reachable by anyone on the
                Internet.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">API network:</emphasis>Exposes
                all OpenStack APIs, including the OpenStack Networking
                API, to tenants. The IP addresses on this network
                should be reachable by anyone on the Internet. This
                may be the same network as the external network, as it
                is possible to create a subnet for the external
                network that uses IP allocation ranges to use only
                less than the full range of IP addresses in an IP
                block.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</chapter>
