<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 version="5.0"
  xml:id="module001-ch001-intro-text">
  <title>Introduction To OpenStack</title>
  <para>Cloud Computing’s hype has certainly attracted IT Giants and
    the entire Open Source community's attention, amidst all this
    chaos of disrupting the software world and the way we saw and
    thought about it. We need to enlighten ourselves with this massive
    change as time again, entire Open Source community has seen the
    rise of yet another project which is called as OpenStack. It is
    believed that OpenStack will have a similar impact on the future
    computing as Linux had on the ‘Post Unix’ era. This is not only
    affecting the softwares, IT industry or the OpenSource world but
    also the Scientific, Commercial and Domestic part of the world.
    Cloud Computing has proven and solved many challenges and also cut
    time and expenditure, OpenStack pitches in to make OPEX an Open
    phenomenon. It is going to innovate Education to a further greater
    extent, that too at an unimaginable and massive rate. Every
    student will be exposed with the tools and the resources which are
    locked in at high level scientific and corporate places which are
    usually tough to get in touch with, further innovating the pace of
    education and expanding its possibilities. Being open in nature,
    these resources are free to use and modify, tailor them at no cost,
    shape them as per your requirements and let the cloud do all the
    hard work.</para>
  <para>In data centers today, many computers suffer under-utilization
    in computing power and networking bandwidth. For example, projects
    may need a large amount of computing capacity to complete a
    computation, but no longer need the computing power after
    completing the computation. You want cloud computing when you want
    a service that's available on-demand with the flexibility to bring
    it up or down through automation or with little intervention. Much
    like the electrical power we receive each day, cloud computing
    provides subscribers or users with access to a shared collection
    of computing resources: networks for transfer, servers for
    storage, and applications or services for completing tasks.</para>
  <para>These are the compelling features of a cloud:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>On-demand self-service: Users can provision servers and
        networks with little human intervention.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Network access: Any computing capabilities are available
        over the network. Many different devices are allowed access
        through standardized mechanisms.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Resource pooling: Multiple users can access clouds that
        serve other consumers according to demand.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Elasticity: Provisioning is rapid and scales out or in
        based on need.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Metered or measured service: Just like utilities that are
        paid for by the hour, clouds should optimize resource use and
        control it for the level of service or type of servers such as
        storage or processing.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>Cloud computing offers different service models depending on
    the capabilities a consumer may require.</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>SaaS: Software as a Service. Provides the consumer the
        ability to use the software in a cloud environment, such as
        web-based email for example.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>PaaS: Platform as a Service. Provides the consumer the
        ability to deploy applications through a programming language
        or tools supported by the cloud platform provider. An example
        of platform as a service is an Eclipse/Java programming
        platform provided with no downloads required.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>IaaS: Infrastructure as a Service. Provides infrastructure
        such as computer instances, network connections, and storage
        so that people can run any software or operating
        system.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>When you hear terms such as public cloud or private cloud,
    these refer to the deployment model for the cloud. A private cloud
    operates for a single organization, but can be managed on-premise
    or off-premise. A public cloud has an infrastructure that is
    available to the general public or a large industry group and is
    likely owned by a cloud services company.</para>
  <para>Clouds can also be described as hybrid. A hybrid cloud can be
    a deployment model, as a composition of both public and private
    clouds, or a hybrid model for cloud computing may involve both
    virtual and physical servers.</para>
  <para>Cloud computing can help with large-scale computing needs or
    can lead consolidation efforts by virtualizing servers to make
    more use of existing hardware and potentially release old hardware
    from service. Cloud computing is also used for collaboration
    because of its high availability through networked computers.
    Productivity suites for word processing, number crunching, and
    email communications, and more are also available through cloud
    computing. Cloud computing also avails additional storage to the
    cloud user, avoiding the need for additional hard drives on each
    user's desktop and enabling access to huge data storage capacity
    online in the cloud.</para>
  <para>Let’s take a peek into OpenStack, see what it means
    technically, its reach and its impact on the entire world.</para>
  <para>OpenStack is an Open source software for building private and
    public clouds which delivers a massively scalable cloud operating
    system.</para>
  <informaltable class="c20">
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OpenStack is backed up by a global
          community of technologists, developers, researchers,
          corporations and cloud computing experts.</td>
        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/image11.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject></td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </informaltable>
</chapter>
