<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0"
    xml:id="module002-ch002-openstack-networking-concepts">
    <title>OpenStack Networking Concepts</title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Network Types</emphasis></para>
    <para>The OpenStack Networking configuration provided by the
        Rackspace Private Cloud cookbooks allows you to choose between
        VLAN or GRE isolated networks, both provider- and
        tenant-specific. From the provider side, an administrator can
        also create a flat network.</para>
    <para>The type of network that is used for private tenant networks
        is determined by the network_type attribute, which can be
        edited in the Chef override_attributes. This attribute sets
        both the default provider network type and the only type of
        network that tenants are able to create. Administrators can
        always create flat and VLAN networks. GRE networks of any type
        require the network_type to be set to gre.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Namespaces</emphasis></para>
    <para>For each network you create, the Network node (or Controller
        node, if combined) will have a unique network namespace
        (netns) created by the DHCP and Metadata agents. The netns
        hosts an interface and IP addresses for dnsmasq and the
        quantum-ns-metadata-proxy. You can view the namespaces with
        the ip netns [list], and can interact with the namespaces with
        the ip netns exec &lt;namespace&gt; &lt;command&gt;
        command.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Metadata</emphasis></para>
    <para>Not all networks or VMs need metadata access. Rackspace
        recommends that you use metadata if you are using a single
        network. If you need metadata, you may also need a default
        route. (If you don't need a default route, no-gateway will
        do.)</para>
    <para>To communicate with the metadata IP address inside the
        namespace, instances need a route for the metadata network
        that points to the dnsmasq IP address on the same namespaced
        interface. OpenStack Networking only injects a route when you
        do not specify a gateway-ip in the subnet.</para>
    <para>If you need to use a default route and provide instances
        with access to the metadata route, create the subnet without
        specifying a gateway IP and with a static route from 0.0.0.0/0
        to your gateway IP address. Adjust the DHCP allocation pool so
        that it will not assign the gateway IP. With this
        configuration, dnsmasq will pass both routes to instances.
        This way, metadata will be routed correctly without any
        changes on the external gateway.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">OVS Bridges</emphasis></para>
    <para>An OVS bridge for provider traffic is created and configured
        on the nodes where single-network-node and single-compute are
        applied. Bridges are created, but physical interfaces are not
        added. An OVS bridge is not created on a Controller-only
        node.</para>
    <para>When creating networks, you can specify the type and
        properties, such as Flat vs. VLAN, Shared vs. Tenant, or
        Provider vs. Overlay. These properties identify and determine
        the behavior and resources of instances attached to the
        network. The cookbooks will create bridges for the
        configuration that you specify, although they do not add
        physical interfaces to provider bridges. For example, if you
        specify a network type of GRE, a br-tun tunnel bridge will be
        created to handle overlay traffic.</para>
</chapter>