<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0"
    xml:id="module003-ch003-obj-store-capabilities">
    <title>Object Storage Capabilities</title>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>OpenStack provides redundant, scalable object
                storage using clusters of standardized servers capable
                of storing petabytes of data</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Object Storage is not a traditional file system, but
                rather a distributed storage system for static data
                such as virtual machine images, photo storage, email
                storage, backups and archives. Having no central
                "brain" or master point of control provides greater
                scalability, redundancy and durability.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Objects and files are written to multiple disk
                drives spread throughout servers in the data center,
                with the OpenStack software responsible for ensuring
                data replication and integrity across the
                cluster.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Storage clusters scale horizontally simply by adding
                new servers. Should a server or hard drive fail,
                OpenStack replicates its content from other active
                nodes to new locations in the cluster. Because
                OpenStack uses software logic to ensure data
                replication and distribution across different devices,
                inexpensive commodity hard drives and servers can be
                used in lieu of more expensive equipment.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para><guilabel>Swift Characteristics</guilabel></para>
    <para>The key characteristics of Swift include:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>All objects stored in Swift have a URL</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>All objects stored are replicated 3x in
                as-unique-as-possible zones, which can be defined as a
                group of drives, a node, a rack etc.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>All objects have their own metadata</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Developers interact with the object storage system
                through a RESTful HTTP API</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Object data can be located anywhere in the
                cluster</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>The cluster scales by adding additional nodes --
                without sacrificing performance, which allows a more
                cost-effective linear storage expansion vs. fork-lift
                upgrades</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Data doesn’t have to be migrated to an entirely new
                storage system</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>New nodes can be added to the cluster without
                downtime</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Failed nodes and disks can be swapped out with no
                downtime</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Runs on industry-standard hardware, such as Dell,
                HP, Supermicro etc.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <figure>
        <title>Object Storage(Swift)</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/image39.png"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>Developers can either write directly to the Swift API or use
        one of the many client libraries that exist for all popular
        programming languages, such as Java, Python, Ruby and C#.
        Amazon S3 and RackSpace Cloud Files users should feel very
        familiar with Swift. For users who have not used an object
        storage system before, it will require a different approach
        and mindset than using a traditional filesystem.</para>
</chapter>