<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0"
    xml:id="module002-ch004-floating-ips">
    <title>Floating IP Addresses And Security Rules</title>
    <para>OpenStack Networking has the concept of Fixed IPs and
        Floating IPs. Fixed IPs are assigned to an instance on
        creation and stay the same until the instance is explicitly
        terminated. Floating ips are ip addresses that can be
        dynamically associated with an instance. This address can be
        disassociated and associated with another instance at any
        time.</para>
        <para>Various tasks carried out by Floating IP's as of
        now.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>create IP ranges under a certain group, only
                    available for admin role.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>allocate an floating IP to a certain tenant,
                    only available for admin role.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>deallocate an floating IP from a certain
                    tenant</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>associate an floating IP to a given
                    instance</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>disassociate an floating IP from a certain
                    instance</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
            <para>Just as shown by the above figure, we will have
                nova-network-api to support nova client floating
                commands. nova-network-api will invoke neutron cli lib
                to interactive with neutron server via API. The data
                about floating IPs will be stored in to neutron DB.
                Neutron Agent, which is running on compute host will
                enforce the floating IP.</para>
            <para><guilabel>Multiple Floating
                IP Pools</guilabel></para>
            <para>The L3 API in OpenStack Networking supports multiple
                floating IP pools. In OpenStack Networking, a floating
                IP pool is represented as an external network and a
                floating IP is allocated from a subnet associated with
                the external network. Since each L3 agent can be
                associated with at most one external network, we need
                to invoke multiple L3 agent to define multiple
                floating IP pools. 'gateway_external_network_id'in L3
                agent configuration file indicates the external
                network that the L3 agent handles. You can run
                multiple L3 agent instances on one host.</para>
            <para>In addition, when you run multiple L3 agents, make
                sure that handle_internal_only_routers is set to
                Trueonly for one L3 agent in an OpenStack Networking
                deployment and set to Falsefor all other L3 agents.
                Since the default value of this parameter is True, you
                need to configure it carefully.</para>
            <para>Before starting L3 agents, you need to create
                routers and external networks, then update the
                configuration files with UUID of external networks and
                start L3 agents.</para>
            <para>For the first agent, invoke it with the following
                l3_agent.ini where handle_internal_only_routers is
                True.</para>
</chapter>
