<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 version="5.0"
  xml:id="module001-ch002-brief-overview">
  <title>Brief Overview</title>
  <para>OpenStack is a cloud operating system that controls large
    pools of compute, storage, and networking resources throughout a
    datacenter. It is all managed through a dashboard that gives
    administrators control while empowering their users to provision
    resources through a web interface.</para>
  <para>OpenStack is a global collaboration of developers and cloud
    computing technologists producing the ubiquitous open source cloud
    computing platform for public and private clouds. The project aims
    to deliver solutions for all types of clouds by being</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>simple to implement</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>massively scalable</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>feature rich.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>To check out more information on OpenStack visit <link
      xlink:href="http://goo.gl/Ye9DFT"
    >http://goo.gl/Ye9DFT</link></para>
  <para><guilabel> OpenStack Foundation:</guilabel></para>
    <para>The OpenStack Foundation, established September 2012, is an
      independent body providing shared resources to help achieve the
      OpenStack Mission by protecting, empowering, and promoting
      OpenStack software and the community around it. This includes users,
      developers and the entire ecosystem. For more information visit
      http://goo.gl/3uvmNX.</para>
  <para><guilabel> Who's behind OpenStack? </guilabel></para>
    <para>Founded by Rackspace Hosting and NASA, OpenStack has grown
      to be a global software community of developers collaborating on
      a standard and massively scalable open source cloud operating
      system. The OpenStack Foundation promotes the development,
      distribution and adoption of the OpenStack cloud operating
      system. As the independent home for OpenStack, the Foundation
      has already attracted more than 7,000 individual members from
      100 countries and 850 different organizations. It has also secured more than
      $10 million in funding and is ready to fulfill the OpenStack
      mission of becoming the ubiquitous cloud computing platform.
      Checkout <link xlink:href="http://goo.gl/BZHJKd">http://goo.gl/BZHJKd</link>for more on the same.</para>
    <figure>
      <title>Nebula (NASA)</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/image23.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>The goal of the OpenStack Foundation is to serve developers,
      users, and the entire ecosystem by providing a set of shared
      resources to grow the footprint of public and private OpenStack
      clouds, enable technology vendors targeting the platform and
      assist developers in producing the best cloud software in the
      industry.</para>
  <para><guilabel>Who uses OpenStack?</guilabel></para>
    <para>Corporations, service providers, VARS, SMBs, researchers,
      and global data centers looking to deploy large-scale cloud
      deployments for private or public clouds leveraging the support
      and resulting technology of a global open source community. This is just
      three years into OpenStack, it's new, it's yet to
      mature and has immense possibilities. How do I say that? All
      these ‘buzz words’ will fall into a properly solved jigsaw
      puzzle as you go through this article.</para>
  <para><guilabel>It's Open Source:</guilabel></para>
    <para>All of the code for OpenStack is freely available under the
      Apache 2.0 license. Anyone can run it, build on it, or submit
      changes back to the project. This open development model is one
      of the best ways to foster badly-needed cloud standards, remove
      the fear of proprietary lock-in for cloud customers, and create
      a large ecosystem that spans cloud providers.</para>
  <para><guilabel>Who it's for:</guilabel></para>
    <para>Enterprises, service providers, government and academic
      institutions with physical hardware that would like to build a
      public or private cloud.</para>
  <para><guilabel>How it's being used today:</guilabel></para>
    <para>Organizations like CERN, Cisco WebEx, DreamHost, eBay, The
      Gap, HP, MercadoLibre, NASA, PayPal, Rackspace and University of
      Melbourne have deployed OpenStack clouds to achieve control,
      business agility and cost savings without the licensing fees and
      terms of proprietary software. For complete user stories visit
        <link xlink:href="http://goo.gl/aF4lsL"
        >http://goo.gl/aF4lsL</link>, this should give you a good idea
      about the importance of OpenStack.</para>
</chapter>
