<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
  xml:id="module001-ch001-intro-text">
  <title>Introduction to OpenStack</title>
  <para>OpenStack is a cloud operating system that controls large
    pools of compute, storage, and networking resources throughout a
    data center, all managed through a dashboard that gives
    administrators control while empowering users to provision
    resources through a web interface.</para>
  <para>Cloud computing provides users with access to a shared
    collection of computing resources: networks for transfer, servers
    for storage, and applications or services for completing
    tasks.</para>
  <para>The compelling features of a cloud are:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>On-demand self-service: Users can automatically provision
        needed computing capabilities, such as server time and network
        storage, without requiring human interaction with each service
        provider.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Network access: Any computing capabilities are available
        over the network. Many different devices are allowed access
        through standardized mechanisms.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Resource pooling: Multiple users can access clouds that
        serve other consumers according to demand.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Elasticity: Provisioning is rapid and scales out or is
        based on need.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Metered or measured service: Cloud systems can optimize
        and control resource use at the level that is appropriate for
        the service. Services include storage, processing, bandwidth,
        and active user accounts. Monitoring and reporting of resource
        usage provides transparency for both the provider and consumer
        of the utilized service.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>Cloud computing offers different service models depending on
    the capabilities a consumer may require.</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>SaaS: Software as a Service. Provides the consumer the
        ability to use the software in a cloud environment, such as
        web-based email for example.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>PaaS: Platform as a Service. Provides the consumer the
        ability to deploy applications through a programming language
        or tools supported by the cloud platform provider. An example
        of platform as a service is an Eclipse/Java programming
        platform provided with no downloads required.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>IaaS: Infrastructure as a Service. Provides infrastructure
        such as computer instances, network connections, and storage
        so that people can run any software or operating
        system.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>Terms such as public cloud or private cloud refer to the
    deployment model for the cloud. A private cloud operates for a
    single organization, but can be managed on-premise or off-premise.
    A public cloud has an infrastructure that is available to the
    general public or a large industry group and is likely owned by a
    cloud services company.</para>
  <para>Clouds can also be described as hybrid. A hybrid cloud can be
    a deployment model, as a composition of both public and private
    clouds, or a hybrid model for cloud computing may involve both
    virtual and physical servers.</para>
  <para>Cloud computing can help with large-scale computing needs or
    can lead consolidation efforts by virtualizing servers to make
    more use of existing hardware and potentially release old hardware
    from service. Cloud computing is also used for collaboration
    because of its high availability through networked computers.
    Productivity suites for word processing, number crunching, and
    email communications, and more are also available through cloud
    computing. Cloud computing also avails additional storage to the
    cloud user, avoiding the need for additional hard drives on each
    user's desktop and enabling access to huge data storage capacity
    online in the cloud.</para>
  <para>When you explore OpenStack and see what it means technically,
    you can see its reach and impact on the entire world.</para>
  <para>OpenStack is an open source software for building private and
    public clouds which delivers a massively scalable cloud operating
    system.</para>
  <informaltable class="c20">
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OpenStack is backed up by a global
          community of technologists, developers, researchers,
          corporations and cloud computing experts.</td>
        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/image11.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject></td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </informaltable>
</chapter>
