<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 version="5.0"
  xml:id="module001-ch004-openstack-architecture">
  <title>OpenStack Architecture</title>
  <para><guilabel>Conceptual Architecture</guilabel></para>
    <para>The OpenStack project as a whole is designed to deliver a
      massively scalable cloud operating system. To achieve this, each
      of the constituent services are designed to work together to
      provide a complete Infrastructure as a Service (IaaS). This
      integration is facilitated through public application
      programming interfaces (APIs) that each service offers (and in
      turn can consume). While these APIs allow each of the services
      to use another service, it also allows an implementer to switch
      out any service as long as they maintain the API. These are
      (mostly) the same APIs that are available to end users of the
      cloud.</para>
    <para>Conceptually, you can picture the relationships between the
      services as so:</para>
  <figure>
    <title>Conceptual Diagram</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="figures/image13.jpg"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Dashboard ("Horizon") provides a web front end to the
          other OpenStack services</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Compute ("Nova") stores and retrieves virtual disks
          ("images") and associated metadata in Image
          ("Glance")</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Network ("Quantum") provides virtual networking for
          Compute.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Block Storage ("Cinder") provides storage volumes for
          Compute.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Image ("Glance") can store the actual virtual disk files
          in the Object Store("Swift")</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>All the services authenticate with Identity
          ("Keystone")</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>This is a stylized and simplified view of the architecture,
      assuming that the implementer is using all of the services
      together in the most common configuration. It also only shows
      the "operator" side of the cloud -- it does not picture how
      consumers of the cloud may actually use it. For example, many
      users will access object storage heavily (and directly).</para>
  <para><guilabel>Logical Architecture</guilabel></para>
    <para>This picture is consistent with the conceptual architecture
      above:</para>
  <figure>
    <title>Logical Diagram</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="figures/image31.jpg"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>End users can interact through a common web interface
          (Horizon) or directly to each service through their
          API</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>All services authenticate through a common source
          (facilitated through keystone)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Individual services interact with each other through
          their public APIs (except where privileged administrator
          commands are necessary)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>In the sections below, we'll delve into the architecture for
      each of the services.</para>
  <para><guilabel>Dashboard</guilabel></para>
      <para>Horizon is a modular Django web application that provides
    an end user and administrator interface to OpenStack
    services.</para>
  <figure>
    <title>Horizon Dashboard</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="figures/image10.jpg"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
      <para>As with most web applications, the architecture is fairly
        simple:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Horizon is usually deployed via mod_wsgi in Apache.
            The code itself is separated into a reusable python module
            with most of the logic (interactions with various
            OpenStack APIs) and presentation (to make it easily
            customizable for different sites).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>A database (configurable as to which one) which relies
              mostly on the other services for data. It also stores very
              little data of its own.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>From a network architecture point of view, this service
        will need to be customer accessible as well as be able to talk
        to each service's public APIs. If you wish to use the
        administrator functionality (i.e. for other services), it will
        also need connectivity to their Admin API endpoints (which
        should be non-customer accessible).</para>
  <para><guilabel>Compute</guilabel></para>
      <para>Nova is the most complicated and distributed component of
        OpenStack. A large number of processes cooperate to turn end
        user API requests into running virtual machines. Below is a
        list of these processes and their functions:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>nova-api accepts and responds to end user compute API
            calls. It supports OpenStack Compute API, Amazon's EC2 API
            and a special Admin API (for privileged users to perform
            administrative actions). It also initiates most of the
            orchestration activities (such as running an instance) as
            well as enforces some policy (mostly quota checks).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The nova-compute process is primarily a worker daemon
            that creates and terminates virtual machine instances via
            hypervisor's APIs (XenAPI for XenServer/XCP, libvirt for
            KVM or QEMU, VMwareAPI for VMware, etc.). The process by
            which it does so is fairly complex but the basics are
            simple: accept actions from the queue and then perform a
            series of system commands (like launching a KVM instance)
            to carry them out while updating state in the
            database.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>nova-volume manages the creation, attaching and
            detaching of z volumes to compute instances (similar
            functionality to Amazon’s Elastic Block Storage). It can
            use volumes from a variety of providers such as iSCSI or
            Rados Block Device in Ceph. A new OpenStack project,
            Cinder, will eventually replace nova-volume functionality.
            In the Folsom release, nova-volume and the Block Storage
            service will have similar functionality.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The nova-network worker daemon is very similar to
            nova-compute and nova-volume. It accepts networking tasks
            from the queue and then performs tasks to manipulate the
            network (such as setting up bridging interfaces or
            changing iptables rules). This functionality is being
            migrated to Quantum, a separate OpenStack service. In the
            Folsom release, much of the functionality will be
            duplicated between nova-network and Quantum.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The nova-schedule process is conceptually the simplest
            piece of code in OpenStack Nova: it takes a virtual machine
            instance request from the queue and determines where it
            should run (specifically, which compute server host it
            should run on).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The queue provides a central hub for passing messages
            between daemons. This is usually implemented with RabbitMQ
            today, but could be any AMPQ message queue (such as Apache
            Qpid). New to the Folsom release is support for Zero
            MQ.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The SQL database stores most of the build-time and
            runtime state for a cloud infrastructure. This includes
            the instance types that are available for use, instances
            in use, networks available and projects. Theoretically,
            OpenStack Nova can support any database supported by
            SQL-Alchemy but the only databases currently being widely
            used are sqlite3 (only appropriate for test and
            development work), MySQL and PostgreSQL.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Nova also provides console services to allow end users
            to access their virtual instance's console through a
            proxy. This involves several daemons (nova-console,
            nova-novncproxy and nova-consoleauth).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Nova interacts with many other OpenStack services:
        Keystone for authentication, Glance for images and Horizon for
        web interface. The Glance interactions are central. The API
        process can upload and query Glance while nova-compute will
        download images for use in launching images.</para>
  <para><guilabel>Object Store</guilabel></para>
      <para>The swift architecture is very distributed to prevent any
        single point of failure as well as to scale horizontally. It
        includes the following components:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Proxy server (swift-proxy-server) accepts incoming
            requests via the OpenStack Object API or just raw HTTP. It
            accepts files to upload, modifications to metadata or
            container creation. In addition, it will also serve files
            or container listing to web browsers. The proxy server may
            utilize an optional cache (usually deployed with memcache)
            to improve performance.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Account servers manage accounts defined with the
            object storage service.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Container servers manage a mapping of containers (i.e
            folders) within the object store service.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Object servers manage actual objects (i.e. files) on
            the storage nodes.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>There are also a number of periodic processes which run
            to perform housekeeping tasks on the large data store. The
            most important of these is the replication services, which
            ensures consistency and availability through the cluster.
            Other periodic processes include auditors, updaters and
            reapers.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Authentication is handled through configurable WSGI
        middleware (which will usually be Keystone).</para>
  <para><guilabel>Image Store</guilabel></para>
      <para>The Glance architecture has stayed relatively stable since
        the Cactus release. The biggest architectural change has been
        the addition of authentication, which was added in the Diablo
        release. Just as a quick reminder, Glance has four main parts
        to it:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>glance-api accepts Image API calls for image
            discovery, image retrieval and image storage.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>glance-registry stores, processes and retrieves
            metadata about images (size, type, etc.).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>A database to store the image metadata. Like Nova, you
            can choose your database depending on your preference (but
            most people use MySQL or SQlite).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>A storage repository for the actual image files. In
            the diagram above, Swift is shown as the image repository,
            but this is configurable. In addition to Swift, Glance
            supports normal filesystems, RADOS block devices, Amazon
            S3 and HTTP. Be aware that some of these choices are
            limited to read-only usage.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>There are also a number of periodic processes which run on
        Glance to support caching. The most important of these is the
        replication services, which ensures consistency and
        availability through the cluster. Other periodic processes
        include auditors, updaters and reapers.</para>
      <para>As you can see from the diagram in the Conceptual
        Architecture section, Glance serves a central role to the
        overall IaaS picture. It accepts API requests for images (or
        image metadata) from end users or Nova components and can
        store its disk files in the object storage service,
        Swift.</para>
  <para><guilabel>Identity</guilabel></para>
      <para>Keystone provides a single point of integration for
        OpenStack policy, catalog, token and authentication.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>keystone handles API requests as well as providing
            configurable catalog, policy, token and identity
            services.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Each Keystone function has a pluggable backend which
            allows different ways to use the particular service. Most
            support standard backends like LDAP or SQL, as well as Key
            Value Stores (KVS).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Most people will use this as a point of customization for
        their current authentication services.</para>
  <para><guilabel>Network</guilabel></para>
      <para>Quantum provides "network connectivity as a service"
        between interface devices managed by other OpenStack services
        (most likely Nova). The service works by allowing users to
        create their own networks and then attach interfaces to them.
        Like many of the OpenStack services, Quantum is highly
        configurable due to it's plug-in architecture. These plug-ins
        accommodate different networking equipment and software. As
        such, the architecture and deployment can vary dramatically.
        In the above architecture, a simple Linux networking plug-in
        is shown.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>quantum-server accepts API requests and then routes
            them to the appropriate quantum plugin for action.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Quantum plugins and agents perform the actual actions
            such as plugging and unplugging ports, creating networks
            or subnets and IP addressing. These plugins and agents
            differ depending on the vendor and technologies used in
            the particular cloud. Quantum ships with plugins and
            agents for: Cisco virtual and physical switches, Nicira
            NVP product, NEC OpenFlow products, Openvswitch, Linux
            bridging and the Ryu Network Operating System.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The common agents are L3 (layer 3), DHCP (dynamic host
            IP addressing) and the specific plug-in agent.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Most Quantum installations will also make use of a
            messaging queue to route information between the
            quantum-server and various agents as well as a database to
            store networking state for particular plugins.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Quantum will interact mainly with Nova, where it will
        provide networks and connectivity for its instances.</para>
  <para><guilabel>Block Storage</guilabel></para>
      <para>Cinder separates out the persistent block storage
        functionality that was previously part of OpenStack Compute
        (in the form of nova-volume) into it's own service. The
        OpenStack Block Storage API allows for manipulation of
        volumes, volume types (similar to compute flavors) and volume
        snapshots.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>cinder-api accepts API requests and routes them to
            cinder-volume for action.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>cinder-volume acts upon the requests by reading or
            writing to the Cinder database to maintain state,
            interacting with other processes (like cinder-scheduler)
            through a message queue and directly upon block storage
            providing hardware or software. It can interact with a
            variety of storage providers through a driver
            architecture. Currently, there are drivers for IBM,
            SolidFire, NetApp, Nexenta, Zadara, linux iSCSI and other
            storage providers.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Much like nova-scheduler, the cinder-scheduler daemon
            picks the optimal block storage provider node to create
            the volume on.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Cinder deployments will also make use of a messaging
            queue to route information between the cinder processes as
            well as a database to store volume state.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Like Quantum, Cinder will mainly interact with Nova,
        providing volumes for its instances.</para>
</chapter>
