<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
  xml:id="training-cluster-by-script">
  <title>Building the Training Cluster, Scripted</title>
    <para>Setting Up Test Environment</para>
  <para>For using Virtual Box as test environment, you need to attach three network adapters</para>
  <para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Host-Only/ Bridged -- 10.10.10.51 (Guest) -- 10.10.10.xx (Host IP for
          Host-Only)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Host-Only/ Bridged -- 192.168.100.51 (Guest) -- 192.168.100.xx (Host IP for
          Host-Only)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Bridged/NAT -- DHCP -- These Scripts should be run without internet connection after
          Pre-Install.sh. If your networking configuration is not exact a few command will not work.
          you need to change the Templates/* to the required IP Addresses for custom
          networks.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist></para>
   <para><link xlink:href="./training-labs/training-guides-cluster-scripts.tar"> Extract the
            scripts locally by downloading and running the scripts tar file.</link></para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Testing</emphasis></para>
    <para>As of now only */Scripts/ folders content are being tested. Please run the file
          ~/Scripts/test_scripts.sh for testing all the scripts at once with one click.</para>
    <para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Test Scripts Individually</emphasis>. Run the Scripts inside
                the Scripts Folder to check whether the shell scripts are properly functioning. You
                Don't Need to install Vitual Box although it is advised to do so, as there is a good
                chance that you may end up breaking your host machine.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">How to Test them</emphasis>. Testing these scripts is as
                simple as running them. Although some of the scripts need the required Input
                parameters. If you do not want to run them manually then you may run the
                Scripts/test_scripts.sh file. No Need for Virutalbox Guest Addons for testing the
                scripts as units.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Test Entire System</emphasis> you need to install Virtual Box,
                install Ubuntu Server 12.04 or 13.04. After installation you also need to install
                Virtual Box Guest Addons. To install Virtual Box guest addons you need do the
                following : Either use the Virtual Box Guest Addons Installation via. ISO,
                  <literal>#apt-get install linux-headers-generic #mount /dev/cdrom0/ /tmp/cdrom #cd
                  /tmp/cdrom/ #./virtualbox</literal>Or You May use Ubuntu Repositories for the
                same <literal>#apt-get install linux-headers-generic #apt-get
                  --no-install-recommends install virtualbox-guest-additions</literal></para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </para>
</section>
