<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0"
    xml:id="managing-openstack-object-storage-with-swift-cli">
    <title>Manage object storage</title>
    <para>The OpenStack Object Storage service provides the swift
        command-line interface (CLI) that enables you to gather
        statistics, list items, update metadata, upload, download, and
        delete files. This client is based on the native swift client
        library, <literal>client.py</literal>, which seamlessly
        re-authenticates if the current token expires during
        processing, retries operations multiple times, and provides a
        processing concurrency of 10. </para>
        <para>Users have roles on accounts. For example, the admin
        role enables full access to all containers and objects in an
        account. </para>
    <para>You can set access control lists (ACLs) are set at the container level
        and support lists for read and write access, which are set
        with the <literal>X-Container-Read</literal> and
            <literal>X-Container-Write</literal> header
        respectively.</para>
        <para>You can use the swift client to set the ACLs by using the
            <command>post</command> subcommand with the <parameter>-r</parameter> parameter for the read access and
            <parameter>-w</parameter> option for the write access. The following example enables the testuser user
            to read objects in the container:</para>
            <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>swift post -r 'testuser'</userinput></screen>
<para>You can also use this command with a list of users.</para>
        <para>If you use the StaticWeb middleware to enable
            OpenStack Object Storage to serve public web content,
            be aware of the ACL syntax for
            managing allowed referrers. The syntax is <literal>.r:</literal>
            followed by a list of allowed referrers. For example,
            the following command gives object access to all referring domains access:</para>
            <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>swift post -r '.r:*'</userinput></screen>
</section>
