<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="managing-openstack-object-storage-with-swift-cli">
    <title>Manage objects and containers</title>
    <para>The OpenStack Object Storage Service provides the
            <command>swift</command> client, which is a command-line
        interface (CLI). Use this client to list objects and
        containers, upload objects to containers, and download or
        delete objects from containers. You can also gather statistics
        and update metadata for accounts, containers, and objects.</para>
    <para>This client is based on the native swift client library,
            <literal>client.py</literal>, which seamlessly
        re-authenticates if the current token expires during
        processing, retries operations multiple times, and provides a
        processing concurrency of 10.</para>
    <para>Users have roles on accounts. For example, a user with the
        admin role has full access to all containers and objects in an
        account. You can set access control lists (ACLs) at the
        container level and support lists for read and write access,
        which you set with the <literal>X-Container-Read</literal> and
            <literal>X-Container-Write</literal> header,
        respectively.</para>
    <para>To give a user read access, use the <command>swift
            post</command> command with the <parameter>-r</parameter>
        parameter. To give a user write access, use the
            <parameter>-w</parameter> parameter.</para>
    <para>The following example enables the
            <literal>testuser</literal> user to read objects in the
        container:</para>
    <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>swift post -r 'testuser'</userinput></screen>
    <para>You can also use this command with a list of users.</para>
    <para>If you use StaticWeb middleware to enable Object Storage to
        serve public web content, use <literal>.r:</literal>, followed
        by a list of allowed referrers.</para>
    <para>The following command gives object access to all referring
        domains:</para>
    <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>swift post -r '.r:*'</userinput></screen>
</section>
