<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [ <!ENTITY % openstack SYSTEM "../common/entities/openstack.ent"> %openstack; ]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="large-object-creation">
    <title>Large objects</title>
    <para>To discover whether your Object Storage system supports this
        feature, see <xref linkend="discoverability"/>. Alternatively,
        check with your service provider.</para>
    <para>By default, the content of an object cannot be greater than
        5&nbsp;GB. However, you can use a number of smaller objects to
        construct a large object. The large object is comprised of two
        types of objects:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Segment objects</emphasis>
                store the object content. You can divide your content
                into segments, and upload each segment into its own
                segment object. Segment objects do not have any
                special features. You create, update, download, and
                delete segment objects just as you would normal
                objects.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>A <emphasis role="bold">manifest object</emphasis>
                links the segment objects into one logical large
                object. When you download a manifest object, Object
                Storage concatenates and returns the contents of the
                segment objects in the response body of the request.
                This behavior extends to the response headers returned
                by &GET; and &HEAD; requests. The
                    <literal>Content-Length</literal> response header
                value is the total size of all segment objects. Object
                Storage calculates the <literal>ETag</literal>
                response header value by taking the
                    <literal>ETag</literal> value of each segment,
                concatenating them together, and returning the MD5
                checksum of the result. The manifest object types
                are:</para>
            <variablelist wordsize="10">
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><emphasis role="bold">Static large
                            objects</emphasis></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The manifest object content is an
                            ordered list of the names of the segment
                            objects in JSON format. See <xref
                                linkend="static-large-objects"
                            />.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><emphasis role="bold">Dynamic large
                            objects</emphasis></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The manifest object has no content but
                            it has a
                                <literal>X-Object-Manifest</literal>
                            metadata header. The value of this header
                            is
                            <literal>{container}/{prefix}</literal>,
                            where <literal>{container}</literal> is
                            the name of the container where the
                            segment objects are stored, and
                                <literal>{prefix}</literal> is a
                            string that all segment objects have in
                            common. See <xref
                                linkend="dynamic-large-object-creation"
                            />.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <note>
        <para>If you make a &COPY; request by using a manifest object
            as the source, the new object is a normal, and not a
            segment, object. If the total size of the source segment
            objects exceeds 5&nbsp;GB, the &COPY; request fails.
            However, you can make a duplicate of the manifest object
            and this new object can be larger than 5&nbsp;GB.</para>
    </note>
    <section xml:id="static-large-objects">
        <title>Static large objects</title>
        <para>To create a static large object, divide your content
            into pieces and create (upload) a segment object to
            contain each piece.</para>
        <para>You must record the <literal>ETag</literal> response
            header that the &PUT; operation returns. Alternatively,
            you can calculate the MD5 checksum of the segment prior to
            uploading and include this in the <literal>ETag</literal>
            request header. This ensures that the upload cannot
            corrupt your data.</para>
        <para>List the name of each segment object along with its size
            and MD5 checksum in order.</para>
        <para>Create a manifest object. Include the
                <literal>?multipart-manifest=put</literal> query
            string at the end of the manifest object name to indicate
            that this is a manifest object.</para>
        <para>The body of the &PUT; request on the manifest object
            comprises a json list, where each element contains the
            following attributes:</para>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><code>path</code></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The container and object name in the format:
                            <code>{container-name}/{object-name}</code>.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><code>etag</code></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The MD5 checksum of the content of the
                        segment object. This value must match the
                            <literal>ETag</literal> of that
                        object.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><code>size_bytes</code></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The size of the segment object. This value
                        must match the
                            <literal>Content-Length</literal> of that
                        object.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <example>
            <title>Static large object manifest list</title>
            <para>This example shows three segment objects. You can
                use several containers and the object names do not
                have to conform to a specific pattern, in contrast to
                dynamic large objects.</para>
            <literallayout class="monospaced"><xi:include href="samples/slo-manifest-example.txt" parse="text"/></literallayout>
        </example>
        <para>The <literal>Content-Length</literal> request header
            must contain the length of the json content&mdash;not the
            length of the segment objects. However, after the &PUT;
            operation completes, the <literal>Content-Length</literal>
            metadata is set to the total length of all the object
            segments. A similar situation applies to the
                <literal>ETag</literal>. If used in the &PUT;
            operation, it must contain the MD5 checksum of the json
            content. The <literal>ETag</literal> metadata value is
            then set to be the MD5 checksum of the concatenated
                <literal>ETag</literal> values of the object segments.
            You can also set the <literal>Content-Type</literal>
            request header and custom object metadata.</para>
        <para>When the &PUT; operation sees the
                <literal>?multipart-manifest=put</literal> query
            parameter, it reads the request body and verifies that
            each segment object exists and that the sizes and ETags
            match. If there is a mismatch, the &PUT;operation
            fails.</para>
        <para>If everything matches, the manifest object is created.
            The <literal>X-Static-Large-Object</literal> metadata is
            set to <literal>true</literal> indicating that this is a
            static object manifest.</para>
        <para>Normally when you perform a &GET; operation on the
            manifest object, the response body contains the
            concatenated content of the segment objects. To download
            the manifest list, use the
                <literal>?multipart-manifest=get</literal> query
            parameter. The resulting list is not formatted the same as
            the manifest you originally used in the &PUT;
            operation.</para>
        <para>If you use the &DELETE; operation on a manifest object,
            the manifest object is deleted. The segment objects are
            not affected. However, if you add the
                <literal>?multipart-manifest=delete</literal>
            query parameter, the segment objects are deleted and if
            all are successfully deleted, the manifest object is also
            deleted.</para>
        <para>To change the manifest, use a &PUT; operation with the
                <literal>?multipart-manifest=put</literal> query
            parameter. This request creates a manifest object. You can
            also update the object metadata in the usual way.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="dynamic-large-object-creation">
        <title>Dynamic large objects</title>
        <para>You must segment objects that are larger than 5&nbsp;GB
            before you can upload them. You then upload the segment
            objects like you would any other object and create a
            dynamic large manifest object. The manifest object tells
            Object Storage how to find the segment objects that
            comprise the large object. The segments remain
            individually addressable, but retrieving the manifest
            object streams all the segments concatenated. There is no
            limit to the number of segments that can be a part of a
            single large object.</para>
        <para>To ensure the download works correctly, you must upload
            all the object segments to the same container and ensure
            that each object name is prefixed in such a way that it
            sorts in the order in which it should be concatenated. You
            also create and upload a manifest file. The manifest file
            is a zero-byte file with the extra
                <literal>X-Object-Manifest</literal>
            <code>{container}/{prefix}</code> header, where
                <code>{container}</code> is the container the object
            segments are in and <code>{prefix}</code> is the common
            prefix for all the segments. You must UTF-8-encode and
            then URL-encode the container and common prefix in the
                <literal>X-Object-Manifest</literal> header.</para>
        <para>It is best to upload all the segments first and then
            create or update the manifest. With this method, the full
            object is not available for downloading until the upload
            is complete. Also, you can upload a new set of segments to
            a second location and update the manifest to point to this
            new location. During the upload of the new segments, the
            original manifest is still available to download the first
            set of segments.</para>
        <example>
            <title>Upload segment of large object request:
                HTTP</title>
            <literallayout class="monospaced"><xi:include href="samples/large-object-upload-segment-req.txt" parse="text"/></literallayout>
        </example>
        <para>No response body is returned. A status code of
                    <returnvalue>2<replaceable>nn</replaceable></returnvalue>
            (between 200 and 299, inclusive) indicates a successful
            write; status <errorcode>411</errorcode>
            <errortext>Length Required</errortext> denotes a missing
                <literal>Content-Length</literal> or
                <literal>Content-Type</literal> header in the request.
            If the MD5 checksum of the data written to the storage
            system does NOT match the (optionally) supplied ETag
            value, a <errorcode>422</errorcode>
            <errortext>Unprocessable Entity</errortext> response is
            returned.</para>
        <para>You can continue uploading segments, like this example
            shows, prior to uploading the manifest.</para>
        <example>
            <title>Upload next segment of large object request:
                HTTP</title>
            <literallayout class="monospaced"><xi:include href="samples/large-object-upload-next-segment-req.txt" parse="text"/></literallayout>
        </example>
        <para>Next, upload the manifest you created that indicates the
            container where the object segments reside. Note that
            uploading additional segments after the manifest is
            created causes the concatenated object to be that much
            larger but you do not need to recreate the manifest file
            for subsequent additional segments.</para>
        <example>
            <title>Upload manifest request: HTTP</title>
            <literallayout class="monospaced"><xi:include href="samples/upload-manifest-req.txt" parse="text"/></literallayout>
        </example>
        <example>
            <title>Upload manifest response: HTTP</title>
            <literallayout class="monospaced"><xi:include href="samples/upload-manifest-resp.txt" parse="text"/></literallayout>
        </example>
        <para>The <literal>Content-Type</literal> in the response for
            a &GET; or &HEAD; on the manifest is the same as the
                <literal>Content-Type</literal> set during the &PUT;
            request that created the manifest. You can change the
                <literal>Content-Type</literal> by reissuing the &PUT;
            request.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="comparison_dynamic_static_objects">
        <title>Comparison of static and dynamic large objects</title>
        <para>While static and dynamic objects have similar behavior,
            this table describes their differences:</para>
        <table rules="all">
            <caption>Static and dynamic large objects</caption>
            <col width="20%"/>
            <col width="40%"/>
            <col width="40%"/>
            <thead>
                <tr>
                    <td/>
                    <th>Static large object</th>
                    <th>Dynamic large object</th>
                </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
                <tr>
                    <th>End-to-end integrity</th>
                    <td><para>Assured. The list of segments includes
                            the MD5 checksum (<literal>ETag</literal>)
                            of each segment. You cannot upload the
                            manifest object if the
                                <literal>ETag</literal> in the list
                            differs from the uploaded segment object.
                            If a segment is somehow lost, an attempt
                            to download the manifest object results in
                            an error.</para></td>
                    <td><para>Not guaranteed. The eventual consistency
                            model means that although you have
                            uploaded a segment object, it might not
                            appear in the container listing until
                            later. If you download the manifest before
                            it appears in the container, it does not
                            form part of the content returned in
                            response to a &GET; request.</para></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <th>Upload order</th>
                    <td><para>You must upload the segment objects
                            before you upload the manifest
                            object.</para></td>
                    <td><para>You can upload manifest and segment
                            objects in any order. You are recommended
                            to upload the manifest object after the
                            segments in case a premature download of
                            the manifest occurs. However, this is not
                            enforced.</para></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <th>Removal or addition of segment objects</th>
                    <td><para>You cannot add or remove segment objects
                            from the manifest. However, you can create
                            a completely new manifest object of the
                            same name with a different manifest
                            list.</para></td>
                    <td><para>You can upload new segment objects or
                            remove existing segments. The names must
                            simply match the
                                <literal>{prefix}</literal> supplied
                            in
                            <literal>X-Object-Manifest</literal>.</para></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <th>Segment object size and number</th>
                    <td><para>Segment objects must be at least
                            1&nbsp;MB in size (by default). The final
                            segment object can be any size. At most,
                            1000 segments are supported (by
                            default).</para></td>
                    <td><para>Segment objects can be any
                        size.</para></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <th>Segment object container name</th>
                    <td><para>The manifest list includes the container
                            name of each object. Segment objects can
                            be in different containers.</para></td>
                    <td><para>All segment objects must be in the same
                            container.</para></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <th>Manifest object metadata</th>
                    <td><para>The object has
                                <literal>X-Static-Large-Object</literal>
                            set to <literal>true</literal>. You do not
                            set this metadata directly. Instead the
                            system sets it when you &PUT; a static
                            manifest object.</para></td>
                    <td><para>The <literal>X-Object-Manifest</literal>
                            value is the
                                <literal>{container}/{prefix}</literal>,
                            which indicates where the segment objects
                            are located. You supply this request
                            header in the &PUT; operation.</para></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <th>Copying the manifest object</th>
                    <td><para>Include the
                                <literal>?multipart-manifest=get</literal>
                            query string in the &COPY; request. The
                            new object contains the same manifest as
                            the original. The segment objects are not
                            copied. Instead, both the original and new
                            manifest objects share the same set of
                            segment objects.</para>
                    </td>
                    <td><para>The &COPY; operation does not create a
                            manifest object. To duplicate a manifest
                            object, use the &GET; operation to read
                            the value of
                                <literal>X-Object-Manifest</literal>
                            and use this value in the
                                <literal>X-Object-Manifest</literal>
                            request header in a &PUT; operation. This
                            creates a new manifest object that shares
                            the same set of segment objects as the
                            original manifest object.</para></td>
                </tr>
            </tbody>
        </table>
    </section>
</section>
