<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="reboot">
    <title>Reboot an instance</title>

<para>You can soft or hard reboot a running instance. A soft reboot
        attempts a graceful shut down and restart of the instance. A
        hard reboot power cycles the instance.</para>

<procedure> <step><para>By default, when you reboot an instance, it is a soft reboot.</para>
<screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>nova reboot <replaceable>SERVER</replaceable></userinput></screen></step></procedure>

<procedure> <step><para>To perform a hard reboot, pass the <parameter>--hard</parameter> parameter, as follows:</para>
<screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>nova reboot --hard <replaceable>SERVER</replaceable></userinput></screen></step></procedure>

<para>It is also possible to reboot a running instance into
 rescue mode. This operation may be required, if a filesystem
 of an instance becomes corrupted with a prolonged usage,
 for example.</para>

<note>
<para>Pause, suspend, and stop operations are not allowed
 when an instance is running in rescue mode, as triggering
 these actions causes the loss of the original instance
 state and makes it impossible to unrescue the instance.</para>
</note>

<para>Rescue mode provides a mechanism for access, even
 if an image renders the instance inaccessible. By default,
 it starts an instance from the initial image attaching
 the current boot disk as a secondary one.</para>

<procedure> <step><para>To perform an instance reboot into rescue
 mode, run the following command:</para>
<screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>nova rescue <replaceable>SERVER</replaceable></userinput></screen></step></procedure>

<procedure> <step><para>To restart the instance from the normal
 boot disk, run the following command:</para>
<screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>nova unrescue <replaceable>SERVER</replaceable></userinput></screen></step></procedure>

<procedure> <step><para>If you want to rescue an instance with a specific
 image, rather than the default one, use the
 <parameter>--rescue_image_ref</parameter> parameter, as follows:</para>

<screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>nova rescue --rescue_image_ref <replaceable>IMAGE_ID</replaceable><replaceable> SERVER</replaceable></userinput></screen></step></procedure>

</section>
