<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xml:id="compute-system-requirements"    
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <title>Compute and Image System Requirements</title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Hardware</emphasis>: OpenStack
        components are intended to run on standard hardware.
        Recommended hardware configurations for a minimum
        production deployment are as follows for the cloud
        controller nodes and compute nodes for Compute and the
        Image Service, and object, account, container, and proxy
        servers for Object Storage. </para>
    <table rules="all">
        <caption>Hardware Recommendations </caption>
        <col width="20%"/>
        <col width="23%"/>
        <col width="57%"/>
        
        <thead>
            <tr>
                <td>Server</td>
                <td>Recommended Hardware</td>
                <td>Notes</td>
            </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
            <tr>
                <td>Cloud Controller node (runs network, volume, API, scheduler and image
                    services) </td>
                <td>
                    <para>Processor: 64-bit x86</para>
                    <para>Memory: 12 GB RAM </para>
                    <para>Disk space: 30 GB (SATA or SAS or SSD) </para>
                    <para>Volume storage: two disks with 2 TB (SATA) for volumes attached to the
                        compute nodes </para>
                    <para>Network: one 1 GB Network Interface Card (NIC)</para>
                </td>
                <td>
                    <para>Two NICS are recommended but not required. A quad core server with 12
                        GB RAM would be more than sufficient for a cloud controller node.</para>
                    <para>32-bit processors will work for the cloud controller node. </para>
                    <para>The package repositories referred to in this
                        guide do not contain i386 packages.</para>
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Compute nodes (runs virtual instances)</td>
                <td>
                    <para>Processor: 64-bit x86</para>
                    <para>Memory: 32 GB RAM</para>
                    <para>Disk space: 30 GB (SATA)</para>
                    <para>Network: two 1 GB NICs</para>
                </td>
                <td>
                    <para>Note that you cannot run 64-bit VM instances
                        on a 32-bit compute node. A 64-bit compute
                        node can run either 32- or 64-bit VMs,
                        however. </para>
                    <para>With 2 GB RAM you can run one m1.small instance on a node or three
                        m1.tiny instances without memory swapping, so 2 GB RAM would be a
                        minimum for a test-environment compute node. As an example, Rackspace
                        Cloud Builders use 96 GB RAM for compute nodes in OpenStack
                        deployments.</para>
                    <para>Specifically for virtualization on certain hypervisors on the node or
                        nodes running nova-compute, you need a x86 machine with an AMD processor
                        with SVM extensions (also called AMD-V) or an Intel processor with VT
                        (virtualization technology) extensions. </para>
                    <para>For XenServer and XCP refer to the <link
                        xlink:href="http://docs.vmd.citrix.com/XenServer/6.0.0/1.0/en_gb/installation.html#sys_requirements">
                        XenServer installation guide</link> and the <link
                        xlink:href="http://hcl.vmd.citrix.com/">
                        XenServer harware compatibility list</link>.</para>
                    <para>For LXC, the VT extensions are not required.</para>
                    <para>The packages referred to in this guide do not
                        contain i386 packages.</para>
                </td>
            </tr>
            
        </tbody>
    </table>
    <note>
        <para>While certain parts of OpenStack are known to work on
            various operating systems, currently the only
            feature-complete, production-supported host environment is
            Linux.</para></note>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Operating System</emphasis>: OpenStack currently has packages for
        the following distributions: CentOS, Debian, Fedora, RHEL, Debian, and Ubuntu. These
        packages are maintained by community members, refer to <link
            xlink:href="http://wiki.openstack.org/Packaging"
            >http://wiki.openstack.org/Packaging</link> for additional links.
            <note>
            <para os="ubuntu">The Folsom release of OpenStack Compute requires Ubuntu 12.04 or
                later, as the version of libvirt that ships with Ubuntu 11.10 does not function
                properly with OpenStack due to <link
                    xlink:href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/nova/+bug/1011863">bug
                #1011863</link>.</para>
                <para os="fedora">The Folsom release of OpenStack Compute requires Fedora 16 or
                    later, as the version of libvirt that ships with Fedora 15 does not function
                    properly with OpenStack due to <link
                        xlink:href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/nova/+bug/1011863">bug
                        #1011863</link>.</para>
        </note></para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Database</emphasis>: For
        OpenStack Compute, you need access to either a PostgreSQL
        or MySQL database, or you can install it as part of the
        OpenStack Compute installation process. For Object
        Storage, the container and account servers use SQLite, and
        you can install it as part of the installation
        process.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Permissions</emphasis>: You can
        install OpenStack Compute, the Image Service, or Object
        Storage either as root or as a user with sudo permissions
        if you configure the sudoers file to enable all the
        permissions. </para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Network Time Protocol</emphasis>:
        You must install a time synchronization program such as
        NTP. For Compute, time synchronization keeps your cloud
        controller and compute nodes talking to the same time
        server to avoid problems scheduling VM launches on compute
        nodes. For Object Storage, time synchronization ensure the
        object replications are accurately updating objects when
        needed so that the freshest content is served.</para>
</section>
