<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xml:id="configure-creds"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <title>Defining Compute and Image Service Credentials</title>
    <para>The commands in this section can be run on any machine that can access the cloud
        controller node over the network. You can run commands directly on the cloud controller, if
        you like, but it isn't required.</para>
    <para>Create an <filename>openrc</filename> file that can contain these variables that are used
        by the <command>nova</command> (Compute) and <command>glance</command> (Image) command-line
        interface clients. These commands can be run by any user, and the
            <filename>openrc</filename> file  can be stored anywhere. In this document, we store the
            <filename>openrc</filename> file in the <filename>~/creds</filename> directory:</para>

<screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>mkdir ~/creds</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>nano ~/creds/openrc</userinput>
</screen>
    <para>In this example, we are going to create an <filename>openrc</filename> file with
        credentials associated with a user who is not an administrator. Because the user is not an
        administrator, the credential file will use the URL associated with the keystone service
        API, which runs on port <literal>5000</literal>. If we wanted to use the
            <command>keystone</command> command-line tool to perform administrative commands, we
        would use the URL associated with the keystone admin API, which runs on port
            <literal>35357</literal>.</para>

    <para>In the <filename>openrc</filename> file you create, paste these values:</para>
<programlisting><xi:include parse="text" href="samples/openrc.txt"/></programlisting>
    <para>Next, ensure these are used in your environment. If you see
        401 Not Authorized errors on commands using tokens, ensure
        that you have properly sourced your credentials and that all
        the pipelines are accurate in the configuration files.</para>

<screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>source ~/creds/openrc</userinput>
</screen>

<para>Verify your credentials are working by using the <command>nova</command>
client to list the available images:</para>
<screen>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>nova image-list</userinput>
<computeroutput>
+--------------------------------------+--------------+--------+--------+
| ID                                   | Name         | Status | Server |
+--------------------------------------+--------------+--------+--------+
| acafc7c0-40aa-4026-9673-b879898e1fc2 | CirrOS 0.3.1 | ACTIVE |        |
+--------------------------------------+--------------+--------+--------+
</computeroutput>
</screen>
<para>Note that the ID value on your installation will be different.</para>
</section>

