<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section 
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
    version="5.0"
    xml:id="example-installation-architecture">
    <title>Example Installation Architectures</title>
    
    <para>OpenStack Compute uses a shared-nothing, messaging-based
        architecture. While very flexible, the fact that you can install each
        nova- service on an independent server means there are many possible
        methods for installing OpenStack Compute. Here are the types of
        installation architectures:</para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Single node: Only one server runs all nova- services and also
                drives all the virtual instances. Use this configuration only for
                trying out OpenStack Compute, or for development purposes.</para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
            <para>Two nodes: A cloud controller node runs the nova- services
                except for <command>nova-compute</command>, and a compute node runs
                <command>nova-compute</command>. A client computer is likely needed to
                bundle images and interfacing to the servers, but a client is not
                required. Use this configuration for proof of concepts or development
                environments.</para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
            <para>Multiple nodes: You can add more compute nodes to the two node
                installation by simply installing <command>nova-compute</command> on
                an additional server and copying a <filename>nova.conf</filename> file
                to the added node. This would result in a multiple node installation.
                You can also add a volume controller and a network controller as
                additional nodes in a more complex multiple node installation. A
                minimum of 4 nodes is best for running multiple virtual instances that
                require a lot of processing power.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>This is an illustration of one possible multiple server installation
        of OpenStack Compute; virtual server networking in the cluster may
        vary.</para>
    
    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/NOVA_install_arch.png" scale="80"/>
        </imageobject>
    </inlinemediaobject></para>
    
    <para>An alternative architecture would be to add more messaging servers
        if you notice a lot of back up in the messaging queue causing performance
        problems. In that case you would add an additional RabbitMQ server in
        addition to or instead of scaling up the database server. Your
        installation can run any nova- service on any server as long as the
        <filename>nova.conf</filename> is configured to point to the RabbitMQ
        server and the server can send messages to the server.</para>
    
    <para>Multiple installation architectures are possible, here is another
        example illustration.</para>
    
    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/NOVA_compute_nodes.png" scale="40"/>
        </imageobject>
    </inlinemediaobject></para>
</section>
