<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xml:id="installing-additional-compute-nodes"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <title>Installing Additional Compute Nodes</title>
    <para>There are many different ways to perform a multinode install
        of Compute in order to scale out your deployment and run more
        compute nodes, enabling more virtual machines to run
        simultaneously. </para>
    <para>Ensure that the networking on each node is configured as documented in the <link
            linkend="compute-configuring-guest-network">Pre-configuring the network</link>
        section.</para>
    <para>In this case, you can install all the nova- packages and
        dependencies as you did for the Cloud Controller node, or just
        install nova-compute. Your installation can run any nova-
        services anywhere, so long as the service can access
            <filename>nova.conf</filename> so it knows where the
        Rabbitmq or Qpid messaging server is installed.</para>
    <para>When running in a high-availability mode for networking, the
        compute node is where you configure the compute network, the
        networking between your instances. Learn more about
        high-availability for networking in the Compute Adminstration
        manual. </para>
    <para>Because you may need to query the database from the compute
        node and learn more information about instances, the nova
        client and MySQL client or PostgresSQL client packages should
        be installed on any additional compute nodes.</para>
    <para>Copy the <filename>nova.conf</filename> from your controller node to all additional
        compute nodes. As mentioned in the section entitled <link
            linkend="compute-minimum-configuration-settings">Configuring OpenStack Compute</link>,
        modify the following configuration options so that they match the IP address of the compute
        host:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para><literal>my_ip</literal></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><literal>vncserver_listen</literal></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><literal>vncserver_proxyclient_address</literal></para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</section>
