<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xml:id="setting-up-openstack-compute-environment-on-the-compute-node"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <title>Setting Up OpenStack Compute Environment on the Compute Node</title>
    <para>
        These are the commands you run to ensure the database schema is current, and
        then set up a user and project, if you are using built-in auth with the
        <code>--use_deprecated_auth</code> flag rather than the Identity Service. We'll walk through these to offer a validation step and show that the cloud is accepting commands. 
    </para>
    <para>
        <literallayout class="monospaced">sudo nova-manage user admin &lt;user_name>
nova-manage project create &lt;project_name> &lt;user_name>
nova-manage network create &lt;network-label> --bridge=&lt;bridgename> &lt;IP-range-of-network-CIDR> &lt;number-of-networks-to-define-for-project> &lt;addresses-in-each-network> </literallayout>
    </para>
    <para>Here is an example of what this looks like with real values
        entered and values returned: </para>
    <literallayout class="monospaced">$ sudo nova-manage user admin dub
export EC2_ACCESS_KEY=a42e03c9-656d-4c11-a660-80ed374a4cfb
export EC2_SECRET_KEY=a00a3a32-726a-4e1e-b0c8-24e7df55c959

$ sudo nova-manage project create dubproject dub

$ sudo nova-manage network create novanet --bridge_interface=br100 192.168.100.0/24 1 256</literallayout>
    <para>For this example, the number of IPs is /24 which will be compatible with the ‘fixed-range’
        set in nova.conf. Currently, there can only be one network, and this set up would use the
        max IPs available in a /24. You can choose values that let you use any valid amount that you
        would like. </para>
    <para>The nova-manage service assumes that the first IP address is
        your network (like 192.168.11.0), that the 2nd IP is your
        gateway (192.168.11.1), and that the broadcast is the very
        last IP in the range you defined (192.168.11.255). If this is
        not the case you will need to manually edit the sql db
        ‘networks’ table.o. </para>
    <para>When you run the nova-manage network create command, entries are made
        in the ‘networks’ and ‘fixed_ips’ table. However, one of the networks listed in the
        ‘networks’ table needs to be marked as bridge in order for the code to know that a
        bridge exists. The network in the Nova networks table is marked as bridged
        automatically for Flat Manager.</para>
    
   
</section>