<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="ch_limitations">
    <title>Limitations</title>
    <para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>No equivalent for nova-network
                        --multi_host flag:</emphasis> Nova-network has
                    a model where the L3, NAT, and DHCP processing
                    happen on the compute node itself, rather than a
                    dedicated networking node. OpenStack Networking
                    now support running multiple l3-agent and dhcp-agents
                    with load being split across those agents, but the
                    tight coupling of that scheduling with the location of
                    the VM is not supported in Grizzly.  The Havana release is expected
                    to include an exact replacement for the --multi_host flag
                    in nova-network.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>Linux network namespace required on nodes running neutron-l3-agent
                        or neutron-dhcp-agent if overlapping IPs are in use: </emphasis>. In order
                    to support overlapping IP addresses, the OpenStack Networking DHCP and L3 agents
                    use Linux network namespaces by default. The hosts running these processes must
                    support network namespaces. To support network namespaces, the following are
                    required:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Linux kernel 2.6.24 or newer (with CONFIG_NET_NS=y in kernel
                            configuration) and</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>iproute2 utilities ('ip' command) version 3.1.0 (aka 20111117) or
                            newer</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>To check whether your host supports namespaces try running the following as
                    root:</para>
                <screen><computeroutput>ip netns add test-ns
ip netns exec test-ns ifconfig</computeroutput></screen>
                <para>If the preceding commands do not produce errors, your platform is likely
                    sufficient to use the dhcp-agent or l3-agent with namespace. In our experience,
                    Ubuntu 12.04 or later support namespaces as does Fedora 17 and new, but some
                    older RHEL platforms do not by default. It may be possible to upgrade the
                    iproute2 package on a platform that does not support namespaces by default.</para>
                <para>If you need to disable namespaces, make sure the
                        <filename>neutron.conf</filename> used by neutron-server has the following
                    setting:</para>
                <screen><computeroutput>allow_overlapping_ips=False</computeroutput></screen>
                <para>and that the dhcp_agent.ini and l3_agent.ini have the following
                    setting:</para>
                <screen><computeroutput>use_namespaces=False</computeroutput></screen>
                <note><para>If the host does not support namespaces then the <systemitem class="service"
                            >neutron-l3-agent</systemitem> and <systemitem class="service"
                            >neutron-dhcp-agent</systemitem> should be run on different hosts. This
                        is due to the fact that there is no isolation between the IP addresses
                        created by the L3 agent and by the DHCP agent. By manipulating the routing
                        the user can ensure that these networks have access to one another.</para></note>
                <para>If you run both L3 + DHCP services on the same node, you should enable
                    namespaces to avoid conflicts with routes :</para>
                    <screen><computeroutput>use_namespaces=True</computeroutput></screen>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <itemizedlist><listitem>
                <para><emphasis>No IPv6 support for L3 agent:</emphasis> The neutron-l3-agent, used
                    by many plugins to implement L3 forwarding, supports only IPv4 forwarding.
                    Currently, There are no errors provided if you configure IPv6 addresses via the
                    API.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>ZeroMQ support is experimental</emphasis>: Some agents, including
                    neutron-dhcp-agent, neutron-openvswitch-agent, and neutron-linuxbridge-agent use
                    RPC to communicate. ZeroMQ is an available option in the configuration file, but
                    has not been tested and should be considered experimental. In particular, there
                    are believed to be issues with ZeroMQ and the dhcp agent.</para>
            </listitem><listitem>
                <para><emphasis>MetaPlugin is experimental</emphasis>: This release includes a
                    "MetaPlugin" that is intended to support multiple plugins at the same time for
                    different API requests, based on the content of those API requests. This
                    functionality has not been widely reviewed or tested by the core team, and
                    should be considered experimental until further validation is performed.</para>
            </listitem>
           </itemizedlist>
    </para>
</chapter>
