<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <!-- Warning: Do not edit this file. It is automatically
             generated and your changes will be overwritten.
             The tool to do so lives in the tools directory of this
             repository -->
        <para xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
        <table rules="all">
          <caption>Description of configuration options for images</caption>
           <col width="50%"/>
           <col width="50%"/>
           <thead>
              <tr>
                  <td>Configuration option=Default value</td>
                  <td>(Type) Description</td>
              </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
              <tr>
                       <td>glance_api_insecure=False</td>
                       <td>(BoolOpt) Allow to perform insecure SSL (https) requests to glance</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>glance_api_servers=$glance_host:$glance_port</td>
                       <td>(ListOpt) A list of the glance api servers available to cinder ([hostname|ip]:port)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>glance_api_ssl_compression=False</td>
                       <td>(BoolOpt) Whether to attempt to negotiate SSL layer compression when using SSL (https) requests. Set to False to disable SSL layer compression. In some cases disabling this may improve data throughput, eg when high network bandwidth is available and you are using already compressed image formats such as qcow2 .</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>glance_api_version=1</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Version of the glance api to use</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>glance_host=$my_ip</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) default glance hostname or ip</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>glance_num_retries=0</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) Number retries when downloading an image from glance</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>glance_port=9292</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) default glance port</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>gpfs_images_dir=None</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) Path to GPFS Glance repository as mounted on Nova nodes</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>gpfs_images_share_mode=None</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) Set this if Glance image repo is on GPFS as well so that the image bits can be transferred efficiently between Glance and Cinder.  Valid values are copy or copy_on_write. copy performs a full copy of the image, copy_on_write efficiently shares unmodified blocks of the image.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>gpfs_max_clone_depth=0</td>
                       <td>(IntOpt) A lengthy chain of copy-on-write snapshots or clones could have impact on performance.  This option limits the number of indirections required to reach a specific block. 0 indicates unlimited.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>gpfs_mount_point_base=None</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) Path to the directory on GPFS mount point where volumes are stored</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>gpfs_sparse_volumes=True</td>
                       <td>(BoolOpt) Create volumes as sparse files which take no space. If set to False volume is created as regular file. In this case volume creation may take a significantly longer time.</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>image_conversion_dir=/tmp</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) parent dir for tempdir used for image conversion</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>instance_format=[instance: %(uuid)s]</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) If an instance is passed with the log message, format it like this</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>instance_uuid_format=[instance: %(uuid)s]</td>
                       <td>(StrOpt) If an instance UUID is passed with the log message, format it like this</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                       <td>use_multipath_for_image_xfer=False</td>
                       <td>(BoolOpt) Do we attach/detach volumes in cinder using multipath for volume to image and image to volume transfers?</td>
              </tr>
       </tbody>
        </table>
        </para>
