<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="configuring-object-storage-features">
    <title>Configure Object Storage features</title>
    <section xml:id="swift-zones">
        <title>Object Storage zones</title>
        <para>In OpenStack Object Storage, data is placed across
            different tiers of failure domains. First, data is spread
            across regions, then zones, then servers, and finally
            across drives. Data is placed to get the highest failure
            domain isolation. If you deploy multiple regions, the
            Object Storage service places the data across the regions.
            Within a region, each replica of the data should be stored
            in unique zones, if possible. If there is only one zone,
            data should be placed on different servers. And if there
            is only one server, data should be placed on different
            drives.</para>
        <para>Regions are widely separated installations with a
            high-latency or otherwise constrained network link between
            them. Zones are arbitrarily assigned, and it is up to the
            administrator of the Object Storage cluster to choose an
            isolation level and attempt to maintain the isolation
            level through appropriate zone assignment. For example, a
            zone may be defined as a rack with a single power source.
            Or a zone may be a DC room with a common utility provider.
            Servers are identified by a unique IP/port. Drives are
            locally attached storage volumes identified by mount
            point.</para>
        <para>In small clusters (five nodes or fewer), everything is
            normally in a single zone. Larger Object Storage
            deployments may assign zone designations differently; for
            example, an entire cabinet or rack of servers may be
            designated as a single zone to maintain replica
            availability if the cabinet becomes unavailable (for
            example, due to failure of the top of rack switches or a
            dedicated circuit). In very large deployments, such as
            service provider level deployments, each zone might have
            an entirely autonomous switching and power infrastructure,
            so that even the loss of an electrical circuit or
            switching aggregator would result in the loss of a single
            replica at most.</para>
        <section xml:id="swift-zones-rackspacerecs">
            <title>Rackspace zone recommendations</title>
            <para>For ease of maintenance on OpenStack Object Storage,
                Rackspace recommends that you set up at least five
                nodes. Each node is assigned its own zone (for a total
                of five zones), which gives you host level redundancy.
                This enables you to take down a single zone for
                maintenance and still guarantee object availability in
                the event that another zone fails during your
                maintenance.</para>
            <para>You could keep each server in its own cabinet to achieve cabinet level isolation,
                but you may wish to wait until your Object Storage service is better established
                before developing cabinet-level isolation. OpenStack Object Storage is flexible; if
                you later decide to change the isolation level, you can take down one zone at a time
                and move them to appropriate new homes.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="swift-raid-controller">
        <title>RAID controller configuration</title>
        <para>OpenStack Object Storage does not require RAID. In fact,
            most RAID configurations cause significant performance
            degradation. The main reason for using a RAID controller
            is the battery-backed cache. It is very important for data
            integrity reasons that when the operating system confirms
            a write has been committed that the write has actually
            been committed to a persistent location. Most disks lie
            about hardware commits by default, instead writing to a
            faster write cache for performance reasons. In most cases,
            that write cache exists only in non-persistent memory. In
            the case of a loss of power, this data may never actually
            get committed to disk, resulting in discrepancies that the
            underlying file system must handle.</para>
        <para>OpenStack Object Storage works best on the XFS file
            system, and this document assumes that the hardware being
            used is configured appropriately to be mounted with the
                <command>nobarriers</command> option. For more
            information, refer to the XFS FAQ: <link
                xlink:href="http://xfs.org/index.php/XFS_FAQ"
                >http://xfs.org/index.php/XFS_FAQ</link>
        </para>
        <para>To get the most out of your hardware, it is essential
            that every disk used in OpenStack Object Storage is
            configured as a standalone, individual RAID 0 disk; in the
            case of 6 disks, you would have six RAID 0s or one JBOD.
            Some RAID controllers do not support JBOD or do not
            support battery backed cache with JBOD. To ensure the
            integrity of your data, you must ensure that the
            individual drive caches are disabled and the battery
            backed cache in your RAID card is configured and used.
            Failure to configure the controller properly in this case
            puts data at risk in the case of sudden loss of
            power.</para>
        <para>You can also use hybrid drives or similar options for
            battery backed up cache configurations without a RAID
            controller.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="object-storage-rate-limits">
        <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
        <title>Throttle resources through rate limits</title>
        <para>Rate limiting in OpenStack Object Storage is implemented
            as a pluggable middleware that you configure on the proxy
            server. Rate limiting is performed on requests that result
            in database writes to the account and container SQLite
            databases. It uses memcached and is dependent on the proxy
            servers having highly synchronized time. The rate limits
            are limited by the accuracy of the proxy server
            clocks.</para>
        <section xml:id="configuration-for-rate-limiting">
            <title>Configure rate limiting</title>
            <para>All configuration is optional. If no account or
                container limits are provided, no rate limiting
                occurs. Available configuration options
                include:</para>
            <xi:include
                href="../../common/tables/swift-proxy-server-filter-ratelimit.xml"/>
            <para>The container rate limits are linearly interpolated
                from the values given. A sample container rate
                limiting could be:</para>
            <para>container_ratelimit_100 = 100</para>
            <para>container_ratelimit_200 = 50</para>
            <para>container_ratelimit_500 = 20</para>
            <para>This would result in:</para>
            <table rules="all">
                <caption>Values for Rate Limiting with Sample
                    Configuration Settings</caption>
                <tbody>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Container Size</td>
                        <td>Rate Limit</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>0-99</td>
                        <td>No limiting</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>100</td>
                        <td>100</td>
                    </tr>

                    <tr>
                        <td>150</td>
                        <td>75</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>500</td>
                        <td>20</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>1000</td>
                        <td>20</td>
                    </tr>
                </tbody>
            </table>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="object-storage-healthcheck">
        <title>Health check</title>
        <para>Provides an easy way to monitor whether the Object Storage proxy server is alive. If
            you access the proxy with the path <filename>/healthcheck</filename>, it responds with
                <literal>OK</literal> in the response body, which monitoring tools can use.</para>
        <xi:include
            href="../../common/tables/swift-account-server-filter-healthcheck.xml"
        />
    </section>
    <section xml:id="object-storage-domain-remap">
        <title>Domain remap</title>
        <para>Middleware that translates container and account parts
            of a domain to path parameters that the proxy server
            understands.</para>
        <xi:include
            href="../../common/tables/swift-proxy-server-filter-domain_remap.xml"
        />
    </section>
    <section xml:id="object-storage-cname-lookup">
        <title>CNAME lookup</title>
        <para>Middleware that translates an unknown domain in the host
            header to something that ends with the configured
            <code>storage_domain</code> by looking up the given domain's CNAME
            record in DNS.</para>
        <xi:include
            href="../../common/tables/swift-proxy-server-filter-cname_lookup.xml"
        />
    </section>
    <section xml:id="object-storage-tempurl">
        <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
        <title>Temporary URL</title>
        <para>Allows the creation of URLs to provide temporary access to objects. For example, a
            website may wish to provide a link to download a large object in OpenStack Object
            Storage, but the Object Storage account has no public access. The website can generate a
            URL that provides GET access for a limited time to the resource. When the web browser
            user clicks on the link, the browser downloads the object directly from Object Storage,
            eliminating the need for the website to act as a proxy for the request. If the user
            shares the link with all his friends, or accidentally posts it on a forum, the direct
            access is limited to the expiration time set when the website created the link.</para>
        <para>A temporary URL is the typical URL associated with an
            object, with two additional query parameters:<variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><literal>temp_url_sig</literal></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A cryptographic signature</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><literal>temp_url_expires</literal></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>An expiration date, in Unix time</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist></para>
        <para>An example of a temporary
            URL:<programlisting>
    https://swift-cluster.example.com/v1/AUTH_a422b2-91f3-2f46-74b7-d7c9e8958f5d30/container/object?
    temp_url_sig=da39a3ee5e6b4b0d3255bfef95601890afd80709&amp;
    temp_url_expires=1323479485
</programlisting></para>
        <para>To create temporary URLs, first set the <literal>X-Account-Meta-Temp-URL-Key</literal>
            header on your Object Storage account to an arbitrary string. This string serves as a
            secret key. For example, to set a key of
                <literal>b3968d0207b54ece87cccc06515a89d4</literal> using the
                <command>swift</command> command-line tool:</para>
        <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>swift post -m "Temp-URL-Key:<replaceable>b3968d0207b54ece87cccc06515a89d4</replaceable>"</userinput></screen>
        <para>Next, generate an HMAC-SHA1 (RFC 2104) signature to
            specify:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Which HTTP method to allow (typically
                        <literal>GET</literal> or
                        <literal>PUT</literal>)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The expiry date as a Unix timestamp</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The full path to the object</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The secret key set as the
                        <literal>X-Account-Meta-Temp-URL-Key</literal></para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>Here is code generating the signature for a GET for 24
            hours on
            <code>/v1/AUTH_account/container/object</code>:</para>
        <programlisting language="python">import hmac
from hashlib import sha1
from time import time
method = 'GET'
duration_in_seconds = 60*60*24
expires = int(time() + duration_in_seconds)
path = '/v1/AUTH_a422b2-91f3-2f46-74b7-d7c9e8958f5d30/container/object'
key = 'mykey'
hmac_body = '%s\n%s\n%s' % (method, expires, path)
sig = hmac.new(key, hmac_body, sha1).hexdigest()
s = 'https://{host}/{path}?temp_url_sig={sig}&amp;temp_url_expires={expires}'
url = s.format(host='swift-cluster.example.com', path=path, sig=sig, expires=expires)</programlisting>
        <para>Any alteration of the resource path or query arguments
            results in a <errorcode>401</errorcode>
            <errortext>Unauthorized</errortext> error. Similarly, a
            PUT where GET was the allowed method returns a
                <errorcode>401</errorcode>. HEAD is allowed if GET or
            PUT is allowed. Using this in combination with browser
            form post translation middleware could also allow
            direct-from-browser uploads to specific locations in
            Object Storage.</para>
            <note>
                <para>Changing the
                        <literal>X-Account-Meta-Temp-URL-Key</literal>
                    invalidates any previously generated temporary
                    URLs within 60 seconds (the memcache time for the
                    key). Object Storage supports up to two keys, specified by
                        <literal>X-Account-Meta-Temp-URL-Key</literal>
                    and
                        <literal>X-Account-Meta-Temp-URL-Key-2</literal>.
                    Signatures are checked against both keys, if
                    present. This is to allow for key rotation without
                    invalidating all existing temporary URLs.</para>
            </note>
        <para>Object Storage includes a script called
                <command>swift-temp-url</command> that generates the
            query parameters automatically:</para>
        <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>bin/swift-temp-url GET 3600 /v1/AUTH_account/container/object mykey</userinput>
<computeroutput>/v1/AUTH_account/container/object?
temp_url_sig=5c4cc8886f36a9d0919d708ade98bf0cc71c9e91&amp;
temp_url_expires=1374497657</computeroutput></screen>
        <para>Because this command only returns the path, you must
            prefix the Object Storage host name (for example,
                <literal>https://swift-cluster.example.com</literal>).</para>
        <para>With GET Temporary URLs, a
                <literal>Content-Disposition</literal> header is set
            on the response so that browsers interpret this as a file
            attachment to be saved. The file name chosen is based on
            the object name, but you can override this with a
                <literal>filename</literal> query parameter. The
            following example specifies a filename of <filename>My
                Test File.pdf</filename>:</para>
        <programlisting>https://swift-cluster.example.com/v1/AUTH_a422b2-91f3-2f46-74b7-d7c9e8958f5d30/container/object?
temp_url_sig=da39a3ee5e6b4b0d3255bfef95601890afd80709&amp;
temp_url_expires=1323479485&amp;
filename=My+Test+File.pdf</programlisting>
        <para>To enable Temporary URL functionality, edit
                <filename>/etc/swift/proxy-server.conf</filename> to
            add <literal>tempurl</literal> to the
                <literal>pipeline</literal> variable defined in the
                <literal>[pipeline:main]</literal> section. The
                <literal>tempurl</literal> entry should appear
            immediately before the authentication filters in the
            pipeline, such as <literal>authtoken</literal>,
                <literal>tempauth</literal> or
                <literal>keystoneauth</literal>. For
            example:<programlisting>[pipeline:main]
pipeline = pipeline = healthcheck cache <emphasis role="bold">tempurl</emphasis> authtoken keystoneauth proxy-server</programlisting></para>

        <xi:include
            href="../../common/tables/swift-proxy-server-filter-tempurl.xml"
        />
    </section>
    <section xml:id="object-storage-name-check">
        <title>Name check filter</title>
        <para>Name Check is a filter that disallows any paths that
            contain defined forbidden characters or that exceed a
            defined length.</para>
        <xi:include
            href="../../common/tables/swift-proxy-server-filter-name_check.xml"
        />
    </section>
    <section xml:id="object-storage-constraints">
        <title>Constraints</title>
        <para>To change the OpenStack Object Storage internal limits,
            update the values in the
                <literal>swift-constraints</literal> section in the
                <filename>swift.conf</filename> file. Use caution when
            you update these values because they affect the
            performance in the entire cluster.</para>
        <xi:include
            href="../../common/tables/swift-swift-swift-constraints.xml"
        />
    </section>
    <section xml:id="object-storage-dispersion">
        <title>Cluster health</title>
        <para>Use the <command>swift-dispersion-report</command> tool
            to measure overall cluster health. This tool checks if a
            set of deliberately distributed containers and objects are
            currently in their proper places within the cluster. For
            instance, a common deployment has three replicas of each
            object. The health of that object can be measured by
            checking if each replica is in its proper place. If only 2
            of the 3 is in place the object’s health can be said to be
            at 66.66%, where 100% would be perfect. A single object’s
            health, especially an older object, usually reflects the
            health of that entire partition the object is in. If you
            make enough objects on a distinct percentage of the
            partitions in the cluster,you get a good estimate of the
            overall cluster health. In practice, about 1% partition
            coverage seems to balance well between accuracy and the
            amount of time it takes to gather results. The first thing
            that needs to be done to provide this health value is
            create a new account solely for this usage. Next, you need
            to place the containers and objects throughout the system
            so that they are on distinct partitions. The
            <command>swift-dispersion-populate</command> tool does this
            by making up
            random container and object names until they fall on
            distinct partitions. Last, and repeatedly for the life of
            the cluster, you must run the
                <command>swift-dispersion-report</command> tool to
            check the health of each of these containers and objects.
            These tools need direct access to the entire cluster and
            to the ring files (installing them on a proxy server
            suffices). The
                <command>swift-dispersion-populate</command> and
                <command>swift-dispersion-report</command> commands
            both use the same configuration file,
                <filename>/etc/swift/dispersion.conf</filename>.
            Example <filename>dispersion.conf</filename> file:</para>
        <programlisting language="ini">
[dispersion]
auth_url = http://localhost:8080/auth/v1.0
auth_user = test:tester
auth_key = testing
</programlisting>
        <para>There are also configuration options for specifying the
            dispersion coverage, which defaults to 1%, retries,
            concurrency, and so on. However, the defaults are usually
            fine. Once the configuration is in place, run
                <command>swift-dispersion-populate</command> to
            populate the containers and objects throughout the
            cluster. Now that those containers and objects are in
            place, you can run
                <command>swift-dispersion-report</command> to get a
            dispersion report, or the overall health of the cluster.
            Here is an example of a cluster in perfect health:</para>
        <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>swift-dispersion-report</userinput>
<computeroutput>Queried 2621 containers for dispersion reporting, 19s, 0 retries
100.00% of container copies found (7863 of 7863)
Sample represents 1.00% of the container partition space

Queried 2619 objects for dispersion reporting, 7s, 0 retries
100.00% of object copies found (7857 of 7857)
Sample represents 1.00% of the object partition space
</computeroutput></screen>
        <para>Now, deliberately double the weight of a device in the
            object ring (with replication turned off) and re-run the
            dispersion report to show what impact that has:</para>
        <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>swift-ring-builder object.builder set_weight d0 200</userinput>
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>swift-ring-builder object.builder rebalance</userinput>
...
<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>swift-dispersion-report</userinput>
<computeroutput>Queried 2621 containers for dispersion reporting, 8s, 0 retries
100.00% of container copies found (7863 of 7863)
Sample represents 1.00% of the container partition space

Queried 2619 objects for dispersion reporting, 7s, 0 retries
There were 1763 partitions missing one copy.
77.56% of object copies found (6094 of 7857)
Sample represents 1.00% of the object partition space
</computeroutput></screen>
        <para>You can see the health of the objects in the cluster has
            gone down significantly. Of course, this test environment
            has just four devices, in a production environment with
            many devices the impact of one device change is much less.
            Next, run the replicators to get everything put back into
            place and then rerun the dispersion report:</para>
        <programlisting>
... start object replicators and monitor logs until they're caught up ...
$ swift-dispersion-report
Queried 2621 containers for dispersion reporting, 17s, 0 retries
100.00% of container copies found (7863 of 7863)
Sample represents 1.00% of the container partition space

Queried 2619 objects for dispersion reporting, 7s, 0 retries
100.00% of object copies found (7857 of 7857)
Sample represents 1.00% of the object partition space
</programlisting>
        <para>Alternatively, the dispersion report can also be output
            in json format. This allows it to be more easily consumed
            by third-party utilities:</para>
        <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>swift-dispersion-report -j</userinput>
<computeroutput>{"object": {"retries:": 0, "missing_two": 0, "copies_found": 7863, "missing_one": 0,
"copies_expected": 7863, "pct_found": 100.0, "overlapping": 0, "missing_all": 0}, "container":
{"retries:": 0, "missing_two": 0, "copies_found": 12534, "missing_one": 0, "copies_expected":
12534, "pct_found": 100.0, "overlapping": 15, "missing_all": 0}}</computeroutput></screen>
        <xi:include
            href="../../common/tables/swift-dispersion-dispersion.xml"
        />
    </section>
    <section xml:id="object-storage-slo">
        <!-- Usage documented in http://docs.openstack.org/developer/swift/overview_large_objects.html -->
        <title>Static Large Object (SLO) support</title>
        <para>This feature is very similar to Dynamic Large Object
            (DLO) support in that it enables the user to upload many
            objects concurrently and afterwards download them as a
            single object. It is different in that it does not rely on
            eventually consistent container listings to do so.
            Instead, a user-defined manifest of the object segments is
            used.</para>
        <xi:include
            href="../../common/tables/swift-proxy-server-filter-slo.xml"
        />
    </section>
    <section xml:id="object-storage-container-quotas">
        <title>Container quotas</title>
        <para>The <code>container_quotas</code> middleware implements simple quotas that can be
            imposed on Object Storage containers by a user with the ability to set container
            metadata, most likely the account administrator. This can be useful for limiting the
            scope of containers that are delegated to non-admin users, exposed to formpost uploads,
            or just as a self-imposed sanity check.</para>
        <para>Any object PUT operations that exceed these quotas
            return a 413 response (request entity too large) with a
            descriptive body.</para>
        <para>Quotas are subject to several limitations: eventual
            consistency, the timeliness of the cached container_info
            (60 second ttl by default), and it is unable to reject
            chunked transfer uploads that exceed the quota (though
            once the quota is exceeded, new chunked transfers are
            refused).</para>
        <para>Set quotas by adding meta values to the container. These
            values are validated when you set them:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>X-Container-Meta-Quota-Bytes: Maximum size of
                    the container, in bytes.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>X-Container-Meta-Quota-Count: Maximum object
                    count of the container.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <xi:include
            href="../../common/tables/swift-proxy-server-filter-container-quotas.xml"
        />
    </section>
    <section xml:id="object-storage-account-quotas">
        <title>Account quotas</title>
        <para>The <parameter>x-account-meta-quota-bytes</parameter>
            metadata entry must be requests (PUT, POST) if a given
            account quota (in bytes) is exceeded while DELETE requests
            are still allowed.</para>
        <para>The <parameter>x-account-meta-quota-bytes</parameter>
            metadata entry must be
            set to store and enable the quota. Write requests to this
            metadata entry are only permitted for resellers. There is
            no account quota limitation on a reseller account even if
            <parameter>x-account-meta-quota-bytes</parameter> is set.
        </para>
        <para>Any object PUT operations that exceed the quota return a
            413 response (request entity too large) with a descriptive
            body.</para>
        <para>The following command uses an admin account that own the
            Reseller role to set a quota on the test account:</para>
        <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>swift -A http://127.0.0.1:8080/auth/v1.0 -U admin:admin -K admin \
--os-storage-url=http://127.0.0.1:8080/v1/AUTH_test post -m quota-bytes:10000</userinput></screen>
        <para>Here is the stat listing of an account where quota has
            been set:</para>
        <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>swift -A http://127.0.0.1:8080/auth/v1.0 -U test:tester -K testing stat</userinput>
<computeroutput>Account: AUTH_test
Containers: 0
Objects: 0
Bytes: 0
Meta Quota-Bytes: 10000
X-Timestamp: 1374075958.37454
X-Trans-Id: tx602634cf478546a39b1be-0051e6bc7a</computeroutput></screen>
        <para>This command removes the account quota:</para>
        <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>swift -A http://127.0.0.1:8080/auth/v1.0 -U admin:admin -K admin --os-storage-url=http://127.0.0.1:8080/v1/AUTH_test post -m quota-bytes:</userinput></screen>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="object-storage-bulk-delete">
        <title>Bulk delete</title>
        <para>Use <code>bulk-delete</code> to delete multiple files
           from an account
            with a single request. Responds to DELETE requests with a
            header 'X-Bulk-Delete: true_value'. The body of the DELETE
            request is a new line-separated list of files to delete.
            The files listed must be URL encoded and in the
            form:</para>
        <programlisting>
    /container_name/obj_name
    </programlisting>
        <para>If all files are successfully deleted (or did not
        exist), the operation returns <code>HTTPOk</code>. If any
        files failed to delete, the operation returns
        <code>HTTPBadGateway</code>.  In both cases, the response body
        is a JSON dictionary that shows the number of files that were
        successfully deleted or not found. The files that failed are
        listed.</para>
        <xi:include
            href="../../common/tables/swift-proxy-server-filter-bulk.xml"
        />
    </section>
    <xi:include href="section_configure_s3.xml"/>
    <section xml:id="object-storage-drive-audit">
        <title>Drive audit</title>
        <para>The <option>swift-drive-audit</option> configuration
            items reference a script that can be run by using
                <command>cron</command> to watch for bad drives. If
            errors are detected, it unmounts the bad drive, so that
            OpenStack Object Storage can work around it. It takes the
            following options:</para>
        <xi:include
            href="../../common/tables/swift-drive-audit-drive-audit.xml"
        />
    </section>
    <section xml:id="object-storage-form-post">
        <title>Form post</title>
        <para>Middleware that provides the ability to upload objects
            to a cluster using an HTML form POST. The format of the
            form is:</para>
        <programlisting>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;form action="&lt;swift-url&gt;" method="POST"
      enctype="multipart/form-data"&gt;
  &lt;input type="hidden" name="redirect" value="&lt;redirect-url&gt;" /&gt;
  &lt;input type="hidden" name="max_file_size" value="&lt;bytes&gt;" /&gt;
  &lt;input type="hidden" name="max_file_count" value="&lt;count&gt;" /&gt;
  &lt;input type="hidden" name="expires" value="&lt;unix-timestamp&gt;" /&gt;
  &lt;input type="hidden" name="signature" value="&lt;hmac&gt;" /&gt;
  &lt;input type="file" name="file1" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;input type="submit" /&gt;
&lt;/form&gt;]]&gt;
</programlisting>
        <para>The <literal>swift-url</literal> is the URL to the Object Storage destination, such
            as: <uri>https://swift-cluster.example.com/v1/AUTH_account/container/object_prefix</uri>
            The name of each file uploaded is appended to the specified
            <literal>swift-url</literal>. So, you can upload directly to the root of container with
            a URL like: <uri>https://swift-cluster.example.com/v1/AUTH_account/container/</uri>
            Optionally, you can include an object prefix to better separate different users’
            uploads, such as:
                <uri>https://swift-cluster.example.com/v1/AUTH_account/container/object_prefix</uri>
        </para>
        <note>
            <para>The form method must be POST and the enctype must be
                set as <literal>multipart/form-data</literal>.</para>
        </note>
        <para>The redirect attribute is the URL to redirect the
            browser to after the upload completes. The URL has status
            and message query parameters added to it, indicating the
            HTTP status code for the upload (2xx is success) and a
            possible message for further information if there was an
            error (such as <literal>“max_file_size
            exceeded”</literal>).</para>
        <para>The <literal>max_file_size</literal> attribute must be
            included and indicates the largest single file upload that
            can be done, in bytes.</para>
        <para>The <literal>max_file_count</literal> attribute must be
            included and indicates the maximum number of files that
            can be uploaded with the form. Include additional
                <code>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;input type="file"
                name="filexx"/&gt;]]&gt;</code> attributes if
            desired.</para>
        <para>The expires attribute is the Unix timestamp before which
            the form must be submitted before it is
            invalidated.</para>
        <para>The signature attribute is the HMAC-SHA1 signature of
            the form. This sample Python code shows how to compute the
            signature:</para>
        <programlisting language="python">
import hmac
from hashlib import sha1
from time import time
path = '/v1/account/container/object_prefix'
redirect = 'https://myserver.com/some-page'
max_file_size = 104857600
max_file_count = 10
expires = int(time() + 600)
key = 'mykey'
hmac_body = '%s\n%s\n%s\n%s\n%s' % (path, redirect,
    max_file_size, max_file_count, expires)
signature = hmac.new(key, hmac_body, sha1).hexdigest()
</programlisting>
        <para>The key is the value of the
                <literal>X-Account-Meta-Temp-URL-Key</literal> header
            on the account.</para>
        <para>Be certain to use the full path, from the
                <literal>/v1/</literal> onward.</para>
        <para>The command-line tool
                <command>swift-form-signature</command> may be used
            (mostly just when testing) to compute expires and
            signature.</para>
        <para>The file attributes must appear after the other
            attributes to be processed correctly. If attributes come
            after the file, they are not sent with the sub-request
            because on the server side, all attributes in the file
            cannot be parsed unless the whole file is read into memory
            and the server does not have enough memory to service
            these requests. So, attributes that follow the file are
            ignored.</para>
        <xi:include
            href="../../common/tables/swift-proxy-server-filter-formpost.xml"
        />
    </section>
    <section xml:id="object-storage-static-web">
        <title>Static web sites</title>
        <para>When configured, this middleware serves container data
            as a static web site with index file and error file
            resolution and optional file listings. This mode is
            normally only active for anonymous requests.</para>
        <xi:include
            href="../../common/tables/swift-proxy-server-filter-staticweb.xml"
        />
    </section>
    <xi:include href="section_object-storage-cors.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="section_object-storage-listendpoints.xml"/>
</section>
