<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="swift-general-service-configuration">
    <title>Object Storage general service configuration</title>
    <para>
        Most Object Storage services fall into two categories, Object Storage's wsgi servers
        and background daemons.
   </para>
    <para>
        Object Storage uses paste.deploy to manage server configurations. Read more at <link xlink:href="http://pythonpaste.org/deploy/">http://pythonpaste.org/deploy/</link>.
   </para>
    <para>
        Default configuration options are set in the `[DEFAULT]` section,
        and any options specified there can be overridden in any of the
        other sections when the syntax <literal>set option_name = value</literal>
        is in place.</para>
    <para>
        Configuration for servers and daemons can be expressed together in
        the same file for each type of server, or separately. If a required
        section for the service trying to start is missing there will be an
        error. Sections not used by the service are ignored.
   </para>
    <para>
        Consider the example of an Object Storage node. By convention
        configuration for the <systemitem
        class="service">object-server</systemitem>, <systemitem
        class="service">object-updater</systemitem>, <systemitem
        class="service">object-replicator</systemitem>, and
        <systemitem class="service">object-auditor</systemitem> exist
        in a single file
        <filename>/etc/swift/object-server.conf</filename>:
   </para>
    <programlisting language="ini">
[DEFAULT]

[pipeline:main]
pipeline = object-server

[app:object-server]
use = egg:swift#object

[object-replicator]
reclaim_age = 259200

[object-updater]

[object-auditor]
</programlisting>
    <para>
        Object Storage services expect a configuration path as the first argument:
   </para>
    <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>swift-object-auditor</userinput>
<computeroutput>Usage: swift-object-auditor CONFIG [options]

Error: missing config path argument
</computeroutput></screen>
    <para>
        If you omit the object-auditor section, this file cannot be used
        as the configuration path when starting the
        <command>swift-object-auditor</command> daemon:
   </para>
    <screen><prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>swift-object-auditor /etc/swift/object-server.conf</userinput>
<computeroutput>Unable to find object-auditor config section in /etc/swift/object-server.conf
</computeroutput></screen>
    <para>
        If the configuration path is a directory instead of a file all of
        the files in the directory with the file extension &quot;.conf&quot;
        will be combined to generate the configuration object which is
        delivered to the Object Storage service. This is referred to generally as
        &quot;directory-based configuration&quot;.
   </para>
    <para>
        Directory-based configuration leverages ConfigParser's native
        multi-file support. Files ending in &quot;.conf&quot; in the given
        directory are parsed in lexicographical order. File names starting
        with '.' are ignored. A mixture of file and directory configuration
        paths is not supported - if the configuration path is a file, only
        that file will be parsed.
   </para>
    <para>
        The Object Storage service management tool
        <filename>swift-init</filename>
        has adopted the convention of looking for
        <filename>/etc/swift/{type}-server.conf.d/</filename> if the file
        <filename>/etc/swift/{type}-server.conf</filename> file does not
        exist.
   </para>
    <para>
        When using directory-based configuration, if the same option under
        the same section appears more than once in different files, the last
        value parsed is said to override previous occurrences. You can
        ensure proper override precedence by prefixing the files in the
        configuration directory with numerical values, as in the following
        example file layout:
   </para>
    <programlisting>
/etc/swift/
    default.base
    object-server.conf.d/
        000_default.conf -&gt; ../default.base
        001_default-override.conf
        010_server.conf
        020_replicator.conf
        030_updater.conf
        040_auditor.conf
</programlisting>
    <para>
        You can inspect the resulting combined configuration object using
        the <command>swift-config</command> command-line tool.
   </para>
   <para>All the services of an Object Store deployment share a common
       configuration in the <literal>[swift-hash]</literal> section of the
       <filename>/etc/swift/swift.conf</filename> file. The
       <option>swift_hash_path_suffix</option> and
       <option>swift_hash_path_prefix</option> values must be identical on all
       the nodes.</para>
   <xi:include href="../../common/tables/swift-swift-swift-hash.xml"/>
</section>
