<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="nova_cli_evacuate">
    <title>Instance evacuation</title>
    <para>As cloud administrator, while you are managing your cloud, you
        may get to the point where one of the cloud compute nodes fails.
        For example, due to hardware malfunction.
        At that point you may use server evacuation in order to make managed
        instances available again.
    </para>

    <section xml:id="evacuation_procedure">
        <title>Before Evacuation</title>

        <para>
            With the information about instance configuration, like if
            it is running on shared storage, you can choose the required
            evacuation parameters for your case. Use the
            <command>nova host-list</command>
            command to list the hosts and find new host for the evacuated
            instance.
            In order to preserve user data on server disk, target host has to
            have preconfigured shared storage with down host.
            As well, you have to validate that the current vm host is down.
            Otherwise the evacuation will fail with error.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="evacuate_shared">
        <title>To evacuate your server without shared storage:</title>
        <para>
            <command>nova evacuate</command>
            performs an instance evacuation from down host to specified
            host. The instance will be booted from a new disk,
            but will preserve the configuration, e.g. id, name, uid, ip...etc.
            New instance password can be passed to the command using the <literal>--password &lt;pwd&gt;</literal> option.
            If not given it will be generated and printed after the command finishes successfully.
        </para>
        <programlisting language="bash" role="gutter: false">
            <prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>nova evacuate <replaceable>evacuated_server_name</replaceable> <replaceable>host_b</replaceable></userinput>
        </programlisting>
        <para>
            The command returns a new server password.
            <informalexample>
                <screen>
                    <computeroutput><?db-font-size 70%?>
+-----------+--------------+
| Property  |    Value     |
+-----------+--------------+
| adminPass | kRAJpErnT4xZ |
+-----------+--------------+
                    </computeroutput>
                </screen>
            </informalexample>
        </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="evacuate_non_shared">
        <title>Evacuate server to specified host and preserve user data</title>
        <para>
            In order to preserve the user disk data on the evacuated
            server the OpenStack Compute should be deployed with shared
            filesystem.
            Refer to the shared storage section in the
            <link xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/trunk/openstack-compute/admin/content/configuring-migrations.html">Configure migrations guide</link>
            in order to configure your system. In this scenario the password will remain unchanged.
        </para>
        <programlisting language="bash" role="gutter: false">
            <prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>nova evacuate <replaceable>evacuated_server_name</replaceable> <replaceable>host_b</replaceable> --on-shared-storage</userinput>
        </programlisting>
    </section>
</section>
