<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
xml:id="vmware">
  <title>VMware vSphere</title>
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
  <section xml:id="vmware-intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>OpenStack Compute supports the VMware vSphere product family. This section
      describes the additional configuration required to launch VMWare-based
      virtual machine images.  vSphere versions 4.1 and greater are supported.</para>
    <para>There are two OpenStack Compute drivers that can be used with vSphere:</para>  
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>vmwareapi.VMwareVCDriver: a driver that lets nova-compute 
      communicte with a VMware vCenter server managing a cluster of ESX hosts.  With
      this driver and access to shared storage, advanced vSphere features like 
      vMotion, High Availability, and Dynamic Resource Scheduling (DRS) are availabile.
      With this driver, one nova-compute service is run per vCenter cluster. 
      </para></listitem> 
      <listitem><para>vmwareapi.VMwareESXDriver: a driver that lets nova-compute
      communicate directly to an ESX host, but does not support advanced VMware
      features.  With this driver, one nova-compute service is run per ESX host.
      </para></listitem> 
   </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="vmware-prereqs">
    <title>Prerequisites</title>
    <para>You will need to install the following software installed on each 
	nova-compute node:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>python-suds: This software is needed by the nova-compute service to
	communicate with vSphere APIs. If not installed, the "nova-compute" service 
	shuts down with the message: "Unable to import suds".</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
	<para>Tomcat server: This is required to serve up a local version of 
	the vSphere WSDL file (see below).</para></listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>On ubuntu, these packages can be installed by running:</para>
<screen>sudo apt-get install python-suds tomcat6 </screen>
  <para>Next, download the the SDK from <link xlink:href="http://www.vmware.com/support/developer/vc-sdk/">http://www.vmware.com/support/developer/vc-sdk/</link> and copy it into 
 <filename>/var/lib/tomcat6/webapps</filename>. You should ensure that the WSDL is available, in eg <filename> /var/lib/tomcat6/webapps/vmware/SDK/wsdl/vim25/vimService.wsdl</filename>.  Below we will point nova.conf to fetch this WSDL
file from Tomcat using a URL pointing to localhost.</para>
  </section>

<section xml:id="VMWareVCDriver_details">
<title>Using the VMwareVCDriver</title> 
<para>This section covers details of using the VMwareVCDriver.</para> 
<section xml:id="VMWareVCDriver_configuration_options">
    <title>VMWareVCDriver configuration options</title>
<para>When using the VMwareVCDriver (i.e., vCenter) with OpenStack Compute, 
nova.conf must include the following VMWare-specific config options:
</para>

<programlisting>vmwareapi_host_ip=&lt;vCenter host IP&gt;
vmwareapi_host_username=&lt; vCenter username&gt;
vmwareapi_host_password=&lt; vCenter password&gt;
vmwareapi_cluster_name=&lt; vCenter cluster name&gt;
vmwareapi_wsdl_loc=http://127.0.0.1:8080/vmware/SDK/wsdl/vim25/vimService.wsdl
</programlisting>
<para>Remember that you will have only one nova-compute service per cluster. 
It is recommended that this host run as a VM with high-availability enabled as
part of that same cluster.</para>
<para>Also note that many of the nova.conf options mentioned elsewhere in this
document that are relevant to libvirt do not apply to using this driver.</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="VMwareVCDriver_limitations">
<title>Requirements + Limitations</title> 
<para>The VMwareVCDriver is new in Grizzly, and as a result there are 
some important deployment requirements and limitations to be aware of.  
In many cases, these items will be addressed in future releases.</para> 
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>Each cluster can only be configured with a single Datastore.  If multiple
	Datastores are configured, the first one returned via the vSphere API will be
	used.  
	</para>
    </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>Because a single nova-compute is used per cluster, the nova-scheduler
         views this as a single host with resources amounting to the aggregate 
	resources of all ESX hosts managed by the cluster.  This may result in 
	unexpected behavior depending on your choice of scheduler.
	</para>
    </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>Security Groups are not supported if Nova-Network is used.  
         Security Groups are only supported if the VMware driver is used 
	in conjunction with the 
	the OpenStack Networking Service running the Nicira NVP plugin.  
	</para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
</section> 
</section>  

<section xml:id="VMWareESXDriver_details">
<title>Using the VMwareESXDriver</title> 
<para>This section covers details of using the VMwareESXDriver.</para> 
<section xml:id="VMWareESXDriver_configuration_options">
    <title>VMWareESXDriver configuration options</title>
<para>When using the VMwareESXDriver (i.e., no vCenter) with OpenStack Compute, 
configure nova.conf with the following VMWare-specific config options:
</para>

<programlisting>vmwareapi_host_ip=&lt;ESXi host IP&gt;
vmwareapi_host_username=&lt; ESXi host username&gt;
vmwareapi_host_password=&lt; ESXi host password&gt;
vmwareapi_wsdl_loc=http://127.0.0.1:8080/vmware/SDK/wsdl/vim25/vimService.wsdl
</programlisting>
<para>Remember that you will have one nova-compute service per ESXi host. 
It is recommended that this host run as a VM on the same ESXi host it is 
managing.</para> 
<para>Also note that many of the nova.conf options mentioned elsewhere in this
document that are relevant to libvirt do not apply to using this driver.</para>
</section> 
<section xml:id="VMwareESXDriver_limitations">
<title>Requirements + Limitations</title> 
<para>The ESXDriver is unable to take advantage of many of the advanced capabilities
associated with the vSphere platform, namely vMotion, High Availability, and 
Dynamic Resource Scheduler (DRS).</para> 
</section> 
</section>

<section xml:id="VMWare_images">
<title>Images with VMware vSphere</title> 
<para>When using either VMware driver, images should be uploaded to the OpenStack
Image Service in the VMDK format.  For example:</para> 
<screen>glance add name="ubuntuLTS" disk_format=vmdk container_format=ovf \
is_public=true vmware_adaptertype="lsiLogic" vmware_disktype="preallocated" \
vmware_ostype="ubuntu64Guest" &lt; ubuntuLTS-flat.vmdk </screen>
</section>

<section xml:id="VMWare_networking">
<title>Networking with VMware vSphere</title> 
   <para>The VMware driver support networking with both Nova-Network and the 
	Openstack Networking Service.</para> 
   <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>If using nova-network with the FlatManager or FlatDHCPManager, before
	provisioning VMs, create a port group with the same name as the 
	'flat_network_bridge' value in nova.conf (default is 'br100').  All VM NICs
	will be attached to this port group.</para> 
    </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>If using nova-network with the VlanManager, before provisioning VMs, 
	make sure the 'vmwareapi_vlan_interface' configuration option is set to match
        the ESX host interface that will handle VLAN-tagged VM traffic.
        OpenStack Compute will automatically create the corresponding port
	groups.</para> 
    </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>If using the OpenStack Networking Service, before provisining VMs, 
       create a port group with the same name as the 'vmware.integration_bridge' 
       value in nova.conf (default is 'br-int').  All VM NICs will be attached to this
       port group for management by the OpenStack Networking Plugin.</para>   
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
</section>

<section xml:id="VMWare_volumes">
<title>Volumes with VMware vSphere</title> 
<para>The VMware driver has limited support for attaching Volumes from the 
OpenStack Block Storage service, supporting attachments only if the volume
driver type is 'iscsi'.  There is no support for volumes based on vCenter Datastores
in this release.</para> 
</section>
</section>

