<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="user-requirements-network-focus">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>User requirements</title>
    <para>Network-focused architectures vary from the general-purpose
      architecture designs. Certain network-intensive applications influence
      these architectures. Some of the business requirements that influence
      the design include:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Network latency through slow page loads, degraded video
              streams, and low quality VoIP sessions impacts the user
              experience. Users are often not aware of how network design and
              architecture affects their experiences. Both enterprise customers
              and end-users rely on the network for delivery of an application.
              Network performance problems can result in a negative experience
              for the end-user, as well as productivity and economic loss.
           </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Regulatory requirements: Consider regulatory
              requirements about the physical location of data as it traverses
              the network. In addition, maintain network segregation of private
              data flows while ensuring an encrypted network between cloud
              locations where required. Regulatory requirements for encryption
              and protection of data in flight affect network architectures as
              the data moves through various networks.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Many jurisdictions have legislative and regulatory requirements
      governing the storage and management of data in cloud environments.
      Common areas of regulation include:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Data retention policies ensuring storage of persistent data
              and records management to meet data archival requirements.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Data ownership policies governing the possession and
              responsibility for data.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Data sovereignty policies governing the storage of data in
              foreign countries or otherwise separate jurisdictions.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Data compliance policies govern where information can and
              cannot reside in certain locations.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Examples of such legal frameworks include the data protection
      framework of the European Union
      (<link xlink:href="http://ec.europa.eu/justice/data-protection/">http://ec.europa.eu/justice/data-protection/</link>)
      and the requirements of the Financial Industry Regulatory Authority
      (<link xlink:href="http://www.finra.org/Industry/Regulation/FINRARules">http://www.finra.org/Industry/Regulation/FINRARules</link>)
      in the United States. Consult a local regulatory body for more
      information.</para>
    <section xml:id="high-availability-issues-network-focus">
      <title>High availability issues</title>
      <para>Depending on the application and use case, network-intensive
        OpenStack installations can have high availability requirements.
        Financial transaction systems have a much higher requirement for high
        availability than a development application. Use network availability
        technologies, for example quality of service (QoS), to improve the
        network performance of sensitive applications such as VoIP and video
        streaming.</para>
      <para>High performance systems have SLA requirements for a minimum
        QoS with regard to guaranteed uptime, latency, and bandwidth. The level
        of the SLA can have a significant impact on the network architecture and
        requirements for redundancy in the systems.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="risks-network-focus">
      <title>Risks</title>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Network misconfigurations</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Configuring incorrect IP addresses, VLANs, and routers
              can cause outages to areas of the network or, in the worst-case
              scenario, the entire cloud infrastructure. Automate network
              configurations to minimize the opportunity for operator error
              as it can cause disruptive problems.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Capacity planning</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Cloud networks require management for capacity and growth
              over time. Capacity planning includes the purchase of network
              circuits and hardware that can potentially have lead times
              measured in months or years.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Network tuning</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Configure cloud networks to minimize link loss, packet loss,
              packet storms, broadcast storms, and loops.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Single Point Of Failure (SPOF)</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Consider high availability at the physical and environmental
              layers. If there is a single point of failure due to only one
              upstream link, or only one power supply, an outage can become
              unavoidable.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Complexity</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>An overly complex network design can be difficult to
              maintain and troubleshoot. While device-level configuration
              can ease maintenance concerns and automated tools can handle
              overlay networks, avoid or document non-traditional interconnects
              between functions and specialized hardware to prevent
              outages.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Non-standard features</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>There are additional risks that arise from configuring the
              cloud network to take advantage of vendor specific features.
              One example is multi-link aggregation (MLAG) used to provide
              redundancy at the aggregator switch level of the network. MLAG
              is not a standard and, as a result, each vendor has their own
              proprietary implementation of the feature. MLAG architectures
              are not interoperable across switch vendors, which leads to
              vendor lock-in, and can cause delays or inability when upgrading
              components.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="security-network-focus"><title>Security</title>
    <para>Users often overlook or add security after a design implementation.
      Consider security implications and requirements before designing the
      physical and logical network topologies. Make sure that the networks are
      properly segregated and traffic flows are going to the correct
      destinations without crossing through locations that are undesirable.
      Consider the following example factors:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Firewalls</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Overlay interconnects for joining separated tenant networks</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Routing through or avoiding specific networks</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>How networks attach to hypervisors can expose security
      vulnerabilities. To mitigate against exploiting hypervisor breakouts,
      separate networks from other systems and schedule instances for the
      network onto dedicated compute nodes. This prevents attackers
      from having access to the networks from a compromised instance.</para>
    </section>
</section>
