<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="operational-considerations-networking-focus">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Operational Considerations</title>
    <para>Network focused OpenStack clouds have a number of
        operational considerations that will influence the selected
        design. Topics including, but not limited to, dynamic routing
        of static routes, service level agreements, and ownership of
        user management all need to be considered.</para>
    <para>One of the first required decisions is the selection of a
        telecom company or transit provider. This is especially true
        if the network requirements include external or site-to-site
        network connectivity.</para>
    <para>Additional design decisions need to be made about monitoring
        and alarming. These can be an internal responsibility or the
        responsibility of the external provider. In the case of using
        an external provider, SLAs will likely apply. In addition,
        other operational considerations such as bandwidth, latency,
        and jitter can be part of a service level agreement.</para>
    <para>The ability to upgrade the infrastructure is another subject
        for consideration. As demand for network resources increase,
        operators will be required to add additional IP address blocks
        and add additional bandwidth capacity. Managing hardware and
        software life cycle events, for example upgrades,
        decommissioning, and outages while avoiding service
        interruptions for tenants, will also need to be
        considered.</para>
    <para>Maintainability will also need to be factored into the
        overall network design. This includes the ability to manage
        and maintain IP addresses as well as the use of overlay
        identifiers including VLAN tag IDs, GRE tunnel IDs, and MPLS
        tags. As an example, if all of the IP addresses have to be
        changed on a network, a process known as renumbering, then the
        design needs to support the ability to do so.</para>
    <para>Network focused applications themselves need to be addressed
        when concerning certain operational realities. For example,
        the impending exhaustion of IPv4 addresses, the migration to
        IPv6 and the utilization of private networks to segregate
        different types of traffic that an application receives or
        generates. In the case of IPv4 to IPv6 migrations,
        applications should follow best practices for storing IP
        addresses. It is further recommended to avoid relying on IPv4
        features that were not carried over to the IPv6 protocol or
        have differences in implementation.</para>
    <para>When using private networks to segregate traffic,
        applications should create private tenant networks for
        database and data storage network traffic, and utilize public
        networks for client-facing traffic. By segregating this
        traffic, quality of service and security decisions can be made
        to ensure that each network has the correct level of service
        that it requires.</para>
    <para>Finally, decisions must be made about the routing of network
        traffic. For some applications, a more complex policy
        framework for routing must be developed. The economic cost of
        transmitting traffic over expensive links versus cheaper
        links, in addition to bandwidth, latency, and jitter
        requirements, can be used to create a routing policy that will
        satisfy business requirements.</para>
    <para>How to respond to network events must also be taken into
        consideration. As an example, how load is transferred from one
        link to another during a failure scenario could be a factor in
        the design. If network capacity is not planned correctly,
        failover traffic could overwhelm other ports or network links
        and create a cascading failure scenario. In this case, traffic
        that fails over to one link overwhelms that link and then
        moves to the subsequent links until the all network traffic
        stops.</para>
</section>