<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="user-requirements-network-focus">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>User requirements</title>
    <para>Network focused architectures vary from the general purpose
        designs. They are heavily influenced by a specific subset of
        applications that interact with the network in a more
        impacting way. Some of the business requirements that will
        influence the design include:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>User experience: User experience is impacted by
                network latency through slow page loads, degraded
                video streams, and low quality VoIP sessions. Users
                are often not aware of how network design and
                architecture affects their experiences. Both
                enterprise customers and end-users rely on the network
                for delivery of an application. Network performance
                problems can provide a negative experience for the
                end-user, as well as productivity and economic loss.
           </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Regulatory requirements: Networks need to take into
                consideration any regulatory requirements about the
                physical location of data as it traverses the network.
                For example, Canadian medical records cannot pass
                outside of Canadian sovereign territory. Another
                network consideration is maintaining network
                segregation of private data flows and ensuring that
                the network between cloud locations is encrypted where
                required. Network architectures are affected by
                regulatory requirements for encryption and protection
                of data in flight as the data moves through various
                networks.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Many jurisdictions have legislative and regulatory
        requirements governing the storage and management of data in
        cloud environments. Common areas of regulation include:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Data retention policies ensuring storage of
                persistent data and records management to meet data
                archival requirements.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Data ownership policies governing the possession and
                responsibility for data.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Data sovereignty policies governing the storage of
                data in foreign countries or otherwise separate
                jurisdictions.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Data compliance policies governing where information
                needs to reside in certain locations due to regular
                issues and, more importantly, where it cannot reside
                in other locations for the same reason.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Examples of such legal frameworks include the data
        protection framework of the European Union (<link
        xlink:href="http://ec.europa.eu/justice/data-protection/">http://ec.europa.eu/justice/data-protection/</link>)
        and the requirements of the Financial Industry Regulatory
        Authority (<link
        xlink:href="http://www.finra.org/Industry/Regulation/FINRARules">http://www.finra.org/Industry/Regulation/FINRARules</link>)
        in the United States. Consult a local regulatory body for more
        information.</para>
    <section xml:id="high-availability-issues-network-focus">
      <title>High availability issues</title>
    <para>OpenStack installations with high demand on network
        resources have high availability requirements that are
        determined by the application and use case. Financial
        transaction systems will have a much higher requirement for
        high availability than a development application. Forms of
        network availability, for example quality of service (QoS),
        can be used to improve the network performance of sensitive
        applications, for example VoIP and video streaming.</para>
    <para>Often, high performance systems will have SLA requirements
        for a minimum QoS with regard to guaranteed uptime, latency
        and bandwidth. The level of the SLA can have a significant
        impact on the network architecture and requirements for
        redundancy in the systems.</para></section>
    <section xml:id="risks-network-focus">
      <title>Risks</title>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Network misconfigurations</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Configuring incorrect IP
                addresses, VLANs, and routes can cause outages to
                areas of the network or, in the worst-case scenario,
                the entire cloud infrastructure. Misconfigurations can
                cause disruptive problems and should be automated to
                minimize the opportunity for operator error.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Capacity planning</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Cloud networks need to be managed
                for capacity and growth over time. There is a risk
                that the network will not grow to support the
                workload. Capacity planning includes the purchase of
                network circuits and hardware that can potentially
                have lead times measured in months or more.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Network tuning</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Cloud networks need to be configured
                to minimize link loss, packet loss, packet storms,
                broadcast storms, and loops.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Single Point Of Failure (SPOF)</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>High availability
                must be taken into account even at the physical and
                environmental layers. If there is a single point of
                failure due to only one upstream link, or only one
                power supply, an outage becomes unavoidable.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Complexity</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>An overly complex network design becomes
                difficult to maintain and troubleshoot. While
                automated tools that handle overlay networks or device
                level configuration can mitigate this, non-traditional
                interconnects between functions and specialized
                hardware need to be well documented or avoided to
                prevent outages.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Non-standard features</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>There are additional risks
                that arise from configuring the cloud network to take
                advantage of vendor specific features. One example is
                multi-link aggregation (MLAG) that is being used to
                provide redundancy at the aggregator switch level of
                the network. MLAG is not a standard and, as a result,
                each vendor has their own proprietary implementation
                of the feature. MLAG architectures are not
                interoperable across switch vendors, which leads to
                vendor lock-in, and can cause delays or inability when
                upgrading components.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="security-network-focus"><title>Security</title>
    <para>Security is often overlooked or added after a design has
        been implemented. Consider security implications and
        requirements before designing the physical and logical network
        topologies. Some of the factors that need to be addressed
        include making sure the networks are properly segregated and
        traffic flows are going to the correct destinations without
        crossing through locations that are undesirable. Some examples
        of factors that need to be taken into consideration are:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Firewalls</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Overlay interconnects for joining separated tenant
                networks</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Routing through or avoiding specific networks</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Another security vulnerability that must be taken into
        account is how networks are attached to hypervisors. If a
        network must be separated from other systems at all costs, it
        may be necessary to schedule instances for that network onto
        dedicated compute nodes. This may also be done to mitigate
        against exploiting a hypervisor breakout allowing the attacker
        access to networks from a compromised instance.</para>
    </section>
</section>
