<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
  xml:id="bk000-under-construction">
  <title>Start Here</title>
  <chapter xml:id="under-construction"><title>OpenStack Training Guides Are Under Construction</title>
    <para>We need your help! This is a community driven project to provide the user group community
    access to OpenStack training materials. We cannot make this work without your help.</para>
  <para>There are few ways to get involved. The easiest way is to use the training guides. Look at
    the end of each section and you will see the Submit a Bug link. When you find something that can
    be improved or fixed, submit a bug by clicking on the link.</para>
  <para>If you want to get involved with the effort around OpenStack community training, read on,
    here are the options:</para>
  <para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <formalpara><title>Attending a user group using the training materials</title>
          <para>The OpenStack community training started at the SFBay OpenStack User Group. More
            information this user group and others using the training guides on the <link
              xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/OpenStackUserGroups">OpenStack User Groups
              page</link>.</para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
      <listitem>
          <formalpara><title>Teach / Lead a user group using the training materials</title>
          <para>Awesome! Your experience will not only give you more experience with OpenStack, but
            you will help some people find new jobs. We have put all the information about <link
              xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/OpenStackUserGroups/HowTo#Running_a_Hackathon"
              >How To Run An OpenStack Hackathon</link> here.</para></formalpara>
        </listitem>
      <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Helping to create the training pages</title>
          <para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>We are currently working on creating the Associate Training Guide. It is the
                    first of four training guides. We are using the <link
                      xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/grizzly/openstack-compute/install/apt/content/"
                      >Basic Install Guide docs</link> as the source for most of the material. The
                    basic idea is we link as much of the material from existing documentation so we
                    reuse and improve the existing docs. The topics in the Associate Training Guide
                    are in a bunch of KanBan story board cards. Each card in the story board
                    represents something that an Associate trainee needs to learn. But first things
                    first, you need to get some basic tools and accounts installed and configured
                    before you can really start.</para>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Getting Accounts and Tools:</emphasis> We can't do
                    this without operators and developers using and creating the content. Anyone can
                    contribute content. You will need the tools to get started. Go to the <link
                      xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/trunk/openstack-training/content/getting-tools-and-accounts.html"
                      >Getting Tools and Accounts</link> page.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Pick a Card:</emphasis> Once you have your tools ready
                    to go, you can assign some work to yourself. Go to the <link
                      xlink:href="https://trello.com/board/openstack-training/51d6e5fee37248fd5b003de9"
                      >Training Trello/KanBan storyboard</link> and assign a card / user story from
                    the Sprint Backlog to yourself. If you don't have a Trello account, no problem,
                    just create one. Email seanrob@yahoo-inc.com and you will have access.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">Create the Content:</emphasis> Each card / user story
                    from the KanBan story board will be a separate chunk of content you will add to
                    the openstack-manuals repository openstack-training sub-project. I created a
                    template file to explain the xi:include syntax. The <emphasis role="bold"
                      >user-story-includes-template.xml</emphasis> file is in the <emphasis
                      role="bold">openstack-manuals/openstack-training/</emphasis> directory. I also
                    assigned one of the cards <link
                      xlink:href="https://trello.com/c/n274jOdP/9-as-a-trainee-i-need-to-be-able-to-understand-how-to-install-ubuntu-12-04-or-13-04-in-later-versions"
                      >Install Ubuntu 12.04 LTS</link> to myself. I moved it from the Sprint board
                    to the Doing board. I then created a branch using Git. You will need to create
                    branch in order to create new material. If you don't know what a branch is, no
                    problem. Go to the <link
                      xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/trunk/openstack-training/content/operator-create-branch.html"
                      >Creating a Branch</link> page. Once my branch was created, I then opened my
                    XML editor Oxygen and opened the set file <emphasis role="bold"
                      >st-training-guides.xml</emphasis>. The XML structure follows the hierarchy
                    Set -> Book -> Chapter -> Section. The <emphasis role="bold"
                      >st-training-guides.xml</emphasis> file holds the set level. Notice the set
                    file uses xi:include statements to include the books. We want to open the
                    associate book. Open the associate book and you will see the chapter include
                    statements. These are the chapters that make up the Associate Training Guide
                    book. I wanted to add my new content from my assigned card <link
                      xlink:href="https://trello.com/c/n274jOdP/9-as-a-trainee-i-need-to-be-able-to-understand-how-to-install-ubuntu-12-04-or-13-04-in-later-versions"
                      >Install Ubuntu 12.04 LTS</link> to the <emphasis role="bold"
                      >bk001-ch003-asssociate-general.xml</emphasis> file. Look at the file to see
                    my example. Once I finished adding and editing, I  needed to merge the new
                    content. Review <link
                      xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/trunk/openstack-training/content/operator-create-branch.html"
                      >Creating a Branch</link> again for instructions on how to complete the branch
                    merge. Thats it!</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        <note>
          <para>Here are more details on commiting changes to OpenStack <link
                xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/trunk/openstack-training/content/operator-fix-documentation-bug.html"
                >fixing a documentation bug</link> , <link
                xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Gerrit_Workflow">Gerrit Workflow</link>,
                <link xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Documentation/HowTo">Documentation
                  HowTo</link> and , <link xlink:href="http://git-scm.com/doc">Git Documentation</link></para>
        </note>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>More details on the OpenStack Training project.</para>
  <para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><link xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Training-manuals">OpenStack Training
            Wiki</link> (describes the project in detail)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><link
            xlink:href="https://blueprints.launchpad.net/openstack-manuals/+spec/training-manuals"
            >OpenStack Training blueprint</link>(this is the key project page)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><link xlink:href="http://www.meetup.com/openstack/">Bi-Weekly SFBay Hackathon meetup
            page</link>(we discuss project details with all team members)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><link xlink:href="https://etherpad.openstack.org/sfbay-openstack">Bi-Weekly SFBay
            Hackathon Etherpad</link>(meetup notes)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><link xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Meetings/training-manuals">Core
            Training Weekly Meeting Agenda</link>(we review project action items here)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><link
            xlink:href="https://trello.com/board/openstack-training/51d6e5fee37248fd5b003de9"
            >Training Trello/KanBan storyboard</link>(we develop high level project action items
          here)</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </para>
  <para><link xlink:href="https://blueprints.launchpad.net/openstack-manuals/+filebug" xlink:show="new">Submit a bug. Enter the summary as "Training, " with a few words. Be descriptive as possible in the description field. Open the tag pull-down and enter training-manuals.</link>
  </para>
  </chapter>
</book>
