<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="operational-considerations-massive-scale">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Operational Considerations</title>
    <para>In order to run at massive scale, it is important to plan on
        the automation of as many of the operational processes as
        possible. Automation includes the configuration of
        provisioning, monitoring and alerting systems. Part of the
        automation process includes the capability to determine when
        human intervention is required and who should act. The
        objective is to increase the ratio of operational staff to
        running systems as much as possible to reduce maintenance
        costs. In a massively scaled environment, it is impossible for
        staff to give each system individual care.</para>
    <para>Configuration management tools such as Puppet or Chef allow
        operations staff to categorize systems into groups based on
        their role and thus create configurations and system states
        that are enforced through the provisioning system. Systems
        that fall out of the defined state due to errors or failures
        are quickly removed from the pool of active nodes and
        replaced.</para>
    <para>At large scale the resource cost of diagnosing individual
        systems that have failed is far greater than the cost of
        replacement. It is more economical to immediately replace the
        system with a new system that can be provisioned and
        configured automatically and quickly brought back into the
        pool of active nodes. By automating tasks that are labor
        intensive, repetitive, and critical to operations with
        automation, cloud operations teams are able to be managed more
        efficiently because fewer resources are needed for these
        babysitting tasks. Administrators are then free to tackle
        tasks that cannot be easily automated and have longer-term
        impacts on the business such as capacity planning.</para>
    <section xml:id="the-bleeding-edge"><title>The Bleeding Edge</title>
    <para>Running OpenStack at massive scale requires striking a
        balance between stability and features. For example, it might
        be tempting to run an older stable release branch of OpenStack
        to make deployments easier. However, when running at massive
        scale, known issues that may be of some concern or only have
        minimal impact in smaller deployments could become pain points
        at massive scale. If the issue is well known, in many cases,
        it may be resolved in more recent releases. The OpenStack
        community can help resolve any issues reported by the applying
        the collective expertise of the OpenStack developers.</para>
    <para>When issues crop up, the number of organizations running at
        a similar scale is a relatively tiny proportion of the
        OpenStack community, therefore it is important to share these
        issues with the community and be a vocal advocate for
        resolving them. Some issues only manifest when operating at
        large scale and the number of organizations able to duplicate
        and validate an issue is small, so it will be important to
        document and dedicate resources to their resolution.</para>
    <para>In some cases, the resolution to the problem is ultimately
        to deploy a more recent version of OpenStack. Alternatively,
        when the issue needs to be resolved in a production
        environment where rebuilding the entire environment is not an
        option, it is possible to deploy just the more recent separate
        underlying components required to resolve issues or gain
        significant performance improvements. At first glance, this
        could be perceived as potentially exposing the deployment to
        increased risk to and instability. However, in many cases it
        could be an issue that has not been discovered yet.</para>
    <para>It is advisable to cultivate a development and operations
        organization that is responsible for creating desired
        features, diagnose and resolve issues, and also build the
        infrastructure for large scale continuous integration tests
        and continuous deployment. This helps catch bugs early and
        make deployments quicker and less painful. In addition to
        development resources, the recruitment of experts in the
        fields of message queues, databases, distributed systems, and
        networking, cloud and storage is also advisable.</para></section>
    <section xml:id="growth-and-capacity-planning"><title>Growth and Capacity Planning</title>
    <para>An important consideration in running at massive scale is
        projecting growth and utilization trends to plan capital
        expenditures for the near and long term. Utilization metrics
        for compute, network, and storage as well as a historical
        record of these metrics are required. While securing major
        anchor tenants can lead to rapid jumps in the utilization
        rates of all resources, the steady adoption of the cloud
        inside an organizations or by public consumers in a public
        offering will also create a steady trend of increased
        utilization.</para></section>
    <section xml:id="skills-and-training"><title>Skills and Training</title>
    <para>Projecting growth for storage, networking, and compute is
        only one aspect of a growth plan for running OpenStack at
        massive scale. Growing and nurturing development and
        operational staff is an additional consideration. Sending team
        members to OpenStack conferences, meetup events, and
        encouraging active participation in the mailing lists and
        committees is a very important way to maintain skills and
        forge relationships in the community. A list of OpenStack
        training providers in the marketplace can be found here:
        http://www.openstack.org/marketplace/training/.</para>
    </section>
</section>