<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0"
    xml:id="user-requirements-massive-scale-overview">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>User Requirements</title>
    <para>More so than other scenarios, defining user requirements for
        a massively scalable OpenStack design architecture dictates
        approaching the design from two different, yet sometimes
        opposing, perspectives: the cloud user, and the cloud
        operator. The expectations and perceptions of the consumption
        and management of resources of a massively scalable OpenStack
        cloud from the user point of view is distinctly different from
        that of the cloud operator.</para>
    <para>Many jurisdictions have legislative and regulatory
        requirements governing the storage and management of data in
        cloud environments. Common areas of regulation include:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Data retention policies ensuring storage of
                persistent data and records management to meet data
                archival requirements.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Data ownership policies governing the possession and
                responsibility for data.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Data sovereignty policies governing the storage of
                data in foreign countries or otherwise separate
                jurisdictions.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Data compliance policies governing certain types of
                information needs to reside in certain locations due
                to regular issues and, more importantly, cannot reside
                in other locations for the same reason.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Examples of such legal frameworks include the data
        protection framework of the European Union
        (http://ec.europa.eu/justice/data-protection/ ) and the
        requirements of the Financial Industry Regulatory Authority
        (http://www.finra.org/Industry/Regulation/FINRARules/ ) in the
        United States. Consult a local regulatory body for more
        information.</para>
    <section xml:id="user-requirements-massive-scale"><title>User Requirements</title>
    <para>Massively scalable OpenStack clouds have the following user
        requirements:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>The cloud user expects repeatable, dependable, and
                deterministic processes for launching and deploying
                cloud resources. This could be delivered through a
                web-based interface or publicly available API
                endpoints. All appropriate options for requesting
                cloud resources need to be available through some type
                of user interface, a command-line interface (CLI), or
                API endpoints.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Cloud users expect a fully self-service and
                on-demand consumption model. When an OpenStack cloud
                reaches the "massively scalable" size, it means it is
                expected to be consumed "as a service" in each and
                every way.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>For a user of a massively scalable OpenStack public
                cloud, there will be no expectations for control over
                security, performance, or availability. Only SLAs
                related to uptime of API services are expected, and
                very basic SLAs expected of services offered. The user
                understands it is his or her responsibility to address
                these issues on their own. The exception to this
                expectation is the rare case of a massively scalable
                cloud infrastructure built for a private or government
                organization that has specific requirements.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>As might be expected, the cloud user requirements or
        expectations that determine the design are all focused on the
        consumption model. The user expects to be able to easily
        consume cloud resources in an automated and deterministic way,
        without any need for knowledge of the capacity, scalability,
        or other attributes of the cloud's underlying
        infrastructure.</para></section>
    <section xml:id="operator-requirements-massive-scale"><title>Operator Requirements</title>
    <para>Whereas the cloud user should be completely unaware of the
        underlying infrastructure of the cloud and its attributes, the
        operator must be able to build and support the infrastructure,
        as well as how it needs to operate at scale. This presents a
        very demanding set of requirements for building such a cloud
        from the operator's perspective:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>First and foremost, everything must be capable of
                automation. From the deployment of new hardware,
                compute hardware, storage hardware, or networking
                hardware, to the installation and configuration of the
                supporting software, everything must be capable of
                being automated. Manual processes will not suffice in
                a massively scalable OpenStack design
                architecture.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>The cloud operator requires that capital expenditure
                (CapEx) is minimized at all layers of the stack.
                Operators of massively scalable OpenStack clouds
                require the use of dependable commodity hardware and
                freely available open source software components to
                reduce deployment costs and operational expenses.
                Initiatives like OpenCompute (more information
                available at http://www.opencompute.org) provide
                additional information and pointers. To cut costs,
                many operators sacrifice redundancy. For example,
                redundant power supplies, redundant network
                connections, and redundant rack switches.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Companies operating a massively scalable OpenStack
                cloud also require that operational expenditures
                (OpEx) be minimized as much as possible. It is
                recommended that cloud-optimized hardware is a good
                approach when managing operational overhead. Some of
                the factors that need to be considered include power,
                cooling, and the physical design of the chassis. It is
                possible to customize the hardware and systems so they
                are optimized for this type of workload because of the
                scale of these implementations.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Massively scalable OpenStack clouds require
                extensive metering and monitoring functionality to
                maximize the operational efficiency by keeping the
                operator informed about the status and state of the
                infrastructure. This includes full scale metering of
                the hardware and software status. A corresponding
                framework of logging and alerting is also required to
                store and allow operations to act upon the metrics
                provided by the metering and monitoring solution(s).
                The cloud operator also needs a solution that uses the
                data provided by the metering and monitoring solution
                to provide capacity planning and capacity trending
                analysis.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>A massively scalable OpenStack cloud will be a
                multi-site cloud. Therefore, the user-operator
                requirements for a multi-site OpenStack architecture
                design are also applicable here. This includes various
                legal requirements for data storage, data placement,
                and data retention; other jurisdictional legal or
                compliance requirements; image
                consistency-availability; storage replication and
                availability (both block and file/object storage); and
                authentication, authorization, and auditing (AAA),
                just to name a few. Refer to the "Multi-Site" section
                for more details on requirements and considerations
                for multi-site OpenStack clouds.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Considerations around physical facilities such as
                space, floor weight, rack height and type,
                environmental considerations, power usage and power
                usage efficiency (PUE), and physical security must
                also be addressed by the design architecture of a
                massively scalable OpenStack cloud.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></section>
</section>