<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="arch-guide-intro-massive-scale">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>A massively scalable architecture is defined as a cloud
        implementation that is either a very large deployment, such as
        one that would be built by a commercial service provider, or
        one that has the capability to support user requests for large
        amounts of cloud resources. An example would be an
        infrastructure in which requests to service 500 instances or
        more at a time is not uncommon. In a massively scalable
        infrastructure, such a request is fulfilled without completely
        consuming all of the available cloud infrastructure resources.
        While the high capital cost of implementing such a cloud
        architecture makes it cost prohibitive and is only spearheaded
        by few organizations, many organizations are planning for
        massive scalability moving toward the future.</para>
    <para>A massively scalable OpenStack cloud design presents a
        unique set of challenges and considerations. For the most part
        it is similar to a general purpose cloud architecture, as it
        is built to address a non-specific range of potential use
        cases or functions. Typically, it is rare that massively
        scalable clouds are designed or specialized for particular
        workloads. Like the general purpose cloud, the massively
        scalable cloud is most often built as a platform for a variety
        of workloads. Massively scalable OpenStack clouds are
        generally built as commercial public cloud offerings since
        single private organizations rarely have the resources or need
        for this scale.</para>
    <para>Services provided by a massively scalable OpenStack cloud
        will include:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Virtual-machine disk image library</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Raw block storage</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>File or object storage</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Firewall functionality</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Load balancing functionality</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Private (non-routable) and public (floating) IP
                addresses</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Virtualized network topologies</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Software bundles</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Virtual compute resources</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Like a general purpose cloud, the instances deployed in a
        massively scalable OpenStack cloud will not necessarily use
        any specific aspect of the cloud offering (compute, network,
        or storage). As the cloud grows in scale, the scale of the
        number of workloads can cause stress on all of the cloud
        components. Additional stresses are introduced to supporting
        infrastructure including databases and message brokers. The
        architecture design for such a cloud must account for these
        performance pressures without negatively impacting user
        experience.</para>
</section>
