<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="ch004_book-introduction">
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
  <title>Introduction to OpenStack</title>
  <para>This guide provides security insight into OpenStack
    deployments. The intended audience is cloud architects, deployers,
    and administrators. In addition, cloud users will find the guide
    both educational and helpful in provider selection, while auditors
    will find it useful as a reference document to support their
    compliance certification efforts. This guide is also recommended
    for anyone interested in cloud security.</para>
  <para>Each OpenStack deployment embraces a wide variety of
    technologies, spanning Linux distributions, database systems,
    messaging queues, OpenStack components themselves, access control
    policies, logging services, security monitoring tools, and much
    more. It should come as no surprise that the security issues
    involved are equally diverse, and their in-depth analysis would
    require several guides. We strive to find a balance, providing
    enough context to understand OpenStack security issues and their
    handling, and provide external references for further information.
    The guide could be read from start to finish or sampled as
    necessary like a reference.</para>
  <para>We briefly introduce the kinds of clouds: private, public, and
    hybrid before presenting an overview of the OpenStack components
    and their related security concerns in the remainder of the
    chapter.</para>
  <section xml:id="ch004_book-introduction-idp117824">
    <title>Cloud types</title>
    <para>OpenStack is a key enabler in adoption of cloud technology
      and has several common deployment use cases. These are commonly
      known as Public, Private, and Hybrid models. The following
      sections use the National Institute of Standards and Technology
      (NIST) <link
        xlink:href="http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/nistpubs/800-145/SP800-145.pdf"
        >definition of cloud</link> to introduce these different types
      of cloud as they apply to OpenStack.</para>
    <section xml:id="ch004_book-introduction-idp119328">
      <title>Public cloud</title>
      <para>According to NIST, a public cloud is one in which the
        infrastructure is open to the general public for consumption.
        OpenStack public clouds are typically run by a service
        provider and can be consumed by individuals, corporations, or
        any paying customer. A public cloud provider may expose a full
        set of features such as software-defined networking, block
        storage, in addition to multiple instance types. Due to the
        nature of public clouds, they are exposed to a higher degree
        of risk. As a consumer of a public cloud you should validate
        that your selected provider has the necessary certifications,
        attestations, and other regulatory considerations. As a public
        cloud provider, depending on your target customers, you may be
        subject to one or more regulations. Additionally, even if not
        required to meet regulatory requirements, a provider should
        ensure tenant isolation as well as protecting management
        infrastructure from external attacks.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ch004_book-introduction-idp121488">
      <title>Private cloud</title>
      <para>At the opposite end of the spectrum is the private cloud.
        As NIST defines it, a private cloud is provisioned for
        exclusive use by a single organization comprising multiple
        consumers, such as business units. It may be owned, managed,
        and operated by the organization, a third-party, or some
        combination of them, and it may exist on or off premises.
        Private cloud use cases are diverse, as such, their individual
        security concerns vary.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ch004_book-introduction-idp123456">
      <title>Community cloud</title>
      <para>NIST defines a community cloud as one whose
        infrastructure is provisioned for the exclusive use by a
        specific community of consumers from organizations that have
        shared concerns. For example, mission, security requirements,
        policy, and compliance considerations. It may be owned,
        managed, and operated by one or more of the organizations in
        the community, a third-party, or some combination of them, and
        it may exist on or off premises.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ch004_book-introduction-idp125312">
      <title>Hybrid cloud</title>
      <para>A hybrid cloud is defined by NIST as a composition of two
        or more distinct cloud infrastructures, such as private, community, or
        public, that remain unique entities, but are bound together by
        standardized or proprietary technology that enables data and
        application portability, such as cloud bursting for load
        balancing between clouds. For example an online retailer may
        have their advertising and catalogue presented on a public
        cloud that allows for elastic provisioning. This would enable
        them to handle seasonal loads in a flexible, cost-effective
        fashion. Once a customer begins to process their order, they
        are transferred to the more secure private cloud backend that
        is PCI compliant.</para>
      <para>For the purposes of this document, we treat Community and
        Hybrid similarly, dealing explicitly only with the extremes of
        Public and Private clouds from a security perspective. Your
        security measures depend where your deployment falls upon the
        private public continuum.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ch004_book-introduction-idp128528">
    <title>OpenStack service overview</title>
    <para>OpenStack embraces a modular architecture to provide a set
      of core services that facilitates scalability and elasticity as
      core design tenets. This chapter briefly reviews OpenStack
      components, their use cases and security considerations.</para>
    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata contentdepth="374" contentwidth="976"
            fileref="static/marketecture-diagram.png" format="PNG"
            scalefit="1"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
            fileref="static/marketecture-diagram.png" format="PNG"
            scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject></para>
    <section xml:id="ch004_book-introduction-idp134736">
      <title>Compute</title>
      <para>OpenStack Compute service (nova) provides services to
        support the management of virtual machine instances at scale,
        instances that host multi-tiered applications, dev/test
        environments, "Big Data" crunching Hadoop clusters, and/or
        high performance computing.</para>
      <para>The Compute service facilitates this management through an
        abstraction layer that interfaces with supported hypervisors,
        which we address later on in more detail.</para>
      <para>Later in the guide, we focus generically on the
        virtualization stack as it relates to hypervisors.</para>
      <para>For information about the current state of feature
        support, see <link
          xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/HypervisorSupportMatrix"
          >OpenStack Hypervisor Support Matrix</link>.</para>
      <para>The security of Compute is critical for an OpenStack
        deployment. Hardening techniques should include support for
        strong instance isolation, secure communication between
        Compute sub-components, and resiliency of public-facing
          <glossterm>API</glossterm> endpoints.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ch004_book-introduction-idp138800">
      <title>Object Storage</title>
      <para>The OpenStack Object Storage service (swift) provides
        support for storing and retrieving arbitrary data in the
        cloud. The Object Storage service provides both a native API
        and an Amazon Web Services S3 compatible API. The service
        provides a high degree of resiliency through data replication
        and can handle petabytes of data.</para>
      <para>It is important to understand that object storage differs
        from traditional file system storage. It is best used for
        static data such as media files (MP3s, images, videos),
        virtual machine images, and backup files.</para>
      <para>Object security should focus on access control and
        encryption of data in transit and at rest. Other concerns may
        relate to system abuse, illegal or malicious content storage,
        and cross authentication attack vectors.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ch004_book-introduction-idp141536">
      <title>Block Storage</title>
      <para>The OpenStack Block Storage service (cinder) provides
        persistent block storage for compute instances. The Block
        Storage service is responsible for managing the life-cycle of
        block devices, from the creation and attachment of volumes to
        instances, to their release.</para>
      <para>Security considerations for block storage are similar to
        that of object storage.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ch004_book-introduction-idp143424">
      <title>OpenStack Networking</title>
      <para>The OpenStack Networking service (neutron, previously
        called quantum) provides various networking services to cloud
        users (tenants) such as IP address management,
          <glossterm>DNS</glossterm>, <glossterm>DHCP</glossterm>,
        load balancing, and security groups (network access rules,
        like firewall policies). It provides a framework for software
        defined networking (SDN) that allows for pluggable integration
        with various networking solutions.</para>
      <para>OpenStack Networking allows cloud tenants to manage their
        guest network configurations. Security concerns with the
        networking service include network traffic isolation,
        availability, integrity and confidentiality.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ch004_book-introduction-idp145600">
      <title>Dashboard</title>
      <para>The OpenStack dashboard (horizon) provides a
        web-based interface for both cloud administrators and cloud
        tenants. Through this interface administrators and tenants can
        provision, manage, and monitor cloud resources. Horizon is
        commonly deployed in a public facing manner with all the usual
        security concerns of public web portals.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ch004_book-introduction-idp147104">
      <title>Identity service</title>
      <para>The OpenStack Identity service (keystone) is a <emphasis
          role="bold">shared service</emphasis> that provides
        authentication and authorization services throughout the
        entire cloud infrastructure. The Identity service has
        pluggable support for multiple forms of authentication.</para>
      <para>Security concerns here pertain to trust in authentication,
        management of authorization tokens, and secure
        communication.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ch004_book-introduction-idp149712">
      <title>Image Service</title>
      <para>The OpenStack Image Service (glance) provides disk image
        management services. The Image Service provides image
        discovery, registration, and delivery services to the
        Compute service, as needed.</para>
      <para>Trusted processes for managing the life cycle of disk
        images are required, as are all the previously mentioned
        issues with respect to data security.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ch004_book-introduction-idp152400">
      <title>Other supporting technology</title>
      <para>OpenStack relies on messaging for internal communication
        between several of its services. By default, OpenStack uses
        message queues based on the Advanced Message Queue Protocol
        (<glossterm baseform="Advanced Message Queuing Protocol (AMQP)">AMQP
        </glossterm>). Similar to most OpenStack services, it supports
        pluggable components. Today the implementation backend could be
          <glossterm>RabbitMQ</glossterm>,
        <glossterm>Qpid</glossterm>, or
        <glossterm>ZeroMQ</glossterm>.</para>
      <para>As most management commands flow through the message
        queueing system, it is a primary security concern for any
        OpenStack deployment. Message queueing security is discussed
        in detail later in this guide.</para>
      <para>Several of the components use databases though it is not
        explicitly called out. Securing the access to the databases
        and their contents is yet another security concern, and
        consequently discussed in more detail later in this
        guide.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
