<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         version="5.0"
         xml:id="ch015_case-studies-management">
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Case studies: management interfaces</title>
    <para>Previously we discussed typical OpenStack management
    interfaces and associated backplane issues. We will now approach
    these issues by returning to our Alice and Bob case study.
    Specifically, we will look into how both Alice and Bob will
    address:</para>
    <itemizedlist><listitem>
        <para>Cloud administration</para>
      </listitem>
<listitem>
        <para>Self service</para>
      </listitem>
<listitem>
        <para>Data replication and recovery</para>
      </listitem>
<listitem>
        <para>SLA and security monitoring</para>
      </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
    <section xml:id="ch015_case-studies-management-idp48432">
      <title>Alice's private cloud</title>
      <para>When building her private cloud, while air-gapped, Alice still needs to consider her service management interfaces. Before deploying her private cloud, Alice has completed her system documentation. Specifically she has identified which OpenStack services will exist in each security domain. From there Alice has further restricted access to management interfaces by deploying a combination of IDS, SSL encryption, and physical network isolation. Additionally, Alice requires high availability and redundant services. Thus, Alice sets up redundant infrastructure for various OpenStack API services.</para>
      <para>Alice also needs to provide assurances that the physical servers and hypervisors have been built from a known secure state into a well-defined configuration. To enable this, Alice uses a combination of a Configuration Management platform to configure each machine according to the standards and regulations she must comply with. It will also enable Alice to report periodically on the state of her cloud and perform remediation to a known state should anything be out of the ordinary. Additionally, Alice provides hardware assurances by using a PXE system to build her nodes from a known set of base images. During the boot process, Alice provides further assurances by enabling Intel TXT and related trusted boot technologies provided by the hardware.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ch015_case-studies-management-idp51424">
      <title>Bob's public cloud</title>
      <para>As a public cloud provider, Bob is concerned with both the continuous availability of management interfaces and the security of transactions to the management interfaces. To that end Bob implements multiple redundant OpenStack API endpoints for the services his cloud will run. Additionally on the public network Bob uses SSL to encrypt all transactions between his customers and his cloud interfaces. To isolate his cloud operations Bob has physically isolated his management, instance migration, and storage networks.</para>
      <para>To ease scaling and reduce management overhead Bob implements a configuration management system. For customer data assurances, Bob offers a backup as a service product as requirements will vary between customers. Finally, Bob does not provide a "baremetal" or the ability to schedule an entire node, so to reduce management overhead and increase operational efficiency Bob does not implement any node boot time security.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
