<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         version="5.0"
         xml:id="ch028_case-studies-identity-management">
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Case studies: Identity management</title>
    <para>
      In this case study we discuss how Alice and Bob would address
      configuration of OpenStack core services. These include the
      Identity service, dashboard, and Compute services. Alice will be
      concerned with integration into the existing government
      directory services, while Bob will need to provide access to the
      public.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="ch028_case-studies-identity-management-idp87424">
      <title>Alice's private cloud</title>
      <para>
        Alice's enterprise has a well-established directory service
        with two-factor authentication for all users. She configures
        the Identity service to support an external authentication
        service supporting authentication with government-issued
        access cards. She also uses an external LDAP server to provide
        role information for the users that is integrated with the
        access control policy. Due to FedRAMP compliance requirements,
        Alice implements two-factor authentication on the management
        network for all administrator access.
      </para>
      <para>
        Alice also deploys the dashboard to manage many aspects of the
        cloud. She deploys the dashboard with HSTS to ensure that only
        HTTPS is used. The dashboard resides within an internal
        subdomain of the private network domain name system.
      </para>
      <para>
        Alice decides to use SPICE instead of VNC for the virtual
        console. She wants to take advantage of the emerging
        capabilities in SPICE.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ch028_case-studies-identity-management-idp131936">
      <title>Bob's public cloud</title>
      <para>
        Because Bob must support authentication for the general
        public, he decides to use use user name and password
        authentication. He has concerns about brute force attacks
        attempting to crack user passwords, so he also uses an
        external authentication extension that throttles the number of
        failed login attempts. Bob's management network is separate
        from the other networks within his cloud, but can be reached
        from his corporate network through ssh. As recommended
        earlier, Bob requires administrators to use two-factor
        authentication on the Management network to reduce the risk
        from compromised administrator passwords.</para>
      <para>Bob also deploys the dashboard to manage many aspects of
      the cloud. He deploys the dashboard with HSTS to ensure that
      only HTTPS is used. He has ensured that the dashboard is
      deployed on a second-level domain due to the limitations of the
      same-origin policy. He also disables
      <option>HORIZON_IMAGES_ALLOW_UPLOAD</option> to prevent resource
      exhaustion.</para>
      <para>Bob decides to use VNC for his virtual console for its
      maturity and security features.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
