<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         version="5.0"
         xml:id="ch026_compute">
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Compute</title>
    <para>The Compute service (nova) is one of the more complex OpenStack services. It runs in many locations throughout the cloud and interacts with a variety of internal services. For this reason, most of our recommendations regarding best practices for Compute service configuration are distributed throughout this book. We provide specific details in the sections on Management, API Endpoints, Messaging, and Database.</para>
    <section xml:id="ch026_compute-idp45072">
      <title>Virtual console selection</title>
      <para>One decision a cloud architect will need to make regarding
      Compute service configuration is whether to use <glossterm
      baseform="Virtual Network Computing (VNC)">VNC</glossterm> or
      <glossterm>SPICE</glossterm>. Below we provide some details on
      the differences between these options.</para>
      <section xml:id="ch026_compute-idp46336">
        <title>Virtual Network Computer (VNC)</title>
        <para>OpenStack can be configured to provide remote desktop console access to instances for tenants and/or administrators using the Virtual Network Computer (VNC) protocol.</para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="ch026_compute-idp48352">
        <title>Capabilities</title>
        <itemizedlist><listitem>
            <para>
              The OpenStack dashboard (horizon) can provide a VNC
              console for instances directly on the web page using the
              HTML5 noVNC client. This requires the <systemitem
              class="service">nova-novncproxy</systemitem> service to
              bridge from the public network to the management
              network.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The <command>nova</command> command-line utility can
            return a URL for the VNC console for access by the
            <systemitem class="service">nova</systemitem> Java VNC
            client. This requires the <systemitem
            class="service">nova-xvpvncproxy</systemitem> service to
            bridge from the public network to the management
            network.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="ch026_compute-idp51760">
        <title>Security considerations</title>
        <itemizedlist><listitem>
            <para>The <systemitem
            class="service">nova-novncproxy</systemitem> and
            <systemitem class="service">nova-xvpvncproxy</systemitem>
            services by default open public-facing ports that are
            token authenticated.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <!-- TODO - check if havana had this feature -->
            <para>By default, the remote desktop traffic is not encrypted. Havana is expected to have VNC connections secured by Kerberos.</para>
          </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="ch026_compute-idp54592">
        <title>References</title>
        <para><link xlink:href="http://blog.malchuk.ru/2013/05/21/47">Secure Connections to VNC ports</link></para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="ch026_compute-idp55824">
        <title>Simple Protocol for Independent Computing Environments (SPICE)</title>
        <para>As an alternative to VNC, OpenStack provides remote desktop access to guest virtual machines using the Simple Protocol for Independent Computing Environments (SPICE) protocol.</para>
        <section xml:id="ch026_compute-idp57120">
          <title>Capabilities</title>
          <itemizedlist><listitem>
              <para>
                SPICE is supported by the OpenStack dashboard
                (horizon) directly on the instance web page. This
                requires the <systemitem
                class="service">nova-spicehtml5proxy</systemitem>
                service.
              </para>
            </listitem>
<listitem>
              <para>The nova command-line utility can return a URL for SPICE console for access by a SPICE-html client.</para>
            </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="ch026_compute-idm4576">
          <title>Limitations</title>
          <itemizedlist><listitem>
              <para>Although SPICE has many advantages over VNC, the spice-html5 browser integration currently doesn't really allow admins to take advantage of any of the benefits. To take advantage of SPICE features like multi-monitor, USB pass through, etc. admins are recommended to use a standalone SPICE client within the Management Network.</para>
            </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="ch026_compute-idp83168">
          <title>Security considerations</title>
          <itemizedlist><listitem>
              <para>The <systemitem
              class="service">nova-spicehtml5proxy</systemitem>
              service by default opens public-facing ports that are
              token authenticated.</para>
            </listitem>
<listitem>
              <para>The functionality and integration are still evolving. We will access the features in the next release and make recommendations.</para>
            </listitem>
<listitem>
              <para>As is the case for VNC, at this time we recommend using SPICE from the management network in addition to limiting use to few individuals.</para>
            </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="ch026_compute-idp86912">
          <title>References</title>
          <para><link xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/trunk/config-reference/content/spice-console.html">SPICE Console</link></para>
          <para><link xlink:href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=913607">Red Hat bug 913607</link></para>
          <para><link xlink:href="http://openstack.redhat.com/forum/discussion/67/resolved-spice-support-in-rdo-grizzly/p1">SPICE support in RDO Grizzly</link></para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>
