<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="ch025_web-dashboard">
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
  <title>Dashboard</title>
  <para>Horizon is the OpenStack dashboard that provides users a self-service
    portal to provision their own resources within the limits set by
    administrators. These include provisioning users, defining instance flavors,
    uploading VM images, managing networks, setting up security groups, starting
    instances, and accessing the instances through a console.</para>
  <para>The dashboard is based on the Django web framework, therefore
    secure deployment practices for Django apply directly to horizon.
    This guide provides a popular set of Django security
    recommendations, further information can be found by reading the
      <link
      xlink:href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/1.5/#security"
      >Django deployment and security documentation</link>.</para>
  <para>The dashboard ships with reasonable default security settings,
    and has good <link
      xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/developer/horizon/topics/deployment.html"
      >deployment and configuration documentation</link>.</para>
  <section xml:id="ch025_web-dashboard-idp237648">
    <title>Basic web server configuration</title>
    <para>The dashboard should be deployed as a Web Services Gateway
      Interface (WSGI) application behind an HTTPS proxy such as
      Apache or nginx. If Apache is not already in use, we recommend
      nginx since it is lighter weight and easier to configure
      correctly.</para>
    <para>When using nginx, we recommend <link
        xlink:href="http://docs.gunicorn.org/en/latest/deploy.html"
        >gunicorn</link> as the wsgi host with an appropriate number
      of synchronous workers. We strongly advise against deployments
      using fastcgi, scgi, or uWSGI. We strongly advise against the
      use of synthetic performance benchmarks when choosing a wsgi
      server.</para>
    <para>When using Apache, we recommend <link
        xlink:href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/1.5/howto/deployment/wsgi/modwsgi/"
        >mod_wsgi</link> to host dashboard.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ch025_web-dashboard-idp240704">
    <title>HTTPS</title>
    <para>
      Deploy the dashboard behind a secure
      <glossterm>HTTPS</glossterm> server by using a valid, trusted
      certificate from a recognized certificate authority
      (CA). Private organization-issued certificates are only
      appropriate when the root of trust is pre-installed in all user
      browsers.</para>
    <para>Configure HTTP requests to the dashboard domain to redirect
      to the fully qualified HTTPS URL.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ch025_web-dashboard-idp242624">
    <title>HTTP Strict Transport Security (HSTS)</title>
    <para>It is highly recommended to use HTTP Strict Transport
    Security (HSTS).</para>
    <note>
      <para>If you are using an HTTPS proxy in front of your web
      server, rather than using an HTTP server with HTTPS
      functionality, follow the <link
        xlink:href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/1.5/ref/settings/#secure-proxy-ssl-header"
        >Django documentation on modifying the SECURE_PROXY_SSL_HEADER
        variable</link>.</para>
    </note>
    <para>See the chapter on PKI/SSL Everywhere for more specific
      recommendations and server configurations for HTTPS
      configurations, including the configuration of HSTS.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ch025_web-dashboard-idp245456">
    <title>Front end caching</title>
    <para>Since dashboard is rendering dynamic content passed directly
      from OpenStack API requests, we do not recommend front end
      caching layers such as varnish. In Django, static media is
      directly served from Apache or nginx and already benefits from
      web host caching.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ch025_web-dashboard-idp246880">
    <title>Domain names</title>
    <para>Many organizations typically deploy web applications at
      subdomains of an overarching organization domain. It is natural
      for users to expect a domain of the form
        <uri>openstack.example.org</uri>. In this context, there are
      often many other applications deployed in the same second-level
      namespace, often serving user-controlled content. This name
      structure is convenient and simplifies name server
      maintenance.</para>
    <para>We strongly recommend deploying horizon to a
        <emphasis>second-level domain</emphasis>, such as
        <uri>https://example.com</uri>, and advise against deploying
      horizon on a <emphasis>shared subdomain</emphasis> of any level,
      for example <uri>https://openstack.example.org</uri> or
        <uri>https://horizon.openstack.example.org</uri>. We also
      advise against deploying to bare internal domains like
        <uri>https://horizon/</uri>.</para>
    <para>This recommendation is based on the limitations browser
      same-origin-policy. The recommendations in this guide cannot
      effectively protect users against known attacks if dashboard is
      deployed on a domain which also hosts user-generated content,
      such as scripts, images, or uploads of any kind, even if the
      user-generated content is on a different subdomain. This
      approach is used by most major web presences, such as
      googleusercontent.com, fbcdn.com, github.io, and twimg.com, to
      ensure that user generated content stays separate from cookies
      and security tokens.</para>
    <para>Additionally, if you decline to follow this recommendation
      above about second-level domains, it is vital that you avoid the
      cookie backed session store and employ HTTP Strict Transport
      Security (HSTS). When deployed on a subdomain, dashboard's
      security is only as strong as the weakest application deployed
      on the same second-level domain.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ch025_web-dashboard-idp251760">
    <title>Static media</title>
    <para>Dashboard's static media should be deployed to a subdomain
      of the dashboard domain and served by the web server. The use of
      an external content delivery network (CDN) is also acceptable.
      This subdomain should not set cookies or serve user-provided
      content. The media should also be served with HTTPS.</para>
    <para>Django media settings are documented at <link
        xlink:href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/1.5/ref/settings/#static-root"
        >https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/1.5/ref/settings/#static-root</link>.</para>
    <para>Dashboard's default configuration uses <link
        xlink:href="http://django-compressor.readthedocs.org/"
        >django_compressor</link> to compress and minify css and
      JavaScript content before serving it. This process should be
      statically done before deploying dashboard, rather than using
      the default in-request dynamic compression and copying the
      resulting files along with deployed code or to the CDN server.
      Compression should be done in a non-production build
      environment. If this is not practical, we recommend disabling
      resource compression entirely. Online compression dependencies
      (less, nodejs) should not be installed on production
      machines.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ch025_web-dashboard-idp255696">
    <title>Secret key</title>
    <para>Dashboard depends on a shared SECRET_KEY setting for some
      security functions. It should be a randomly generated string at
      least 64 characters long. It must be shared across all active
      dashboard instances. Compromise of this key may allow a remote
      attacker to execute arbitrary code. Rotating this key
      invalidates existing user sessions and caching. Do not commit
      this key to public repositories.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ch025_web-dashboard-idp257248">
    <title>Session back-end</title>
    <para>Horizon's default session back-end
        (<emphasis>django.contrib.sessions.backends.signed_cookies</emphasis>)
      stores user data in <emphasis>signed</emphasis> but
        <emphasis>unencrypted </emphasis>cookies stored in the
      browser. This approach allows the most simple session backend
      scaling since each dashboard instance is stateless, but it comes
      at the cost of <emphasis>storing sensitive access tokens in the
        client browser</emphasis> and transmitting them with every
      request. This backend ensures that session data has not been
      tampered with, but the data itself is not encrypted other than
      the encryption provided by HTTPS.</para>
    <para>If your architecture allows it, we recommend using
        <emphasis>django.contrib.sessions.backends.cache</emphasis> as
      your session backend with memcache as the cache. Memcache must
      not be exposed publicly, and should communicate over a secured
      private channel. If you choose to use the signed cookies
      backend, refer to the Django documentation understand the
      security trade-offs.</para>
    <para>For further details, consult the <link
        xlink:href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/1.5/topics/http/sessions/#configuring-the-session-engine"
        >Django session backend documentation</link>.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ch025_web-dashboard-idp262288">
    <title>Allowed hosts</title>
    <para>Configure the ALLOWED_HOSTS setting with the domain or
      domains where the dashboard is available. Failure to configure this
      setting (especially if not following the recommendation above
      regarding second level domains) opens the dashboard to a number of
      serious attacks. Wild card domains should be avoided.</para>
    <para>For further details, see the <link
        xlink:href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/1.5/ref/settings/#allowed-hosts"
        >Django documentation on settings</link>.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ch025_web-dashboard-idp264272">
    <title>Cookies</title>
    <para>Session Cookies should be set to HTTPONLY:</para>
    <programlisting>SESSION_COOKIE_HTTPONLY = True</programlisting>
    <para>Never configure CSRF or session cookies to have a wild card
      domain with a leading dot. Horizon's session and CSRF cookie
      should be secured when deployed with HTTPS:</para>
    <programlisting>Code CSRF_COOKIE_SECURE = True
SESSION_COOKIE_SECURE = True</programlisting>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ch025_web-dashboard-idp266976">
    <title>Password auto complete</title>
    <para>We recommend that implementers do not change the default
      password auto complete behavior. Users choose stronger passwords
      in environments that allow them to use the secure browser
      password manager. Organizations which forbid the browser
      password manager should enforce this policy at the desktop
      level.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ch025_web-dashboard-idp268448">
    <title>Cross Site Request Forgery (CSRF)</title>
    <para>Django has a dedicated middleware for <link
        xlink:href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/1.5/ref/contrib/csrf/#how-it-works"
        >cross-site request forgery</link> (CSRF).</para>
    <para>Dashboard is designed to discourage developers from
      introducing cross-site scripting vulnerabilities with custom
      dashboards. However, it is important to audit custom dashboards,
      especially ones that are javascript-heavy for inappropriate use
      of the @csrf_exempt decorator. Dashboards which do not follow
      these recommended security settings should be carefully
      evaluated before restrictions are relaxed.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ch025_web-dashboard-idp270608">
    <title>Cross Site Scripting (XSS)</title>
    <para>Unlike many similar systems, OpenStack dashboard allows the
      entire Unicode character set in most fields. This means
      developers have less latitude to make escaping mistakes that
      open attack vectors for cross-site scripting (XSS).</para>
    <para>Dashboard provides tools for developers to avoid creating
      XSS vulnerabilities, but they only work if developers use them
      correctly. Audit any custom dashboards, paying particular
      attention to use of the mark_safe function, use of is_safe with
      custom template tags, the safe template tag, anywhere auto escape
      is turned off, and any JavaScript which might evaluate
      improperly escaped data.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ch025_web-dashboard-idp272832">
    <title>Cross Origin Resource Sharing (CORS)</title>
    <para>Configure your web server to send a restrictive CORS header
      with each response, allowing only the dashboard domain and
      protocol:</para>
    <programlisting>Access-Control-Allow-Origin: https://example.com/</programlisting>
    <para>Never allow the wild card origin.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ch025_web-dashboard-idp275056">
    <title>Horizon image upload</title>
    <para>We recommend that implementers <link
        xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/developer/horizon/topics/deployment.html#file-uploads"
        >disable HORIZON_IMAGES_ALLOW_UPLOAD</link> unless they have
      implemented a plan to prevent resource exhaustion and denial of
      service.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ch025_web-dashboard-idp276864">
    <title>Upgrading</title>
    <para>Django security releases are generally well tested and
      aggressively backwards compatible. In almost all cases, new
      major releases of Django are also fully backwards compatible
      with previous releases. Dashboard implementers are strongly
      encouraged to run the latest stable release of Django with
      up-to-date security releases.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ch025_web-dashboard-idp278672">
    <title>Debug</title>
    <para>Make sure DEBUG is set to False in production. In Django,
      DEBUG displays stack traces and sensitive web server state
      information on any exception.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
