<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         version="5.0"
         xml:id="ch022_case-studies-api-endpoints">
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Case studies: API endpoints</title>
    <para>In this case study we discuss how Alice and Bob would address endpoint configuration to secure their private and public clouds. Alice's cloud is not publicly accessible, but she is still concerned about securing the endpoints against improper use. Bob's cloud, being public, must take measures to reduce the risk of attacks by external adversaries.</para>
    <section xml:id="ch022_case-studies-api-endpoints-idp3824">
      <title>Alice's private cloud</title>
      <para>
        Alice's organization requires that the security architecture
        protect the access to the public and private endpoints, so she
        elects to use the Apache SSL proxy on both public and internal
        services. Alice's organization has implemented its own
        certificate authority. Alice contacts the PKI office in her
        agency that manages her PKI and certificate issuance. Alice
        obtains certificates issued by this CA and configures the
        services within both the public and management security
        domains to use these certificates. Since Alice's OpenStack
        deployment exists entirely on a disconnected from the Internet
        network, she makes sure to remove all default CA bundles that
        contain external public CA providers to ensure the OpenStack
        services only accept client certificates issued by her
        agency's CA. Alice has registered all of the services in the
        Identity service's catalog, using the internal URLs for access
        by internal services. She has installed host-based intrusion
        detection on all of the API endpoints.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ch022_case-studies-api-endpoints-idp6592">
      <title>Bob's public cloud</title>
      <para>
        Bob must also protect the access to the public and private
        endpoints, so he elects to use the Apache SSL proxy on both
        public and internal services. On the public services, he has
        configured the certificate key files with certificates signed
        by a well-known Certificate Authority. He has used his
        organization's self-signed CA to sign certificates in the
        internal services on the Management network. Bob has
        registered his services in the Identity service's catalog,
        using the internal URLs for access by internal services. Bob's
        public cloud runs services on SELinux, which he has configured
        with a mandatory access control policy to reduce the impact of
        any publicly accessible services that may be compromised. He
        has also configured the endpoints with a host-based IDS.
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
