<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="ch024_authentication">
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
  <title>Identity</title>
  <para>The OpenStack Identity service (keystone) supports multiple
    methods of authentication, including username &amp; password,
    LDAP, and external authentication methods. Upon successful
    authentication, The Identity Service provides the user with an
    authorization token used for subsequent service requests.</para>
  <para>Transport Layer Security TLS/SSL provides authentication
    between services and persons using X.509 certificates. Although
    the default mode for SSL is server-side only authentication,
    certificates may also be used for client authentication.</para>
  <section xml:id="ch024_authentication-idp195568">
    <title>Authentication</title>
    <section xml:id="ch024_authentication-idp196256">
      <title>Invalid login attempts</title>
      <para>The Identity Service does not provide a method to limit
        access to accounts after repeated unsuccessful login attempts.
        Repeated failed login attempts are likely brute-force attacks
        (Refer figure Attack-types). This is a more significant issue
        in Public clouds.</para>
      <para>Prevention is possible by using an external authentication
        system that blocks out an account after some configured number
        of failed login attempts. The account then may only be
        unlocked with further side-channel intervention.</para>
      <para>If prevention is not an option, detection can be used to
        mitigate damage.Detection involves frequent review of access
        control logs to identify unauthorized attempts to access
        accounts. Possible remediation would include reviewing the
        strength of the user password, or blocking the network source
        of the attack through firewall rules. Firewall rules on the
        keystone server that restrict the number of connections could
        be used to reduce the attack effectiveness, and thus dissuade
        the attacker.</para>
      <para>In addition, it is useful to examine account activity for
        unusual login times and suspicious actions, with possibly
        disable the account. Oftentimes this approach is taken by
        credit card providers for fraud detection and alert.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ch024_authentication-idp241008">
      <title>Multi-factor authentication</title>
      <para>Employ multi-factor authentication for network access to
        privileged user accounts. The Identity Service supports
        external authentication services through the Apache web server
        that can provide this functionality. Servers may also enforce
        client-side authentication using certificates.</para>
      <para>This recommendation provides insulation from brute force,
        social engineering, and both spear and mass phishing attacks
        that may compromise administrator passwords.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ch024_authentication-idp243184">
    <title>Authentication methods</title>
    <section xml:id="ch024_authentication-idp243824">
      <title>Internally implemented authentication methods</title>
      <para>The Identity Service can store user credentials in an SQL
        Database, or may use an LDAP-compliant directory server. The
        Identity database may be separate from databases used by other
        OpenStack services to reduce the risk of a compromise of the
        stored credentials.</para>
      <para>
        When you use a user name and password to authenticate,
        Identity does not enforce policies on password strength,
        expiration, or failed authentication attempts as recommended
        by NIST Special Publication 800-118 (draft).  Organizations
        that desire to enforce stronger password policies should
        consider using Identity extensions or external authentication
        services.</para>
      <para>LDAP simplifies integration of Identity authentication
        into an organization's existing directory service and user
        account management processes.</para>
      <para>Authentication and authorization policy in OpenStack may
        be delegated to an external LDAP server. A typical use case is
        an organization that seeks to deploy a private cloud and
        already has a database of employees, the users. This may be in
        an LDAP system. Using LDAP as a source of authority
        authentication, requests to Identity Service are delegated to
        the LDAP service, which will authorize or deny requests based
        on locally set policies. A token is generated on successful
        authentication.</para>
      <para>Note that if the LDAP system has attributes defined for
        the user such as admin, finance, HR etc, these must be mapped
        into roles and groups within Identity for use by the various
        OpenStack services. The <filename>/etc/keystone.conf</filename>
        file maps LDAP attributes to Identity attributes.</para>
      <para>The Identity Service <emphasis role="bold">MUST
          NOT</emphasis> be allowed to write to LDAP services used for
        authentication outside of the OpenStack deployment as this
        would allow a sufficiently privileged keystone user to make
        changes to the LDAP directory. This would allow privilege
        escalation within the wider organization or facilitate
        unauthorized access to other information and resources. In
        such a deployment, user provisioning would be out of the realm
        of the OpenStack deployment.</para>
      <note>
        <para>There is an <link
            xlink:href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/ossn/+bug/1168252"
            >OpenStack Security Note (OSSN) regarding keystone.conf
            permissions</link>.</para>
        <para>There is an <link
            xlink:href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/ossn/+bug/1155566"
            >OpenStack Security Note (OSSN) regarding potential DoS
            attacks</link>.</para>
      </note>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ch024_authentication-idp251520">
      <title>External authentication methods</title>
      <para>Organizations may desire to implement external
        authentication for compatibility with existing authentication
        services or to enforce stronger authentication policy
        requirements. Although passwords are the most common form of
        authentication, they can be compromised through numerous
        methods, including keystroke logging and password compromise.
        External authentication services can provide alternative forms
        of authentication that minimize the risk from weak
        passwords.</para>
      <para>These include:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Password policy enforcement: Requires user passwords
            to conform to minimum standards for length, diversity of
            characters, expiration, or failed login attempts.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Multi-factor authentication: The authentication
            service requires the user to provide information based on
            something they have, such as a one-time password token or
            X.509 certificate, and something they know, such as a
            password.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Kerberos</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ch024_authentication-idp256832">
    <title>Authorization</title>
    <para>The Identity Service supports the notion of groups and
      roles. Users belong to groups. A group has a list of roles.
      OpenStack services reference the roles of the user attempting to
      access the service. The OpenStack policy enforcer middleware
      takes into consideration the policy rule associated with each
      resource and the user's group/roles and tenant association to
      determine if he/she has access to the requested resource.</para>
    <para>The Policy enforcement middleware enables fine-grained
      access control to OpenStack resources. Only admin users can
      provision new users and have access to various management
      functionality. The cloud tenant would be able to only spin up
      instances, attach volumes, etc.</para>
    <section xml:id="ch024_authentication-idp259168">
      <title>Establish formal access control policies</title>
      <para>Prior to configuring roles, groups, and users, document
        your required access control policies for the OpenStack
        installation. The policies should be consistent with any
        regulatory or legal requirements for the organization. Future
        modifications to access control configuration should be done
        consistently with the formal policies. The policies should
        include the conditions and processes for creating, deleting,
        disabling, and enabling accounts, and for assigning privileges
        to the accounts. Periodically review the policies and ensure
        that configuration is in compliance with approved
        policies.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ch024_authentication-idp261600">
      <title>Service authorization</title>
      <para>As described in the <link
          xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/admin-guide-cloud/content/index.html"
            ><citetitle>OpenStack Cloud Administrator
            Guide</citetitle></link>, cloud administrators must define
        a user for each service, with a role of Admin. This service
        user account provides the service with the authorization to
        authenticate users.</para>
      <para>The Compute and Object Storage services can be configured
        to use either the "tempAuth" file or Identity Service to store
        authentication information. The "tempAuth" solution MUST NOT
        be deployed in a production environment since it stores
        passwords in plain text.</para>
      <para>The Identity Service supports client authentication for
        SSL which may be enabled. SSL client authentication provides
        an additional authentication factor, in addition to the
        username / password, that provides greater reliability on user
        identification. It reduces the risk of unauthorized access
        when user names and passwords may be compromised. However,
        there is additional administrative overhead and cost to issue
        certificates to users that may not be feasible in every
        deployment.</para>
      <note>
        <para>We recommend that you use client authentication with SSL
          for the authentication of services to the Identity
          Service.</para>
      </note>
      <para>The cloud administrator should protect sensitive
        configuration files for unauthorized modification. This can be
        achieved with mandatory access control frameworks such as
        SELinux, including <filename>/etc/keystone.conf</filename> and
        X.509 certificates.</para>

      <para>For client authentication with SSL, you need to issue
        certificates. These certificates can be signed by an external
        authority or by the cloud administrator. OpenStack services by
        default check the signatures of certificates and connections
        fail if the signature cannot be checked. If the administrator
        uses self-signed certificates, the check might need to be
        disabled. To disable these certificates, set
          <code>insecure=False</code> in the
          <code>[filter:authtoken]</code> section in the
          <filename>/etc/nova/api.paste.ini</filename> file. This
        setting also disables certificates for other
        components.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ch024_authentication-idp267040">
      <title>Administrative users</title>
      <para>We recommend that admin users authenticate using Identity
        Service and an external authentication service that supports
        2-factor authentication, such as a certificate. This reduces
        the risk from passwords that may be compromised. This
        recommendation is in compliance with NIST 800-53 IA-2(1)
        guidance in the use of multi factor authentication for network
        access to privileged accounts.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ch024_authentication-idp268960">
      <title>End users</title>
      <para>The Identity Service can directly provide end-user
        authentication, or can be configured to use external
        authentication methods to conform to an organization's
        security policies and requirements.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ch024_authentication-idp270544">
    <title>Policies</title>
    <para>Each OpenStack service has a policy file in JSON format,
      called <filename>policy.json</filename>. The policy
      file specifies rules, and the rule that governs each resource. A
      resource could be API access, the ability to attach to a volume,
      or to fire up instances.</para>
    <para>The policies can be updated by the cloud administrator to
      further control access to the various resources. The middleware
      could also be further customized. Note that your users must be
      assigned to groups/roles that you refer to in your
      policies.</para>
    <para>Below is a snippet of the Block Storage service
      <filename>policy.json</filename> file.</para>
    <programlisting language="json"><xi:include href="../common/samples/authentication.json" parse="text"/></programlisting>
    <para>Note the <emphasis role="bold">default</emphasis> rule
      specifies that the user must be either an admin or the owner of
      the volume. It essentially says only the owner of a volume or
      the admin may create/delete/update volumes. Certain other
      operations such as managing volume types are accessible only to
      admin users.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ch024_authentication-idp276176">
    <title>Tokens</title>
    <para>Once a user is authenticated, a token is generated and used
      internally in OpenStack for authorization and access. The
      default token <emphasis role="bold">lifespan</emphasis>
        is<emphasis role="bold"> 24 hours</emphasis>. It is
      recommended that this value be set lower but caution needs to be
      taken as some internal services will need sufficient time to
      complete their work. The cloud may not provide services if
      tokens expire too early. An example of this would be the time
      needed by the Compute service to transfer a disk image onto the
      hypervisor for local caching.</para>
    <para>The following example shows a PKI token. Note that, in
      practice, the token id value is about 3500 bytes. We shorten it
      in this example.</para>
    <programlisting language="json"><xi:include href="../common/samples/token.json" parse="text"/></programlisting>
    <para>Note that the token is often passed within the structure of
      a larger context of an Identity Service response. These
      responses also provide a catalog of the various OpenStack
      services. Each service is listed with its name, access endpoints
      for internal, admin, and public access.</para>
    <para>The Identity Service supports token revocation. This
      manifests as an API to revoke a token, to list revoked tokens
      and individual OpenStack services that cache tokens to query for
      the revoked tokens and remove them from their cache and append
      the same to their list of cached revoked tokens.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ch024_authentication-idp287584">
    <title>Future</title>
    <para>Domains are high-level containers for projects, users and
      groups. As such, they can be used to centrally manage all
      keystone-based identity components. With the introduction of
      account domains, server, storage and other resources can now be
      logically grouped into multiple projects (previously called
      tenants) which can themselves be grouped under a master
      account-like container. In addition, multiple users can be
      managed within an account domain and assigned roles that vary
      for each project.</para>
    <para>The Identity V3 API supports multiple domains. Users of
      different domains may be represented in different authentication
      backends and even have different attributes that must be mapped
      to a single set of roles and privileges, that are used in the
      policy definitions to access the various service
      resources.</para>
    <para>Where a rule may specify access to only admin users and
      users belonging to the tenant, the mapping may be trivial. In
      other scenarios the cloud administrator may need to approve the
      mapping routines per tenant.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
