<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % openstack SYSTEM "../common/entities/openstack.ent">
%openstack;
]>
<chapter xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         version="5.0"
         xml:id="ch034_tenant-secure-networking-best-practices">
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Networking services security best practices</title>
    <para>This section discusses OpenStack Networking configuration best practices as they apply to tenant network security within your OpenStack deployment.</para>
    <section xml:id="ch034_tenant-secure-networking-best-practices-idp44592">
      <title>Tenant network services workflow</title>
      <para>OpenStack Networking provides users real self services of network resources and configurations. It is important that cloud architects and operators evaluate their design use cases in providing users the ability to create, update, and destroy available network resources.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ch034_tenant-secure-networking-best-practices-idp46080">
      <title>Networking resource policy engine</title>
      <para>A policy engine and its configuration file,
      <filename>policy.json</filename>, within OpenStack Networking
      provides a method to provide finer grained authorization of
      users on tenant networking methods and objects. It is important
      that cloud architects and operators evaluate their design and
      use cases in providing users and tenants the ability to create,
      update, and destroy available network resources as it has a
      tangible effect on tenant network availability, network
      security, and overall OpenStack security. For a more detailed
      explanation of OpenStack Networking policy definition, please
      refer to the <link
      xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/admin-guide-cloud/content/section_networking_auth.html">Authentication
      and authorization section</link> in the <citetitle>OpenStack
      Cloud Administrator Guide</citetitle>.</para>
      <note><para>It is important to review the default networking
      resource policy and modify the policy appropriately for your
      security posture.</para></note>
      <para>If your deployment of OpenStack provides multiple external
      access points into different security domains it is important
      that you limit the tenant's ability to attach multiple vNICs to
      multiple external access points&mdash;this would bridge these
      security domains and could lead to unforeseen security
      compromise. It is possible mitigate this risk by utilizing the
      host aggregates functionality provided by OpenStack Compute or
      through splitting the tenant VMs into multiple tenant projects
      with different virtual network configurations.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ch034_tenant-secure-networking-best-practices-idp51440">
      <title>Security groups</title>
      <para>
        The OpenStack Networking Service provides security group
        functionality using a mechanism that is more flexible and
        powerful than the security group capabilities built into
        OpenStack Compute. Thus, when using OpenStack Networking,
        <filename>nova.conf</filename> should always disable built-in
        security groups and proxy all security group calls to the
        OpenStack Networking API. Failure to do so will result in
        conflicting security policies being simultaneously applied by
        both services. To proxy security groups to OpenStack
        Networking, use the following configuration values:</para>
      <itemizedlist><listitem>
          <para><option>firewall_driver</option> must be set to
          <literal>nova.virt.firewall.NoopFirewallDriver</literal> so
          that <systemitem class="service">nova-compute</systemitem>
          does not perform iptables-based filtering itself.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><option>security_group_api</option> must be set to
          <literal>neutron</literal> so that all security group
          requests are proxied to the OpenStack Networking
          service.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Security groups and security group rules allow administrators and tenants the ability to specify the type of traffic and direction (ingress/egress) that is allowed to pass through a virtual interface port. A security group is a container for security group rules. When a virtual interface port is created in OpenStack Networking it is associated with a security group. If a security group is not specified, the port will be associated with a 'default' security group. By default this group will drop all ingress traffic and allow all egress. Rules can be added to this group in order to change the behaviour.</para>
      <para>When using the security group API through OpenStack Compute, security groups are applied to all virtual interface ports on an instance. The reason for this is that OpenStack Compute security group APIs are instance based and not virtual interface port based as OpenStack Networking.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ch034_tenant-secure-networking-best-practices-idp58016">
      <title>Quotas</title>

      <para>Quotas provide the ability to limit the number of network
      resources available to tenants. You can enforce default quotas
      for all tenants. The
      <filename>/etc/neutron/neutron.conf</filename> includes these
      options for quota:</para>
      <programlisting language="ini">[QUOTAS]
# resource name(s) that are supported in quota features
quota_items = network,subnet,port

# default number of resource allowed per tenant, minus for unlimited
#default_quota = -1

# number of networks allowed per tenant, and minus means unlimited
quota_network = 10

# number of subnets allowed per tenant, and minus means unlimited
quota_subnet = 10

# number of ports allowed per tenant, and minus means unlimited
quota_port = 50

# number of security groups allowed per tenant, and minus means unlimited
quota_security_group = 10

# number of security group rules allowed per tenant, and minus means unlimited
quota_security_group_rule = 100

# default driver to use for quota checks
quota_driver = neutron.quota.ConfDriver</programlisting>
      <para>
        OpenStack Networking also supports per-tenant quotas limit
        through a quota extension API. To enable per-tenant quotas,
        you must set the <literal>quota_driver</literal> option in
        <filename>neutron.conf</filename>.</para>
      <programlisting language="ini">quota_driver = neutron.db.quota_db.DbQuotaDriver</programlisting>
    </section>
  </chapter>
