<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         version="5.0"
         xml:id="ch035_case-studies-networking">
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Case studies: Networking</title>
    <para>In this case study we discuss how Alice and Bob would address providing networking services to the user.</para>
    <section xml:id="ch035_case-studies-networking-idp37440">
      <title>Alice's private cloud</title>
      <para>A key objective of Alice's cloud is to integrate with the
      existing auth services and security resources. The key design
      parameters for this private cloud are a limited scope of
      tenants, networks and workload type. This environment can be
      designed to limit what available network resources are available
      to the tenant and what are the various default quotas and
      security policies are available. The network policy engine can
      be modified to restrict creation and changes to network
      resources. In this environment, Alice might want to leverage
      nova-network in the application of security group polices on a
      per instance basis vs. neutron's application of security group
      polices on a per port basis. L2 isolation in this environment
      would leverage VLAN tagging. The use of VLAN tags will allow
      great visibility of tenant traffic by leveraging existing
      features and tools of the physical infrastructure.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ch035_case-studies-networking-idp40064">
      <title>Bob's public cloud</title>
      <para>A major business driver for Bob is to provide an advanced
      networking services to his customers. Bob's customers would like
      to deploy multi-tiered application stacks. This multi-tiered
      application are either existing enterprise application or newly
      deployed applications. Since Bob's public cloud is a
      multi-tenancy enterprise service, the choice to use for L2
      isolation in this environment is to use overlay
      networking. Another aspect of Bob's cloud is the self-service
      aspect where the customer can provision available networking
      services as needed. These networking services encompass L2
      networks, L3 Routing, Network <glossterm>ACL</glossterm> and
      NAT. It is important that per-tenant quota's be implemented in
      this environment.</para>
      <para>An added benefit with utilizing OpenStack Networking is
      when new advanced networking services become available, these
      new features can be easily provided to the end customers.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
