<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         version="5.0"
         xml:id="ch032_networking-best-practices">
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Networking services</title>
    <para>In the initial architectural phases of designing your OpenStack Network infrastructure it is important to ensure appropriate expertise is available to assist with the design of the physical networking infrastructure, to identify proper security controls and auditing mechanisms.</para>
    <para>OpenStack Networking adds a layer of virtualized network services - giving tenants the capability to architect their own, virtual networks. These virtualized services are not as currently as mature as their traditional networking counterparts. It is important to be aware of the current state of these virtualized services and what controls may need to be implemented at the virtualized and traditional network boundary.</para>
    <section xml:id="ch032_networking-best-practices-idp45376">
      <title>L2 isolation using VLANs and tunneling</title>
      <para>OpenStack networking can employ two different mechanisms for traffic segregation on a per tenant/network combination: VLANs (IEEE 802.1Q tagging) or L2 tunnels using GRE encapsulation. Which method you choose for traffic segregation and isolation is determined by the scope and scale of your OpenStack deployment.</para>
      <section xml:id="ch032_networking-best-practices-idp46832">
        <title>VLANs</title>
        <para>VLANs are realized as packets on a specific physical network containing IEEE 802.1Q headers with a specific VLAN ID (VID) field value. VLAN networks sharing the same physical network are isolated from each other at L2, and can even have overlapping IP address spaces. Each distinct physical network supporting VLAN networks is treated as a separate VLAN trunk, with a distinct space of VID values. Valid VID values are 1 through 4094.</para>
        <para>VLAN configuration complexity depends on your OpenStack design requirements. In order to allow OpenStack Networking to efficiently use VLANs, you must allocate a VLAN range (one for each tenant) and turn each compute node physical switch port into a VLAN trunk port.</para>
        <note>
          <para>NOTE: If you intend for your network to support more than 4094 tenants VLAN is probably not the correct option for you as multiple 'hacks' are required to extend the VLAN tags to more than 4094 tenants.</para>
        </note>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="ch032_networking-best-practices-idp50512">
        <title>L2 tunneling</title>
        <para>Network tunneling encapsulates each tenant/network combination with a unique "tunnel-id" that is used to identify the network traffic belonging to that combination. The tenant's L2 network connectivity is independent of physical locality or underlying network design. By encapsulating traffic inside IP packets, that traffic can cross Layer-3 boundaries, removing the need for preconfigured VLANs and VLAN trunking. Tunneling adds a layer of obfuscation to network data traffic, reducing the visibility of individual tenant traffic from a monitoring point of view.</para>
        <para>OpenStack Networking currently only supports GRE encapsulation with planned future support of VXLAN due in the Havana release.</para>
        <para>The choice of technology to provide L2 isolation is dependent upon the scope and size of tenant networks that will be created in your deployment. If your environment has limited VLAN ID availability or will have a large number of L2 networks, it is our recommendation that you utilize tunneling.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ch032_networking-best-practices-idp54784">
      <title>Network services</title>
      <para>The choice of tenant network isolation affects how the network security and control boundary is implemented for tenant services. The following additional network services are either available or currently under development to enhance the security posture of the OpenStack network architecture.</para>
      <section xml:id="ch032_networking-best-practices-idp56112">
        <title>Access control lists</title>
        <para>OpenStack Compute supports tenant network traffic access controls directly when deployed with the legacy nova-network service, or may defer access control to the OpenStack Networking service.</para>
        <para>Note, legacy nova-network security groups are applied to all virtual interface ports on an instance using IPTables.</para>
        <para>Security groups allow administrators and tenants the ability to specify the type of traffic, and direction (ingress/egress) that is allowed to pass through a virtual interface port. Security groups rules are stateful L2-L4 traffic filters.</para>
        <para>It is our recommendation that you enable security groups
          through OpenStack Networking.</para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="ch032_networking-best-practices-idp59008">
        <title>L3 routing and NAT</title>
        <para>OpenStack Networking routers can connect multiple L2 networks, and can also provide a <emphasis>gateway</emphasis> that connects one or more private L2 networks to a shared <emphasis>external</emphasis> network, such as a public network for access to the Internet.</para>
        <para>The L3 router provides basic Network Address Translation (NAT) capabilities on <emphasis>gateway</emphasis> ports that uplink the router to external networks. This router SNATs (Static NAT) all traffic by default, and supports floating IPs, which creates a static one-to-one mapping from a public IP on the external network to a private IP on one of the other subnets attached to the router.</para>
        <para>It is our recommendation to leverage per tenant L3 routing and Floating IPs for more granular connectivity of tenant VMs.</para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="ch032_networking-best-practices-idp62880">
        <title>Quality of Service (QoS)</title>
        <para>The ability to set QoS on the virtual interface ports of tenant instances is a current deficiency for OpenStack Networking. The application of QoS for traffic shaping and rate-limiting at the physical network edge device is insufficient due to the dynamic nature of workloads in an OpenStack deployment and can not be leveraged in the traditional way. QoS-as-a-Service (QoSaaS) is currently in development for the OpenStack Networking Havana release as an experimental feature. QoSaaS is planning to provide the following services:</para>
        <itemizedlist><listitem>
            <para>Traffic shaping through DSCP markings</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Rate-limiting on a per port/network/tenant basis.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Port mirroring (through open source or third-party plug-ins)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Flow analysis (through open source or third-party plug-ins)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>Tenant traffic port mirroring or Network Flow monitoring is currently not an exposed feature in OpenStack Networking. There are third-party plug-in extensions that do provide Port Mirroring on a per port/network/tenant basis. If Open vSwitch is used on the networking hypervisor, it is possible to enable sFlow and port mirroring, however it will require some operational effort to implement.</para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="ch032_networking-best-practices-idp69408">
        <title>Load balancing</title>
        <para>An experimental feature in the Grizzly release of OpenStack Networking is Load-Balancer-as-a-service (LBaaS). The LBaaS API gives early adopters and vendors a chance to build implementations of the technology. The reference implementation however, is still experimental and should likely not be run in a production environment. The current reference implementation is based on HA-Proxy. There are third-party plug-ins in development for extensions in OpenStack Networking to provide extensive L4-L7 functionality for virtual interface ports.</para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="ch032_networking-best-practices-idp71664">
        <title>Firewalls</title>
        <para>FW-as-a-Service (FWaaS) is currently in development for the OpenStack Networking Havana release as an experimental feature. FWaaS will address the need to manage and leverage the rich set of security features provided by typical firewall products which are typically far more comprehensive than what is currently provided by security groups. There are third-party plug-ins in development for extensions in OpenStack Networking to support this.</para>
        <para>It is critical during the design of an OpenStack Networking infrastructure to understand the current features and limitations of network services that are available. Understanding where the boundaries of your virtual and physical networks will help you add the required security controls in your environment.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ch032_networking-best-practices-idp74544">
      <title>Network services extensions</title>
      <para>Here is a list of known plug-ins provided by the open source community or by SDN companies that work with OpenStack Networking:</para>
      <para>Big Switch Controller plug-in, Brocade neutron plug-in
      Brocade neutron plug-in, Cisco UCS/Nexus plug-in, Cloudbase
      Hyper-V plug-in, Extreme Networks plug-in, Juniper Networks
      neutron plug-in, Linux Bridge plug-in, Mellanox neutron plug-in,
      MidoNet plug-in, NEC OpenFlow plug-in, Open vSwitch plug-in,
      PLUMgrid plug-in, Ruijie Networks plug-in, Ryu OpenFlow
      Controller plug-in, VMware NSX plug-in.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ch032_networking-best-practices-idp78032">
      <title>Networking services limitations</title>
      <para>OpenStack Networking has the following known limitations:</para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Overlapping IP addresses</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              If nodes that run either <systemitem
              class="service">neutron-l3-agent</systemitem> or
              <systemitem
              class="service">neutron-dhcp-agent</systemitem> use
              overlapping IP addresses, those nodes must use Linux
              network namespaces. By default, the DHCP and L3 agents
              use Linux network namespaces. However, if the host does
              not support these namespaces, run the DHCP and L3 agents
              on different hosts.</para>
            <para>
              If network namespace support is not present, a further
              limitation of the L3 agent is that only a single logical
              router is supported.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Multi-host DHCP-agent</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              OpenStack Networking supports multiple L3 and DHCP
              agents with load balancing. However, tight coupling of
              the location of the virtual machine is not
              supported.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>No IPv6 support for L3 agents</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The neutron-l3-agent, used by many plug-ins to implement
              L3 forwarding, supports only IPv4 forwarding.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>
  </chapter>
