<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         version="5.0"
         xml:id="ch049_case-studies-tenant-data">
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Case studies: tenant data</title>
    <para>
      Returning to Alice and Bob, we will use this section to dive
      into their particular tenant data privacy
      requirements. Specifically, we will look into how Alice and Bob
      both handle tenant data, data destruction, and data
      encryption.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="ch049_case-studies-tenant-data-idp44416">
      <title>Alice's private cloud</title>
      <para>
        As stated during the introduction to Alice's case study, data
        protection is of an extremely high priority. She needs to
        ensure that a compromise of one tenant's data does not cause
        loss of other tenant data. She also has strong regulator
        requirements that require documentation of data destruction
        activities. Alice does this using the following:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Establishing procedures to sanitize tenant data when
              a program or project ends.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Track the destruction of both the tenant data and
              metadata through ticketing in a CMDB.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem><para>For Volume storage:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Physical server issues</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>To provide secure ephemeral instance storage,
                Alice implements qcow2 files on an encrypted
                filesystem.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ch049_case-studies-tenant-data-idp51856">
      <title>Bob's public cloud</title>
      <para>
        As stated during the introduction to Bob's case study, tenant
        privacy is of an extremely high priority. In addition to the
        requirements and actions Bob will take to isolate tenants from
        one another at the infrastructure layer, Bob also needs to
        provide assurances for tenant data privacy. Bob does this
        using the following:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Establishing procedures to sanitize customer data
            when a customer churns.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Track the destruction of both the customer data and
            metadata through ticketing in a CMDB.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>For Volume storage:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Physical server issues</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>To provide secure ephemeral instance storage, Bob
                implements qcow2 files on an encrypted filesystems.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
</chapter>
