<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         version="5.0"
         xml:id="ch061_compliance-overview">
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Compliance overview</title>
    <para>An OpenStack deployment may require compliance activities for many purposes, such as regulatory and legal requirements, customer need, privacy considerations, and security best practices. Compliance, when done correctly, unifies and strengthens the other security topics discussed in this guide. This chapter has several objectives:</para>
    <itemizedlist><listitem>
        <para>Review common security principles.</para>
      </listitem>
<listitem>
        <para>Discuss common control frameworks and certification resources to achieve industry certifications or regulator attestations.</para>
      </listitem>
<listitem>
        <para>Act as a reference for auditors when evaluating OpenStack deployments.</para>
      </listitem>
<listitem>
        <para>Introduce privacy considerations specific to OpenStack and cloud environments.</para>
      </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
    <section xml:id="ch061_compliance-overview-idp48672">
      <title>Security principles</title>
      <para>Industry standard security principles provide a baseline
      for compliance certifications and attestations. If these
      principles are considered and referenced throughout an OpenStack
      deployment, certification activities may be simplified.</para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry><term>Layered defenses</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Identify where risks exist in a cloud architecture and
              apply controls to mitigate the risks. In areas of
              significant concern, layered defences provide multiple
              complementary controls to further mitigate risk. For
              example, to ensure adequate isolation between cloud
              tenants, we recommend hardening QEMU, using a hypervisor
              with SELinux support, enforcing mandatory access control
              policies, and reducing the overall attack surface. The
              foundational principle is to harden an area of concern
              with multiple layers of defense such that if any one
              layer is compromised, other layers will exist to offer
              protection and minimize exposure.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>Fail securely</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              In the case of failure, systems should be configured to
              fail into a closed secure state. For example, SSL
              certificate verification should fail closed by severing
              the network connection if the CNAME doesn't match the
              server's DNS name. Software often fails open in this
              situation, allowing the connection to proceed without a
              CNAME match, which is less secure and not
              recommended.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>Least privilege</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Only the minimum level of access for users and system
              services is granted. This access is based upon role,
              responsibility and job function. This security principal
              of least privilege is written into several international
              government security policies, such as NIST 800-53
              Section AC-6 within the United States.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>Compartmentalize</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Systems should be segregated in a such way that if one
              machine, or system-level service, is compromised the
              security of the other systems will remain
              intact. Practically, the enablement and proper usage of
              SELinux helps accomplish this goal.</para>
        </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Promote privacy</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The amount of information that can be gathered about a
              system and its users should be minimized.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Logging capability</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Appropriate logging is implemented to monitor for
              unauthorized use, incident response and forensics. It is
              highly recommended that selected audit subsystems be
              Common Criteria certified, which provides non-attestable
              event records in most countries.</para>
        </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>
  </chapter>
