<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         version="5.0" xml:id="section_ceilometer_dashboard">
    <title>View cloud usage statistics</title>
    <para>The Telemetry module provides user-level usage data for OpenStack-based clouds,
        which can be used for customer billing, system monitoring, or alerts. Data can be
        collected by notifications sent by existing OpenStack components (for example,
        usage events emitted from Compute) or by polling the infrastructure (for example,
        libvirt).
  </para>
    <note><para>You can only view metering statistics on the dashboard (available only to administrators). The Telemetry service
        must be set up and administered through the <command>ceilometer</command> command-line
        interface (CLI).
  </para>
        <para>For basic administration information, refer to the "Measure Cloud Resources" chapter in the
            <citetitle>OpenStack End User Guide</citetitle>.</para></note>
  <section xml:id="dashboard_view_resource_stats">
        <title>View resource statistics</title>
        <procedure>
            <step>
                <para>Log in to the OpenStack dashboard as a user with Admin privileges.</para>
            </step>
            <step><para>On the <guilabel>Admin</guilabel> tab, click the
                <guilabel>Resource Usage</guilabel> category.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Click the:
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem><para><guilabel>Global Disk Usage</guilabel> tab to view disk usage per tenant (project).</para></listitem>
                        <listitem><para><guilabel>Global Network Traffic Usage</guilabel> tab to view ingress or egress usage per tenant
                                (project).</para></listitem>
                        <listitem><para><guilabel>Global Object Storage Usage</guilabel> tab to view incoming and outgoing storage bytes per tenant (project).</para></listitem>
                        <listitem><para><guilabel>Global Network Usage</guilabel> tab to view duration and creation requests for
                                networks, subnets, routers, ports, and floating IPs, per  tenant
                                (project).</para></listitem>
                        <listitem><para><guilabel>Stats</guilabel> tab to view a multi-series line chart with user-defined metrics.
                                You group by project, define the value type (min, max, avg, or sum),
                                and specify the time period (or even use a calendar to define a date
                                range).</para></listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </para>
            </step>
        </procedure>
    </section>
</section>
